<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Liquid crystal materials (LCMs) have drawn significant attention due to their wide applications in organic optoelectronic devices, such as optical information displays and storage devices [
  <a rid="B1-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-materials-12-01919">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-materials-12-01919">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-materials-12-01919">3</a>]. However, most of the liquid crystal materials investigated are not fluorescent materials and thus limit the application of liquid crystal displays. Therefore, luminescent liquid crystal materials (LLCMs) with intrinsic fluorescence properties and an organized structure are highly desired, and have been rapidly developed and used in anisotropic light-emitting diodes, polarized organic lasers, information storage, and sensors [
  <a rid="B1-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-materials-12-01919">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-materials-12-01919">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-materials-12-01919">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-materials-12-01919">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-materials-12-01919">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-materials-12-01919">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-materials-12-01919">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-materials-12-01919">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-materials-12-01919">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-materials-12-01919">10</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the promising features of fluorescent LCMs, the incorporation of luminescent functional groups into LCMs while retaining the mesomorphic properties is still challenging, because most of the fluorescent molecules are only highly emissive in a solution, and their fluorescence quantum yields are greatly decreased from the solution to the condensed state [
  <a rid="B11-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-materials-12-01919">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-materials-12-01919">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-materials-12-01919">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-materials-12-01919">14</a>]. Therefore, a new approach is necessary to synergistically generate efficient luminescence in the mesophase. Thus, much research has been devoted to the design and synthesis of new florescent materials that can emit intense fluorescence in the solid state, such as a series of solid-state emissive organic molecules developed by Tang et al., which exhibit so-called aggregation-induced emissions (AIE) [
  <a rid="B15-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-materials-12-01919">15</a>]. By taking the benefit of the aggregation-induced emissions and the organization of liquid crystal, a variety of LCMs with AIE properties have been developed and show promising applications in the field of optoelectronic materials [
  <a rid="B1-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-materials-12-01919">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-materials-12-01919">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-materials-12-01919">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Red-emitting materials, especially those where the emission wavelength includes the deep-red and near-infrared radiation (NIR) range, have attracted great attention in the fields of materials science, chemistry, and biology [
  <a rid="B16-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-materials-12-01919">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-materials-12-01919">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-materials-12-01919">18</a>]; however, materials that can emit a red light generally require a narrow Highest Occupied Molecular Orbital (HOMO) and Lowest Unoccupied Molecular Orbital (LUMO) band gap, and thus, most of the reported strategies to generate red emission are directed to introducing electron-donating and electron-accepting groups to the termini of π-conjugated moieties [
  <a rid="B19-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-materials-12-01919">19</a>]. However, molecules with such types of structure generally have a strong tendency to form π–π stacking in the solid state, resulting in luminescence quenching caused by the dipole-dipole interactions from the donor and acceptor segments; therefore, most of the red-emitting materials are susceptible to concentration quenching and become either weakly luminescent or even not emissive at all in the condensed state [
  <a rid="B20-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-materials-12-01919">20</a>]. In this case, the development of red-emitting materials with high fluorescence efficiency (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>) and liquid crystal properties is highly desired, although, to the best of our knowledge, only a few examples of LCMs that emit a red light have been reported [
  <a rid="B16-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-materials-12-01919">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-materials-12-01919">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-materials-12-01919">18</a>]. Huang et al. synthesized a red-emitting spirobifluorene containing a diphenylamine group as donor and a dicyanoethenyl group as acceptor in the termini. This type of molecule shows an emission maximum at 644 nm with a quantum yield of 0.33 [
  <a rid="B19-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-materials-12-01919">19</a>]. In this molecular design, the nonplanar structure of the diphenylamino moiety and the spiro framework contribute to the suppression of π–π stacking of the dye in the solid state, and the choice of a dicyanoethenyl moiety as an acceptor is the key to generating red emission. Osuka et al. introduced four hexyl groups to the 2, 5, 8, and 11 positions of perylene tetracarboxylic acid bisimide, resulting in a highly emissive dye with an emission maximum of 635 nm and fluorescence efficiency of 0.59. These results are remarkable compared to the perylene tetracarboxylic acid bisimide without the hexyl groups (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>
  <sub>powder</sub> = 0.07) [
  <a rid="B21-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-materials-12-01919">21</a>]. Cocchi et al. reported a NIR excimer-based organic light-emitting diode with a high efficiency of 14.5% ± 0.2% photon/electron that exhibits exclusive NIR excimer emission peaking at a wavelength of 700 nm [
  <a rid="B22-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-materials-12-01919">22</a>]. Vollbrecht et al. quantified the relationship between the red-shift and interplanar distance by investigating perylene-, phenanthroperylene- and dinaphthocoronene-esters. According to their research, the energy difference (ΔE
  <sub>Shift</sub>) will increase with a smaller value of interplanar distance [
  <a rid="B23-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-materials-12-01919">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-materials-12-01919">24</a>]. Recently, Anthony et al. developed a triphenylamine and N-methyl barbituric acid/indane dione-based donor–acceptor derivative with red-emitting material and quantum yields of 0.14 to 0.41 [
  <a rid="B25-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-materials-12-01919">25</a>]. Park et al. developed a distyrylbenzene-based D-A-D-A-D red/near-infrared-emitting material with a quantum efficiency of 0.36 [
  <a rid="B26-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-materials-12-01919">26</a>]. Zhang et al. developed organoboron-based compounds with NIR emission and quantum efficiencies of 0.21–0.30 [
  <a rid="B27-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-materials-12-01919">27</a>]. Tang et al. developed an N, N-dimethyl-attached fumaronitrile-based (D–A) molecule that had a quantum efficiency of 0.27 [
  <a rid="B28-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-materials-12-01919">28</a>]. These examples indicate that intense red-emitting materials could be generated through a rational molecular design, but to the best of our knowledge, materials that exhibit deep-red emission with wavelengths close to 700 nm are still rare.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this research, we synthesized 4,7-bis (thiophen-2-yl) benzo[c][1,2,5]thiadiazole derivative (BTC0) with a quantum efficiency of 0.1 in the solid state with a deep-red emission of 689 nm. Interestingly, a simple introduction of hexyl groups to the terminus of 4,7-bis(thiophen-2-yl)benzo[c][1,2,5]thiadiazole derivative (BTC6) using a palladium-catalyzed Stille coupling reaction was able to generate an intense deep-red emission at approximately 689 nm in the solid state with a rather high fluorescence quantum yield of 0.26. The attached flexible aliphatic hexyl chains provided the molecules with smectic liquid crystal features upon heating.</p>
</sec>
