<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. The Photophysical Properties of BTC0 and BTC6 in Solution</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The UV-vis, photoluminescence (PL) and excitation spectra are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f002" href="#materials-12-01919-f002">Figure 2</a>. In 
  <a rid="materials-12-01919-t001" ref-type="table" href="#materials-12-01919-t001">Table 1</a>, the wavelength of absorption and emission maximum, extinction coefficient (ε), Stokes shift, quantum yield (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>
  <sub>F</sub>), lifetime (
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>f</sub>), radiative decay rate constant (
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>r</sub>), and nonradiative decay rate constant (
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>nr</sub>) are summarized. The results showed that BTC6 and BTC0 had multiple absorption bands in both the solution and the solid state, with one band approximately 500 nm assigned to the intramolecular charge transfer from the donor to the acceptor core and the other band at approximately 350 nm assigned to the π–π* transition. In addition, the solvatochromic effect of the PL spectra was observed (
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-01919" href="#app1-materials-12-01919">Figure S1c,d, and Table S1</a>). When the solvent polarity was increased gradually from low-polarity hexane to high-polarity DMSO, both BTC6 and BTC0 exhibited a large redshift of approximately 70 nm, which indicated that the first singlet excited state (S
  <sub>1</sub>) of the dye possessed a strong intramolecular charge transfer characteristic.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing the spectra of BTC6 and BTC0 in the solution (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f002" href="#materials-12-01919-f002">Figure 2</a>a,b), they did not exhibit marked differences with respect to spectral shape and the wavelengths of absorption and emission maximum. Additionally, the values of the Stokes shift, quantum yield (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>
  <sub>F</sub>), lifetime &lt;
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>f</sub>&gt;, radiative decay rate constant (k
  <sub>n</sub>), and nonradiative decay rate constant (k
  <sub>nr</sub>) were very similar (
  <a rid="materials-12-01919-t001" ref-type="table" href="#materials-12-01919-t001">Table 1</a>, and 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-01919" href="#app1-materials-12-01919">Figure S2a</a>), indicative of the similar optical properties of the compounds in the solution. We presumed that the molecules existed in a practically monodispersed isolated state in dilute solution and that the length of the alkyl chain did not affect the electronic transition; therefore, the compounds had similar optical properties in the dilute solution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By contrast, the two compounds showed a different optical performance in the solid state. Obviously, BTC0 had a smaller quantum yield and lifetime (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>
  <sub>F</sub> = 0.10, &lt;
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>f</sub>&gt; = 1.97 ns) compared to that of BTC6 (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>
  <sub>F</sub> = 0.26, &lt;
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>f</sub>&gt; = 7.17 ns). Furthermore, the k
  <sub>r</sub> value of BTC0 (5.07 × 10
  <span class="sup">7</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was 1.3 times that of BTC6 (3.63 × 10
  <span class="sup">7</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), while the k
  <sub>nr</sub> value of BTC0 (4.57 × 10
  <span class="sup">8</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was nearly 5 times that of BTC6 (1.03 × 10
  <span class="sup">8</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>). The significant enhancement of the k
  <sub>nr</sub> in BTC0 was ascribed to the acceleration of the nonradiative deactivation channel arising from π−π interactions. 
 </p>
</sec>
