<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot3-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. PXRD Patterns of the Crystalline Powders of BTC0 and BTC6</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the X-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f003" href="#materials-12-01919-f003">Figure 3</a>), the results showed that the distance between adjacent molecules of BTC6 was 4.16 Å, which is greater than the typical intermolecular π–π interactions of 3.80 Å. Thus, BTC6 avoided the quenching of fluorescence in the solid state. Moreover, BTC0 showed a closer distance (3.37 and 3.59 Å) within the range of intermolecular π–π stacking, thus making the intermolecular π–π interactions sufficiently strong to quench the fluorescence in the solid state. Apparently, the alkyl chains of the molecule trigger showed a different aggregation, as shown by the distinct differences in optical properties. BTC0 without alkyl chains had a strong interaction among the coupled cores to induce a short distance stacking of 3.37 and 3.59 Å. BTC6 with alkyl chains had van der Waals interactions among the alkyl side chains, which provided force to counterbalance against the interactions between the coupled cores, resulting in a longer distance of 4.16 Å. In summary, we can conclude that the existence of an alkyl chain induced the enhancement of optical properties in the solid state.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, we determined the types of molecular aggregation. Two main species of dye aggregates are distinguished in the literature: For 
  <span class="italic">H</span>-aggregates, the absorption maximum of the aggregate is blue-shifted with respect to the isolated chromophore and fluorescence of the isolated chromophore is lost in the aggregate; for 
  <span class="italic">J</span>-aggregates, the absorption and emission maxima are red-shifted and no quenching occurs in the aggregate state [
  <a rid="B29-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-materials-12-01919">29</a>,
  <a rid="B30-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-materials-12-01919">30</a>,
  <a rid="B31-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-materials-12-01919">31</a>]. The common structural model for such aggregates is based on the longitudinal offset of the dye molecules, which is sometimes described as the deck-of-cards model (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f003" href="#materials-12-01919-f003">Figure 3</a>), in which the cards represent the molecules stacked on top of each other [
  <a rid="B32-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-materials-12-01919">32</a>,
  <a rid="B33-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-materials-12-01919">33</a>]. By comparing the absorption and excitation spectra, the excitation at approximately 570 nm was the cause of emission and was red-shifted with respect to the isolated chromophore, indicating the formation of 
  <span class="italic">J</span>-type aggregates.
 </p>
</sec>
