<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Electrochemical Properties of BTC0 and BTC6</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical calculations demonstrated that the molecules had LUMO and HOMO energy levels of –2.6 and –5.0 eV, respectively (
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-01919" href="#app1-materials-12-01919">Figure S3</a>). To evaluate the compound energy levels experimentally, we investigated their electrochemical properties using cyclic voltammetry (CV) and differential pulse voltammetry (DPV) with ferrocene used as an internal standard. The electrochemical HOMO-LUMO band gaps are presented in 
  <a rid="materials-12-01919-t002" ref-type="table" href="#materials-12-01919-t002">Table 2</a>. These results clearly indicated that the alkyl chain slightly affected the HOMO-LUMO levels and the band gap of the dyes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f004" href="#materials-12-01919-f004">Figure 4</a>, BTC0 and BTC6 exhibited a similar reversible reduction process. However, they showed a different oxidation process: BTC6 had two oxidation potentials, while BTC0 just had one oxidation potential. This characteristic can be explained by the molecular structure of BTC6. In BTC6, the active para-hydrogen in benzene was replaced by an inactive alkyl chain, which provided a protective effect and caused BTC6 to have a high resistance toward decomposition reactions, such as dimerization. Hence, BTC6 had a second oxidation potential, while BTC0 underwent decomposition reactions at that corresponding potential (such as electropolymerization, 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-01919" href="#app1-materials-12-01919">Figure S4</a>). In summary, we can conclude that the alkyl chain can enhance the electrochemical stability of the molecule by replacing the active groups. Usually, the wider reversible redox potential range is favorable for the processes of device fabrication and other kinds of applications (organic light emitting diodes, sensors, etc.).
 </p>
</sec>
