<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot5-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Thermal Properties and the Liquid Crystalline Phase</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The thermal properties of the two molecules were investigated by thermogravimetric analysis (TGA) and differential scanning calorimetry (DSC). The TGA analysis revealed that the 5% weight loss temperatures (
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>d</sub>) of BTC6 and BTC0 were 366 and 314 °C, respectively (
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-01919" href="#app1-materials-12-01919">Figure S5</a>). This result indicated that BTC6 had a better thermal stability, which can be attributed to the attached hexyl chain on BTC6, which can absorb more heat than BTC0.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the heating process, BTC0 showed crystal phases below 236 °C and an isotropic liquid phase above that temperature (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f005" href="#materials-12-01919-f005">Figure 5</a>a). In the cooling process, reverse phase transitions were observed. Interestingly, BTC6 showed a mesophase between the crystal phase and the isotropic liquid phase (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f005" href="#materials-12-01919-f005">Figure 5</a>b). In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01919-f006" href="#materials-12-01919-f006">Figure 6</a>a, the texture of the mesophase observed with a polarized microscope (POM) is shown, namely, a fan-shaped texture, which is characteristic of the smectic phase [
  <a rid="B35-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-materials-12-01919">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-materials-12-01919">36</a>,
  <a rid="B37-materials-12-01919" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-materials-12-01919">37</a>]. The smectic phase was reasonable because the enthalpy changes in the phase transition from the crystal phase to the mesophase (34.1 J/g) were larger than those from the mesophase to the isotropic liquid phase (5.12 J/g). This result means that in the mesophase, the crystal structure was considerably disrupted, but the ordered structure remained. This characteristic can be explained by the molecular structure of BTC6 with a rigid central core and flexible side chains.
 </p>
</sec>
