<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Experimental Section</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Measurements</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Air and water sensitive synthetic manipulations were performed under a nitrogen atmosphere using standard Schlenk techniques. All chemicals were purchased from Annaiji (Shanghai, China) or TCI (Tokyo, Japan) and used as received without further purification. The NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker (Billerica, MA, USA, 400 MHz) spectrometer by using tetramethylsilane (0 ppm for 
   <span class="sup">1</span>H and 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR) as an internal standard. Absorption and fluorescence spectra were recorded on a Pekin Elmer Lambda 950 spectrophotometer (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA) and a Thermo Lumina spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Waltham, MA, USA), respectively, in a solution at room temperature (298 K) in a quartz cuvette of 1 cm path length. For the fluorescence lifetime measurements we used a FluoroCube spectrometer (HORIBA Jobin Yvon, Kyoto, Japan) equipped with a picosecond pulse laser and a picosecond photon detection module (TBX). The fluorescence quantum yield was recorded on a Hamamatsu absolute PL quantum yield spectrometer C11347-11. All calculations were performed with Spartan 2016 and the geometry of the molecule was optimized through density functional theory (DFT) calculations at the restricted B3LYP level with 6-31G*(d) basis set. X-ray diffraction data were collected at 298 K on a Bruker D8 Advance with Cu Kα radiation (Billerica, MA, USA). The elemental analyses were carried out on an Elementar vario MICRO cube. The thermal properties of samples were measured using TA DSC7020 (TA Instruments, New Castle, DE, USA) in differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) and TGA-Q50 in thermogravimetric analysis (TGA). Fourier transform infrared (FT-IR) spectra were recorded on a Nicolet 6700 spectrometer device (Thermo Fisher Scientific Waltham, MA, USA).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-materials-12-01919" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Materials and Synthesis </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1-bromo-4-hexylbenzene was purchased from Annaiji Chemical Company and used as received. 4,7-bis-(5-(trimethylstannyl) thiophene-2-yl) benzo[1,2,5]thiadiazole was purchased from Derthon Optoelectronic Materials Science Technology Co. ltd., (Shenzhen, China), and used as received. Other chemicals and solvents were commercially available and used as received unless otherwise claimed. The molecules were investigated by NMR, FTIR and elemental analyses (
   <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-01919" href="#app1-materials-12-01919">Figures S6–S11</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="bold">4,7-bis(5-phenylthiophen-2-yl)benzo[c][1,2,5]thiadiazole (BTC0)</span>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="sup">1</span>H NMR (CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>, 400 MHz, TMS, 298 K): 
   <span class="italic">δ</span> 8.13 (d, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 3.9 Hz, 2H), 7.91 (s, 2H), 7.72 (d, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 7.7 Hz, 4H), 7.47–7.38 (m, 6H), 7.32 (t, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 7.4 Hz, 2H).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR (CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>, 100 MHz, TMS, 298 K): 
   <span class="italic">δ</span> 152.61, 145.62, 138.67, 134.13, 128.97, 128.63, 127.85, 125.85, 125.39, 124.11.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytically calculated for C
   <sub>26</sub>H
   <sub>16</sub>N
   <sub>2</sub>S
   <sub>3</sub> (%): C, 68.99; H, 3.56; N, 6.19; S, 21.25. Found: C, 69.06; H, 3.37; N, 6.24; S, 21.48.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="bold">4,7-bis(thiophene-2-yl)benzo[c][1,2,5]thiadiazole (BTC6)</span>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A 50 mL two-necked round bottom flask was charged with 4,7-Di(5-trimethyltin-thiophene)-2,1,3-benzothiadiazole (100 mg, 0.16 mmol), 1-Bromo-4-hexylbenzene (115 mg, 0.48 mmol), Pd
   <sub>2</sub>(dba)
   <sub>3</sub> (14.65 mg, 0.016 mmol), P(o-toyl)
   <sub>3</sub> (19.5 mg, 0.064 mmol), evacuated and back-filled with argon three times. Chlorobenzene (10 mL) was added via syringe. The reaction mixture was stirred at 110 °C for 24 h. Then, the solvent was evaporated under reduced pressure. Water was poured into the reaction mixture, extracted with DCM 3 times, the combined organic layer was washed with brine, and dried over MgSO
   <sub>4</sub>. The solvent was removed by evaporation under reduced pressure, and the resulting red solid was purified through column chromatography (silica gel, hexane: EtOAc = 5:1) to afford the target compound as red powder (95 mg, 96%).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="sup">1</span>H NMR (CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>, 400 MHz, TMS, 298 K): 
   <span class="italic">δ</span> 8.08 (s, 2H), 7.84 (s, 2H), 7.61 (d, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 7.7 Hz, 4H), 7.36 (d, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 3.8 Hz, 2H), 7.22 (d, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 7.9 Hz, 4H), 2.64 (t, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 7.5 Hz, 4H), 1.65 (q, 
   <span class="italic">J</span> = 7.4 Hz, 4H), 1.42–1.23 (m, 12H), 0.94–0.86 (m, 6H).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR (CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>, 100 MHz, TMS, 298 K): 
   <span class="italic">δ</span> 152.56, 138.16, 128.96, 128.63, 125.76, 125.24, 123.57, 35.71, 31.74, 31.38, 29.01, 22.63, 14.11.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytically calculated for C
   <sub>38</sub>H
   <sub>40</sub>N
   <sub>2</sub>S
   <sub>3</sub> (%): C, 73.50; H, 6.49; N, 4.51; S, 15.49. Found: C, 73.46; H, 6.89; N, 4.58; S, 15.64.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
