<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the quantum simulations for molecular energies it has been assumed that the HF wave function is a “good” approximation of the ground state wave function. However, validity of this assumption is rather limited, and construction of multiconfigurational wave functions is crucial to describe a wide variety of chemistries. The proposed approach generates multiconfigurational wave functions utilizing diradical characters computed from the occupation number of BS-UHF natural orbitals. Numerical calculations on the covalent bond dissociation of H
  <sub>2</sub>, ethane, ethylene, and acetylene and electronic ground state of phenylene-1,4-dinitrene revealed that the multiconfigurational wave functions prepared using diradical characters have large overlap with the reference (full-CI or CAS-CI) wave functions. The worst case in the systems under study is found in the triple bond dissociation of acetylene, but the square overlap value is still 0.882. In the proposed approach, the number of orbital pairs having non-negligible diradical characters as well as diradical characters is automatically determined from the BS-UHF calculations. Preparation of the multiconfigurational wave functions on quantum registers can be accomplished by introducing ancilla qubits retaining information on diradical characters, and perform Bell state preparations and Fredkin gates, conditional on the ancilla qubits. The proposed approach enables us to efficiently take into account static electron correlation effects via diradical characters. In the case of prominent dynamical electron correlations, the square overlap becomes smaller, and additional computations such as ASP and ASCI may be preferable to ensure sufficiently large overlap with the full-CI root. We can reasonably assume that the multiconfigurational wave functions prepared using diradical characters are good initial guesses for further computations like ASP and ASCI. Note that the prepared wave function is a spin eigenfunction, and it contains 2
  <span class="italic">k</span>-ple excited configurations from the RHF configuration, where 
  <span class="italic">k</span> is the number of diradical characters used for the preparation of wave function. The multiconfigurational wave function is inherently suitable as the initial guess wave function for not only the QPEA-based full-CI calculations but also other computational models like VQE.
 </p>
</sec>
