<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Localised orbitals</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Visualisation of orbitals is an important aspect of many types of research. A series of orbital visualisation options, such as localised orbitals and electron localisation functions are provided (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> illustrates a few of the orbital visualisation options).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Orbital visualisation. Standard ab initio quantum chemistry methods yield delocalised orbitals that extend over the entire molecule. Localised orbitals can be found as linear combinations of the occupied delocalised orbitals by a unitary transformation. In Molden the Foster-Boys [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>] scheme is employed to localize molecular orbitals. The 
     <span class="italic">left-hand panel</span> shows the localised orbital of Iron(III) meso tartaric acid. This calculation proves that there is a bond between the irons and the coordinated water molecules (ultimate 
     <span class="italic">left</span> and 
     <span class="italic">right</span> in the figure). The absence of nodal planes between iron (
     <span class="italic">yellow</span>) and water(s) is tantamount to the presence of electron density (a bond) between irons and water. The right-hand panel shows an example of the ELF on 2,5 Dimethoxyfuran with evidence of lone pairs and covalent bonds. 
     <span class="italic">Inset</span> a ball-and-stick representation of the molecule (carbon in 
     <span class="italic">brown</span>, oxygen in 
     <span class="italic">red</span>, hydrogen in 
     <span class="italic">white</span>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="10822_2017_42_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e743" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Masunov et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>], for example, introduced a new method to eliminate the spin-contamination in broken symmetry density functional theory calculations. They investigated two complexes of which one had strongly localized magnetic orbitals on which previous spin-contamination eliminate schemes worked well. The other complex had strongly delocalised magnetic orbitals on which previous schemes failed while their new scheme works well. Both restricted and unrestricted natural orbitals were visualized with the help of Molden.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In his landmark article on the free radical catalysis by galactose oxidase, Whittaker [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] used Molden to calculate visualise the crucial SOMO (Singly occupied molecular orbital) to determine at which atom the radical electron is located.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For a newly designed anilate-based material with luminescence properties, for example, the electrostatic potential calculated by Molden was used to strengthen the conclusions from the analyses of the atomic charges [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Atzori et al. wrote: “The isodensity surface mapped with the electrostatic potential shows for all systems that the oxygen atoms are the source of greater negative charge accumulation followed by the nitrogen atom of the CN moiety. Moreover, there is a moderate negative charge accumulation on the carbon atoms linked to the Cl and CN groups, whereas the remaining four carbon atoms, which are linked to the oxygen atoms, exhibit a positive charge. The chlorine atoms present a typical positive charge on the opposite side of the C–Cl vector and a ring of negative charge perpendicular to the same vector” [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hunt et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>] used Molden’s electron density map and Laplacian contour facility to examine charge densities, natural bond orbitals, and delocalised molecular orbitals in ionic liquids to explain the relative acidity of different sites on the imidazolium ring and variation in hydrogen-bond donor and acceptor propensities.
 </p>
</sec>
