<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Visualisation of spectra</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Visualisation of infrared and Raman spectra was already in place at the time of the first Molden paper. This functionality has been expanded with the option to create a html page and auxiliary files, containing an interactive spectrum in combination with an animation of the selected vibration with the jmol viewer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>] An example is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>; see also 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wetche.cmbi.ru.nl/%20calspec/database/0000004/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://wetche.cmbi.ru.nl/ calspec/database/0000004/</span>. A.jdx file of the spectrum is written for use with the jspecview program [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. UV-spectra are constructed and visualized from TD-DFT calculations with Gaussian. 
  <span class="sup">1</span>H and 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR spectra are constructed and visualized when magnetic shielding and J-coupling information is available from the Gaussian output. With a click on the ‘J’ button, the J-coupling between two selected atoms is displayed. The magnetic shielding and J-coupling corresponding with rotationally equivalent hydrogens can be averaged interactively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Interactive spectrum as .html document. Clicking on a peak in the spectrum or in the table underneath the spectrum results in the animation of the associated molecular vibration in the molecular display to the 
     <span class="italic">left</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="10822_2017_42_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e818" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vidal-Iglesias [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], for example, made assignments of the calculated frequencies of monolayers of 4-aminobenzenethiol (4-ABT) on copper, based on the visualisation of the vibrational normal modes and the Surface-Enhanced Raman spectrum (SERS) using Molden. They write “Surface-enhanced raman scattering (SERS) spectra of self-assembled monolayers of 4 aminobenzenethiol (4-ABT) on copper (Cu) and silver (Ag) surfaces decorated with Cu and Ag nanostructures, respectively, have been obtained with lasers at 532, 632.8, 785, and 1064 nm. Density functional theory (DFT) has been used to obtain calculated vibrational frequencies of the 4-ABT and 4,4′-dimercaptoazobenzene (4,4′-DMAB) molecules adsorbed on model Cu surfaces.”
 </p>
</sec>
