<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">IR/UV setup</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental setup for the IR/UV experiments is described in detail elsewhere [
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">29</a>,
  <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">50</a>], thus only a brief description is given here. All experiments were carried out in a molecular beam apparatus consisting of a differentially pumped linear time-of-flight (TOF) mass spectrometer with a pulsed valve (Series 9 and pulse driver Iota One, General Valve, 500 µm orifice) for skimmed jet expansion. PVE was synthesized according to the procedure reported in [
  <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">51</a>] (cf. 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a> for details). MeOH (Sigma-Aldrich, ≥99.7%) and PVE were both supplied via separate cooled reservoirs (approx. −8 °C and −13 °C, respectively) and co-expanded with the carrier gas neon (2.5–3.0 bar).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the one- and two-color R2PI, the IR/R2PI and the UV/IR/UV experiments up to three tunable nanosecond laser systems were necessary, including two independent UV laser systems and one IR laser system. The UV laser radiation is obtained via second harmonic generation in a BBO crystal using the output of a dye laser (Cobra-Stretch and PrecisionScan, Sirah). They are pumped by the second harmonic (532 nm) of a Nd:YAG laser (SpitLight 600 and SpitLight 1000, Innolas). The IR laser radiation in the range of 3520–3750 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> is generated by difference frequency mixing (DFM) in a LiNbO
  <sub>3</sub> crystal using the fundamental (1064 nm) of a seeded Nd:YAG laser (Quanta-Ray Pro-230, Spectra-Physics) and the output of a further dye laser (PrecisionScan, Sirah), which is pumped by the second harmonic (532 nm) of the same Nd:YAG laser. Amplification of the resulting IR radiation is obtained by an optical parametric amplification (OPA) process in a further LiNbO
  <sub>3</sub> crystal using the output of the DFM process and the fundamental (1064 nm) of the Nd:YAG laser.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the IR/R2PI spectra, the IR laser was fired 50 ns prior to the UV excitation laser, whereas for the UV/IR/UV spectra the IR laser was fired 2.0–3.0 ns after the UV excitation laser. The time delay between UV excitation and ionizing laser was 4.0–4.5 ns.</p>
</sec>
