<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary   </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Systematic analysis of recent quantum chemistry data performed in this work confirms, at a qualitative level, the exponential character of the correlations between electron descriptors, such as BO
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>ij</sub>
  </span> or ρ
  <sub>c(
   <span class="italic">ij</span>)
  </sub>, and the length of chemical bonds, 
  <span class="italic">R
   <sub>ij</sub>
  </span>. This character is universal because it is valid for any type of interaction (ionic, covalent 
  <span class="italic">etc.</span>), including metal–metal bonds. It was shown that the BO
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>ij</sub>
  </span>–
  <span class="italic">R
   <sub>ij</sub>
  </span> correlations, based on the quantum chemistry data for a given 
  <span class="italic">i–j</span> atom pair, are very close to those known in crystal chemistry in the framework of the bond valence model (BVM). The difference between them does not exceed the unavoidable dispersion of the quantum chemistry data, arising from the different degree of approximation of the wavefunctions from which they are derived. This result qualitatively confirms the BO conservation principle, which is the basis of the BVM. It also means that proper parameters of exponential correlations can be estimated based on a combination of structural and quantum chemistry data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, the work validates the BVM application to any type of compound, and we hope it will encourage materials scientists to apply the model to compounds with metal–metal bonds. The BVM is based on tabulated bond valence parameters. Our study shows that a similar database of empiric topological parameters, which will relate the ρ
  <sub>c(
   <span class="italic">ij</span>)
  </sub> (and possibly other topological functions) to the interatomic distances, can be created based on a systematic analysis of the literature data. Such a database should allow for prediction of the ED topology in any complex compound.
 </p>
</sec>
