<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Computational methods</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ground state and first excited state electronic structure calculations were completed using GAMESS
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
   </span>. Optimization of ground state geometries and calculation of molecular orbitals were completed with DFT using the B3LYP functional and 6–311 + G(2d,p) basis set. A previous study confirmed the accuracy of this functional and basis set for SEVO and another inhaled anesthetic, halothane
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>. We compared our optimized geometries, ground state dipole moments, and molecular orbitals with previous studies to confirm the accuracy of our calculations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span>. Images of molecular orbitals in Supplementary Figs 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>–
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5</a> were created using wxMacMolPlt
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
   </span>. Electronic properties of the first excited state, including the excitation energy, transition dipole moment, oscillator strength, and TPA cross-section, were completed with TD-DFT using the same functional and basis set.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sevoflurane (C
   <sub>4</sub>H
   <sub>3</sub>F
   <sub>7</sub>O) and isoflurane (C
   <sub>3</sub>H
   <sub>2</sub>ClF
   <sub>5</sub>O) were obtained commercially and used without further purification methods. No impurities were found in their respective mass spectra (See Supplementary Figs 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S6</a>–
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S7</a>). HPLC grade methanol (≥99.9%) and diethyl ether (≥99.9%) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich and used as received.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Steady-state spectroscopy</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UV-Vis absorption spectra (190–900 nm) were measured on an Agilent 8432 UV−visible spectrometer. Fluorescence spectra were collected on a Varian Cary Eclipse fluorimeter. 1.0 cm pathlength quartz cuvettes were used for all measurements.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Classical two-photon excited fluorescence (TPEF)</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The two-photon excited fluorescence technique
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
   </span> was used for the classical two-photon experiments. Our experimental setup has been described elsewhere
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
   </span>. In brief, the pure liquid (or a liquid solution of the compound of interest) contained in a 1 cm path length quartz cuvette is excited with the output beam of a Ti:Sapphire femtosecond pulsed laser (KMLabs, 800 nm, Δt ~30 fs) with a 80 MHz repetition rate. The fluorescence emission was collected at a 90° angle to the excitation beam. Fluorescence emission at a selected wavelength was detected using a monochromator (ORIEL, Cornerstone 130) and a photomultiplier tube (Hamamatsu). The power of the 800 nm excitation beam was changed by using a variable neutral density filter.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Entangled two-photon spectroscopy</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The entangled two-photon spectroscopy technique has been previously described
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span>. A sketch of the experimental setup used in this work is presented in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>. Orthogonally polarized entangled photon pairs were generated by the spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC) process. A 0.5 mm BBO (
   <span class="italic">β</span>-Barium Borate) crystal (type II) is pumped with the second harmonic generation (SHG) beam, 400 nm, of a Ti:Sapphire pulsed laser emitting ~70 fs pulses (MaiTai, Spectra Physics). Entangled photon intensity is varied by changing the pump power on the SPDC crystal with a variable neutral density filter. Transmitted entangled photons are focused onto an avalanche photodiode (SPCM-AQR13, PerkinElmer). Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> shows the complete set-up, previously shown by Harpham 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>.
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Experimental setup used for entangled two-photon spectroscopy.</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47651_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e991" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
