<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Salt-bridge, cation-π, and amide bridge interactions could very frequently occur in proteins because 10 (Arg, Lys, Asp, Glu, Phe, Tyr, Trp, His, Asn and Gln) of the 20 natural amino acids can participate in at least one of these three types of interactions. The very high interaction energies of salt-bridge, cation-π, and amide bridge interactions make these interactions remarkably stronger than other molecular interaction types, such as hydrogen bonds, electrostatic interactions, and van der Waals interactions. These three types of interactions may not be properly described by molecular dynamics (MD) using the currently available force field parameters [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref063">63</a>]. The interaction energies provided in this study are calculated from the optimized structures of amino acid side chains, which may be different from the actual interaction geometries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the natural world, the environments of proteins are very complex. The surfaces of proteins may be exposed to aqueous solution, while hydrophobic pockets inside the proteins may be in environments that, to a certain degree, more closely resemble the gaseous phase. However, the hydrophobic pockets are not completely equivalent to the gaseous phase because of the electrostatic fields formed by the polar groups of aa residues. In this study, the calculated energies in aqueous solution and in vacuo may reveal the limitations of the three types of interactions in different protein environments.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the hydrophobic pockets, the salt-bridge interactions are very strong; however, they are weaker than the salt-bridge interactions in vacuo because of the electrostatic field produced by polar sidechains. Further, the salt-bridge bonds are weakened in aqueous solution and may be broken in acidic conditions. The cation-π and amide bridge interactions are less affected by solvation and pH conditions. Generally speaking, the aromatic amino acids (Phe, Tyr, Trp and His) are hydrophobic residues to a certain degree, and the amino acid cations (Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span> Lys
  <span class="sup">+</span> and His
  <span class="sup">+</span>) are hydrophilic residues. Therefore, cation-π interactions could occur at hydrophobic and hydrophilic interfaces. The salt-bridge, cation-π, and amide bridge interactions often play important roles in protein-protein, protein-peptide, and protein-ligand interactions.
 </p>
</sec>
