<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The binding sites of amantadine in M2 proton channel</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The binding sites of amantadine in the M2 proton channel [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref026">26</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref027">27</a>] of the influenza A virus has drawn great attention and stimulated broad discussion among many authors [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref067">67</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref070">70</a>]. The structure of the channel and four of its particularly important residues (Ser-31, His-37, Trp-41, and Asp-44) is shown in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g005">Fig 5A</a>
  </span>. The general conclusion of previous studies [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref067">67</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref068">68</a>] is that the amantadine binding location could be inside the pore of the M2 channel or outside the M2 channel on a lipid-facing side, depending on the ligand concentration and the dynamic steps [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref067">67</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref068">68</a>].
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0137113.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0137113.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The structure of the M2 proton channel of influenza A virus (PDB code: 2RLF).</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">A)</span> Possible binding sites (Ser-31, His-37, Trp-41, and Asp-44) of amantadine. 
    <span class="bold">B)</span> The cation-π interaction between amantadine and His-37 in M2 proton channel. 
    <span class="bold">C)</span> The salt-bridge interaction between amantadine and Asp-44. 
    <span class="bold">D)</span> The cation-π interaction between amantadine and Trp-41.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0137113.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the amantadine enters the channel pore, the best binding sites are the four His-37 residues, which form stable cation-π interactions with the amine group (NH
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span>) of amantadine. When the amantadine ligand binds to the outside of the M2 channel near the gate of the channel, a favored binding site is the Asp-44, where the NH
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span> of amantadine and the anionic Asp
  <span class="sup">−</span>-44 form a very stable salt-bridge, as shown in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g005">Fig 5C</a>
  </span>. The salt-bridge interaction energy between Asp
  <span class="sup">-</span> and amantadine could reach -70 to -500 kJ/mol, depending on the solvation environment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The M2 protein is a proton channel. In acidic conditions, the salt bridge between amantadine and Asp-44 is at risk of being broken. When it does break, the amantadine may come into the channel and form a cation-π bond with Trp-41. According to MP2/6–311+G(d,p) calculations, the cation-π interaction energy between amantadine and the Trp-41 is -78.70 kJ/mol [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref069">69</a>] in the gaseous phase. However, in an aqueous solution, this cation-π interaction energy may decrease to -13.27 kJ/mol. In 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g005">Fig 5</a>,
  </span> the salt-bridge and cation-π interactions are indicated by yellow cycles.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently, in almost 95% of the cases where the influenza A virus is encountered, the virus has the S31N mutation that confers drug resistance. There is a silver lining to the nearly ubiquitous presence of this mutated Asn-31residue. It may provide a good binding site for inhibitor design; new inhibitors could bind at Asn-31 through amide bridge interactions.</p>
</sec>
