<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inhibitor design targeting neuraminidase of influenza A virus</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the design of drugs that target host proteins, salt-bridge interactions may play a very important role and often account for a large portion of the binding free energies. Oseltamivir and zanamivir were designed based on the neuraminidase (NA) structure (1F8B) of the influenza A virus [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref070">70</a>]. The structure of NA 1F8B is shown in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g006">Fig 6A</a>
  </span> and features a ligand located in a pocket consisting of 17 residues (Ala118, Leu119, Asn151, Ser152, Leu156, Pro178, Ser198, Met222, Asp224, Ser246, Val247, Trp276, Tyr292, Ile294, Gln371, Leu406, and Phe425). In ref [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref071">71</a>], 49 drugs and ligands (including oseltamivir and zanamivir) are aligned and docked with the neuraminidase (1F8B), as shown in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g006">Fig 6B</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0137113.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0137113.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The neuraminidase (NA) structure of influenza A virus (PDB code: 1F8B).</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">A)</span> The binding pocket for ligands in the neuraminidase (NA) of influenza A virus. The hydrophobic pocket consists of 17 residues (Ala118, Leu119, Asn151, Ser152, Leu156, Pro178, Ser198, Met222, Asp224, Ser246, Val247, Trp276, Tyr292, Ile294, Gln371, Leu406, and Phe425). 
    <span class="bold">B)</span> The docking structure and salt-bridge interactions of 49 drugs (or ligands) in the binding pocket of neuraminidase (1F8B). There is a formal salt-bridge between the carboxyl group (–COO
    <span class="sup">-</span>) of the ligands and the residue Arg
    <span class="sup">+</span>-371. The other two arginine residues (Arg
    <span class="sup">+</span>-118 and Arg
    <span class="sup">+</span>-292) are on either side of the carboxyl group (–COO
    <span class="sup">-</span>), forming two partial salt-bridge bonds with the oxygen atoms of the carboxyl group. The three salt-bridge bonds are indicated by yellow circles.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0137113.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the docking structure, all 49 of the ligands possess the same pharmacophore, the carboxyl group (COO
  <span class="sup">-</span>), which is surrounded by three arginine residues (Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span>-118, Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span>-292, and Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span>-371). Between the pharmacophore (COO
  <span class="sup">-</span>) and the Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span>-371 residue, there is a very strong salt-bridge bond, and the distances between the two oxygen atoms of the carboxyl group (COO
  <span class="sup">-</span>) and the two—NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups of Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span>-371 are 1.72 Å and 1.63 Å, respectively. The interaction energy of the salt-bridge could be as high as-526 kJ/mol in the gaseous phase. The other two arginine residues (Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span>-118 and Arg
  <span class="sup">+</span>-292) are on either side of the carboxyl group (COO
  <span class="sup">-</span>), forming two partial salt-bridge bonds with the two oxygen atoms of the carboxyl group. The three salt-bridge bonds are indicated by yellow circles in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g006">Fig 6B</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
