<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Binding site of amantadine in the HCV p7 ion channel</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The NMR solution structure of the p7 ion channel (PDB code: 2M6X) of the hepatitis C virus (HCV) was first solved by Chou and his colleagues [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref030">30</a>]. In the p7 channel, there are six similar hydrophobic pockets between the peripheral and the pore-forming helices, consisting of Leu-52, Val-53, Leu-55, and Leu-56 from H3 and Phe-20, Val-25, and Val-26 from H2 [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref030">30</a>]. The ligand amantadine is located in the hydrophobic pockets, as shown in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g007" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g007">Fig 7A</a>
  </span>. In the binding location described by Chou and colleagues, the pharmacophore group (NH
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span>) of the amantadine points to the aromatic indole ring of Trp-21, forming a stable cation-π bond (indicated by light green dished line), as shown in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g007" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g007">Fig 7B</a>
  </span>. The binding energy of the cation-π interaction could be -86.41 kJ/mol in the hydrophobic pocket, where the environment is similar to the gaseous phase.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0137113.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0137113.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The structure and binding sites of amantadine in p7 ion channel (PDB code: 2M6X) of the hepatitis C virus (HCV).</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">A)</span> In the p7 channel, the ligand amantadine is in the six hydrophobic pockets consisting of Leu 52, Val 53, Leu55, and Leu 56 from H3 and Phe 20, Val 25, and Val 26 from H2. The hydrophobic residues are shown in green and Trp-21 is shown in white lines. 
    <span class="bold">B)</span> The cation-π interaction between the NH
    <sub>3</sub>
    <span class="sup">+</span> group of amantadine and the aromatic indole ring of Trp-21. When Leu20 is replaced by Phe20 (yellow color), the ammonium group (NH
    <sub>3</sub>
    <span class="sup">+</span>) of amantadine may shift its orientation and form a cation-π bond with Phe20. This mayreasonably explain the Leu20Phe mutation that confers drug resistance in some p7 channel subtypes. 
    <span class="bold">C)</span> The molecular orbital (MO) of the cation-π interaction between the NH
    <sub>3</sub>
    <span class="sup">+</span> group and the aromatic indole ring. The cation perpendicularly points to the π-plane.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0137113.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the structure of the p7 channel protein 2M6X, the Phe-20 (yellow ball-stick drawing in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0137113.g007" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0137113.g007">Fig 7B</a>
  </span>) is a mutated residue that replaces the original Leu-20, which is a drug-resistant mutation, as identified in clinical trials [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref072">72</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref074">74</a>]. When the Leu-20 is replaced by Phe-20, the ammonium group (NH
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span>) of amantadine may reorient itself, allowing it to make a cation-π bond with Phe-20. The cation-π energy of the interaction of amantadine with Phe (-60.28 kJ/mol) is smaller than that of the interaction of amantadine with Trp (-86.41 kJ/mol). However, in some subtypes of the p7 channel the position of Phe-20 may be more favorable than that of Trp-21. This may give a reasonable explanation for the drug-resistant Leu20Phe mutation in some p7 channel subtypes.
 </p>
</sec>
