<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The twenty natural amino acids (abbreviated as aa), which are characterized by their unique side chains, are the building blocks of proteins and peptides [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref005">5</a>]. Consequently, the interactions between aa side chains are the dominant factors in determining protein structures and interactions. These aa interactions are responsible for protein recognition [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref006">6</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref007">7</a>], protein folding [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref008">8</a>], protein-protein and protein-peptide interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref010">10</a>], protein-ligand docking [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref011">11</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref012">12</a>], protein-DNA (or RNA) interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref013">13</a>], and information transmission by signal peptides in protein metabolism [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref015">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the structural diversity of the 20 amino acid side chains, the aa side chain interactions exhibit very different energetic contributions and physical properties, which cannot be explained simply by the familiar interaction types, such as hydrogen bonds [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref016">16</a>], van der Waals interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref017">17</a>], electrostatic interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref018">18</a>], and hydrophobic interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref019">19</a>]. In protein chemistry, hydrogen bonds that have energies in the range of 8 to 30 kJ/mol [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref021">21</a>] are considered to be strong interactions. However, some aa side chain interactions in different aa pairs may be remarkably stronger than (or comparable to) hydrogen bonds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strong aa interactions, other than common hydrogen bonds, include salt bridge, cation-π, and amide bridge interactions, which often play important roles in protein-protein and protein-ligand interactions. For example, salt bridge interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref022">22</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref024">24</a>] play important role in the amyloid-beta plaque growth of Alzheimer’s and related diseases, and in oseltamivir–neuraminidase binding interaction of M2 proton channel in the influenza A virus [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref025">25</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref027">27</a>]. The cation-π interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref029">29</a>] make main energetic contribution in the binding interaction between the ammonium group (NH
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span>) of amantadine and the aromatic residue Trp-21 in the p7 ion channel [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref030">30</a>] of HCV (hepatitis C virus).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study the three strong aa side chain interaction types (salt bridge, cation-π, and amide bridge interactions) are theoretically studied. The energies of the three types of aa interactions are calculated in the gaseous phase and in aqueous solutions using high level quantum chemical methods and basis sets. Three typical examples of aa side chain interactions in drug design are analyzed based on the theoretical study results, including the inhibitor design targeting the neuraminidase (NA) [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref025">25</a>] of the influenza A virus, the M2 proton channel protein [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref026">26</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref027">27</a>] of the influenza A virus, and the p7 ion channel protein [
  <a rid="pone.0137113.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0137113.ref030">30</a>] of the hepatitis C virus (HCV).
 </p>
</sec>
