<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lanthanum complexes find their usage as catalysts, for example, in the transesterification of triglycerides to monoesters [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref001">1</a>], important in the making of biodiesel fuel, in the synthesis of novel antioxidants with high superoxide scavenging activity [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref002">2</a>], in asymmetric epoxidation reactions [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref003">3</a>], in P
  <sub>4</sub> activation by lanthanum naphthalene complex [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref004">4</a>], etc. Furthermore, lanthanum complexes may serve as extreme pressure lubrication additives in paraffin oil [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref005">5</a>], they may display pH sensitivity [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref006">6</a>], and are of interest to studies on chelator design [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref007">7</a>] and polymer build up [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref008">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cerium(III) complexes display low toxicity when compared to other lanthanide ions and are, for example, of interest in the design of new drugs targeting DNA [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref009">9</a>]. They, of course, may also be used as catalysts, for example in the catalytic cleavage of phosphate esters, an important reaction which mimetizes the hydrolytic cleavage of DNA [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref010">10</a>]. Also, due to the relative ease by which they can convert to Ce(IV), Ce(III) complexes may act as antioxidation agents, for example, as a hydroxyl radical quencher in fuel cell electrolyte membranes [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref011">11</a>]. The structure of novel Ce(III) complexes are also thoroughly studied due to their several potential applications [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref012">12</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref013">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 4f
  <span class="sup">2</span> electronic configuration of Pr(III) gives rise to a series of electronic states, and therefore luminescence of Pr(III) covers a wide range of wavelengths, ranging from the ultraviolet to the near infrared. However, Pr(III) luminescence is rarely observed in the visible region[
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref014">14</a>]–the most important use of Pr(III) complexes in luminescent and electroluminescent devices being as near infrared emitters [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref015">15</a>]. Biological activities of praseodymium complexes have also been observed due to their substantial affinities for many biomolecules, as are the cases of DNA-binding [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref016">16</a>] and their presence in Schiff-base complexes [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref017">17</a>]. Further, the large variety of architectures of Pr(III) complexes have been receiving continued interest, as novel complexes are being reported [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref018">18</a>], including a complex of Pr(III) with organofluorotitanate ligands with coordination number 12 [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref019">19</a>]. Furthermore, larger clusters are being prepared, as is the case of the tetramer [Pr
  <sub>4</sub>Cl
  <sub>10</sub>(OH)
  <sub>2</sub>(thiazole)
  <sub>8</sub>(H
  <sub>2</sub>O)
  <sub>2</sub>], the first thiazole complex of a lanthanide ion reported [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref020">20</a>], and of the three-dimensional 5-aminoisophtalate Pr(III) polymeric complex which presents good gas storage capabilities [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref021">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, the theoretical modeling of complexes of La(III), Ce(III), and Pr(III) is an open area of research, important for the selection of ligands, of counter ions, of specific coordination geometries, of metal to ligand ratios, of polymer framework topologies, of thermal and photostability, for the fine tuning of optical and magnetic properties, and so on.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previously, our research group introduced the Sparkle Model [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref023">23</a>], originally to allow the calculation of Eu(III) complexes within the semiempirical AM1 model [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref024">24</a>], together with a prescription to compute the UV-Visible electronic spectra of the complexes using another semiempirical model, INDO/S [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref025">25</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref028">28</a>]. The model was then successfully applied to the design of luminescent Eu(III) complexes [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref029">29</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref032">32</a>] and proven useful for the prediction of ligand field parameters [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref033">33</a>]. In 2004, we introduced Gaussian functions in the core-core repulsion of our sparkle model in order to make it consistent with AM1, something that greatly improved the accuracy of the model [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref034">34</a>]. Thus, in 2005 we introduced the new model, we called Sparkle/AM1 for all trivalent lanthanide ions [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref035">35</a>]. Since then, we have further introduced the Sparkle Model for La (III), Ce (III), and Pr (III) for PM3 [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref036">36</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref038">38</a>], for PM6 [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref039">39</a>], for PM7 [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref040">40</a>], and RM1 [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref041">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sparkle model proved very accurate for more ionic bonds of the hard-hard type, such as the cases of directly coordinated oxygen and nitrogen atoms. However, the sparkle model fails when other types of atoms are directly coordinated to the lanthanide ion, as is the cases of carbon, sulfur, and the heavier halogens.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to be able to address all types of bonds between the central trivalent lanthanide ion and its ligands, we introduced in 2013 a new and more perfected model, we called the RM1 model for the lanthanides, and presented parameters for Eu(III), Gd(III), Tb(III) [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref042">42</a>], Dy(III), Ho(III), and Er(III) [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref043">43</a>]. In this model, we considered the lanthanide ion to be a regular neutral atom within RM1 [
  <a rid="pone.0124372.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124372.ref044">44</a>] where the semiempirical core represents the electronic configuration [Xe]4f
  <span class="sup">n</span>, with n varying from 0 for La (III) to 14 for Lu (III), and we add three electrons to a valence shell comprised of the semiempirical atomic orbitals 5d, 6s, and 6p. This new RM1 model for the lanthanides proved to be very general and capable of much more accurately describing the multitude of different bonds that show up in lanthanide chemistry.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present article, we further extend the RM1 model for the lanthanides to complexes of La(III), Ce(III), and Pr(III).</p>
</sec>
