<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions and further works</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herein, we have shown that re-occurring tasks in Quantum Chemistry scientific experiments can be facilitated by re-using and sharing workflows. We introduce and formally describe the concept of the atomic workflow. Atomic workflows represent basic operations for example optimization, frequency calculation, population analysis, etc. in Quantum Chemistry. Since these operations are performed in multiple scientific experiments they can be shared among these experiments. We also propose to build workflow libraries that manage and publish atomic workflows. Workflow libraries are domain specific, i.e. each scientific domain may have its own workflow library with several sub-domains. Having atomic workflows researchers can combine them into complex workflows called meta-workflows. We propose to use atomic workflows as building blocks for complex meta
  <span class="sup">n</span>-workflows. We extend the existing formal description of meta-workflows to support sharing atomic workflows incorporating them into meta-workflows. The Quantum Chemistry uses among others the WS-PGRADE workflow systems to create workflows and run scientific workflows through science gateways such as the MoSGrid Portal and the SHIWA Portal. We developed and formalized a template based approach to create WS-PGRADE meta-workflows to incorporate atomic workflows. Chemists, who become acquainted to workflows, can apply this technology to scientific problems. The work of dissecting a chemical theoretical problem into basic operations and defining the relevant atomic workflows is illustrated by spectroscopic analysis, optical and structural benchmarking and inorganic polymerization catalysis analysis workflows. We have created and uploaded 26 atomic workflows into the Quantum Chemistry workflow library that contains five sub-domains. We incorporated these atomic workflows into 12 meta-workflows. Considering developing atomic workflows and incorporating them into meta-workflows we can conclude that the re-use of the atomic workflows significantly decreases the efforts and time needed for creating scientific experiments. As a result, it makes the research more efficient. In future work, we plan to apply this concept to more complex scientific experiments where input preparation and output parsing is more involved
 </p>
</sec>
