<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Example 2: Screening Absorption Characteristics of Organic Molecules</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the following example a series of organic chromophores is screened to select molecules with absorption wavelength in a desired range. As a simple criterion for a first selection we calculate the DFT HOMO–LUMO gap. The set of molecules is taken from the chemical database GDB-17,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22" href="#ref22">22</a>
  </span> which provides structures in 
  <span class="italic">SMILES</span> format. The flowchart and the workflow to carry out this screening is illustrated in 
  <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">Figure 
   <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">3</a>
  </a>.
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>QMflows workflow for a multilevel geometry optimization followed by an excited states calculation on the relaxed structure. The QMflows actions are highlighted in red, while the results of the action are highlighted in green.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ci-2019-00384y_0003" id="gr3" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, the 
  <span class="italic">SMILES</span> strings representing the target molecules are converted to 3D chemical structures using Molkit. For each molecule, an initial geometry optimization is performed using the computationally inexpensive DFTB method followed by a single point DFT calculation with the SAOP functional. The HOMO and LUMO energies are extracted, and the best performing candidates, those with HOMO–LUMO gaps within the desired energy range, are selected for further study by DFT structure optimization and TD-DFT calculation of the lowest excited states. This workflow illustrates manipulation of structures, extraction of selected data, and workflows in which the number of jobs is determined at runtime. The full code is provided in 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jcim.9b00384/suppl_file/ci9b00384_si_001.pdf" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Example S2</span> in the Supporting Information. Notice that there are no dependencies between the calculations for different molecules, and this fact is automatically picked by Noodles that generates a dependency graph where the jobs of different molecules are independent from each other and therefore are marked to run in parallel.
 </p>
</sec>
