<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FTIR spectra</div>
 <p id="p0130" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Drug-Protein interaction and conformational changes can be interpreted from FTIR spectra as depicted in 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a>. Infrared spectra were taken employing diffuse reflectance accessory with Deuterium triglycine sulphate (DTGS) detector at resolution of 4 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. The infrared spectrum of pure BSA and HSA and their interaction with one of the drug, AMT has been shown in 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a>. The protein structures have been studied and interpreted through the various amide groups in peptide group, however, of all the amide modes the amide I is most widely studied. The I and II peak of amide have been occurred at the range of 1500–1600 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and 1600-1700 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively. For the significant study of secondary structure of proteins enlighten more usefulness of amide band I. Hence amide bond is more sensitive to the changes in the secondary structure of protein [
  <a rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib50">50</a>, 
  <a rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib51">51</a>].
  <div id="fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>FTIR spectra of (a) BSA and (b) HSA with antidepressant drug AMT and CDs at pH 7.4.</p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0030" class="alt-text">Fig. 5</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0135" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the stretching of the C=O bonds, the protein amide I bond is observed at 1655 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and the amide II bond, due to the coupled interaction of C–N stretching and N–H bending is observed at 1549 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. It is evident from the figure that the proteins amide I band appeared at FTIR spectrum of free HSA and BSA in phosphate buffer solution and the difference absorption spectra upon binding with antidepressant drug are given in 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a> for (A) BSA and for (B) HSA respectively. It shows that the peak position of amide I was shifted from 1670 to 1643.1 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in HSA-Drug system, while that of amide II was shifted from 1554.4 to 1567.8 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in HSA-Drug systems. These data shows the antidepressants drug has interacted with both serum albumins and the secondary structural changes leading to conformational changes.
 </p>
</sec>
