<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="p0010" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fluorescent carbon nanodots have received increasing attention in a wide variety of analytical and biomedical applications owing to their outstanding properties such as minimal toxicity, superior biocompatibility, tunable photoluminescence and good water solubility [
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">4</a>]. The binding mechanism of proteins with ligands from last few years have shed light on different areas of research and its important applications in numerous fields of science, such as the development of new biomaterials, biochemistry, food chemistry or pharmaceutical sciences [
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">6</a>, 
  <a rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib7">7</a>, 
  <a rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">9</a>, 
  <a rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib10">10</a>]. The nature of interaction between the drug molecule and protein gives new opportunity for the development of new drugs. Since drugs are the compounds which are carried by albumin, it is necessary to study the interaction of new drug with protein [
  <a rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib11">11</a>, 
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">13</a>, 
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib15">15</a>]. Serum albumins are a model globular protein which play a key role for acting as a carrier for several endogenous compounds. It has proved the most valuable invented globular proteins, used for transportation and metabolism of many biologically active compounds in the body [
  <a rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib16">16</a>, 
  <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">17</a>, 
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="p0015" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Serum albumin has a well-established structure, having physicochemical properties, a versatile binding capacity stability and water solubility [
  <a rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19">19</a>, 
  <a rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib20">20</a>]. In the present scenario bovine serum albumin (BSA) has created an extensive area of research because of its presence in blood plasma of animals. It consist a single polypeptide chain of 583 amino acids and contains 17 cysteine residues (eight disulfide bonds and one free thiol). It is divided into three specific binding sites (I, II and III) for high-affinity of drugs. Every sites is consists of two subdomains (A and B). Human serum albumin (HSA) contributes about 80% of the osmotic pressure of blood [
  <a rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">22</a>]. It bears residue of 585 amino acids with molar mass of 66,411 g mol
  <span class="sup">-1</span> having 17 disulfide bridges and free thiol (SH) group. Moreover, HSA consist of single tryptophan (TRP 214) present in subdomain IIA [
  <a rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib23">23</a>, 
  <a rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib24">24</a>, 
  <a rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib25">25</a>]. The theme has a better insight for research fields such as clinical medicine, chemistry and life sciences.
 </p>
 <p id="p0020" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A tricyclic antidepressant drug (TCA) category of drug amitryptiline hydrocloride (N,N-dimethyl-3-(2-tricyclo [9.4.0.03,8]pentadeca-1 (15),3,5,7,11,13-hexaenylidene)propan-1-amine; hydrochloride), desipramine hydrochloride (3-(10,11-dihydro-5H-dibenzo [b,f]azepin-5-yl)-N-methylpropan-1-amine; hydrochloride) achlorpromazine hydrochloride (3-(2-chlorophenothiazin-10-yl)-N,N-dimethylpropan-1-amine; hydrochloride) has been widely used to treat major depression sickness, manic disorder and also for schizophrenia [
  <a rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib26">26</a>, 
  <a rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib27">27</a>, 
  <a rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib28">28</a>, 
  <a rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib29">29</a>]. The outcomes of the study of interaction of drug with SA and plasma of human or living tissue for diagnosing disease, controlling the amount of drug, obtaining optimum therapeutic concentration, controlling its side effects, evaluating the stability as well as the toxicology of the drug and complications of drug abuse.
 </p>
 <p id="p0025" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Shahabadi et al. 
  <a rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib29">[29]</a> observed the interaction of venlafaxin hydrochloride with bovine serum albumin (VEN-BSA) and revealed that the Stern-Volmer quenching constant 
  <span class="italic">K</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">sv</span>
  </sub> is inversely correlated together with temperature and concentration. This suggests the probable quenching mechanism of binding reaction which is initiated due to complex formation. Field et al. 
  <a rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib30">[30]</a> studied a development of quantum dots (QD) based-protein bioconjugate that provides for extracellular control of multicomponent drug release system. These results confirmed by time-resolved measurements of the QD donor excited state lifetime before and after maltose-induced conjugate release. Chamani and his co-workers 
  <a rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib31">[31]</a> reported the binding of ciprofloxacin to human serum albumin (HSA) in the presence and absence of silver nanoparticles of three sizes as well as their various behaviors in drug delivery. These consists of, for example, the use of incident excitation light for the photocleavage of labile linkers and the application of magnetic, ultrasonic, or radiofrequency fields to facilitate drug release from properly sensitive nanocarriers. However, these drug release modalities are not without their margins [
  <a rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib33">33</a>, 
  <a rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib34">34</a>]. The current researchers established that control intracellular release of drug cargos from nanobioconjugate carrier is critical for the successful implementation of nanoparticle (NP)-mediated drug delivery (NMDD) [
  <a rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib35">35</a>, 
  <a rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib36">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="p0030" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In biophysical research, the most important idea is the interaction of drug molecule with biological molecule. Studies on drug-protein interaction are important in pharmacology and pharmacokinetics. Generally, the binding nature of drug-albumins is dynamic and reversible [
  <a rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib37">37</a>, 
  <a rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib38">38</a>, 
  <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">39</a>, 
  <a rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib40">40</a>]. We have already reported in previous paper [
  <a rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib41">41</a>, 
  <a rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib42">42</a>, 
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">43</a>] the interaction of serum albumins with fluorescent carbon quantum dots, surfactants and antidepressant drugs by surface tensiometer, conductivity meter and spectroscopic techniques. Herein, the present investigation focused on the interaction of serum albumins (
  <a rid="sch1" ref-type="fig" href="#sch1">Scheme 1</a>) with antidepressant drugs (
  <a rid="sch2" ref-type="fig" href="#sch2">Scheme 2</a>) in absence and presence of carbon quantum dots (CDs). The carbon quantum dots (CDs) synthesized by one-pot method using PEG (Polyethylene glycol-200) and glucose. The analysis of binding of different ligands with protein using multispectroscopic techniques such as fluorescence measurement, UV-Vis absorption, dynamic light scattering (DLS) and Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FT-IR), which have high sensitivity, reproducibility, cost effective and convenience. It plays emphasis role on the special binding site and the effect of antidepressant drugs on the secondary structure of serum albumins.
  <div id="sch1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Scheme 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structure of serum albumins (Source – 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/" id="intref0015" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.rcsb.org/</span>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0040" class="alt-text">Scheme 1</span>
   <div xlink:href="sc1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="sch2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Scheme 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structure of drugs.</p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0045" class="alt-text">Scheme 2</span>
   <div xlink:href="sc2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
