<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijms-20-03227" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alkynes are important intermediates during the oxidation of hydrocarbon fuels, and they are critical initiation species towards soot formation [
  <a rid="B1-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijms-20-03227">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijms-20-03227">2</a>]. The development of a detailed combustion mechanism to predict the combustion properties of alkynes and soot formation requires a better understanding of the reactivity of alkyne molecules, especially the alkyne molecules with phenyl group. In combustion reaction systems, hydrogen (H) and hydroxy (OH) radicals are usually the most abundant radicals [
  <a rid="B3-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijms-20-03227">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijms-20-03227">4</a>], and the hydrogen abstraction reactions of alkynes by H and OH radicals play a critical role in understanding the reactivity of alkyne molecules among various reaction pathways. In addition, the activation of alkyne molecules is also a challenging area in organic chemistry [
  <a rid="B5-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijms-20-03227">5</a>]. A better understanding of the reactivity of these molecules based on theoretical chemical calculations is also fundamental to organic chemistry.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For alkyne molecules, H-atom abstraction from the acetylenic sites can be ignored due to the large bond dissociation energies (BDEs) [
  <a rid="B6-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijms-20-03227">6</a>]. However, abstraction from the propargyl C-H sites forming resonance-stabilized propargyl radicals is believed to be an important step in the formation of large Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAHs) and soot [
  <a rid="B2-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijms-20-03227">2</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijms-20-03227">4</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijms-20-03227">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijms-20-03227">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijms-20-03227">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijms-20-03227">10</a>]. Hence, understanding the underlying chemistry and obtaining accurate rate constants for these abstraction reactions are fundamental to understand the combustion properties of alkynes and soot formation and develop reliable detailed combustion mechanisms. However, limited research has been carried out for the abstraction reactions of alkynes and most studies for alkynes are still limited to propyne.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Miller et al. analyzed the reaction of H with propyne based on a C
  <sub>3</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub> potential and found that the abstraction reaction channel at the propargyl C-H site is also important, especially at high temperatures [
  <a rid="B11-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijms-20-03227">11</a>]. They also compared the computed results with experiment by Bentz et al. [
  <a rid="B12-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijms-20-03227">12</a>] and good agreement was obtained. Rosado-Reyes et al. studied the thermal reaction of H atoms with propyne in a heated single pulse-shock tube and derived rate constants for H-atom attack on propyne [
  <a rid="B13-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijms-20-03227">13</a>]. Hansen et al. [
  <a rid="B14-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijms-20-03227">14</a>] incorporated the rate constants obtained by Miller et al. [
  <a rid="B11-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijms-20-03227">11</a>] to understand the isomer-specific combustion chemistry in allene and propyne flames and proposed that implementing the accurate theoretical results for important reactions is critical for an accurate prediction of combustion properties. Zádor and Miller used the KinBot software to explore the potential energy surfaces for OH + allene and OH + propyne reactions systematically [
  <a rid="B15-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijms-20-03227">15</a>]. It was demonstrated that the major channel of these bimolecular reactions at high temperatures is the abstraction reactions to the formation of propargyl and H
  <sub>2</sub>O, also indicating the studied reaction systems are very important for soot formation at high temperatures. In addition, Senosiain et al. performed a theoretical study of diacetylene with OH radicals and found that direct abstraction reaction channels for alkyne molecules are very important [
  <a rid="B16-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijms-20-03227">16</a>]. Besides these typical studies on allene/propyne and diacetylene, few studies have been performed on larger alkyne molecules. Systematic studies on structure and reaction site effect on energy barriers and rate constants for the H-atom abstraction reactions at the propargyl sites of alkynes are badly needed to develop accurate detailed combustion mechanisms.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the above considerations, in this study, we employ high-level ab initio methods together with transition state theory to study the hydrogen abstraction reactions by H and OH radicals for a series of alkynes with different structural propargyl C-H sites. To obtain accurate reaction barriers and enthalpies for large reaction systems studied in this work, the high-level W1BD [
  <a rid="B17-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijms-20-03227">17</a>] and CCSD(T)/CBS [
  <a rid="B18-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijms-20-03227">18</a>] methods are used as benchmark methods for small systems to select a proper DFT method for large reactions. The rate constants are computed based on quantum chemistry calculations. The structure and reaction site effect on the energies and rate constants for the abstraction reactions at propargyl C-H sites are systematically investigated.
 </p>
</sec>
