<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot1-ijms-20-03227" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Geometry Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f001" href="#ijms-20-03227-f001">Figure 1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f002" href="#ijms-20-03227-f002">Figure 2</a> depict the optimized transition state structures at M06-2X/cc-pVTZ level of theory. It should be noted that the lowest energy conformation for each species is obtained by scanning all the relevant internal rotational degrees of freedom and then the global minimum point is used for optimization. As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f001" href="#ijms-20-03227-f001">Figure 1</a>, the C-H bond breaking along the reaction coordinate are elongated from an averaged value of 1.09 Å to an averaged value of 1.24 Å and the angles of C-H-H between the breaking C-H bond and the forming H-H bond are near-linear.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unlike the simple TS structures for H-atom abstraction reactions of alkynes by H atoms at the propargyl reaction sites, the TS structures of abstraction reactions by OH radical are more complex due to the interaction of oxygen atom with other functional groups in the reactant molecules. For the studied reactants of propyne, 1-butyne, 1-pentyne, penta-1,4-diyne, 4-penten-1-yne, and isopentyne, the OH radical is nearly parallel along the C≡C triplet bond of the reactants. However, for 3-phenyl-1-propyne and but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene, the OH radical tends to locate above the benzene ring and the OH radical is nearly parallel along the C-C bond connecting the phenyl group.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To further confirm the minimal structures corresponding to the global minima, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f003" href="#ijms-20-03227-f003">Figure 3</a> shows the hindrance potential of relaxed scans of the internal rotation of H atom in OH radical for 1-butyne, 4-penten-1-yne, and 3-phenyl-1-propyne. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f004" href="#ijms-20-03227-f004">Figure 4</a> illustrates the Mulliken charge distributions [
  <a rid="B19-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijms-20-03227">19</a>] of the TSs for these three reactions. The relative energies between the highest and lowest structures are computed at the CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ level of theory to validate the scanned results at the M06-2X/cc-pVTZ level of theory. It has been verified that the two theoretical methods can give similar energy curves and the deviations between CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ and M06-2X/cc-pVTZ are within 0.5 kcal mol
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f004" href="#ijms-20-03227-f004">Figure 4</a>, for the TS of H-abstraction reaction of 1-butyne by OH radical, the energy difference between the lowest and highest energy conformations is 1.23 kcal mol
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. The negative charge distributions of the two carbon atoms in the C≡C triplet bond attract the H atom in OH radical pointing to the C≡C triplet bond resulting in the O–H bond parallel to the C≡C triplet bond. The energy difference between the lowest and highest energy conformations for 4-penten-1-yne and 3-phenyl-1-propyne are 1.48 and 1.46 kcal mol
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, respectively. The charge distribution of the C atom near the propargyl site in the C=C double bond (−0.062) is slightly large than that in the C≡C triplet bond (−0.086), which makes the OH radical toward parallel to the C≡C triplet bond. However, the strong negative charge distributions of phenyl group in 3-phenyl-1-propyne attract the OH radical shifting toward the aromatic ring to form a more stable TS structure.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f003" href="#ijms-20-03227-f003">Figure 3</a>, the most unstable TS structures of these three reactants are found when the H atom in OH radical shifts toward the opposite sites along the C≡C triplet bond. Similar trend is observed for the other reaction systems. Based on the above analysis, it can be concluded that the formation of the lowest energy conformations of the TSs for the studied reaction systems are mainly affected through the electron-withdrawing inductive effect by the surrounding groups around the reactivity center. Specifically, the lone pair of electrons of oxygen atom are attracted by the conjugated π-system of phenyl group which is similar to the mesomeric effect. Since the electron-withdrawing inductive effect (-
  <span class="italic">I</span> effect) of phenyl group is stronger than C=C double bond and C≡C triplet bond, the OH radical prefers to shift toward the aromatic ring to form a more stable TS structure. In addition, the delocalization effect of the C=C double bond of 4-penten-1-yne is less competitive compared with the C≡C triplet bond, the TS structure of the former is expected to be less stable. Furthermore, due to the interaction between the reactants and OH radical, reactant complexes (RCs) and product complexes (PCs) are formed via weakly hydrogen bond and IRC analysis results are adopted to determine the geometries of these complexes. The optimized geometries are provided as 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-20-03227" href="#app1-ijms-20-03227">Supplementary Materials</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
