<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec4-ijms-20-03227" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This work reports a systematic ab initio and chemical kinetic study of H-abstraction reactions from a series of alkyne molecules by H and OH radicals at the propargyl C-H site. Different types of propargyl C-H sites and the effect of methyl, ethyl, vinyl, phenyl and acetylenic groups in the studied alkyne molecules on reaction reactivity are considered. Geometry optimizations for all species are performed at M06-2X/cc-pVTZ level of theory and each optimized geometry is confirmed to be the lowest energy conformation by scanning all the relevant internal rotational degrees of freedom. It is found that the TS structures of the H-abstraction reactions by H radical are similar, while the existence of vinyl, phenyl and acetylenic groups greatly affects the TS structures of the H-abstraction reactions by OH radical due to the electron-withdrawing inductive effect.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To obtain reliable energy information, accurate W1BD and CCSD(T)/CBS methods are used as benchmark for small reaction systems toward the selection of accurate DFT functionals for large reaction systems. The effect of basis set during DFT calculations are considered and it is found that the M08-HX/cc-pVTZ method exhibits better performance among the selected DFT functionals. General trends of the reaction barriers of the H-abstraction reactions from these alkyne molecules by H and OH radicals have been outlined. The computed results reveal that the reaction barriers decrease as the nature of the abstracted H atom at the propargyl C-H site from primary through secondary to tertiary. The existence of vinyl, phenyl and acetylenic groups also decreases the energy barriers with the following order: vinyl &gt; phenyl &gt; acetylenic.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the quantum chemistry calculations, rate constants are computed using the canonical transition state theory with tunneling correction and the treatment of internal rotations. The computed rate constants for abstraction reactions of propyne by H and OH radicals are compared with literature data and show good agreement. The TSs for H-abstraction reactions from eight alkynes by H and/or OH radicals are further divided into three types: primary propargyl, secondary propargyl and tertiary propargyl radicals. The high-pressure limiting rate constants of the tertiary propargyl radicals are consistently faster than those of the secondary propargyl radicals for H-abstraction reactions by H and OH radicals. For the secondary propargyl radicals, the ability of different groups on increasing reaction activity of H-abstraction reactions by H atom is: –C
  <sub>2</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub> (negative) &lt; –CH
  <sub>3</sub> &lt; –C
  <sub>6</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub> ≈ –C
  <sub>2</sub>H &lt; –C
  <sub>2</sub>H
  <sub>3</sub>, while the trend for H-abstraction reactions by OH atom is –C
  <sub>6</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub> (negative) &lt; –C
  <sub>2</sub>H ≈ –CH
  <sub>3</sub> &lt; –C
  <sub>2</sub>H
  <sub>3</sub>. Finally, the computed rate constants are fitted into the three-parameter Arrhenius expressions to facilitate kinetic modeling studies. Compared with literature studies on small reactions in this work, the employed ab initio calculations together with statistical transition state theory provide an accurate description of the chemical kinetics of the studied abstraction reactions. However, the subsequent reactions of the formed radicals of alkyne molecules can exhibit complex reaction pathways, which may need direct dynamics to uncover [
  <a rid="B52-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijms-20-03227">52</a>]. Currently, direct dynamics is limited to small polyatomic systems because it still depends on accurate potential energy surfaces (PES) from ab initio calculations. The benchmark results of DFT methods in this work also provide fundamental information to select efficient method for PES constructions used in future direct dynamics studies on these reaction systems.
 </p>
</sec>
