<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec2-ijms-20-03227" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Results and Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate the structure and reaction site effect on the abstraction reactions from propargyl C-H sites, eight alkyne molecules with different propargyl C-H sites are considered. The studied alkyne molecules are propyne, 1-butyne, 1-pentyne, penta-1,4-diyne, 4-penten-1-yne, isopentyne, 3-phenyl-1-propyne, and but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene, which can represent the primary, secondary, tertiary, and doubly secondary propargyl H atoms of alkynes and the effect of phenyl substituents which is important for soot precursor formation is also considered.</p>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-ijms-20-03227" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Geometry Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f001" href="#ijms-20-03227-f001">Figure 1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f002" href="#ijms-20-03227-f002">Figure 2</a> depict the optimized transition state structures at M06-2X/cc-pVTZ level of theory. It should be noted that the lowest energy conformation for each species is obtained by scanning all the relevant internal rotational degrees of freedom and then the global minimum point is used for optimization. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f001" href="#ijms-20-03227-f001">Figure 1</a>, the C-H bond breaking along the reaction coordinate are elongated from an averaged value of 1.09 Å to an averaged value of 1.24 Å and the angles of C-H-H between the breaking C-H bond and the forming H-H bond are near-linear.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unlike the simple TS structures for H-atom abstraction reactions of alkynes by H atoms at the propargyl reaction sites, the TS structures of abstraction reactions by OH radical are more complex due to the interaction of oxygen atom with other functional groups in the reactant molecules. For the studied reactants of propyne, 1-butyne, 1-pentyne, penta-1,4-diyne, 4-penten-1-yne, and isopentyne, the OH radical is nearly parallel along the C≡C triplet bond of the reactants. However, for 3-phenyl-1-propyne and but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene, the OH radical tends to locate above the benzene ring and the OH radical is nearly parallel along the C-C bond connecting the phenyl group.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To further confirm the minimal structures corresponding to the global minima, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f003" href="#ijms-20-03227-f003">Figure 3</a> shows the hindrance potential of relaxed scans of the internal rotation of H atom in OH radical for 1-butyne, 4-penten-1-yne, and 3-phenyl-1-propyne. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f004" href="#ijms-20-03227-f004">Figure 4</a> illustrates the Mulliken charge distributions [
   <a rid="B19-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijms-20-03227">19</a>] of the TSs for these three reactions. The relative energies between the highest and lowest structures are computed at the CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ level of theory to validate the scanned results at the M06-2X/cc-pVTZ level of theory. It has been verified that the two theoretical methods can give similar energy curves and the deviations between CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ and M06-2X/cc-pVTZ are within 0.5 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f004" href="#ijms-20-03227-f004">Figure 4</a>, for the TS of H-abstraction reaction of 1-butyne by OH radical, the energy difference between the lowest and highest energy conformations is 1.23 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The negative charge distributions of the two carbon atoms in the C≡C triplet bond attract the H atom in OH radical pointing to the C≡C triplet bond resulting in the O–H bond parallel to the C≡C triplet bond. The energy difference between the lowest and highest energy conformations for 4-penten-1-yne and 3-phenyl-1-propyne are 1.48 and 1.46 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, respectively. The charge distribution of the C atom near the propargyl site in the C=C double bond (−0.062) is slightly large than that in the C≡C triplet bond (−0.086), which makes the OH radical toward parallel to the C≡C triplet bond. However, the strong negative charge distributions of phenyl group in 3-phenyl-1-propyne attract the OH radical shifting toward the aromatic ring to form a more stable TS structure.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f003" href="#ijms-20-03227-f003">Figure 3</a>, the most unstable TS structures of these three reactants are found when the H atom in OH radical shifts toward the opposite sites along the C≡C triplet bond. Similar trend is observed for the other reaction systems. Based on the above analysis, it can be concluded that the formation of the lowest energy conformations of the TSs for the studied reaction systems are mainly affected through the electron-withdrawing inductive effect by the surrounding groups around the reactivity center. Specifically, the lone pair of electrons of oxygen atom are attracted by the conjugated π-system of phenyl group which is similar to the mesomeric effect. Since the electron-withdrawing inductive effect (-
   <span class="italic">I</span> effect) of phenyl group is stronger than C=C double bond and C≡C triplet bond, the OH radical prefers to shift toward the aromatic ring to form a more stable TS structure. In addition, the delocalization effect of the C=C double bond of 4-penten-1-yne is less competitive compared with the C≡C triplet bond, the TS structure of the former is expected to be less stable. Furthermore, due to the interaction between the reactants and OH radical, reactant complexes (RCs) and product complexes (PCs) are formed via weakly hydrogen bond and IRC analysis results are adopted to determine the geometries of these complexes. The optimized geometries are provided as 
   <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-20-03227" href="#app1-ijms-20-03227">Supplementary Materials</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-ijms-20-03227" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Reaction Barriers and Enthalpies</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The accuracy of the computed rate constants critically depends on the reliability of reaction barriers; thus, it is important to obtain reliable single-point energy results by employing high-level quantum chemistry methods. However, it is computationally prohibitive for the studied large reaction systems. Hence, we have adopted the accurate W1BD and CCSD(T)/CBS methods to benchmark a series of DFT functionals to select an appropriate DFT method, since different DFT functionals provide very different results for various chemical properties.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To verify the selected benchmark methods, the bond dissociation energies (BDEs) of acetylenic C-H bond and propargyl C-H bond for acetylene and propyne are computed first using W1BD and CCSD(T)/CBS methods as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f005" href="#ijms-20-03227-f005">Figure 5</a>. It can be seen that the computed BDEs for acetylenic C-H and propargyl C-H bonds by using the W1BD and CCSD(T) methods are in very good correlation with the recommended values by Luo et al. [
   <a rid="B6-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijms-20-03227">6</a>], indicating that the W1BD and CCSD(T)/CBS methods should be as accurate as benchmark methods. The BDE of propargyl C-H bond is lower than that of acetylenic C-H bond by 40 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, thus, abstraction reactions at the acetylenic site are very difficult. Hence, in this work, we just focus on the hydrogen abstraction channels at the propargyl C-H sites, and systematically investigate the reaction kinetics of structural variant effect on propargyl C-H reaction sites.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t001">Table 1</a> lists the computed reaction barriers by using high-level W1BD and CCSD(T)/CBS methods and different DFT methods with cc-pVTZ basis set for H-atom abstraction reactions of propyne and 1-butyne by H and OH radicals. The last column represents the absolute average errors compared with the benchmark results from W1BD method. From 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t001">Table 1</a> it can be seen that the results via CCSD(T)/CBS method are in good correlation with those from accurate W1BD method. The absolute average error is 0.23 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, which is also in good accordance with the computed BDEs shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f003" href="#ijms-20-03227-f003">Figure 3</a>, indicating that the two high-level methods can provide consistent reliable energy information for the studied reactions. Among the selected 13 DFT functionals, the M08-HX exhibits the best performance and the absolute average errors compared with W1BD and CCSD(T)/CBS methods are 0.36 and 0.24 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, respectively. The BMK functional shows good performance for abstraction reactions by H radical, but not for abstraction reactions by OH radical. Similarly, the MPW1K shows better performance only for H-atom abstraction reactions by OH radical. Thus, one should be better to validate these DFT methods before directly apply them for these reaction systems to obtain energy information. In addition, to check the performance of M08-HX functional for 3-phenyl-1-propyne and but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene which contain phenyl group, the results calculated from M08-HX are compared with the results from CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ level since CCSD(T)/cc-pVQZ level are still computationally prohibitive for a system with over 10 heavy atoms. For H-atom abstraction reactions of 3-phenyl-1-propyne by H and OH radicals, the computed reaction barriers are 5.14 and −0.22 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span> via CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ method, while the results at M08-HX/cc-pVTZ level are 5.11 and −0.50 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, indicating that the M08-HX/cc-pVTZ level of theory is able to provide reasonable energy information for the studied reaction systems. In addition, from 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t001">Table 1</a>, the MUE of M08-HX functional relative to W1BD method is mainly affected by the H-abstraction of propyne with H radical. The uncertainty of rate constants calculated with reaction barriers at M08-HX level are found to be within a factor of 2 compared with those at W1BD method over the studied temperature ranges. What is interesting to note is that a strong correlation of the reaction barriers at W1BD and M08-HX levels are fitted to Δ
   <span class="italic">E</span>
   <sub>W1BD</sub> = 1.0668 × Δ
   <span class="italic">E</span>
   <sub>M08-HX</sub> + 0.0682 with an adjusted R-squared value of 0.998. Such a correlation expression further reduces the MUE of the four reactions at M08-HX level to 0.075 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span> relative to the results via W1BD method. Based on this linear correlation, the M08-HX barrier heights for the studied systems are corrected to approach those calculated at W1BD level and listed in 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t002" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t002">Table 2</a> and 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t003">Table 3</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t002" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t002">Table 2</a> lists the computed reaction barriers and enthalpies at M08-HX/cc-pVTZ level for the studied H-abstraction reactions by H radical. With the use of this method, the computed potential energies for TSs, RCs and PCs of H-abstraction reactions by OH radical are listed in 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t003">Table 3</a> which are relative to their reactants, respectively. For the studied abstraction reaction of propyne with H atom, the predicted reaction barrier and enthalpies are compared with those by Bentz et al. [
   <a rid="B12-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijms-20-03227">12</a>] at the QCISD(T)/cc-pVTZ//B3LYP/6-31G(d) level of theory. The reaction barrier and enthalpy by M08-HX/cc-pVTZ in this work are 8.23 and −12.07 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, which are slightly lower than the results by Bentz et al. [
   <a rid="B12-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijms-20-03227">12</a>] by 0.92 and 0.65 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, respectively. While the computed barrier at M08-HX/cc-pVTZ level in this work is much closer to the results from Wang et al. by using the composite G3 method [
   <a rid="B20-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijms-20-03227">20</a>]. Compared with those obtained at W1BD and CCSD(T)/CBS methods in this work, the predicted barrier with an value of 8.67 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span> by Miller et al. [
   <a rid="B11-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijms-20-03227">11</a>] at the QCISD(T)/inf//B3LYP/6-311++G(d,p) level of theory is quite close to the present estimation, while the reaction barrier by Bentz et al. [
   <a rid="B12-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijms-20-03227">12</a>] is higher by 0.19 and 0.35 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The energy barrier and enthalpy for the H-abstraction reaction of propyne by OH are 2.00 and −26.31 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span> at M08-HX/cc-pVTZ level, which are also in good agreement with the values of 2.00 and −25.16 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span> which are computed at the UCCSD(T)-F12b/cc-PVQZ-F12 level [
   <a rid="B15-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijms-20-03227">15</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t002" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t002">Table 2</a> and 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t003">Table 3</a>, it can be seen that the averaged reaction barrier and enthalpy of H-abstraction reactions by OH radical are lower than that by H radical by values of 5.62 and 14.24 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, respectively. Hence, the H-abstraction reactions of alkynes by OH radical are kinetically more favored than that by H radical. The structural nature of the alkynes tends to show similar effect on the reaction barriers and enthalpies of H-abstraction reactions by H and OH radicals. For non-aromatic alkynes, the abstraction reaction at the tertiary (3°) propargyl C-H site in isopentyne is the easiest which has the lowest relative reaction barrier of −0.39 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, followed by the secondary (2°) propargyl C-H site in 1-butyne, then the primary (1°) propargyl C-H site in propyne is the most difficult. For the two propargyl C-H sites in 3-phenyl-1-propyne and but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene molecules involving phenyl group, the same trend is also observed that the abstraction reaction at tertiary propargyl C-H site in but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene is easier to occur than that at the secondary propargyl C-H site in 3-phenyl-1-propyne. Thus, the trend for reaction barriers of H-abstraction reactions by H and OH radicals is 
   <span class="italic">E</span>
   <sub>0K</sub>(3°) &lt; 
   <span class="italic">E</span>
   <sub>0K</sub>(2°) &lt; 
   <span class="italic">E</span>
   <sub>0K</sub>(1°). Compared with the results of 1-butyne and 1-pentyne, the length of alkyne chains has negligible effect on the H-abstraction reactions by H radical, but it shows moderate effect on the H-abstraction reactions by OH radical. The reaction barriers of H-abstraction reactions by OH radical decrease with the growth of the chain length. For the five secondary propargyl C-H sites in 1-butyne, 1-pentyne, penta-1,4-diyne, 4-penten-1-yne and 3-phenyl-1-propyne, the existences of vinyl group, phenyl group and acetylenic group all increase the reactivity compared with 1-butyne and 1-pentyne by the following order: vinyl group &gt; phenyl group &gt; acetylenic group. On the other hand, this also means that abstraction reaction at the allylic C-H site is easier than that at the benzyl site, which is easier than that at propargyl site considering the reaction sites connected the other same groups. 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t003">Table 3</a> also shows that for the studied H-abstraction reactions by OH radical, the weakly van der Waals RCs and PCs are formed at the entrance and exit channels. The energies of RCs are lower than the reactants by 3.97–5.58 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, while the PCs are lower than the products by 3.22–4.30 kcal mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span> for the studied reactions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-ijms-20-03227" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Rate Constants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the abstraction reactions by OH radical, rate constants calculations need to consider the formed Van der Waals complexes (RCs and PCs), and two-TS models are usually employed [
   <a rid="B21-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijms-20-03227">21</a>,
   <a rid="B22-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijms-20-03227">22</a>]. However, a series of previous studies indicated that this model only showed significant effect at low temperatures below 200 K [
   <a rid="B21-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijms-20-03227">21</a>,
   <a rid="B22-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijms-20-03227">22</a>,
   <a rid="B23-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijms-20-03227">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijms-20-03227">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijms-20-03227">25</a>,
   <a rid="B26-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijms-20-03227">26</a>]. For the interested combustion relevant temperature range of 500–2500 K, the rate-limiting step is the inner TSs. Furthermore, the formed RCs are unstable at high temperatures. Hence, the abstraction reactions by H and OH radicals are all computed by using canonical TST with 1-D hindered rotor approximations for the treatment of internal rotations. The Fourier-series are used for fitting the scanned results of international rotations. To obtain rate constants with minimal uncertainty, the corrected M08-HX barrier height are adopted.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high-pressure limiting rate constants (
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>) of H-abstraction reaction of propyne by H and OH radicals in this work are compared with available literature data and shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f006" href="#ijms-20-03227-f006">Figure 6</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f007" href="#ijms-20-03227-f007">Figure 7</a>, respectively. From 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f006" href="#ijms-20-03227-f006">Figure 6</a>, the rate constants obtained in this work are in good correlation with the results by Miller et al. [
   <a rid="B11-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijms-20-03227">11</a>] at the QCISD(T)/inf//B3LYP/6-311++G(d,p) level of theory over the studied temperature ranges. The rate constants by Wang et al. [
   <a rid="B20-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijms-20-03227">20</a>] tended to underestimate the rate constants at low temperature. The predicted results show good agreement with the rate constants derived from a heated single pulse-shock tube at temperatures of 874–1196 K by Rosado-Reyes et al. [
   <a rid="B13-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijms-20-03227">13</a>]. For the H-abstraction reaction of propyne with OH, Hansen et al. [
   <a rid="B14-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijms-20-03227">14</a>] esimated the rate constants for this reaction and used in kinetic modeling. The deviations of the rate constants between present results and Zador’s calculations [
   <a rid="B15-ijms-20-03227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijms-20-03227">15</a>] are within a factor of 2 and decrease as temperature increasing. The H-abstraction reaction of propyne by OH radical is in fact important at temperatures over 1000 K and it can be seen that the three different sets of rate constants for this reaction at the interested temperature ranges are close to each other. Overall, the results computed at M08-HX level are in good agreement with literature data, but can significantly reduce the computational cost to obtain accurate reaction barriers compared with other expensive W1BD or CCSD(T) methods.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f008" href="#ijms-20-03227-f008">Figure 8</a> compares the rate constants as a function of temperature for the studied H-abstraction reactions by H radical. The TSs for H-abstraction reactions from eight reactants by H and/or OH radicals can be divided into three types: primary propargyl radical (propyne), secondary propargyl radicals (1-butyne, 1-pentyne, penta-1,4-diyne, 4-penten-1-yne and 3-phenyl-1-propyne) and tertiary propargyl radicals (isopentyne and but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene). As can be seen from the graph, the 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> of the tertiary propargyl radicals are higher than those of the secondary propargyl radicals. For the five secondary propargyl radicals, in comparison with 1-butyne, the trend is 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(1-pentyne) &lt; 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(1-butyne) &lt; 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(3-phenyl-1-propyne) ≈ 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(penta-1,4-diyne) &lt; 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(4-penten-1-yne) which suggests the positive (+) or negative (-) influence of different groups on the reaction activity is: –C
   <sub>2</sub>H
   <sub>5</sub> (-) &lt; –CH
   <sub>3</sub> (+) &lt; –C
   <sub>6</sub>H
   <sub>5</sub> ≈ –C
   <sub>2</sub>H &lt; –C
   <sub>2</sub>H
   <sub>3</sub>. In addition, the –C
   <sub>2</sub>H
   <sub>3</sub> group tends to show stronger influence on the reaction activity especially at low temperature since the deviation between 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(penta-1,4-diyne) and 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(4-penten-1-yne) is larger than those between the other secondary propargyl radicals.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> of the primary propargyl radical (propyne) tends to show different trend with that of the secondary propargyl radicals which is slower at low temperatures, but overtaking the 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> of secondary propargyl radicals at high temperatures. For the tertiary propargyl radicals, 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(isopentyne) is slower than that of but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene at temperatures lower than 1000 K which is consistent with the trend of the secondary propargyl radicals that phenyl group has stronger positive influence on the reaction reactivity. However, as the temperature increasing, 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene) is overtaken by 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub>(isopentyne).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unlike the H-abstraction reactions of the studied alkyne molecules by H radical, the rate constants by OH radical exhibit large differences. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03227-f009" href="#ijms-20-03227-f009">Figure 9</a> shows that the rate constant of a tertiary propargyl radical (isopentyne) is significantly larger than the others over the whole temperature range, while the 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> of a secondary propargyl radical (3-phenyl-1-propyne) is the smallest. It can be clearly seen from this graph that the tertiary propargyl radicals (isopentyne and but-3-yn-2-ylbenzene) have higher 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> than secondary propargyl radicals which is consistent with H-abstraction by H atom. The deviations between the primary and secondary propargyl C-H sites with alkyl groups (propyne, 1-butyne and 1-pentyne) are small which are within 3 times over the whole temperature range. For secondary propargyl radicals, (1) the 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> of penta-1,4-diyne is similar to that of 1-butyne which may suggests the equivalent influence of methyl and acetylenic group on rate constant calculation for H-abstraction reactions of alkynes by OH radical; (2) the vinyl group in 4-penten-1-yne significantly increases the rate constants compared with 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> of 1-butyne. (3) the phenyl group in 3-phenyl-1-propyne significantly decreases the rate constants compared with 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>∞</sub> of 1-butyne. Hence, the methyl, vinyl and acetylenic groups in secondary propargyl radicals tends to increase the reactivity of H-abstraction reaction by OH radical compared with the primary propargyl radicals, the trend of influence for these three group are –C
   <sub>2</sub>H ≈ –CH
   <sub>3</sub> &lt; –C
   <sub>2</sub>H
   <sub>3</sub>. While phenyl group tend to decrease the reactivity of H-abstraction reaction by OH radical. To facilitate kinetic modeling studies, the computed rate constants are fitted into the modified Arrhenius format as shown in 
   <a rid="ijms-20-03227-t004" ref-type="table" href="#ijms-20-03227-t004">Table 4</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
