<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-nanomaterials-09-00872" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Quantum Dots</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f001">Figure 1</a> is a schematic indicating possible changes to a core/shell system, where A-type nanoparticles were deposited first and then coated by another material B. Interdiffusion will lead to intermixing of both components, creating an alloy that will, after sufficiently long time at elevated temperature, become homogeneous (left part of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f001">Figure 1</a>). Segregation can either stabilise the as-deposited core/shell particle (if the material deposited last has the lower free surface energy and so is more stable outside) or modify it in two ways: if A and B have similar free surface energies and a medium-high interface energy, the particle may tend towards lateral de-mixing as indicated in the lower middle part of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f001">Figure 1</a> (and could eventually completely separate into small A and larger B particles if their interface energy was sufficiently high). If A has a much lower free surface energy than A, however, then the core/shell structure can even become inverted, as sketched in the lower right part of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f001">Figure 1</a>. Phase separation will thus be dominated by a competition between inner stresses due to misfit strain and surface stresses due to geometrical shape and free surface effects. It is important to note that interpretation of diffusion and/or segregation relies on knowledge of both as-deposited (initial state) and resulting structure (final state).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is clear that electron microscopy, due to its superior resolution in combination with analytical spectroscopy, holds the key to directly observing and probing such core/shell quantum dot structures [
  <a rid="B13-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-nanomaterials-09-00872">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f002">Figure 2</a> shows as an example colloidal core–shell structures of CdS/ZnS quantum dots that have undergone some intermixing due to interdiffusion where the ADF image (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f002">Figure 2</a>a) alone does not suffice as one needs elemental maps of the distribution of characteristic X-ray emission (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f002">Figure 2</a>b–d) to prove their brighter centres are not just thicker but also preferentially contain the heavy metal cadmium. This result is similar to what has been shown by X-ray mapping for ~10 nm wide CdSe/ZnS core/shell nanoparticles [
  <a rid="B14-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nanomaterials-09-00872">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00872-f003" href="#nanomaterials-09-00872-f003">Figure 3</a> shows a quantitative concentration map obtained from a series of energy-filtered TEM images of an uncapped InGaAs quantum dot grown epitaxially on GaAs in cross-section, indicating indium agglomeration in its centre despite a homogeneous deposition flux, which is due to lateral segregation during epitaxial growth [
  <a rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nanomaterials-09-00872">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-nanomaterials-09-00872">16</a>]. If nominally pure InAs is deposited on GaAs instead, then the islands spontaneously formed on the surface are also found to be a mixed InGaAs alloy which has been explained by a combination of interdiffusion and indium desorption [
  <a rid="B17-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-nanomaterials-09-00872">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Local segregation of In atoms in InGaN islands [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00872">18</a>] and nanowires [
  <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00872">19</a>] has also been observed by plasmon loss mapping using STEM-EELS, with a resolution on the nm-scale.
 </p>
</sec>
