<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-nanomaterials-09-00872" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Quantum Nanowires</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All structures whose length is orders of magnitude larger than their lateral widths may be called nanowires if their widths are sub-micron. If nanowires are made of semiconductors and the lateral dimensions become so small that they influence charge carrier confinement, then they may be called quantum nanowires (QNWs).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As most semiconductors crystallise in the diamond, sphalerite or wurtzite lattices, such QNWs often have prismatic shape with hexagonal cross-sections, the sidewalls being formed by either {111} planes (if cubic) or {1
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="mm11" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <span class="mn">1</span>
      <span class="mo">¯</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>00} planes (if hexagonal). Key structures of technological interest involve axial (core/shell-type) as well as radial (quantum disk-like) heterostructures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the latter case of radial quantum disks, intensity line profiles taken in the centre of the nanowire along its long axis can be used to investigate changes in chemical composition for constant thickness, however, for axial heterostructures, profiles across the core/shell structure also involve drastic variations in thickness, so any type of imaging has to be accompanied by detailed simulations [
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00872">20</a>] to separate chemical concentration from thickness effects, while X-ray spectra generally allow a more direct interpretation of the chemistry of the cores [
  <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00872">21</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
