<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec6-nanomaterials-09-00872" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6. Segregation at Grain Boundaries, Interfaces, Defects and Surfaces</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are some issues particular to segregation in semiconductors:
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">(a)</span>
    <p>Grain boundary segregation can unintentionally and directly lead to the formation of extremely thin quantum wells, down to fractions of monolayers, where imaging approaches can fail even with the best electron microscopes as it is chemical sensitivity and accuracy in measuring chemical profiles that count rather than spatial resolution. Interfaces that appear atomically smooth in lattice images may in fact be chemically graded if the interference pattern is not sufficiently sensitive to those gradients, cf. the case of Ca segregation [
     <a rid="B49-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-nanomaterials-09-00872">49</a>] vs. Ba segregation [
     <a rid="B50-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-nanomaterials-09-00872">50</a>] at SrTiO
     <sub>3</sub> on (La,Ca)MnO
     <sub>3</sub> interfaces. Conversely, strained interfaces can also appear diffuse in imaging when they are actually abrupt, due to long range strain components interfering with the contrast in bright field [
     <a rid="B51-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-nanomaterials-09-00872">51</a>,
     <a rid="B52-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-nanomaterials-09-00872">52</a>] as well as medium-angle dark field [
     <a rid="B12-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nanomaterials-09-00872">12</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">(b)</span>
    <p>For interfaces and grain boundaries thinner than a unit cell or a fraction of a monolayer, a method originally implemented in TEM [
     <a rid="B53-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-nanomaterials-09-00872">53</a>] and later also STEM [
     <a rid="B54-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-nanomaterials-09-00872">54</a>] has been successful in measuring highly accurately the effective chemical width of fractions of monolayers in many material systems, most recently for Ge/Si [
     <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00872">28</a>] and InAs/GaAs [
     <a rid="B55-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-nanomaterials-09-00872">55</a>,
     <a rid="B56-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-nanomaterials-09-00872">56</a>]. This approach uses a plot of atomic ratio measured as a function of scan window size perpendicular to the interface or defect in question. If the spatial resolution is sufficient and the sample does not damage at high electron dose, then atomic resolution images of grain boundaries, ideally correlated with simultaneously acquired EELS, can sometimes directly reveal the positions to which atoms segregate, e.g., heavy metal dopants at interfaces in polycrystalline Si
     <sub>3</sub>N
     <sub>4</sub> [
     <a rid="B57-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-nanomaterials-09-00872">57</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">(c)</span>
    <p>Atomic segregation to lattice defects or surfaces can directly form quantum nanowires or quantum dots, depending on the extension of the defects structure, and both surface segregation and interdiffusion can modify the chemistry of such quantum domain structures further. While many spectroscopic methods in (S)TEM reach only nm-scale rather than lattice resolution, this is often sufficient to detect such surface layers, e.g., thin surface layers of phosphides used for passivation of the sidewalls in GaAs-based quantum nanowires (as in the supporting information to [
     <a rid="B58-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-nanomaterials-09-00872">58</a>]). EDXS point analysis proved Al segregation to dislocation cores in AlGaN [
     <a rid="B59-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-nanomaterials-09-00872">59</a>]. Both ADF imaging and X-ray line scans have been combined in [
     <a rid="B60-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-nanomaterials-09-00872">60</a>] to detect indium segregation to the sidewalls of V-shaped pyramidal surface defects in (In)AlN. ADF and EELS were used to detect oxygen segregation to screw dislocations in GaN [
     <a rid="B61-nanomaterials-09-00872" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-nanomaterials-09-00872">61</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
