<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-molecules-24-01402" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Experimental and Simulated NIR Spectra of Crystalline Melamine</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In decisive contrast to the IR region (
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot1-molecules-24-01402" href="#sec2dot1-molecules-24-01402">Section 2.1</a>), and as evidenced in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>, the NIR bands of crystalline melamine are accurately reproduced on the basis of a finite model. In this case, even the calculations that are based on a single molecule of melamine provide good agreement between the calculated and experimental spectra (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>). If further studies will allow for generalizing this observation, a lower requirement for the model complexity in modeling of NIR spectra could open other opportunities for refining the theoretical approach. For example, a hybrid approach combining higher-level harmonic computations augmenting DVPT2/GVPT2 anharmonic analysis could be used. Barone and co-workers have reported evidences of accurate and affordable hybrid B3LYP(harmonic)/B2PLYP(anharmonic) computations [
  <a rid="B51-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-molecules-24-01402">51</a>,
  <a rid="B52-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-molecules-24-01402">52</a>], as also seen in our previous studies [
  <a rid="B53-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-molecules-24-01402">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The principle difference between the DVPT2 and GVPT2 approaches is the treatment of vibrational resonances; the latter method features an advanced correction for Fermi and Darling-Dennison resonances by the variational method [
  <a rid="B54-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-molecules-24-01402">54</a>]. The improvement does not seem to significantly affect the major NIR bands of melamine (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>). However, improved method allows for calculations of three quanta transitions (i.e., second overtones, 3
  <span class="italic">ν</span>; and ternary combinations, 2
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>x</sub> + 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>y</sub>, and 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>x</sub> + 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>y</sub> + 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>z</sub>). The addition of these minor bands slightly enhances the agreement, for example, below 6500 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and in the region of 4400–4150 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f005" href="#molecules-24-01402-f005">Figure 5</a>). This observation remains similar to our previous estimations that were based on the anharmonic study of methanol molecule and its deuterated isotopomers [
  <a rid="B55-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-molecules-24-01402">55</a>]. We have therein concluded that the bands due to three quanta transitions are only responsible for minority (ca. 20%) of the NIR spectra of methanol [
  <a rid="B55-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-molecules-24-01402">55</a>]. These higher order bands are weak, overlapping bands, and the corresponding spectral information is “diffused” along the wavenumber axis [
  <a rid="B55-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-molecules-24-01402">55</a>]. A similar case may be reported for melamine, and it is probably shared by other molecules. There are some exceptions, e.g., in the literature, 3
  <span class="italic">ν</span>C=O has been reported to appear near 5150–5160 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in gas phase (and near 5122–5076 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in various solvents), as a well resolved band in some molecules with a C=O group [
  <a rid="B56-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-molecules-24-01402">56</a>,
  <a rid="B57-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-molecules-24-01402">57</a>]. No such exceptions were observed for melamine, and close inspection of the theoretical spectra confirms that the majority of the experimental bands were reproduced by both approximations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>). The more comprehensive, but also resource intensive, calculations of additional three quanta transitions of melamine allowed for explaining finer features that were observed in its NIR spectrum (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>). Primarily, the influence of higher order bands may be seen throughout the 6500–5200 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region and in the vicinity of 4300–4100 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>A,B). In the former case (6500–5200 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region), these bands remain very weak. For the latter (4300–4100 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region), there appears a marked band overlapping that gives rise to a broadened feature of moderate intensity at 4300–4200 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, and also a similar one appearing at the high-frequency wing of the ~4090 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> band (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>B). The present study of NIR spectra of crystalline melamine may be compared with our earlier calculations of NIR spectra of medium-chain fatty acids [
  <a rid="B35-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-molecules-24-01402">35</a>]. In contrast to the previously observed significance of the hydrogen-bonding interaction for the NIR region of crystalline sorbic acid [
  <a rid="B35-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-molecules-24-01402">35</a>], NIR bands of melamine reveal surprisingly low sensitivity to the hydrogen-bonding. This occurs despite the fact that melamine interacts strongly and it forms multiple hydrogen-bonds in crystalline states, as recently demonstrated by Yuan et al. [
  <a rid="B41-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-molecules-24-01402">41</a>]. We will discuss in detail the reasons for such distinctiveness of NIR region of melamine in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot3-molecules-24-01402" href="#sec2dot3-molecules-24-01402">Section 2.3</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The agreement with the experimental spectrum is slightly lower in the 5200–4000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region, as the level of band overlapping is very high there. In contrast, the upper NIR region (ca. 6900–6450 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was accurately reproduced in the calculation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>A). The first overtones and the binary combinations bands of NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching modes populate this region (as the primary contributions). Similar to other kinds of X-H vibrations (e.g., OH), these modes are expected in the literature to be sensitive to the molecules’ chemical neighborhood, e.g., prone to red-shifting in hydrogen-bonded complexes. This effect has been clearly observed for alcohols [
  <a rid="B58-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-molecules-24-01402">58</a>] or in our recent NIR investigation of thymol [
  <a rid="B37-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-molecules-24-01402">37</a>]. Surprisingly, in the case of melamine it may be concluded that the first overtones and binary combinations bands of NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching modes are properly reproduced, even in the simplified case of an isolated molecule, for which the inter-molecular interactions are not reflected (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f004" href="#molecules-24-01402-f004">Figure 4</a>A).
 </p>
</sec>
