<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot3-molecules-24-01402" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. An In-Depth Analysis of the Origin of NIR Bands of Crystalline Melamine</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Numerous overlapping bands populate NIR spectra of even relatively simple molecules [
  <a rid="B16-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-molecules-24-01402">16</a>,
  <a rid="B31-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-molecules-24-01402">31</a>]. This makes their detailed analysis difficult, and the interpretation of the leading contributions is not as straightforward as it is for the corresponding IR spectra. To better elucidate these influences and to present them in a clear manner, we have developed a density map (colormap) of spectral contributions to highlight the modes of interest in a straightforward way (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f005" href="#molecules-24-01402-f005">Figure 5</a>). The color range corresponds to the square rooted intensity ratio of the selected simulated bands to the total intensity of modeled spectrum at any given wavenumber 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>i</sub> and additionally proportionalized to the calculated intensity at that point. The yielded value ranges from 0 (no contribution) to 1 (the NIR spectrum is influenced by the selected mode/modes entirely). The corresponding color varies from black to white, and it may be directly interpreted as the intensity of a given mode at a given wavenumber; the colortable is presented underneath the figure. The square root allows for elucidating less pronounced contributions. The density maps that are determined for various selections of modes-of-interest allow for unequivocal and thorough analysis of the influential determinants in the NIR spectrum of crystalline melamine (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f005" href="#molecules-24-01402-f005">Figure 5</a>), while keeping the figure compact and easy to read.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The upper NIR region (ca. 6900–6500 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) is almost entirely populated by the first overtones and the binary combination bands of NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching modes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f005" href="#molecules-24-01402-f005">Figure 5</a>). Other than this exception, the overtone bands of melamine may be described as non-essential for the other regions of NIR spectrum. Instead, the combination bands (binary combinations the most, ternary combinations to a bit lesser degree) play the primary role there. Again, the combinations that involve stretching NH
  <sub>2</sub> modes are the most important factor. The corresponding binary combinations provide very strong influence in the 6900–6500 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region and throughout a broad 5100–4000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region. Ternary combinations that involve NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching modes only give weak influence in the region of 6500–6000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, where the spectral lineshape is rather flat. The highly populated region between 5100–4000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> is mostly influenced by the combinations of stretching modes with deformation modes of NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups. The other influential factor is 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>C-N mode (both in ring as well as between C atoms in ring and NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups). However, the wagging NH
  <sub>2</sub> modes are largely suppressed. The modes that do not influence NIR region are as follows; overtones of 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>ip</sub>ring, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>ip</sub>C-N(H
  <sub>2</sub>), 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>oop</sub>ring, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>oop</sub>C-N(H
  <sub>2</sub>), 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>rock</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>twist</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>wagg</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of the NIR modes reveals a structural pattern. The modes that involve in-plane atoms displacements tend to impact NIR spectrum relatively stringer than those that involve out-of-plane motions. This observation will be discussed in detail in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot4-molecules-24-01402" href="#sec2dot4-molecules-24-01402">Section 2.4</a>, together with the conclusions drawn from the analysis of IR spectrum of melamine (
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot1-molecules-24-01402" href="#sec2dot1-molecules-24-01402">Section 2.1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
