<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-molecules-24-01402" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. The Relationships Between IR and NIR Bands, and the Structural Features of Crystalline Melamine</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Important conclusions may be drawn from the detailed comprehension of both IR and NIR spectra of crystalline melamine. The vibrational modes involving out-of-plane atomic motions are much more essential in the IR region (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f003" href="#molecules-24-01402-f003">Figure 3</a> and 
  <a rid="molecules-24-01402-t001" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01402-t001">Table 1</a>), and thus a proper reflection of the inter-plane structure of crystalline melamine is required. Therefore, calculations that are based on a 3D infinite model of crystal lattice allows for the best description of these vibrations, even with harmonic approximation. However, in the NIR spectrum the most influential modes are those that involve in-plane atomic displacements. Thus, the neighboring planes of crystalline lattice do not impact these motions as much. Therefore, the NIR modes calculated for a single molecule are largely enough to accurately reflect the experimental spectrum.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This also makes perfect sense by comparing the IR vibrations calculated in periodic system to the ones calculated for a single molecule (also refer to 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-24-01402" href="#app1-molecules-24-01402">Table S1 in Supporting Materials</a> presenting the potential energy distribution calculated for melamine). In the calculations that are based on a single molecule (vs. the model of crystalline lattice), the out-of-plane deformation vibrations (e.g., 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>twist</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>wagg</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>oop</sub>ring) are positioned at higher calculated wavenumbers, while the in-plane deformation vibrations are positioned at the lower calculated wavenumbers. Thus, the oscillators with the out-of-plane atomic motions have lower calculated force constants because of neglecting the surrounding crystalline planes. The neglecting of intra-plane interactions of melamine lead to a surprisingly miniscule decrease of the accuracy of the calculated NIR modes. The corresponding vibrations with in-plane atomic motions (primarily 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>NH
  <sub>2</sub>, but also 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>ip</sub>ring, 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>C-N[H
  <sub>2</sub>]) were mostly overestimated in the calculated frequencies, which was easily corrected by applying scaling. These modes are seemingly less affected by the intermolecular interactions of melamine in crystal lattice, including the effects of hydrogen-bonding.
 </p>
</sec>
