<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot5-molecules-24-01402" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. New Insights on the Quantitative Analytical Spectroscopy of Melamine</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Melamine is known food adulterant, and for this reason, it has been frequently focused on analytical IR and NIR spectroscopy [
  <a rid="B9-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-molecules-24-01402">9</a>,
  <a rid="B42-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-molecules-24-01402">42</a>,
  <a rid="B43-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-molecules-24-01402">43</a>,
  <a rid="B44-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-molecules-24-01402">44</a>,
  <a rid="B45-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-molecules-24-01402">45</a>,
  <a rid="B46-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-molecules-24-01402">46</a>]. After reproducing the spectra of melamine, we can more deeply discuss some of the observations that were reported in these previous contributions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NIR bands of melamine remain at relatively similar positions throughout various kinds of samples, unlike its IR bands, which are prone to shifting in response to the chemical environment [
  <a rid="B43-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-molecules-24-01402">43</a>]. This can be fully confirmed by our conclusions from quantum mechanical calculations. Lu et al. [
  <a rid="B42-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-molecules-24-01402">42</a>] have reported that the most relevant spectral region of milk powder useful for the detection of melamine is 5300–4900 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. This region contains the binary and ternary combinations of NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching with NH
  <sub>2</sub> deformation modes of melamine; however, no overtone bands can be found there (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f005" href="#molecules-24-01402-f005">Figure 5</a>). Cantor et al. [
  <a rid="B9-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-molecules-24-01402">9</a>] have found that the most meaningful region for the analysis of melamine content in gelatin by IR spectroscopy is at around 800 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>; the melamine bands therein stem from 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>oop</sub>ring, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>twist</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub>, and 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>wagg</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f003" href="#molecules-24-01402-f003">Figure 3</a> and 
  <a rid="molecules-24-01402-t001" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01402-t001">Table 1</a>). On the other hand, the chemometric models that are based on NIR spectra of gelatin contaminated by melamine have been found to recognize the most the 7000–6500 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region. The NIR bands of melamine due to the first overtones and binary combinations of both symmetric and asymmetric NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching modes can be exclusively found there (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01402-f005" href="#molecules-24-01402-f005">Figure 5</a>). Our study allows for correcting Haughey et al. [
  <a rid="B45-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-molecules-24-01402">45</a>], who ascribed the NIR region of melamine in the vicinity of 6800 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> to only overtone bands.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In more detail, the influential spectral regions in chemometric analysis of melamine content in milk powders based on NIR spectroscopy has been reported by Lim et al. [
  <a rid="B46-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-molecules-24-01402">46</a>]. They have found that the partial least squares regression (PLSR) models have recognized 6763 and 6808 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> as the most meaningful in the analysis. They have concluded that these regions correspond to 6676 and 6529 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> peaks of melamine observed in the spectrum of milk powder. We may now confirm that these two bands arise from the first overtones and binary combinations of 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>as</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>s</sub>NH
  <sub>2</sub> modes of melamine, respectively. These previous chemometric analyses consistently indicate that for the detection and quantification of melamine, its NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching vibrations are the most meaningful; however, we may now indicate that not only the first overtones, but also binary combinations equally contribute. On the other hand, the lower NIR region, where combination bands due to NH
  <sub>2</sub> stretching and deformation modes of melamine are present, is less essential.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Balabin et al. [
  <a rid="B43-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-molecules-24-01402">43</a>] have concluded that, for the samples with high content of melamine, NIR spectroscopy yields better analytical performance than IR spectroscopy. It may be now confirmed that this occurs due to relatively much lower sensitivity of NIR bands to intermolecular interactions with the matrix molecules when compared to IR bands. The hydrogen-bonding influences the IR region of melamine much stronger than the NIR region, in which only minor band shifts and negligible intensity variations occur due to this effect. In such sense, this feature of pure melamine in crystal evidenced here (lower sensitivity of NIR bands than IR bands to the chemical environment of molecules of melamine), seems to also be universally preserved in complex samples consisting of various other molecules and biomolecules, e.g., in milk powder [
  <a rid="B43-molecules-24-01402" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-molecules-24-01402">43</a>]. Thus, analytical IR and NIR spectroscopy can evidence the structural and vibrational properties of melamine that were unveiled in our study to have a direct impact on the detection and quantification of melamine content.
 </p>
</sec>
