<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-molecules-24-01402" sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Experimental</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Melamine was purchased from Alfa Aesar (A11295; ≥99% purity) and used without further purification. The measurement of IR spectra was carried out on a Perkin Elmer Spectrum 100 FT-IR spectrometer that was equipped with an ATR accessory and a diamond prism (PerkinElmer, Inc. Waltham, MA, USA). The spectrometer was controlled by Perkin Elmer Spectrum software (version 10.4.00). The spectra were measured in the 4000–650 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> region with a spectral resolution of 4 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. The number of accumulated scans was 16, and the measurement procedure was triplicated. The measurement was carried out at room temperature (~298 K). Sample preparation and spectra recording procedures were triplicated for each sample.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measurement of NIR spectra was performed on a Büchi NIR Flex N-500 FT-NIR benchtop spectrometer that was controlled by the manufacturer’s NIRWare 1.4.3010 software (BUCHI
  <span class="sup">®</span> AG, Flawil, Switzerland). The spectrometer was equipped with Büchi accessory for solid samples and operated in diffuse reflectance (DRIFT) mode and at room temperature (~298 K). The following recording parameters were selected; spectral resolution, spectral range, and scan number were 8 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (resulting in the interpolated 4 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> of data spacing and 2 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> of absolute accuracy), 10,000–4000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, and 64, respectively. Sample preparation and spectra recording procedures were triplicated for each sample.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental spectra in this work presented adequate quality for qualitative assessment, with no need for preprocessing of any kind.</p>
</sec>
