<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec4-molecules-24-01402" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum mechanical calculations of IR spectra of crystalline melamine were successfully carried out for an infinite (3D periodic) lattice model. All of the experimental IR bands were accurately reproduced, even when using reasonably affordable harmonic approximation. On the other hand, finite models gave very inaccurate calculated IR spectra. In contrast, the NIR spectrum of crystalline melamine was accurately modeled by anharmonic calculations that are based on the model of a single molecule. It is a striking difference in the dependence of the quality vs. model complexity, between these two spectral regions. This result may be explained based on direct comparison of the molecular motions corresponding to the vibrations being influential for the IR and NIR regions.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vibrations involving out-of-plane atomic motions strongly affect the IR region of melamine. Therefore, it is essential to incorporate a proper description of the inter-plane interactions of melamine molecules as they appear in the crystalline lattice. The neglecting of the neighboring molecules in proximity planes leads to a completely incorrect calculated IR spectrum. In contrast, the in-plane vibrations of melamine are less affected by inter-molecular interactions. The vibrations involving in-plane atomic displacements are the most essential for the NIR spectrum of melamine. On the other hand, the out-of-plane motions are either suppressed in intensity or they are located outside of the NIR region. Hence, the calculated NIR spectrum of melamine is not significantly affected by a radical simplification of the molecular model. Even a single molecule model provides accurate reproduction of NIR spectrum of crystalline melamine. It may be concluded that the long-range ordering and, in particular, inter-plane interactions in the crystal lattice of melamine are significantly less important factors for NIR modes than for IR modes. From this observation, another important conclusion may be drawn. Due to the very significant computational cost of anharmonic calculations, the possibility to reduce the complexity of the molecular model (i.e., non-necessity to use 3D infinite model, which is also computationally costly) in the simulation of NIR spectra offers promising possibilities for similar studies of other crystalline materials.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings shed light on the spectral features of melamine that have been reported in analytical spectroscopic studies of melamine as contaminant. In particular, the concluded in literature superiority of NIR spectroscopy in the analysis of the samples with relatively higher content of melamine was explained.</p>
</sec>
