<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To conclude, we have successfully implemented a deterministic RSP protocol over a distance of 35 cm in the microwave regime with continuous variables and explored the influence of different parameters on the remotely prepared states. We have remotely prepared squeezed states with a squeezing level of up to 1.6 dB below the vacuum limit. In our specific RSP implementation, Alice can control the squeezing level and, to some extent, the squeezing angle of the remotely prepared state at the expense of a reduced purity. Additionally, we demonstrate that the protocol can be interpreted as a secure one-time pad near the optimal point. The operational range of both the RSP and quantum one-time pad protocols can be extended to any angle 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>
  <sub>rp</sub> by an additional phase shifter on Alice’s side. The demonstrated protocol opens a way to a multitude of intriguing experiments with quantum microwaves such as probing the Holevo bound limits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, studying the role of quantum discord in quantum communication protocols
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, exploring hybrid continuous-discrete schemes of quantum information processing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>, and implementing quantum illumination protocols
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. Squeezing operations can further be exploited for the preparation of Gottesman-Kitaev-Preskill (GKP) states for continuous-variable quantum error correction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. Our experiment proves that prototypical local quantum networks using continuous-variable quantum microwaves are within experimental reach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
