<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sandwich complexes, that is, compounds bearing exclusively two planar, cyclic and π-bonded ligands, are a fundamental class of compounds in organometallic chemistry. In fact, the discovery of ferrocene [(η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>Fe] by Kealy and Pauson
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> and the subsequent structural analysis by Fischer and Wilkinson paved the way to modern organometallic chemistry
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Ever since, the quest for new sandwich complexes has been a central part of modern organometallic chemistry. In the last decades, sandwich complexes, and particularly ferrocene, have become widely used compounds, which found a variety of applications, e.g. in synthesis, catalysis, electrochemistry, medicine and even as fuel additive
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. In a classical homoleptic sandwich or metallocene complex, two identical aromatic ring systems equally bind with all carbon atoms to a metal center
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Well established examples of this structural motif are the above-mentioned ferrocene, bis(benzene)chromium and uranocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Besides these homoleptic complexes, there are also examples of heteroleptic sandwich complexes ligated by two different aromatic ring systems. As aromatic moieties, rings ranging from three to nine-membered systems have been established in organometallic chemistry. Despite the large variety of possible ligand permutations, considering these seven different ring sizes, only a limited number of structurally characterized ligand combinations has been reported in terms of homoleptic and heteroleptic complexes. These are the four non-substituted homoleptic metallocene archetypes with five to nine-membered rings: [(η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>M]
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, [(η
  <span class="sup">6</span>-C
  <sub>6</sub>H
  <sub>6</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>M]
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, [(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>M]
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, and [(η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>M] (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Considering heteroleptic sandwich complexes, only four non-substituted types were structurally characterized, which are: [(η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)M(η
  <span class="sup">4</span>-C
  <sub>4</sub>H
  <sub>4</sub>)]
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, [(η
  <span class="sup">6</span>-C
  <sub>6</sub>H
  <sub>6</sub>)M(η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)]
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, [(η
  <span class="sup">7</span>-C
  <sub>7</sub>H
  <sub>7</sub>)M(η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)]
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, and [(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)M(η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)] (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. All of these are cyclopentadienyl derivatives combined with four to eight-membered rings.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Examples of sandwich complexes. Structurally characterized homoleptic and heteroleptic metallocenes with C
     <sub>x</sub> ring systems (x = 4–9; M = metal atom)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10976_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e578" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Obviously, the vast majority of sandwich complexes is ligated by cyclopentadienyl derived moieties. In contrast, complexes ligated by larger aromatic monocycles are scarce. Therefore, we define the class of sandwich complexes having more than 16 carbon atoms coordinated to the central metal atom as super sandwich compounds, to distinguish them from classical sandwich complexes.</p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the most recent application of sandwich compounds in rare earth chemistry is their use as single molecule magnets (SMMs)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Such lanthanide-based SMMs have been shown to act as quantum computing units, so-called qudits, for the implementation of Grover´s quantum search algorithm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>, and more recently have displayed magnetic hysteresis at liquid nitrogen temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A popular model for the SMM behavior of mononuclear lanthanide complexes focuses on the stabilization of the corresponding lanthanide ions 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>J</sub> ground state by tuning the local electron density around the lanthanide ion generated by the ligand sphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. Two prominent examples proving this concept are dysprosium and erbium. For example, the highest 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>J</sub> state (±15/2) for dysprosium(III) has an oblate shape, thus an axial ligand field enhances the anisotropic properties of dysprosium containing complexes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Recently, significant advances were reported by using homo- and heteroleptic cyclopentadienyl based dysprosium(III) metallocene cations, which exhibit a highly axial ligand field, enabling record high anisotropy barriers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. On the other hand the highest 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>J</sub> state of erbium(III) is prolate shaped, therefore, an equatorial ligand field is beneficial in this case. This can be achieved by introducing one or two η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub> ligands, which exert a strong equatorial ligand field, into the coordination sphere of erbium ions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. These two examples highlight that the local symmetry generated around the central lanthanide ion, determined by the ligand field and the rigidity of the complex, plays a crucial role in the design of SMMs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. A review published recently pointed out that other, uncommon ligand systems, such as the cyclononatetraenyl anion may shed light on interesting properties in terms of SMM behavior and fundamental magneto-structural correlations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herein, we present a long sought for class of sandwich complexes [(η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)Ln(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)], which exclusively contain fully π-coordinated eight and nine-membered rings. Synthesizing these compounds was already attempted by Streitwieser et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span> in 1973, shortly after the first successful synthesis of KC
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub> was reported by Katz and coworkers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Their strategy was based on a one-pot reaction between LnCl
  <sub>3</sub> (Ln=Ce(III), Pr(III), Nd(III), Sm(III)), K
  <sub>2</sub>C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>, and KC
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>. However, they could only isolate complexes of the type [(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)LnCl(thf)
  <sub>2</sub>] thereby highlighting, that the C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>
  <span class="sup">–</span> anion does not form sandwich complexes analogous to C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="sup">–</span>. After a 45 years quest for [(η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)Ln(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)], we now report a synthetic protocol based on two distinct steps.
 </p>
</sec>
