<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Magnetic properties of [(η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)Er(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)] (3d)
 </div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the single-crystal X-ray structures of 
  <span class="bold">3c</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3d</span> show some disorder, we conclude an almost coplanar η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub> and η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub> arrangement of the ligands as observed in 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span>, based on the Raman-spectroscopic analysis. This arrangement is known to exert an equatorial ligand field, which drastically stabilizes prolate shaped 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>J</sub> states of lanthanide ions. The prime example for this family of trivalent lanthanide ions in terms of single molecule magnetic behavior is without doubt erbium (
  <span class="italic">vide supra</span>), where the equatorial ligand field exerted by a η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub> ligand, can yield SMMs with not just large energy barriers to the relaxation of the magnetization, but also leading to open hysteresis loops at temperatures as high as 10 K
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. We, therefore, carried out detailed magnetic studies on compound 
  <span class="bold">3d</span>, to test whether the asymmetric η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>/η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub> ligand field enhances the magnetic anisotropy of the sandwiched erbium ion. The rationale is two-fold: (
  <span class="italic">i</span>) as mentioned above η8-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub> ligands exert a strong equatorial ligand field, resulting in erbium compounds showing slow relaxation of the magnetization; and (
  <span class="italic">ii</span>) the introduction of a larger cyclic ring as η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub> could allow a closer Er-C contact, which could increase the equatorial ligand field, therefore enhancing the anisotropic characteristics of 
  <span class="bold">3d</span>. DC magnetic susceptibility studies of 
  <span class="bold">3d</span> were conducted in an applied field of 
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>dc</sub> = 1 kOe. At room temperature the 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub>
  <span class="italic">T</span>(
  <span class="italic">T</span>) (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub> is the molar magnetic susceptibility) value is 11.25 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span> K mol
  <span class="sup">–1</span>, in agreement with the expected value for an isolated Er(III) ion (c.f. 11.48 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span> K mol
  <span class="sup">–1</span> for 
  <span class="italic">J</span> = 15/2, g
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">J</span>
  </sub> = 6/5). The moment decreases smoothly upon cooling, until ca. 6 K, where it sharply decreases to 7.13 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span> K mol
  <span class="sup">–1</span> at 2 K (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). The abrupt drop in 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub>
  <span class="italic">T</span>(
  <span class="italic">T</span>) indicates magnetic blocking, where pinning of the magnetic moment in the immobilized crystalline material occurs.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dynamic behavior of 
  <span class="bold">3d</span> was probed via magnetic susceptibility AC studies under zero applied DC field. A single peak is observed in the temperature and frequency dependent out-of-phase magnetic susceptibility, i.e. 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub>”(
  <span class="italic">T</span>) and 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub>”(ν), respectively. This result is in agreement with the dynamic studies for [(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>Er]
  <span class="sup">–</span> 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>, while they differ from the asymmetric [(η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Er(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)] counterparts
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, where two maxima were observed. The 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub>”(
  <span class="italic">T</span>, ν) reveals a temperature dependent maximum at temperatures between 16–26 K, whilst below 15 K the maximum in 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub>”(ν) remains practically constant (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a</a>). Between 18 and 26 K, the Arrhenius analysis of 
  <span class="italic">τ</span> at different temperatures show a relaxation dominated thermally activated Orbach process, whereas below 9 K temperature independent processes dominate. The curvature between 10 and 15 K suggests that other relaxations pathways, such as Raman, are also active. The distribution of the relaxation parameter (
  <span class="italic">α</span>) likewise indicates a narrow distribution of relaxation times between 20 K and 26 K (
  <span class="italic">α</span> ≤ 0.18(1)), while for temperatures below 15 K the parameter is greater (
  <span class="italic">α</span> ≥ 0.18(1)). The energy barrier 
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>eff</sub> of 251(1) cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>0</sub> = 1.3(2) × 10
  <span class="sup">–10</span> s (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b</a>) are very similar to the ones observed for homoleptic and heteroleptic erbium complexes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. The plateau at temperatures between 2 and 5 K marks the quantum tunneling of the magnetization regime, with a 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>QTM</sub> = 0.18(1) s. Application of an optimal field of 2 kG (at which relaxation is slower), efficiently suppressed QTM, leading to an almost purely temperature dependent relaxation (green symbols in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b</a> and SI (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">14</a>)), with a slightly enhanced 
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>eff</sub> = 261(1) cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>.
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Magnetic properties of 
     <span class="bold">3d</span>. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Experimental out-of-phase magnetic susceptibility (
     <span class="italic">χ</span>
     <sub>M</sub>”(ν)) for 
     <span class="bold">3d</span> in the temperature range of 16 to 26 K (filled circles). Solid lines are the fittings to a generalized Debye model. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Arrhenius analysis of the relaxation times (
     <span class="italic">τ</span>) for 
     <span class="bold">3d</span> with 
     <span class="italic">H</span>
     <sub>DC</sub> = 0 (red) and with 
     <span class="italic">H</span>
     <sub>DC</sub> = 2 kG (green). The black line corresponds to the thermally active regime, whilst the blue dashed line represents the QTM regime. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Hysteresis measurements for 
     <span class="bold">3d</span> between ±2 T and from 1.8 K to 10 K employing a field sweep rate of 700 G/s; 
     <span class="bold">d</span> optimized structure of 
     <span class="bold">3d</span> and direction of the principal magnetic anisotropy axis obtained from CASSCF calculations (green arrow). 
     <span class="bold">e</span>
     <span class="italic">ab initio</span> calculated electronic states of the 
     <span class="italic">J</span> = 15/2 manifold of the 
     <span class="sup">4</span>I term of 
     <span class="bold">3d</span> and the most probable relaxation pathway for the magnetization represented by the red arrows, involving spin phonon excitation to the first and second doublets. The thick black lines represent the Kramers doublet states as function of their magnetic moments
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10976_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e2148" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An open magnetic hysteresis is the ultimate proof of the strong anisotropic behavior in SMMs and their bistable magnetic behavior. Extrapolation of the Arrhenius data to low temperature indicates that the observation of magnetic hysteresis below 12 K is feasible, where the relaxation time is 100 s. To confirm the SMM behavior and the slow relaxation observed through AC studies, magnetization hysteresis loops were collected between 1.8–10 K. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7c</a> shows butterfly-like hysteresis loops between 2 and 10 K and a field ranging from ±2 T, leading to a blocking temperature (
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>B</sub>) of 10 K. Note that, albeit the energy barrier being rather large, the hysteresis loops are practically close at zero field, strongly indicating that QTM is rather efficient, as commonly observed in lanthanide-based SMMs.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To gain deeper insight into the relaxation mechanism and the anisotropic magnetic properties of 
  <span class="bold">3d</span>, CASSCF/SO-RASSI/SINGLE_ANISO calculations were performed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. Due to the highly disordered character of the crystal structure of 
  <span class="bold">3d</span>, CASSCF calculation were carried out employing an optimized crystal structure (see SI for details). The electronic calculation predicts a highly axial ground state with g
  <sub>z</sub> = 17.95 and g
  <sub>x,y</sub> ≈ 10
  <span class="sup">–5</span>. As observed in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7d</a>, the anisotropy axis is perpendicular to the η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub> and η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub> planes. Employing the ligand field parameters from electronic calculations, we find that the ground, first and second excited states are almost colinear and highly pure 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>J</sub> = ±15/2 and ±13/2 and ±1/2 states, respectively. The relative energies for the first and second excited state are 140 and 268 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>. The succeeding excited states are highly pure and huddled over 330–490 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>. As it can be observed in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7e</a>, 
  <span class="italic">ab</span>-initio results reproduce rather well the 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <sub>M</sub>
  <span class="italic">T</span>(
  <span class="italic">T</span>) and 
  <span class="italic">M</span>(
  <span class="italic">H</span>) (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>) with only small differences. The discrepancies might arise by structural distortions not reflected in the geometry optimization. Using the average matrix elements of magnetic moment between the electronic states, it is predicted that the most efficient magnetic relaxation pathway is to occur via thermally assisted QTM through the second excited state at 268 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>. As observed, this state is very close to the U
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">eff</span>
  </sub> obtained from dynamic studies (
  <span class="italic">cf</span>. ~260 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7e</a>)). Interestingly, the energy barrier is also very similar to the antisymmetric vibration of the C
  <sub>8</sub>/C
  <sub>9</sub> rings observed in the Raman spectrum (240 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>). As molecular vibrations have been predicted to facilitate spin-phonon coupling, these could be relevant for the relaxation in 
  <span class="bold">3d</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Note that the strongly equatorial ligand field exerted by the η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub> and η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub> ligands is optimal at stabilizing the largest 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>J</sub> state for Er(III), characterized by a prolate electron density, as demonstrated by the magnetic studies and supported by CASSCF calculations. In contrast, for the Dy(III) ions an axial ligand field is more suitable to stabilize the largest 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>J</sub> = 15/2 state, thus the anisotropic magnetic properties in [(η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)Dy(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)] are expectedly worse, as confirmed by AC tests and other reports
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
