<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Raman-spectroscopic analysis</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We further investigated the bonding situation and ligand aromaticity using Raman spectroscopy and vibrational analysis. Fourier transform Raman (FT-Raman) spectra of 
  <span class="bold">3a</span>–
  <span class="bold">3d</span> were recorded powdered samples (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). The band assignments were validated by quantum chemical calculations. The Raman spectra can be divided in two sections: (i) above 300 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> the spectra of all molecules are almost identical as the signals are solely attributable to both sandwich ligands. Vibrational coupling to the lanthanide cations is not expected due to the orthogonality of the in-plane vibrations of the ligands with respect to that of the lanthanide-ring centroid
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. Therefore, the signals at 3042 (η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>) and 3006 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>) are attributed to the fully symmetric C–H-valence motions, those at 1495 (η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>) and 1517 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>) to the antisymmetric C–C-stretching vibrations of the ligands. A third group of bands belongs to the (local) symmetric ring breathing modes at 749 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>sym</sub>(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)) and at 681 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (
  <span class="italic">ν</span>
  <sub>sym</sub>(η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)). Analyzing these modes is an unambiguous proof of the ring size and the bond strength within these aromatic ligand systems. According to normal coordinate analyses on C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>
  <span class="sup">–</span>, C
  <sub>6</sub>H
  <sub>6</sub> and C
  <sub>7</sub>H
  <sub>7</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span> 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> the stretching force constant values of the C–H and C–C bonds are each of comparable size. Assuming, this is furthermore true for larger aromatic C
  <sub>n</sub>H
  <sub>n</sub> monocyclic ligand systems, the approximate wavenumber of the fully symmetric ring breathing mode is easily calculated using a mathematical expression deduced in the Supplemental Information (see Supplementary Equation 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This formula nicely reproduces the observed ring breathing mode energies of the two ligands (
  <span class="italic">ν</span>(C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>2
  <span class="sup">–</span>) = 754 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (calc. 761 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>) and ν(C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>
  <span class="sup">–</span>) = 680 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (calc. 680 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>)) and therefore, confirms the comparable bonding situation in these ligand systems with those of aromatic ligands like C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>
  <span class="sup">–</span>, C
  <sub>6</sub>H
  <sub>6</sub> and C
  <sub>7</sub>H
  <sub>7</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span> (see 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">SI</a> for details). (ii) At vibrational energies lower than 300 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> lanthanide-ring centroid stretching modes are expected in the Raman spectra of [(η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)Ln(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)]. Due to the larger (η
  <span class="sup">9</span>-C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>9</sub>)-Ln bond lengths their vibrations are found between 100 and 166 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>, whereas those of the shorter Ln-(η
  <span class="sup">8</span>-C
  <sub>8</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>) bonds are observed between 236 and 247 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (Nd, 
  <span class="bold">3a</span>: 137.0 (s), 242.1 (s); Sm, 
  <span class="bold">3b</span>: 126.8 (s), 236.0 (vs); Dy, 
  <span class="bold">3c</span>: 100 (s), 237.2 (s) and Er, 
  <span class="bold">3d</span>: 165.9 (m), 207.4 (m)). Both vibrations remind of the symmetric and antisymmetric modes of triatomic linear molecules like CO
  <sub>2</sub>. For these bands, the agreement with the results of the quantum chemical calculations is only of limited accordance due to possible coupling with lattice vibrations (see Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4b</a> in the SI). However, 
  <span class="bold">3a</span>–
  <span class="bold">d</span> are rare cases in modern organometallic chemistry, in which the coordination mode of the ligands can be determined by Raman spectroscopy as sole method.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Raman-spectroscopic analysis. FT-Raman spectrum of [(η
     <span class="sup">9</span>-C
     <sub>9</sub>H
     <sub>9</sub>)Sm(η
     <span class="sup">8</span>-C
     <sub>8</sub>H
     <sub>8</sub>)] 
     <span class="bold">3b</span>. The motion vectors of four prominent bands are inserted. Hydrogen atoms and their motion vectors are omitted for clarity
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10976_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1733" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
