<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CE-LIF of QD-conjugates</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To verify the formation of the conjugates, CE-LIF was used. QDs, QDs-HWR, QDs-HWR-AB, and QDs-HWR-AB-AG were measured to confirm that each step of conjugation was successful. As can be seen from the Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, formation of various species was confirmed. The CdS QDs have negative charge as found by measurement of ζ-potential. Hence they have the highest migration time (5.38 minutes). HWR peptide sequence contains several positively charged amino acids and therefore, the conjugate of QD with HWR exhibited positive charge and its migration time decreased (3.26 minutes). The migration time of QD-HWR-AB complex was 3.78 minutes due to the increase in the size as well as increase of the negative charge. Similarly, when the complex QD-HWR-AB-AG was created (after addition of AG in total concentration 0.026 mg ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), further increase in migration time was observed (4.32 minutes). Moreover, significant increase in the fluorescence intensity is observed when the HWR peptide is connected to CdS QDs. It is supposed that the increase relates to the fluorescence resonance energy transfer occurring within the formed complex. HWR peptide contains 1 molecule of histidine with an aromatic ring responsible for absorption maximum at 390 nm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. Hence the light supplied by the excitation LED was absorbed by the histidine and transferred to the connected QD. This is believed to lead to the fluorescence signal enhancement. However this was not the aim of this study and therefore, it was not further investigated in detail.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Electropherogram recording consequent complex formation by CE-LIF. Fluorescence excitation at 395 nm, total length 47 cm, effective length 40 cm, internal diameter 75 μm, electrolyte - 20 mM sodium borate buffer (pH = 9), separation voltage - 20 kV, injection - 5 psi for 5 s.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48290_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e632" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
