<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MIP-immunoassay design</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two approaches towards the MIP-immunoassay design (schematically shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3A,B</a>) were tested. In the first concept (concept labelled A), only the AG was used as a template and therefore, the MIP selective only for AG was prepared. After that, AG was selectively isolated from the sample and subsequently, the MIP surface (with AG extracted from the sample) was overlaid by the QD-AB conjugate.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematic representation of two concepts of immunoassay combining QD-labelled antibodies and MIP technology. (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) 1-imprinting of the AG, 2-extraction of the AG from the sample by MIP, overlay with QD-AB conjugate, 3-interaction of the conjugate with the extracted AG from the sample, removal of the unreacted conjugate. (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) 1 - imprinting of the complex QD-AB-AG, 2 - QD-AB-AG formed in the sample after addition of QD-AB conjugate into the sample solution and extraction of QD-AB-AG complex from the sample by MIP for removal of interferents from the sample. (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) Correlative Probe and Electron Microscopy (CPEM) imaging of MIP layer with imprinted QD-AB conjugate. 1 – SEM image, 2 - AFM image of the same area and sample in the same coordinate system. 3 – profile of a well formed due to the imprinting process.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48290_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e711" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second approach (concept labelled B), the whole complex QD-AB-AG was imprinted (used as template) and during the analysis, this complex was formed directly within the sample and subsequently extracted by MIP.</p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3C</a>, the surface visualization obtained by Correlative Probe and Electron Microscopy (CPEM) is shown. SEM image (1) and AFM image (2) were obtained simultaneously from the same region of the sample. Mainly two regions of the surface are of our interest (red and blue circle). Even though SEM image shows similar contrast of both regions, AFM imaging clearly confirms differences between the flat surface (blue circle) and wells formed due to the imprinting process (red circle). Profile of one of the wells is shown in (3).
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, significant differences between MIP and NIP were detected in both concepts. The MIP/NIP signal ratio was 13.5 and 3.4 for concept A and concept B, respectively. This result, however demonstrates the concept A to be less influenced by the non-specific adsorption of the sample components on the polymeric layer (NIP signal).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>ICP-MS signal intensities (MIPs and NIPs) obtained by analysis of IgG standard sample by assay concepts A and B described in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48290_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e735" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lower intensities (both MIP and NIP) are observed in concept A compared to concept B. This is probably due to the fact that when the concept A is applied, the antigen only is imprinted, but its orientation in the polydopamine layer may not always be correct; that means, when the antigen is oriented so that the interaction site is not accessible for the QD-labelled antibody, the antigen-antibody interaction is prevented.</p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, the concept B is providing 2.9-fold higher MIP signal compared to concept A suggesting better sensitivity of this approach. The significantly higher NIP signal (11.6-fold) of B concept compared to approach A is probably given by the fact that some mole-cules of AA-QD complex are more prone to non-specific adsorption.</p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LODs of both concepts were calculated according to 3 σ: concept A – 4.2 μg, concept B – 1.6 μg.</p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NIP is prepared under identical conditions and also with identical construction as MIP. The difference is that NIP is prepared without the presence of the template. It is taken as an indicator of non-specific binding. The NIP has functional groups randomly arranged on its surface that interact with analyte and cause to some extent bindings. These non-specific bindings are weaker than those of the MIP. The difference in binding to the MIP and the NIP are caused by selective binding sites in MIP created by imprinting of template molecule
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>. On the surface of NIP, monomer self-association occurs and reduces the number of free functional groups where the analyte can be bound. Therefore NIP is able to bound less amount of analyte.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the above mentioned facts, concept B was evaluated as more sensitive as it yields in lower LOD and therefore, was used for isolation and detection of IgG from complex model sample. For this purpose, the protein ladder was used. It consists of mixture of proteins in range from 10–180 kDa (lysozyme, α-lactalbumin, trypsin inhibitor, carbonic anhydrase, ovalbumin, bovine serum albumin, phosphorylase B, β-galactosidase; 0.1–0.3 mg/ml each). Scheme of experiment is illustrated in the Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5A</a>. The idea of this experiment is that the conjugate QD-AB-AG (QD-antiIgG-IgG) is imprinted. Then the QD-AB (QD-antiIgG) conjugate is added into the solution of protein ladder and the AG (IgG) from the sample is captured forming QD-AB-AG (QD-antiIgG-IgG) conjugate. After the overlay of the MIP by this solution, QD-antiIgG-IgG conjugate is captured in the cavities and interfering proteins are washed.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Schematic representation of isolation and detection IgG from the same complex sample. At first the conjugate (QD-Ab) is added to the complex sample. The conjugate reacts with IgG contained in sample and creates the complex (QD-AB-AG) with them. The complex is bound to the cavity in MIP that is specific for this. The bound complex is subsequently detected by LA-ICP-MS. (B) ICP-MS signal intensities obtained by analysis of model protein mixture either with or without added IgG extracted by the assay schematically shown in (
     <span class="bold">A</span>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48290_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e767" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mixture of proteins with and without addition of IgG was measured. The addition of IgG was 2.5 μg. The mixture of proteins and the QD-AB conjugate was mixed in ratio 1:1. The results are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5B</a>. It is clearly seen that mixture without IgG addition produces the signal intensity indistinguishable from the NIP, which is due to the nonspecific adsorption. However, it is impossible to distinguish whether the sample components are or the QD-AB conjugate are nonspecifically adsorbed on MIP surface. While after the addition of IgG a significant increase of Cd intensity relating to presence of QD-antiIgG-IgG conjugate is observed. It means that the Concept B is able to isolate IgG from the complex sample containing a mixture of proteins. In comparison results for concept B from Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> significantly lower sensitivity and higher LOD was found. This deterioration of the parameters is caused probably due to the matrix effect of the proteins present in the sample.
 </p>
</sec>
