<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optimization of ablation parameters</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Laser ablation parameters as the laser beam fluence, laser spot size and scan speed were optimized to get a combination of both parameters with high sensitivity and high stability (low relative standard deviation - RSD) of the measured signal of 
  <span class="sup">111</span>Cd. For all optimization, the slide was covered by a layer of polydopamine surface imprinted with CdS QDs with a diameter of 18 nm. First, optimization of laser beam fluence and laser spot size was carried out. Laser ablation system operates in 2 modes of laser beam focusing: I) Imaging mode – the laser spot size selected by using suitable aperture and II) Focused mode – the laser spot size selected by moving the lens. In the case of the imaging mode, the laser beam energy was more homogeneous across the laser beam cross section than in case of the Focused mode. To get the highest amount of the ablated material the largest available laser beam diameters for each focusing mode were tested – 110 (imaging) and 250 μm (focused). The laser beam fluence was changed in a range from 0.5 to 6.0 J/cm
  <span class="sup">2</span>. Under optimal laser beam fluence and laser spot size, the optimization of scan speed was done. Each combination of laser spot size and laser beam fluence was done as a line scan in triplicates on different places on the slide. The arithmetic average and relative standard deviations were calculated. The results of the optimization of laser beam spot size and fluence are summarized in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> The pink and blue columns represent the laser beam diameters of 110 and 250 μm, respectively. As expected, the 250 μm laser beam spot provided significantly higher intensities compared to the 110 μm laser beam. In the case of the signal stability, the results obtained by 250 μm laser beam spot exhibited lower RSD compared to 110 μm laser beam spot. Hence, the laser beam spot of 250 μm was selected as optimal. Once the laser beam fluence was optimized, the largest intensities were achieved for 4 and 6 J/cm
  <span class="sup">2</span>. However, the lower stability of the signal was obtained. Therefore, the laser beam fluence of 2 J/cm
  <span class="sup">2</span> was used as a compromise between the signal sensitivity and stability.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Influence of laser beam diameters (110 and 250 μm) and fluence (0.5, 2, 4, and 6 J/cm
     <span class="sup">2</span>) on intensity of 
     <span class="sup">111</span>Cd signal.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48290_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e680" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subsequently, the optimal scan speed was searched. It was found that scan speed affected neither the sensitivity nor the stability of the 
  <span class="sup">111</span>Cd signal. The RSD of the signal intensity varied from 10 to 15% for all 4 tested scan speeds (300, 800, 1200 and 2000 μm/s). Hence, the criterion for selection of scan speed was the duration of the analysis. When the scan speed of 2000 μm/s was applied, the overall duration of the analysis was about 23 s.
 </p>
</sec>
