<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avogadro</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avogadro is an open source, cross-platform desktop application to manipulate and visualize chemical data in 3D. It is available on all major operating systems, and uses Open Babel for much of its file input and output as well as basic forcefields and cheminformatics techniques. Avogadro was already capable of downloading chemical structures from the NIH structure resolver service, editing structures and optimizing those structures.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Input generation from these structures is present for many of the major computational chemistry codes Quixote targets such as GAMESS(US), GAMESS-UK, Gaussian, NWChem, MOPAC and others. These dialogs allow the user to change input parameters before producing input files to be run by the code. The output files from several of these codes can also be read directly, this functionality was recently split out into OpenQube - a library to read quantum computational code log files, and calculate molecular orbitals, electron density and other output.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ultimately, much of this functionality will move into the Quixote parsers, with the OpenQube library concentrating on multithreaded calculation of electronic structure parameters. A native CML reader plugin has also been developed for Avogadro, to read in CML files directly and display the tree structure allowing visual exploration of CML files. As JUMBO and other tools can extract electronic structure, spectra and vibrational data, this plugin is being developed to extract them from the CML document.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avogadro is already network aware, with a network fetch extension interacting with the NIH structure resolver and the Protein Data Bank (PDB). Experimental support for interacting with a local queue manager is also being actively developed, sending input files to the queue manager, and retrieving log files one the calculation is complete. Some data management features are being added, and as Chempound has a web API a plugin for upload, searching and downloading of structures will be added. A MongoDB-based application has been prototyped, using a document store approach to storing chemical data. This approach coupled with Chempound repositories and seamless integration in the GUI will significantly lower barriers for both deposition and retrieval of relevant computational chemistry output.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avogadro forms a central part of the computational chemistry workflow, but is in desparate need of high quality chemical data. The data available from existing online chemical repositories is a good start, but having high quality, discoverable computational chemistry output would significantly improve efficiency in the field. Widespread access to optimized chemical structures using high level theories and large basis sets would benefit everyone from teaching right through to academic research and industry.</p>
</sec>
