<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Community development</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the human resource point of view, the Quixote project operates on a decentralised approach with no central site and with all participants contributing when available, and in whatever quantity they can donate at a particular time. For that reason, different parts of the project progress at variable speeds and technically independently. This means that there is very little effort required in collating and synthesising other than the general ontological problem of agreeing within a community the meaning deployment and use of terms and concepts.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The work is currently driven (
  <span class="italic">cf</span>. use cases) by datasets which are available. This drives the need to write parsers, collate labels into dictionaries, and collate results. In the week of 2011-05-09, for example, we ran daily Skype conferences, with Openly editable Etherpads 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://quixote.wikispot.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://quixote.wikispot.org/</span> generously provided by the Open Knowledge Foundation (OKF) 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://okfn.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://okfn.org/</span>. The participants created tutorial material, wiki pages, examples and discussions which over the week focused us to a core set of between 20-50 dictionary entries that should relate to any computational chemistry output. The input to this effort was informed by logfiles from the Gaussian, NWChem, Jaguar and GAMESS-UK programs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The initial approach has been to parse logfiles with JUMBO-Parser, as this can be applied to any legacy logfiles and does not require alterations of code. (At a later date we shall promote the use of CML-output libraries in major codes.) At this stage it is probably the best approach to analyse the concepts and their structure. A JUMBO-Parser is written for each code and run over a series of example logfiles. Ideally every part of every line is analysed and the semantic content extracted. In practice each new logfile instance can bring novel structure and syntax but it is straightforward to determine which sections have been parsed and which have not. Parsing failure may be because a parser has not been written for those sections, or because the syntax varies between different problems and runs. The parser writer can then determine whether the un-parsed sections are important enough to devote effort to, or whether they are of minor importance and can be effectively deleted.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The process is highly iterative. The parser templates do not cover all possible document sections and initially some parts remain unparsed. The parsers are then amended and re-run; it is relatively simple in XML to determine which parts still need work.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently (2011-06) there are about 200 templates for NWChem, 150 for Gaussian and a small number for Jaguar, GAMESS-UK, GAMESS(US), AMBER and MOPAC 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://openmopac.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://openmopac.net</span>. Each time a parse fails, the section is added as a failing unit test to the template and these also act as tutorial material and a primary source of semantics for the dictionary entries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quixote is designed as a bottom-up community project and co-ordinated through the modern metaphors of wikis, mailing lists, Etherpads and distributed autonomous implementations. The primary entry point is currently 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://quixote.wikispot.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://quixote.wikispot.org/</span> which gives details of current resources and how to get involved.
 </p>
</sec>
