<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each day, countless calculations are run by thousands of computational chemistry researchers around the world, on everything from ageing, dusty desktops to the most powerful supercomputers on the planet. It might be supposed that this would lead to a deluge of valuable data, but the surprising fact remains that most of this data, if it is archived at all, usually lies hidden away on hard disks or buried on tape backups; often lost to the original researcher and never seen by the wider chemistry community at all.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, it is widely accepted that if the results of all these calculations were publicly accessible it would be extremely valuable as it would:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• avoid the costly duplication of results,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• allow different codes to be easily validated and benchmarked,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• provide the data required for the development of new methods,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• provide a valuable resource for data mining,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• provide an easy, automated way of generating and archiving supporting information for publications.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the rare cases when data is made openly available, the output of calculations are inevitably produced in a code-specific format; there being no currently accepted output standard. This means that interpreting or reusing the data requires knowledge of the code, or the use of specific software that understands the output. A standard semantic format will:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• allow tools, (
  <span class="italic">e.g</span>. GUIs) to operate on the input and output of any code supporting the format, vastly increasing their utility and range,
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• enable different codes to interoperate to create complex workflows,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• additionally, if a semantic model underlies the format, data can easily be validated.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The benefits of a common data standard and results databases are obvious, but several previous efforts have failed to address them, largely because of an inability to settle on a data standard or provide any useful tools that would make it worthwhile for code developers to expend the time to make their codes compatible.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Quixote project aims to tackle both of these problems in a pragmatic way, building an infrastructure that can be used to both archive and search calculations on a local hard-drive, or expose the data on publicly accessible servers to make it available to the wider community.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The vision with which we started the Quixote project some months ago is one in which all data generated in computational QC research projects is used with maximal efficiency, is immediately made available online and aggregated into global search indexes, a vision in which no work is duplicated by researchers and everyone can get an overall picture of what has been calculated for a given system, for a given scientific question, in a matter of minutes, a vision in which all players collaborate to achieve maximum interoperability between the different stages of the scientific process of discovery, in which commonly agreed, semantically rich formats are used, and all publications expose the data as readable and reusable supplementary material, thus enforcing reproducibility of the results; a vision in which good practices are wide spread in the community, and the greatest benefit is earned from the effort invested by everyone working in the field.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the prototype presented in this article, which has been validated by real use cases, we believe this vision is beginning to be accomplished.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The methodological approach in Quixote is novel: The data standard will be consolidated around the tools and encourage its adoption by providing code and tool developers with an obvious reason for adopting the data standard; the "If you build it, they will come" approach. The project is rooted in the belief that scientific codes and data should be "Open", and we are therefore focussing our efforts on using existing Open Source solutions and standards where possible, and then developing any additional tools within the project. The Quixote project is itself completely Open, de-centralised and community-driven. It is composed of passionate researchers from around the globe that are happy to collaborate with anyone who shares our aims.</p>
</sec>
