<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Design of Scientific data repositories</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper we describe a novel, flexible, multipurpose repository technology. It arises out of a series of meetings and projects in the computational chemistry (compchem) community which have addressed the desire and need to have repositories available for capturing and disseminating the results of QC calculations. It is also strongly influenced by the eScience ("cyberinfrastructure", "eResearch") programs which have streesed the value of instant semantic access to research information from many disciplines, and by the Open Innovation vision supported by the Scientific Software Working Group of CECAM (Centre Européen de Calcul Atomique et Moléculaire) 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cecam.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cecam.org/</span>, which seeks an innovation model based on sharing, trust and collaboration, and which recognizes the important role played by the availability of reference data and archives of outputs of calculations and simulations. It also coincides with the increasing mandates for data publication from a wide range of funders; our repository can address a large part of these requirements.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper describes a distributed repository technology and the social aspects associated with developing its use. The technology is robust and deployed but the way it may be used is at a very early stage. We address known social issues (sustainability, quality, etc.) but expect that deployment, even in the short term, may look very different from what is reported.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The development and acceptance of Wikipedia may act as a valuable guide and it represents a community-driven activity with community-controlled quality. Although variable, we believe that articles for most mainstream physical sciences are reliable. Thus to help understand and represent moments of inertia in computational chemistry we can link to Wikipedia 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moment_of_inertia" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moment_of_inertia</span>. This contains many hundreds of edits over eight years from many authors - it is almost certainly "correct". Quixote has many of the same features - anyone can contribute content and repurpose it. We expect a culture to emerge where the community sets guidelines for contributions and corrections/annotations. We are building filters ("lenses") so that the community can identify subcollections of specific quality or value.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The background to Quixote includes a number of meetings and projects which specifically addressed the development of infrastructure in computational chemistry and materials. The goal of these was to explore the commonality between approaches and see how data and processes could interoperate. One (Materials Grid) also addressed the design and implementation of a repository for results.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• 2004: A meeting under the UK eScience program "Toward a common data and command representation for quantum chemistry" 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nesc.ac.uk/action/esi/contribution.cfm?Title=394" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nesc.ac.uk/action/esi/contribution.cfm?Title=394</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• 2006: A meeting under the auspices of CECAM "Data representation and code interoperability for computational materials physics and chemistry" 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cecam.org/workshop-50.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cecam.org/workshop-50.html</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• 2005-2010: A 5-year project under the COST D37 program to develop various aspects of interoperability both within the calculation (Q5COST) and between programs (WG5).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• A funded project in computational materials ("Materials Grid") 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.materialsgrid.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.materialsgrid.org/</span> which resulted in considerable development of CML specifications and trial implementations in a number of codes (CASTEP, DLPOLY).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These meetings and projects were exploratory and localized. Within them there was a general agreement that interoperability and access to results would be a great benefit. But they also highlighted the problem that infrastructure development is expensive and, if public, requires political justification for funding. Such funding is perhaps most likely to come from supranational efforts such as computational Grids, where there is a clear imperative for making services as accessible as possible. In COST-D37 the funding was for meetings and interchange visits; the WG5 community made useful but limited progress without dedicated developer or scientist funding.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is often a vicious circle here - a frequent reason for not adopting a new technology in chemistry is "there is no demand for it". This becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy and naturally limits innovation. It is also true that people are often only convinced by seeing a "working system" - hypothetical linkages and implementations have often been wildly optimistic. Therefore without seeing a working repository it is difficult to know what its value is, or the costs of sustaining it.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However the Internet age shows that it is much easier, cheaper and quicker to get new applications off the ground. It should be possible, in a short time and with modest effort, to create a system which demonstrates semantic interoperability and to convince a community of its value. We have successful examples of this reported elsewhere in this issue (OSCAR, Open Bibliography) where an early system has caught the imagination and approval of a section of the community.</p>
</sec>
