<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum Chemical calculations and data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-level quantum chemical (QC) methods have become increasingly available to the broader scientific community through a number of software packages such as Gaussian [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B1" href="#B1">1</a>], GAMESS(US) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>], GAMESS-UK [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B3" href="#B3">3</a>], NWChem [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">4</a>], MOLCAS [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">5</a>] and many more. Additionally, the cost of computer power has experienced an exponential reduction in recent decades and, more importantly, sophisticated approximations have been developed that pursue (and promisingly approach) the holy grail of linear scaling methods [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>]. This has enabled any researcher, with no specific QC training, to perform calculations on large, interesting systems using very accurate methods, thus generating a large amount of valuable and expensive data. Despite the scientific interest of this data and its potential utility to other groups, its lack of homogeneity, organization and accessibility has been recognized as a significant problem by important agents within the scientific community [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B9" href="#B9">9</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These problems, and specially the ones related to the accessibility of data have many consequences that reduce the efficiency of the field. As mentioned, QC methods are computationally expensive: the scaling of the computer effort and storage of high-level computations with the size of the system (
   <span class="italic">N</span>) is harsh, reaching, for example, 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <span class="sup">7</span>, for the most expensive and most accurate wavefunction-based methods, such as Coupled Cluster [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B10" href="#B10">10</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">12</a>]. This makes it very difficult for groups that cannot use supercomputing facilities to have access to high-quality results, even if they possess the expertise to analyze and use the data. Even groups that do have access to powerful computational resources, given the lack of access to previously computed data by other researchers, often face the choice between 
   <span class="italic">two inefficient </span>options: either they spend a lot of human time digging in the literature and contacting colleagues to find out what has already been calculated, or they spend a lot of computer effort (and also human time) calculating the needed data themselves, with the risk of needlessly duplicating work.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another problem originating in the lack of access to computed QC data and the very large number of methods available, is that users typically do not have the integrated information about which method presents the best accuracy 
   <span class="italic">vs</span>. cost relation for a given application. The reason is that comparing one quantum chemical method with another, with classical force fields or with experimental data is non-trivial, the answer frequently depending on the studied molecular system and on the physical observable sought. Moreover, all the details and parameters that define what John Pople termed a 
   <span class="italic">model chemistry </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>], 
   <span class="italic">i.e</span>., the exact set of rules needed to perform a given calculation do not obey a continuous monotonic function. Thus increasing the expense and "accuracy" of a calculation may not always converge to the "correct" solution. As a consequence, the quality of the results does not steadily grow with the computational effort invested, but rather there exist certain tradeoffs that render the relation between them more involved [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B16" href="#B16">16</a>]. Hence, not only the choice of the more efficient QC method for a given problem among the already existing ones, but also the design of novel model chemistries becomes 'more an art than a science' [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B17" href="#B17">17</a>], based more on know-how and empiricism than in a set of systematic procedures.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Design of Scientific data repositories</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper we describe a novel, flexible, multipurpose repository technology. It arises out of a series of meetings and projects in the computational chemistry (compchem) community which have addressed the desire and need to have repositories available for capturing and disseminating the results of QC calculations. It is also strongly influenced by the eScience ("cyberinfrastructure", "eResearch") programs which have streesed the value of instant semantic access to research information from many disciplines, and by the Open Innovation vision supported by the Scientific Software Working Group of CECAM (Centre Européen de Calcul Atomique et Moléculaire) 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cecam.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cecam.org/</span>, which seeks an innovation model based on sharing, trust and collaboration, and which recognizes the important role played by the availability of reference data and archives of outputs of calculations and simulations. It also coincides with the increasing mandates for data publication from a wide range of funders; our repository can address a large part of these requirements.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper describes a distributed repository technology and the social aspects associated with developing its use. The technology is robust and deployed but the way it may be used is at a very early stage. We address known social issues (sustainability, quality, etc.) but expect that deployment, even in the short term, may look very different from what is reported.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The development and acceptance of Wikipedia may act as a valuable guide and it represents a community-driven activity with community-controlled quality. Although variable, we believe that articles for most mainstream physical sciences are reliable. Thus to help understand and represent moments of inertia in computational chemistry we can link to Wikipedia 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moment_of_inertia" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moment_of_inertia</span>. This contains many hundreds of edits over eight years from many authors - it is almost certainly "correct". Quixote has many of the same features - anyone can contribute content and repurpose it. We expect a culture to emerge where the community sets guidelines for contributions and corrections/annotations. We are building filters ("lenses") so that the community can identify subcollections of specific quality or value.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The background to Quixote includes a number of meetings and projects which specifically addressed the development of infrastructure in computational chemistry and materials. The goal of these was to explore the commonality between approaches and see how data and processes could interoperate. One (Materials Grid) also addressed the design and implementation of a repository for results.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• 2004: A meeting under the UK eScience program "Toward a common data and command representation for quantum chemistry" 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nesc.ac.uk/action/esi/contribution.cfm?Title=394" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nesc.ac.uk/action/esi/contribution.cfm?Title=394</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• 2006: A meeting under the auspices of CECAM "Data representation and code interoperability for computational materials physics and chemistry" 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cecam.org/workshop-50.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cecam.org/workshop-50.html</span>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• 2005-2010: A 5-year project under the COST D37 program to develop various aspects of interoperability both within the calculation (Q5COST) and between programs (WG5).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• A funded project in computational materials ("Materials Grid") 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.materialsgrid.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.materialsgrid.org/</span> which resulted in considerable development of CML specifications and trial implementations in a number of codes (CASTEP, DLPOLY).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These meetings and projects were exploratory and localized. Within them there was a general agreement that interoperability and access to results would be a great benefit. But they also highlighted the problem that infrastructure development is expensive and, if public, requires political justification for funding. Such funding is perhaps most likely to come from supranational efforts such as computational Grids, where there is a clear imperative for making services as accessible as possible. In COST-D37 the funding was for meetings and interchange visits; the WG5 community made useful but limited progress without dedicated developer or scientist funding.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is often a vicious circle here - a frequent reason for not adopting a new technology in chemistry is "there is no demand for it". This becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy and naturally limits innovation. It is also true that people are often only convinced by seeing a "working system" - hypothetical linkages and implementations have often been wildly optimistic. Therefore without seeing a working repository it is difficult to know what its value is, or the costs of sustaining it.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However the Internet age shows that it is much easier, cheaper and quicker to get new applications off the ground. It should be possible, in a short time and with modest effort, to create a system which demonstrates semantic interoperability and to convince a community of its value. We have successful examples of this reported elsewhere in this issue (OSCAR, Open Bibliography) where an early system has caught the imagination and approval of a section of the community.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Existing related projects</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These issues, and undoubtedly more that will appear in the future, together with a wealth of scientific problems in neighbouring fields, could be tackled by public, comprehensive, up-to-date, organized, on-line repositories of computational QC data. Additionally, several fields reporting experimental data require it to be presented in a standard validatable form. The crystallography community has long required deposition of data as a prerequisite for publication, and this is now enhanced by machine validation (the CheckCIF philosophy and program 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://checkcif.iucr.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://checkcif.iucr.org/</span>). When data are submitted, the system can comment on whether all appropriate data are present, inspect their values and compare either with known ranges or re-compute relationships between them based on accepted theoretical principles. In this way reviewers and readers can expect that a very large number of potential errors in experiment and publication have been eliminated.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This requirement for deposition of data as part of the publication process is increasingly common in bioscience, like genetics or proteomics, where the NCBI GenBank 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</span> or the Protein Data Bank (PDB) 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/home/home.do" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/home/home.do</span> constitute very successful examples of data sharing and organization. In an age in which both the monetary cost and the accuracy of QC calculations rival those of experimental studies, the need to extrapolate the model to this field seems obvious. We also note that funders are requiring that data be deposited as part of the condition of funding. On the one hand, there exist some in-house solutions that individual research groups or firms have built in order to implement a local-scale data management solution. This is the case of David Feller's Computational Results Database 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tyr3.chem.wsu.edu/~feller/Site/Database.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tyr3.chem.wsu.edu/~feller/Site/Database.html</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">18</a>], an intra-lab database to store and organize more than 100,000 calculations on small to medium-sized molecules, with an emphasis on very high levels of the theory. Also, the commercial standalone application SEURAT 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.synapticscience.com/seurat/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.synapticscience.com/seurat/</span> can open and parse QC data files and allows for metadata customization by the user, thus providing some limited, local databasing capabilities. In the same family of solutions, ChemDataBase [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>] is a data management infrastructure mainly focused on virtual screening which presents the distinctive feature of being able to create and retrieve databases over grid infrastructures. Packages for interacting with QC codes (launching, retrieving and analyzing calculations), such as ECCE 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecce.emsl.pnl.gov/index.shtml" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ecce.emsl.pnl.gov/index.shtml</span> or Ampac 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.semichem.com/ampac/afeatures.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.semichem.com/ampac/afeatures.php</span>, have modest data management capabilities too, although only insofar as it helps to perform their main tasks, and they can be regarded as intra-lab solutions as well. Probably the most complete in-house infrastructure of which we are aware of is the RC
   <span class="sup">3 </span>(Regional Computational Chemistry Collaboratory) developed by the group of David Dixon at the Department of Chemistry of the University of Alabama. The main objective of RC
   <span class="sup">3 </span>is to perform the everyday data backup, collection and metadata assignment for calculations, and to organize them for research purposes. At the time of writing, RC
   <span class="sup">3 </span>has been tested by 36 users for more than a year, and backed-up and organized 1.6 million files, amounting to 1.5TB of data storage. The database contains 144,000 records and it can currently parse multiple QC data formats.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterogeneous data repositories</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A different category of data management solutions from the one discussed above is that constituted by a number of online web-based repositories of QC calculations, normally developed by one research group with a very specific scientific objective in mind. Among them, we can mention the NIST Computational Chemistry Comparison and Benchmark DataBase (CCCDB) 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cccbdb.nist.gov/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cccbdb.nist.gov/</span>, which contains a collection of experimental and calculated 
   <span class="italic">ab initio </span>thermochemical, vibrational, geometric and electrostatic data for a set of gas-phase atoms and small molecules; the Benchmark Energy and Geometry DataBase (BEGDB) www.begdb.com [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>], which includes geometry and energy CCSD(T)/CBS calculations as well as other high-level calculations, with a special emphasis on intermolecular interactions; the DFT Database for RNA Catalysis (QCRNA) 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://theory.rutgers.edu/QCRNA/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://theory.rutgers.edu/QCRNA/</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>], which contains high-level density-functional electronic structure calculations of molecules, complexes and reactions relevant to RNA catalysis; the Atomic Reference Data for Electronic Structure Calculations 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nist.gov/pml/data/dftdata/index.cfm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nist.gov/pml/data/dftdata/index.cfm</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>] compiled at NIST, containing total energies and orbital eigenvalues for the atoms hydrogen through uranium, as computed in several standard variants of density-functional theory, or the thermochemistry database at the Computational Modeling Group of Cambridge's Department of Chemical Engineering 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://como.cheng.cam.ac.uk/index.php?Page=cmcc" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://como.cheng.cam.ac.uk/index.php?Page=cmcc</span>, collecting thermochemical data of small molecules, powered by RDF and SPARQL and offering the output files of the calculations, together with the parsed CML 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cml.sourceforge.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cml.sourceforge.net</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from these solutions (either local or web-based), in which one or a few groups build a complete data management infrastructure, one can also consider the possibility of adopting a modular approach, in which different researchers tackle different parts of the problem, whilst always enforcing the maximum possible interoperability between the modules. The Blue Obelisk group 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blueobelisk.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.blueobelisk.org/</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>] has been championing this approach for a number of years now, and many of the developers of the tools discussed below are members of it. In this category of solutions, we can also mention the Basis Set Exchange (BSE) 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bse.pnl.gov/bse/portal" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://bse.pnl.gov/bse/portal</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B25" href="#B25">25</a>], which provides an exhaustive list and definition of the most common basis sets used in QC calculations, thus facilitating the definition and implementation of semantic content regarding the method used, as well as improving the interoperability among codes at the level of the input data; modern tagging and markup technologies like XML and RDF together with the building of semantic dictionaries, not only to promote interoperability, but to do it in a web-friendly manner that allows one to easily plug modules and build complex online data management projects; the CML language (a chemical extension of XML) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>] is also one of the few cases in which a common semantics has been widely adopted by the chemistry community, and its extension to the QC field is one of the cornerstones of the Quixote project described here. Also on the interoperability front, we can mention the cclib 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cclib.sf.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cclib.sf.net</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>] and CDK 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cdk.sf.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cdk.sf.net</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>] libraries, as well as the OpenBabel toolbox 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://openbabel.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://openbabel.org</span>, which provide many capabilities for reading, converting and displaying QC data in many formats. Regarding the ease of use of possible data management solutions, the Open Source molecular editor and visualizer Avogadro 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://avogadro.openmolecules.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://avogadro.openmolecules.net</span> can certainly be used as a useful module in complex projects, and in fact the design of Quixote is being carried out in collaboration with the developers of Avogadro, with the intention of efficiently interfacing it in future versions. The Java-based viewer Jmol 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jmol.sourceforge.net/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://jmol.sourceforge.net/</span> performs similar tasks.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All in all, and despite the numerous efforts described above, it is clear that a global, unified, powerful solution to the management of data in QC does not exist at present; at the same time that the new internet-based technologies, the existence of vibrant communities, and the wide availability of powerful software to perform the calculations, and to convert and analyze the results, all seem to indicate that the field is ripe to produce a revolutionary (and much needed) change in the model. In this article, we present the beginnings of an attempt to do so.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Quixote solution</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The catalyst for Quixote was a meeting on interoperability and repositories in QC held at ZCAM (Zaragoza Scientific Center for Advanced Modeling), Zaragoza (Spain) in September 2010. There was general agreement on the need for collection and re-dissemination of data. In the final discussion a number of participants felt that there was now enough impetus and technology that something could and should be done. This wasn't a universal view, and we are aware that Quixote is unconventional in its genesis and aspirations - hence the name, reflecting a difficult but hopefully not impossible dream.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We decide to pursue this as an informal "unsponsored" project. It is not actually "unfunded", in that we recognize the critical and valuable cash and in-kind support of several bodies, including CECAM, STFC Daresbury Laboratory, EPSRC, JISC, ZCAM, and the employers of many of the participants. In particular we have been able to hold, and continue to hold, meetings. But there are no sponsor-led targets or requirements. In this it has many of the features of successful virtual projects in ICT (such as Apache, Linux, 
   <span class="italic">etc</span>.) and communal activities such as Wikipedia and Open Street Map.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Speed and ambition were critical and project management has been by deadlines - external events fixed in time for which the project had to have something to show. These have included:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• An 
   <span class="italic">ad hoc </span>meeting in 2010-10 in Cambridge where a number of the participants happened to be. This was to convince ourselves that the project was feasible in our eyes
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• The PMR symposium 2011-01 that has catalysed this set of articles</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• A workshop 2011-03 at STFC Daresbury Laboratory to demonstrate the prototype to a representative set of QC scientists and code developers</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Open repositories (OR11) 2011-06 where the technology was presented to the academic repository community as an argument for the need for domain repositories</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• (planned) A meeting in Zaragoza 2011-08 where the argument for domain repositories will be demonstrated by Quixote.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As of 2011-06 we have a working repository with over 6000 entries, which are searchable chemically, by numeric properties and through metadata.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our primary goal has been to build working, flexible technology without being driven by specific use-cases. This can be seen as heresy, and indeed we might regard it as such ourselves, if it were not that we have spent about 10 years working in semantic chemistry, computational chemistry and repositories and so have anticipated many of the possible use cases and caveats. To help show Quixote's flexibility we now list a number of use cases, any one of which may serve to convince the reader that Quixote has something to offer:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Quixote system (Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a> shows the workflow, Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a> shows the distributed heterogeneity) is very flexible in that it can be installed in several different ways. Here we give a number of possible uses of the system, some of which we have deployed and several more we expect to be useful.
  </p>
  <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Quixote architecture and conversion workflow</span>. The user instructs Lensfield2 to convert output files of different computational chemistry codes into semantically rich CML files. The conversion is performed by JUMBO-Converters following the hints provided in the dictionaries and templates. The generated CML files are then transferred to one or more local and remote chem# repositories using a RESTful web API. The user can search and browse those repositories with a web browser, and can also manipulate and visualize the CML files with Avogadro.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="1758-2946-3-38-1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Quixote distributed repositories</span>. A schematic view of distributed Quixote repositories. Some repositories push documents to the public web, others aggregate from it. There is (deliberately) no check on whether repositories have identical documents. Users can build search strategies that look for individual entries with specific data or make collections of documents that share or contrast properties.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="1758-2946-3-38-2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Collection of results within a group or laboratory. There is a growing desire to capture scientific results at the time of creation, and we have been involved in several projects (CLaRION, JISC XYZ) the impetus of which is to see whether scientists can capture their data as they create it. Computational chemistry is one of the simplest types of results and Quixote has been designed so that a single log file provides most of the input to the repository. This system allows groups and individual researchers to "pick up their results" and transport them to different environments.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Formal publication in journals and theses. Results in a Quixote repository can be made available to other people and parties in the publication process. For example an author could make their results available to a journal before review so that the editors and reviewers could use the data to assess the value of the science. Similarly a graduate student could make their results available as part of their thesis submission and these could be assessed by the examiners. If the thesis and accompanying data are also published in the institutional repository then this provides a simple but very effective way of capturing and preserving the record of scientific experiments.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Teaching and learning resources. Quixote can collect resources used for teaching and can also be used to provide subsets of research objects which are valuable for teaching and learning. For example in the current set there are 75 calculations on benzene, mainly from Henry Rzepa's laboratory and these have been deposited by students carrying these out as part of their undergraduate work. This resource allows us to compare methods and to get information and experience which may help us do similar calculations.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• A collaborative central repository for a project. An increasing number of projects are distributed over geography and discipline. (The current Quixote project is an example.) A repository allows different people and groups in the project to share a central resource in an analogous manner to the use of Bitbucket and similar repositories for sharing code.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• A set of reference data and molecules. Quixote allows us to search for different parameters used in a given problem (
   <span class="italic">e.g</span>. level of theory, number of orbitals, convergence of results, algorithms, 
   <span class="italic">etc</span>.).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Validation sets for software and methods. In a similar manner datasets within Quixote can be used by different groups as reference input to compare results from different programs or different approaches.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Enrichment of data through curation. Quixote is annotatable, so that it is possible for the world community to add their comments to particular entries. If a result is suspect, an annotation can be added. Similarly it is possible to point out related entries highlighting different scientific aspects.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Building blocks for calculations. It is often valuable to start from an unknown program resource (
   <span class="italic">e.g</span>. a molecule whose structure is known and where the calculations are verified) and to modify it slightly for a related calculation, 
   <span class="italic">e.g</span>. by adding additional atoms or by refining the calculation parameters.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Combining data from different sources. As Quixote can also store experimental structures such as crystallographic ones, or experimental data such as spectra it is possible to enhance and combine components of the calculation.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Data-driven science. Now that computational chemistry is relatively cheap and relatively accessible for a very large number of scientists, we foresee that literally millions of processors will be used routinely to calculate theoretical chemistry results. This allows us to carry out data mining from the Quixote repositories with the possibility of discovering new scientific patterns.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Indexing the web. In a similar way to our indexing of crystallography through CrystalEye 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wwmm.ch.cam.ac.uk/crystaleye/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://wwmm.ch.cam.ac.uk/crystaleye/</span> we anticipate that web crawlers can increasingly discover and retrieve published computational chemistry.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Developing software tools. Since Quixote represents an abstraction of many codes, developers writing software for computational chemistry will be able to see the type of semantics which are captured and the structure of the document.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quality</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The collection of the scientific computional record through Quixote could be regarded as an objective process in that each logfile is sufficiently described from the view of repeatability. Any user of Quixote could, if they had access to the code(s), re-run the calculation and "get the same output". The examples of student calculations on benzene in the current content illustrate this view.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand it can be objected that unless a calculation is carried out with professional care then it can not only be meaningless but seriously misleading. Non-experts in QC can obtain these results and can misinterpret them. This is true, but it is a fact of modern Open science - results should be and are available to anyone. Science must evolve social and technical methods to guide people to find the data they want. We can buy a kit and in our garages determine the sequence of a gene or protein without realising the potential experimental errors, or the difficulty of describing the species or strain that it came from. We can buy table-top crystallography sets that will automatically solve the structure of almost all crystalline materials. The results of these experiments are valuable if interpreted correctly and much of the time there is little room for serious error. However we might not realise that one lanthanide might be mistaken for another, that crystals can be twinned, and that certain spacegroups are problematic. Similarly the neophyte may not appreciate the difficulty of getting accurate energies, spin densities, non-bonded interactions, and many more subtleties of computational chemistry. But Pandora's box has been opened and computational chemistry is a commodity open to all. Quixote will help us in making our communal judgments.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are a few objective concerns about quality. The Quixote system converts legacy computational chemistry (logfiles) into semantic form. Automatic conversion will usually have a small number of errors, but mainly in that fields will not be recognized, rather than corrupted. In the early stages the semantics of some quantities may be misinterpreted (many are often laconic "E = 1.2345" - what exactly is E? and what are the units?) Given the exposure of the system to "many eyes" such problems will be few and should be relatively rapid to remove.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fuzzier concern is whether Quixote can grow to gain the confidence of the QC and the non-QC community. Computational chemistry has the unique feature that anyone in the world, given the same input, will create the same output. The question is not whether the log file is an accurate record of the calculation but whether the calculation is valuable. It is quite possible to create junk, often unknowingly, and the commonest way is by inputting junk. A typical example is that many chemoinformatics programs can garble hydrogen counts and formal charges. However there are several criteria that the Quixote user and community can apply:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• If the methodology is very standard, then the results are likely to be usable in a similar way to other results using the same method. For example a very common combination of method and basis for organic molecules is B3LYP + 6-31G**. If another group has successfully employed this for a set of molecules similar to the user's it is likely to be a useful starting point. This does not of course absolve the user from critical judgement but it is better than having nowhere to start.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Automated methods can be used to compare the results of calculations for similar molecules or with varied parameters.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• We particularly encourage collections provided by specified individuals or groups. We have made two available in the current release (Dr. Anna Croft, Prof. Henry Rzepa). The user can browse through collections and get an idea of the type of calculation and the quality of metadata.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Are the data coupled to publication? In CrystalEye almost all records are coupled to primary publications which can be read by the user (assuming that they have access to the journal). There is no technical barrier why this should not be done for articles and theses in computational chemistry. This is harder in compchem until the community develops a culture of publishing data concurrently with articles.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Have the entries been annotated? This feature will shortly be available in Quixote, probably through blogging tools.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Are there criteria for depositing an entry in the particular Quixote repository? Since we expect there to be many repositories, some of them can develop quality criteria for deposition. Some, perhaps the majority, may have human curators. In the first instance it will be important that users can assess the quality of a particular Quixote repository and we are appealing to any scientist who have collections of computational chemistry data that they would be prepared to make available. We expect that there will be a range of levels of quality in Quixote repositories. For example a crawler visiting random web sites for data might store these in an "unvalidated" repository. Users could examine this for new interesting entries and make their own decisions as to their value. The web has many evolved systems for the creation of quality metrics (popularity, usage, recommendations, 
   <span class="italic">etc</span>.) and many of these would make sense for compchem. A journal might set up their own repository (as is done for crystallography). A department could expose its outputs (and thereby gain metrics and esteem) and the contents would be judged on the assessment of the creators.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
