<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Quixote project can manage input and output from any of the main compchem packages including plane-wave and solid-state approaches. The amount of semantic information in the output files can vary from a relatively small amount of metadata for indexing to a complete representation of every information output in the logfile. The community can decide at which point on the spectrum it wishes to extract information and can also retrospectively enhance this by running improved parsers and converters over the archived logfiles and output files.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The current test datasets in the Murray-Rust group are generated by parsing existing logfiles into CML using the JUMBO-Converters software. The amount of detail depends at the moment on the amount of effort that has been put into the parser. The current project is working hard to ensure inter-operability of dictionary terms and concepts by collating a top-level dictionary resource. When this is complete, the files will be re-parsed to reflect the standard semantics.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the first pass, with the per-code parsers, we have been able to get a high conversion rate and a large number of semantic concepts from the most developed parsers. The use cases below represent work to date showing that the approach is highly tractable and can be expected to scale across all types of compchem output and types of calculation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A typical final CML document (heavily truncated for brevity) is shown in Appendix C. This shows the structure of jobs and the typical fields to be found in most calculations.</p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Test dataset 1</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first use case consisted of 1095 files in Gaussian logfile format contributed by Dr. Anna Croft of the University of Bangor. These were deliberately sent without any human description with the challenge that we could use machine methods to determine their scope and motivation. We have applied the JUMBO-Parser to these, of which all except 5 converted without problems. The average time for conversion was between 3-10 seconds depending on the size of file. These files have now been indexed, mainly from the information in the archive section of the logfile but also with the initial starting geometry and control information. A large number of the files appear to be a systematic study of the attack by halogen radicals on aromatic nuclei.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Test dataset 2</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This use case comprised of over 5000 files which Henry Rzepa and collaborators have produced over the years and which have been stored Openly in the Imperial College repository (helix). They are much more varied than the Croft sample and include studies on Möbius computational chemistry, transitional metal complexes and transition state geometries. A considerable proportion of the files emanate from student projects, many of which tackle hitherto novel chemical problems. It is our intention to create a machine-readable catalogues of these files and to determine from first principles their content and, where possible, their intent.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Test dataset 3</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The NWChem distribution (NWChem-6.0) contains a directory (
   <span class="monospace">/QA/tests/</span>) with a large number (212) of varied quality assurance tests for the software. All except 18 of these have been converted satisfactorily. One problem encountered was that the parser had used a large number of regexes which, when concatenated, scaled exponentially, so that some of the conversions took over a minute. We are now re-writing the parser to use linear time methods. These files cover a wider range of chemistry than the Croft and Rzepa contributions, as many of them use plane-wave calculations on solid state problems.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Test dataset 4</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the group of Pablo Echenique, at the Institute of Physical Chemistry "Rocasolano" (CSIC) and the University of Zaragoza, a large number of calculations were performed in peptide systems using the Gaussian quantum chemistry package. These calculations represent an exhaustive study (whose results and aims have been discussed elsewhere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>]), of more than 250 
   <span class="italic">ab initio </span>potential energy surfaces (PESs) of the model dipeptide HCO-L-Ala-NH
   <sub>2</sub>. The model chemistries investigated are constructed as homo- and heterolevels involving possibly different RHF and MP2 calculations for the geometry and the energy. The basis sets used belong to a sample of 39 representants from Pople's split-valence families, ranging from the small 3-21G to the large 6-311++G(2 df, 2 pd). The conformational space of this molecule is scanned by defining a regular 12×12 grid from -165° to 165° in 30° steps in the 2D space spanned by its Ramachandran angles 
   <span class="italic">ϕ </span>and 
   <span class="italic">ψ</span>. This totals more than 35000 Gaussian logfiles, all generated at the standard level of verbosity, some of them corresponding to single-point energy calculations, some of them to energy optimizations. The use of JUMBO-converters through Lensfield 2 has allowed to parse the totality of these files, through a complicated folder tree, generating the corresponding raw XML and structured compchem CML with a very high rate of captured concepts. The total time required to do the parsing was about five hours in an iMac desktop machine with a 2.66 GHz Intel Core 2 Duo processor, and 4 GB of RAM memory, running the Mac OS X 10.6.7 operating system.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quixote repository at Cambridge</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first repository (Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a>) has been built at Cambridge 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://quixote.ch.cam.ac.uk" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://quixote.ch.cam.ac.uk</span> and has been viewable and searchable. In the spirit of Quixote this is not intended to be a central permanent resource but one of many repositories. It is available for an indefinite time as a demonstration of the power and flexibility of the system but not set up as a permanent "archive". It may be possible to couple such repositories to more conventional archive-oriented repositories which act as back-end storage and preservation.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
