<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Existing related projects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These issues, and undoubtedly more that will appear in the future, together with a wealth of scientific problems in neighbouring fields, could be tackled by public, comprehensive, up-to-date, organized, on-line repositories of computational QC data. Additionally, several fields reporting experimental data require it to be presented in a standard validatable form. The crystallography community has long required deposition of data as a prerequisite for publication, and this is now enhanced by machine validation (the CheckCIF philosophy and program 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://checkcif.iucr.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://checkcif.iucr.org/</span>). When data are submitted, the system can comment on whether all appropriate data are present, inspect their values and compare either with known ranges or re-compute relationships between them based on accepted theoretical principles. In this way reviewers and readers can expect that a very large number of potential errors in experiment and publication have been eliminated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This requirement for deposition of data as part of the publication process is increasingly common in bioscience, like genetics or proteomics, where the NCBI GenBank 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</span> or the Protein Data Bank (PDB) 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/home/home.do" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/home/home.do</span> constitute very successful examples of data sharing and organization. In an age in which both the monetary cost and the accuracy of QC calculations rival those of experimental studies, the need to extrapolate the model to this field seems obvious. We also note that funders are requiring that data be deposited as part of the condition of funding. On the one hand, there exist some in-house solutions that individual research groups or firms have built in order to implement a local-scale data management solution. This is the case of David Feller's Computational Results Database 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tyr3.chem.wsu.edu/~feller/Site/Database.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tyr3.chem.wsu.edu/~feller/Site/Database.html</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">18</a>], an intra-lab database to store and organize more than 100,000 calculations on small to medium-sized molecules, with an emphasis on very high levels of the theory. Also, the commercial standalone application SEURAT 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.synapticscience.com/seurat/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.synapticscience.com/seurat/</span> can open and parse QC data files and allows for metadata customization by the user, thus providing some limited, local databasing capabilities. In the same family of solutions, ChemDataBase [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>] is a data management infrastructure mainly focused on virtual screening which presents the distinctive feature of being able to create and retrieve databases over grid infrastructures. Packages for interacting with QC codes (launching, retrieving and analyzing calculations), such as ECCE 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecce.emsl.pnl.gov/index.shtml" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ecce.emsl.pnl.gov/index.shtml</span> or Ampac 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.semichem.com/ampac/afeatures.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.semichem.com/ampac/afeatures.php</span>, have modest data management capabilities too, although only insofar as it helps to perform their main tasks, and they can be regarded as intra-lab solutions as well. Probably the most complete in-house infrastructure of which we are aware of is the RC
  <span class="sup">3 </span>(Regional Computational Chemistry Collaboratory) developed by the group of David Dixon at the Department of Chemistry of the University of Alabama. The main objective of RC
  <span class="sup">3 </span>is to perform the everyday data backup, collection and metadata assignment for calculations, and to organize them for research purposes. At the time of writing, RC
  <span class="sup">3 </span>has been tested by 36 users for more than a year, and backed-up and organized 1.6 million files, amounting to 1.5TB of data storage. The database contains 144,000 records and it can currently parse multiple QC data formats.
 </p>
</sec>
