<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterogeneous data repositories</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A different category of data management solutions from the one discussed above is that constituted by a number of online web-based repositories of QC calculations, normally developed by one research group with a very specific scientific objective in mind. Among them, we can mention the NIST Computational Chemistry Comparison and Benchmark DataBase (CCCDB) 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cccbdb.nist.gov/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cccbdb.nist.gov/</span>, which contains a collection of experimental and calculated 
  <span class="italic">ab initio </span>thermochemical, vibrational, geometric and electrostatic data for a set of gas-phase atoms and small molecules; the Benchmark Energy and Geometry DataBase (BEGDB) www.begdb.com [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>], which includes geometry and energy CCSD(T)/CBS calculations as well as other high-level calculations, with a special emphasis on intermolecular interactions; the DFT Database for RNA Catalysis (QCRNA) 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://theory.rutgers.edu/QCRNA/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://theory.rutgers.edu/QCRNA/</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>], which contains high-level density-functional electronic structure calculations of molecules, complexes and reactions relevant to RNA catalysis; the Atomic Reference Data for Electronic Structure Calculations 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nist.gov/pml/data/dftdata/index.cfm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nist.gov/pml/data/dftdata/index.cfm</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>] compiled at NIST, containing total energies and orbital eigenvalues for the atoms hydrogen through uranium, as computed in several standard variants of density-functional theory, or the thermochemistry database at the Computational Modeling Group of Cambridge's Department of Chemical Engineering 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://como.cheng.cam.ac.uk/index.php?Page=cmcc" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://como.cheng.cam.ac.uk/index.php?Page=cmcc</span>, collecting thermochemical data of small molecules, powered by RDF and SPARQL and offering the output files of the calculations, together with the parsed CML 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cml.sourceforge.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cml.sourceforge.net</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from these solutions (either local or web-based), in which one or a few groups build a complete data management infrastructure, one can also consider the possibility of adopting a modular approach, in which different researchers tackle different parts of the problem, whilst always enforcing the maximum possible interoperability between the modules. The Blue Obelisk group 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.blueobelisk.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.blueobelisk.org/</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>] has been championing this approach for a number of years now, and many of the developers of the tools discussed below are members of it. In this category of solutions, we can also mention the Basis Set Exchange (BSE) 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bse.pnl.gov/bse/portal" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://bse.pnl.gov/bse/portal</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">18</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B25" href="#B25">25</a>], which provides an exhaustive list and definition of the most common basis sets used in QC calculations, thus facilitating the definition and implementation of semantic content regarding the method used, as well as improving the interoperability among codes at the level of the input data; modern tagging and markup technologies like XML and RDF together with the building of semantic dictionaries, not only to promote interoperability, but to do it in a web-friendly manner that allows one to easily plug modules and build complex online data management projects; the CML language (a chemical extension of XML) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>] is also one of the few cases in which a common semantics has been widely adopted by the chemistry community, and its extension to the QC field is one of the cornerstones of the Quixote project described here. Also on the interoperability front, we can mention the cclib 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cclib.sf.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cclib.sf.net</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>] and CDK 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cdk.sf.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cdk.sf.net</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>] libraries, as well as the OpenBabel toolbox 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://openbabel.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://openbabel.org</span>, which provide many capabilities for reading, converting and displaying QC data in many formats. Regarding the ease of use of possible data management solutions, the Open Source molecular editor and visualizer Avogadro 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://avogadro.openmolecules.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://avogadro.openmolecules.net</span> can certainly be used as a useful module in complex projects, and in fact the design of Quixote is being carried out in collaboration with the developers of Avogadro, with the intention of efficiently interfacing it in future versions. The Java-based viewer Jmol 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jmol.sourceforge.net/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://jmol.sourceforge.net/</span> performs similar tasks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All in all, and despite the numerous efforts described above, it is clear that a global, unified, powerful solution to the management of data in QC does not exist at present; at the same time that the new internet-based technologies, the existence of vibrant communities, and the wide availability of powerful software to perform the calculations, and to convert and analyze the results, all seem to indicate that the field is ripe to produce a revolutionary (and much needed) change in the model. In this article, we present the beginnings of an attempt to do so.</p>
</sec>
