<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Institutional repositories, DSpace</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Institutional repositories (running software such as DSpace 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dspace.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.dspace.org/</span> or Fedora 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fedora-commons.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://fedora-commons.org/</span>) may be responsible for storing the raw output files that are transformed into CML by the JUMBO-Converters. Alongside, they will also store basic metadata (authorship, usage rights, related works, 
  <span class="italic">etc</span>.).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This usage of institutional repositories distributes data management responsibilities among the institutions where the creators of the raw output files work. This provides an efficient basic data management support to the creators, and lets topic-specific repositories (such as Quixote's chem#) to focus on leveraging the specialized CML semantics extracted from the raw files, while still linking back to the original raw files at the institutional repositories. This schema also favors re-use of the same primary data by different specialized research topic repositories.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yet antother temporary advantage of this approach is that, as the data collection increases, resource discoverability becomes a real challenge - even for the researcher herself. Even if much data can be extracted from the datafiles, some title and description metadata could be very useful to issue searches and can be provided by the person submitting the files to the repository. In the development phase, other researchers - as well as the dataset creator - would be able to discover and access a given unprocessed dataset without needing to wait for it to get processed and transferred into the final Chempound data repository.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Designing a DSpace-based raw data repository will also allow for defining a 
  <span class="italic">de facto </span>standardized metadata collection for compchem data description that may be very useful for harmonisation of data description in this specific research area - and might eventually evolve into some kind of standard for the discipline. At the present stage, we have done some preliminary work along metadata collection definition. A set of metadata has been defined and is being discussed in order to provide thorough descriptions of raw compchem datasets (potentially extendable to data from other research areas). Once the metadata set for bibliographical description of raw datasets is agreed, fields contained therein will be mapped to existing or new qualified DublinCore (QDC) metadata and a draft format will thus be defined. This format will be implemented at a DSpace-based repository, where trial-and-error storing loops with real datasets will be performed for metadata collection completion and fine -tuning - besides accounting for particular cases.
 </p>
</sec>
