<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quality</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The collection of the scientific computional record through Quixote could be regarded as an objective process in that each logfile is sufficiently described from the view of repeatability. Any user of Quixote could, if they had access to the code(s), re-run the calculation and "get the same output". The examples of student calculations on benzene in the current content illustrate this view.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand it can be objected that unless a calculation is carried out with professional care then it can not only be meaningless but seriously misleading. Non-experts in QC can obtain these results and can misinterpret them. This is true, but it is a fact of modern Open science - results should be and are available to anyone. Science must evolve social and technical methods to guide people to find the data they want. We can buy a kit and in our garages determine the sequence of a gene or protein without realising the potential experimental errors, or the difficulty of describing the species or strain that it came from. We can buy table-top crystallography sets that will automatically solve the structure of almost all crystalline materials. The results of these experiments are valuable if interpreted correctly and much of the time there is little room for serious error. However we might not realise that one lanthanide might be mistaken for another, that crystals can be twinned, and that certain spacegroups are problematic. Similarly the neophyte may not appreciate the difficulty of getting accurate energies, spin densities, non-bonded interactions, and many more subtleties of computational chemistry. But Pandora's box has been opened and computational chemistry is a commodity open to all. Quixote will help us in making our communal judgments.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are a few objective concerns about quality. The Quixote system converts legacy computational chemistry (logfiles) into semantic form. Automatic conversion will usually have a small number of errors, but mainly in that fields will not be recognized, rather than corrupted. In the early stages the semantics of some quantities may be misinterpreted (many are often laconic "E = 1.2345" - what exactly is E? and what are the units?) Given the exposure of the system to "many eyes" such problems will be few and should be relatively rapid to remove.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fuzzier concern is whether Quixote can grow to gain the confidence of the QC and the non-QC community. Computational chemistry has the unique feature that anyone in the world, given the same input, will create the same output. The question is not whether the log file is an accurate record of the calculation but whether the calculation is valuable. It is quite possible to create junk, often unknowingly, and the commonest way is by inputting junk. A typical example is that many chemoinformatics programs can garble hydrogen counts and formal charges. However there are several criteria that the Quixote user and community can apply:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• If the methodology is very standard, then the results are likely to be usable in a similar way to other results using the same method. For example a very common combination of method and basis for organic molecules is B3LYP + 6-31G**. If another group has successfully employed this for a set of molecules similar to the user's it is likely to be a useful starting point. This does not of course absolve the user from critical judgement but it is better than having nowhere to start.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Automated methods can be used to compare the results of calculations for similar molecules or with varied parameters.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• We particularly encourage collections provided by specified individuals or groups. We have made two available in the current release (Dr. Anna Croft, Prof. Henry Rzepa). The user can browse through collections and get an idea of the type of calculation and the quality of metadata.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Are the data coupled to publication? In CrystalEye almost all records are coupled to primary publications which can be read by the user (assuming that they have access to the journal). There is no technical barrier why this should not be done for articles and theses in computational chemistry. This is harder in compchem until the community develops a culture of publishing data concurrently with articles.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Have the entries been annotated? This feature will shortly be available in Quixote, probably through blogging tools.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Are there criteria for depositing an entry in the particular Quixote repository? Since we expect there to be many repositories, some of them can develop quality criteria for deposition. Some, perhaps the majority, may have human curators. In the first instance it will be important that users can assess the quality of a particular Quixote repository and we are appealing to any scientist who have collections of computational chemistry data that they would be prepared to make available. We expect that there will be a range of levels of quality in Quixote repositories. For example a crawler visiting random web sites for data might store these in an "unvalidated" repository. Users could examine this for new interesting entries and make their own decisions as to their value. The web has many evolved systems for the creation of quality metrics (popularity, usage, recommendations, 
  <span class="italic">etc</span>.) and many of these would make sense for compchem. A journal might set up their own repository (as is done for crystallography). A department could expose its outputs (and thereby gain metrics and esteem) and the contents would be judged on the assessment of the creators.
 </p>
</sec>
