<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESTful uploading</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important that the methods for "uploading" and "downloading" files are as flexible as possible. Some collaborators may not have privilleges to run their own server, so they need to be able to upload material to a resource run by other collaborators. However, if the protocols are complex then they may be put off taking part. Similarly, others may wish to delegate this to software agents which poll resources and aggregate material for uploading. Similar variability exists in the download process. Web-based collaborators are becoming used to very lightweight solutions such as Dropbox 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dropbox.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.dropbox.com/</span> where files can be uploaded, and where permitted, downloaded by anyone. We do not expect a single solution to cover everything, and the more emphasis on security, the more effort required. In this phase of Quixote, we are publishing our work to the whole world and do not expect problems of corruption or misappropriation. We have therefore relied on simple proven solutions such as RESTful systems. Some of this is covered in the semantic architecture paper in this issue, and here we simply illustrate that initial systems at Cambridge have been implemented with AtomPub 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5023" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5023</span>. Because the academic repository system has invested effort in the SWORD system 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ukoln.ac.uk/repositories/digirep/index/SWORD" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ukoln.ac.uk/repositories/digirep/index/SWORD</span> (which runs over AtomPub), this allows us to deposit/upload aggregations of files.
 </p>
</sec>
