<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For commonly studied II–VI and III−V semiconductors, effective mass of hole is significantly heavier than that of the corresponding electron
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. As a result, for type-I—bottom of conduction band (top of valence band) of the core being lower (higher) than those of the shell—core/shell QDs, the band-edge hole wavefunction (VBM in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>) is more localized within the inner part of a core/shell QD than the band-edge electron wavefunction (CBM in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>. Thus, the two wavefunctions could experience very different dielectric screening, given the ligand/solvent environment possessing much smaller dielectric constant than the semiconductors. Alternatively, we can state that the dielectric screening becomes geometry-dependent for core/shell QDs and it is no longer suited to treat dielectric screening as the same constant for the two types of basic Auger channels in a given core/shell QD
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. Specifically, for certain core/shell geometry, positive trion may experience substantially stronger dielectric screening than the corresponding negative trion, which would cause reduced Auger rates for the positive trion in comparison with the corresponding negative trion. Evidently, this is a counter factor to the other well-known factors, such as density of states and two types of wavefunction overlapping discussed above. As pointed out above, the latter ones always suggest more efficient Auger recombination of positive trions than that of the corresponding negative trions for CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crossover of the Auger rates of two types of basic channels observed here has neither been predicted by theory nor reported experimentally yet. The experimental and theoretical results suggest that, for the CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs—regardless of the core size—with relatively thin CdS shells, the counter effect of geometry-dependent screening can dominate the other factors for determining the relative Auger rates of the two basic channels. This would result in overall less efficient Auger recombination of positive trion than that of the corresponding negative trion for those specific QDs (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Figures 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a> and  
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a> show that, as the core size increases, the dominating role of geometry-dependent dielectric screening for the QDs with relatively thin CdS shells becomes more dramatic. As the shell thickness increases, the other factors well documented in literature overtake the dominating role and cause rate crossover between the Auger recombination of two basic channels.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geometry-dependent dielectric screening not only is responsible for the Auger rate crossover but also represents a new strategy for Auger engineering, which can independently tune the rate of either basic type of Auger recombination. For instance, by coating core/shell QDs with a medium with high (or low) dielectric constant—either inorganic shell or organic solvent/matrix, Auger recombination rates can be greatly reduced (or enhanced). We are actively working on these directions, aiming to further enlarge the tuning range of the rates of two basic types of Auger recombination.</p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of non-radiative carrier dynamics, two elementary processes are important. One is the carrier cooling assisted by electron-phonon coupling after excitation, and the other is the electron-electron interaction induced Auger recombination. In the current experiment, the measured photoluminescence decay dynamics is in the nanosecond time range after the initial excitation. This is far beyond the initial hot carrier cooling, which typically happens within a few picoseconds. We can thus assume the Auger processes start from the ground state of a trion.</p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a phonon-assisted Auger process
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>. Within this process, not only the electron (or hole) can be excited to their higher energy states through the electron-electron interaction, but phonons can be absorbed or emitted. However, these additional channels do not change the overall oscillator strength of the Auger process. Instead, they just spread out the original zero phonon Auger line, thus broadening the Auger peak. In the current study, this effect has been approximated by using a finite broadening of the energy delta function in the Fermi golden rule in Eq. S6. We have used a peak width of 10 meV (close to kT) to represent this effect. Further increasing the peak width does not significantly change the results.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, our results suggest that further suppression (or enhancement) of Auger recombination is feasible with the new strategy. Related, improvement (or reduction) of the quantum yields of multi-carrier states—bi/multi-excitons and trions—of QDs should be possible. Although the results here are obtained with CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs, above discussion tells us that the new strategy based on geometry-dependent dielectric screening should be generally applicable to nearly all types of core/shell QDs. The core/shell QDs with rationally engineered Auger recombination should greatly promote QDs for important applications, such as high-power light-emitting-diodes, lasers, single-molecule tracking, super-resolution microscope, and advanced quantum light sources.</p>
</sec>
