<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optical measurements on QDs using fluorescence microscope</div>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optical properties of QD micro-liquid films and single QDs were measured using an inverted epifluorescence microscope (Olympus IX 83) equipped with a 60 × oil immersion objective (N.A. = 1.49) and suitable spectral filters. In order to measure the steady-state photoluminescence spectra of single QDs, a 405 nm continuous wave laser (PicoQuant) was used as the excitation light source and a spectrometer with EMCCD (Andor Shamrock 303i) was used to record the spectra.</p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 405 nm laser was switched to a pulsed mode with 1 MHz repetition and ~ 50 ps pulse width for time-resolved photoluminescence spectra measurements. For measuring the biexciton emission lifetime, a 405 nm femtosecond pulsed laser (Light Conversion Pharos + Orpheus + LYRA) with 1 MHz was used instead.</p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to measure the biexciton lifetime and QY of QD micro-liquid films, the emission signals were collected and recorded by a single-photon counting system (a Micro Photon Devices MPD-050-CTD-FC photon detectors with 50 ps resolution and PicoQunat Picoharp 300 TCSPC module) in a TCSPC mode. With different excitation power densities, a series of transient photoluminescence spectra were obtained and thus the biexciton lifetime and QY could be calculated.</p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photoluminescence intensity trajectories and transient photoluminescence spectra of single QD were measured simultaneously with the same single-photon counting system mentioned above in a time-tagged time-resolved (TTTR) mode. The integration time for each data point in the photoluminescence intensity trajectories was 30 ms. Second-order photon intensity correlation measurements were performed with the same system and module with a Hanbury-Brown and Twiss (HBT) intensity correlation set-up comprised of a 50/50 beam splitter and two single-photon detectors.</p>
</sec>
