<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="se0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="pr0010" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum wells (QWLs), quantum wires (QWRs) and quantum dots (QDs) are some mentionable examples of low-dimensional semiconductor systems (LDSS) that have collected serious recognition in the last few decades. There are two reasons that appear to underlie such widespread recognition. Firstly, the nanoscale dimension of LDSS results into profound enhancement of quantum effects in their physical properties (electrical, optical, magnetic etc.) in comparison with the bulk materials. Moreover, LDSS-based devices are also renowned for their high design-flexibility. The enhanced quantum effects and the said flexibility have earmarked LDSS as potential ingredients for manufacturing several high-performance microelectronic and optoelectronic devices. Secondly, from a pedagogic viewpoint; cultivation of LDSS physics provides revisit of many fundamental quantum mechanical concepts 
  <a rid="br0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0010">[1]</a>. Entry of impurity (dopant) to LDSS induces an interplay between the inherent confinement potential of LDSS and the dopant potential. Such interplay gives rise to an effective confinement potential that discernibly alters several physical properties of LDSS from that of an impurity-free state. These modified physical properties mark recognizable signature on the technology-related aspects of LDSS. Naturally, investigations on LDSS physics with impurity contamination have been performed in abundance over the last few decades 
  <a rid="br0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0020">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0030" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0030">[3]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0040" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0040">[4]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0050">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0060">[6]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0070">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0080">[8]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0090">[9]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0100" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0100">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0110" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0110">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0120" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0120">[12]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0130">[13]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0140" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0140">[14]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0150" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0150">[15]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0160" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0160">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0170" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0170">[17]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0180" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0180">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0190" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0190">[19]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0200">[20]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0210" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0210">[21]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0220" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0220">[22]</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="pr0020" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study of magnetic properties of LDSS assumes importance in order to understand electronic magnetism in nanoscale domain which often involves interesting physics 
  <a rid="br0230" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0230">[23]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0240" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0240">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0250" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0250">[25]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0260" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0260">[26]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0270" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0270">[27]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0280" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0280">[28]</a>. Such studies are done in presence of applied magnetic field which changes the energy spectrum of LDSS. A changed energy spectrum, in effect, regulates the performance of optoelectronic devices 
  <a rid="br0290" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0290">[29]</a>. Furthermore, studies of magnetic properties of LDSS are also found to be relevant in several related fields. These fields include particle dynamics of LDSS in an external magnetic field (connected with spintronics), quantum electronic structure of LDSS 
  <a rid="br0260" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0260">[26]</a>, semiconductor-metal transitions in LDSS 
  <a rid="br0300" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0300">[30]</a>, and various other applications. Doping of impurity into LDSS further increases the intricacies in its magnetic properties 
  <a rid="br0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0310">[31]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0320" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0320">[32]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0330" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0330">[33]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0340" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0340">[34]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0350" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0350">[35]</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="pr0030" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Diamagnetic susceptibility (DMS)</span> is an important magnetic property which has been extensively studied for LDSS doped with impurity. Study of DMS maintains close linkage with development of spintronics, quantum chaos, electronic conductivity and various other technological applications of electronic and optoelectronic devices 
  <a rid="br0340" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0340">[34]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0350" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0350">[35]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0360" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0360">[36]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0370" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0370">[37]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0380" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0380">[38]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0390" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0390">[39]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0400" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0400">[40]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0410" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0410">[41]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0420" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0420">[42]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0430" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0430">[43]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0440" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0440">[44]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0450" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0450">[45]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0460" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0460">[46]</a>. Therefore, in view of comprehensive investigation on DMS of LDSS; often, contribution of various physical quantities e.g. effective mass 
  <a rid="br0470" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0470">[47]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0480" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0480">[48]</a>, dielectric constant 
  <a rid="br0490" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0490">[49]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0500" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0500">[50]</a>, hydrostatic pressure and temperature 
  <a rid="br0510" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0510">[51]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0520" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0520">[52]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0530" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0530">[53]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0540" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0540">[54]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0550" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0550">[55]</a> has been explored in detail.
 </p>
 <p id="pr0040" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The output of LDSS-based devices is often influenced by the presence of 
  <span class="italic">noise</span>. Incorporation of noise to the system can be done externally in different ways (also called ‘modes’ or ‘pathways’) leading to different consequences. Two such pathways are called 
  <span class="italic">additive</span> and 
  <span class="italic">multiplicative</span> based on their different extents of interaction with the system. The physical properties of system are also naturally perturbed by the presence of noise. And the size of change in the physical properties of the system noticeably depends on the mode of introduction of noise as mentioned above. It is therefore quite sensible to explore the noise effects on different physical properties of LDSS which ultimately governs the functioning of LDSS based devices.
 </p>
 <p id="pr0050" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this communication we inspect how DMS (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M2" altimg="si2.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">χ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">d</span>
      <span class="mi">i</span>
      <span class="mi">a</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>) of 2-d 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M3" altimg="si1.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
    <span class="mi">G</span>
    <span class="mi">a</span>
    <span class="mi">A</span>
    <span class="mi">s</span>
   </div>
  </div> QD depends on the 
  <span class="italic">binding energy (BE)</span> of the system under the governance of noise. The harmonic oscillator potential defines the 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M4" altimg="si3.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
    <span class="mi">x</span>
    <span class="mo">−</span>
    <span class="mi">y</span>
   </div>
  </div> confinement whereas the 
  <span class="italic">z</span>-confinement is provided by a perpendicular magnetic field. The QD contains 
  <span class="italic">Gaussian</span> impurity as dopant and is simultaneously fed with 
  <span class="italic">Gaussian white noise</span> either via additive or multiplicative route (modes). Variation of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M5" altimg="si2.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">χ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">d</span>
      <span class="mi">i</span>
      <span class="mi">a</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> against magnetic field strength (
  <span class="italic">B</span>) has been monitored for different values of BE of the system. And this monitoring is carried out both with and without noise. The study unveils how BE of the system influences its DMS with some additional delicacies offered by noise.
 </p>
</sec>
