<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although previous studies on the mechanism of action of anesthetics have focused on anesthetics’ ability to interact with macromolecules such as lipid bilayers and proteins, our results show that individual anesthetic molecules can interact with photons. Even more significant is that the halogenated ethers studied here selectively interacted with a quantum system, entangled photons, as opposed to the classical system of photons. This distinction is important because the interaction mechanisms with classical vs entangled photons are different. In both two-photon interactions, the molecule interacting with the photons can take different pathways to go from its initial state to its final state. In classical two-photon interactions, the pathways cannot be controlled, due to the Fourier uncertainty relationship between frequency and time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. However, in entangled two-photon interactions, specific pathways can be selected because the entangled photons are not limited by the Fourier uncertainty principle
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. In other words, during the interaction event with two entangled photons, the molecule and the photons become correlated such that the specific interaction pathway in the molecule is strongly correlated with the quantum state of the photons
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. In order for a molecule to interact with entangled photons, it must be able to interact with the strongly correlated photons such that it enters into a correlation with them and thus affects the state of the photons; in this case, the molecule affects the photons by interacting with them instead of allowing them to transmit through the medium. Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> clearly shows that the anesthetics have the ability to interact with the strongly correlated 800 nm entangled photons in our experiment. This is the first empirical evidence that certain anesthetic molecules can directly interact with particles through a quantum mechanism. In addition, diethyl ether, a structurally similar ether, does not interact with the 800 nm entangled photons (transmission plots provided in Supplementary Figs 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S8</a>–
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). Thus, SEVO and ISO have a unique property that diethyl ether does not have. Although not explored in this work, this property may be related to the specific actions of SEVO and ISO vs diethyl ether. We have only investigated the interaction the ethers have with one wavelength of entangled photons, 800 nm. It is not known whether the ethers studied here can or cannot interact with entangled photons of other wavelengths, and this would be an interesting direction for further study.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This result does not prove any mechanism of anesthetic-induced unconsciousness, but it serves as a first proof-of-principle demonstration that anesthetic molecules meet the initial conditions we have outlined to be necessary for a quantum interaction mechanism that may induce unconsciousness. This result motivates further studies on the possible quantum interactions that anesthetic molecules may have in the brain and the atomic or subatomic particles they may be targeting, such as their interaction with the dynamic electronic states of proteins known to be targeted by general anesthetics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methodologic strengths of this study include a well-defined experimental model that can differentiate quantum vs. non-quantum interactions as well as the use of both halogenated and non-halogenated ethers. Methodologic limitations include the purely 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> experiments, the high concentration of the anesthetics used, the fact that the anesthetic was in liquid rather than gaseous phase, and the lack of spectral resolution. These limitations make it impossible to determine if there is any neurobiological or clinical relevance associated with the resultant data. Furthermore, the data do not suggest that general anesthesia has an exclusively quantum basis because diethyl ether is an effective anesthetic but demonstrated no quantum interactions. However, we have not conducted a systematic study of all possible quantum interactions with photons, including interaction with other entangled photon wavelengths, or other physical substrates such as microtubules, which have been posited to mediate quantum effects of general anesthetics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Further studies should explore other quantum systems as well as more neurobiologically relevant models.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, this is (to our knowledge) the first experimental study to rigorously assess the ability of a general anesthetic to interact with subatomic particles with quantum vs. classical features. The finding that halogenation confers the ability of an ether to engage in quantum mechanical processes advances our understanding of these critically important drugs and motivates further investigation regarding non-classical mechanisms of action.</p>
</sec>
