<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inhalational anesthetics were first used more than 170 years ago, when simple aliphatic ethers, such as diethyl ether, were commonly used to induce unconsciousness. Most inhalational anesthetics in clinical use today are halogenated ethers, such as sevoflurane (SEVO) and isoflurane (ISO), which can be considered derivatives of the anesthetic diethyl ether. To date, a description of the mechanism of anesthetic-induced unconsciousness has been approached from the perspective of classical chemistry interactions between anesthetics and neuronal compounds on the macroscopic level
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. This approach has shown how anesthetics can target particular proteins and protein-based compounds to manipulate the conformation of these compounds found in neurochemical synapses, leading to changes in the chemical potential of the surrounding environment. However, other studies have suggested that anesthetics may undergo a quantum interaction mechanism to induce unconsciousness
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, but—unlike the foundational empirical studies identifying binding between anesthetics and protein targets—it is unclear if general anesthetics can interact directly with quantum systems, including those involving long-distance entanglement. In order for a quantum interaction mechanism to be possible, two initial conditions would have to be met: (1) the anesthetic molecules must have the ability to target particles much smaller than the macroscopic compounds previously studied, as only atomic and subatomic particles will strongly adhere to the unique behaviors of quantum mechanics; and (2) the interactions cannot be explained using classical mechanics. Two previous studies have shown how quantum properties may play a role in anesthetic-induced unconsciousness. Turin 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> reported electron spin changes in fruit flies that occurred after they were given anesthetics, and Li 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span> reported that xenon isotopes without nuclear spin were more potent anesthetics than isotopes with nuclear spin. Although both of these studies indirectly suggest that quantum mechanics might relate to the mechanism of general anesthesia, neither study investigated whether anesthetics could directly interact with a quantum system.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous physical, pharmacological, and neuroscientific studies have not been able to describe completely the mechanism of anesthetic action for SEVO and ISO. Despite studies of SEVO’s and ISO’s NIR/IR optical properties
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, as well as ground state chemical structures and properties
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, very little is known about their linear and nonlinear optical properties in the visible and UV light range and their excited state electronic properties. Although the optical properties of anesthetics have not been studied in an attempt to understand their ability to change neuronal functioning and induce unconsciousness, spectroscopy experiments have been completed on neurons to produce action potentials using only light. Hirase 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> used high intensity pulsed IR light to trigger action potentials in pyramidal neurons. Although this experiment with high energy laser light damaged the cells, Wells 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> performed a similar experiment using IR light with much lower incident laser power and triggered action potentials in neurons 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span>, attributed to a photothermal effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, without damaging the cells. The low light intensity required to trigger the action potentials shows the high sensitivity of neurons to light. In addition to these experimental light sources, biophotons, i.e. light emitted by cells during specific metabolic processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, have been identified in neural tissue and hypothesized as auxiliary carriers in neuronal information transfer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. Thus, the study of photons is justified in the context of neural function and anesthetic-induced disruption of information processing
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we investigated the direct interaction between anesthetics and a quantum system using entangled two-photon spectroscopy. This spectroscopy technique utilizes pairs of photons whose quantum states are strongly correlated such that they must be treated as one body (i.e., they are entangled). The interaction mechanisms of a molecule with entangled photons vs classical photons are different, as shown in previous work by Lee 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. Therefore, both interaction processes must be investigated for a complete understanding of the optical properties of the molecule. Using 800 nm photons in a classical two-photon spectroscopy experiment, neither SEVO nor ISO interacted with the classical photons despite using very high light intensity (i.e., large number of photons) in our experiment. However, SEVO and ISO did interact with the 800 nm entangled photons at extremely low light intensity. By contrast, diethyl ether (a nonhalogenated ether used for reference) did not, showing a unique and unexpected sensitivity to a quantum correlated system in association with halogenation.
 </p>
</sec>
