<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linear optical properties</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies of steady-state UV absorption of SEVO and ISO were completed in the gas phase
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. It was stated that SEVO did not have any absorption above 200 nm, and no absorption spectrum was shown
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. ISO had an UV absorption onset at 215 nm and continued to increase down to 200 nm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, with another report showing the UV absorption continuing to increase down to 120 nm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. To the best of our knowledge, the UV absorption spectra for SEVO and ISO in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> are the first reported absorption spectra for ISO in the liquid phase and for SEVO in any phase. The absorption spectrum for diethyl ether, an aliphatic ether with a similar structure as SEVO and ISO, is shown for comparison. Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> also shows the emission spectra of SEVO and ISO when excited at their respective 
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>max</sub> (while 190 nm may not be the true 
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>max</sub> of liquid SEVO, it was the lowest wavelength available from our spectrophotometer and thus treated as 
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>max</sub> for emission experiments). The emission spectrum for diethyl ether, excited at 210 nm, is also shown for comparison.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>UV absorption and emission spectra of sevoflurane, isoflurane and diethyl ether in liquid phase.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47651_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e385" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The absorption spectrum for ISO peaks at 200 nm, the same as diethyl ether, while the absorption spectrum of SEVO is blue-shifted and continues to increase down to 190 nm without peaking. No absorption was shown for either compound above 270 nm. Previous studies have shown that fluorinated ethers have an UV absorption that is blue-shifted relative to aliphatic ethers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, as we see when comparing SEVO to diethyl ether in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. However, the fluorinated ether ISO, which also contains a chlorine atom, is not blue-shifted from diethyl ether at all. Although diethyl ether shows broad emission from ~270 nm to beyond 400 nm, peaking around 310 nm (which corresponds well with a previous study that reported an emission peak around 306 nm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>), neither SEVO nor ISO show any emission above background noise.
 </p>
</sec>
