<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Angle-resolved photoluminescence spectroscopy</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the interaction strength of optical emitters with light is indicative of their intrinsic TDMs, we apply two independent imaging approaches to reveal the TDMs of the CdSe QRs. In both approaches, isolated CdSe QRs with random azimuthal orientations are dispersed on substrates and loaded onto home-built confocal laser microscopes. We excite the CdSe QRs at a wavelength of 633 nm to ensure that only band-edge optical transitions are involved. We first investigate the QRs utilizing angle-resolved photoluminescence spectroscopy on a Fourier imaging system (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>. See Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> for a detailed description of the setup). This technique allows direct imaging of 
  <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved emission projections containing information about the orientations of the TDMs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. It is essential that a high numerical aperture (NA = 1.4) objective is used to focus the laser beam onto a single QR at a time and collect the corresponding emission. Intensity distributions of the QR emission at the back focal plane of the objective are recorded by a charge-coupled device. Our numerical simulations (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> for details) show that the 
  <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved emission pattern of a uniaxial TDM lying horizontally on a sample surface forms two bright lobes, whereas that of a uniaxial TDM lying vertically to the sample surface form a circular ring with an intensity nearly isotropic in the azimuthal angle (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a, b</a>). The distinct boundary between an inner and an outer region in the momentum space corresponds to the critical angle (
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>C</sub>) of total internal reflection at the glass-air interface, and radiation emits predominantly at angles larger than the critical angle into the high refractive index medium. The outer circle is defined by the maximum collection angle of the objective used in the measurements (
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>NA</sub>). Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d, e</a> show representative 
  <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved radiation patterns measured from single CdSe QRs. Calculated radiation patterns of in-plane uniaxial dipoles with their azimuthal orientations adjusted to match the experimentally measured patterns are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2g, h</a>. Good agreement between the experimentally measured and theoretically simulated radiation patterns can be observed. This is further confirmed by comparing the 
  <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved emission profile cuts from the experiments and calculations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2i</a>). Additional 
  <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved cross sections parallel and perpendicular to the dipole axes shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d, e</a> are presented in Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>, and they show good agreement with the simulated profiles extracted from Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2g, h</a>. This infers that the TDMs in CdSe QRs are in-plane and uniaxial.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved Fourier imaging of single CdSe quantum rings. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Calculated 
     <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved emission pattern of a TDM lying vertically 
     <span class="bold">a</span> and horizontally 
     <span class="bold">b</span> on a sample plane. The critical angle (
     <span class="italic">θ</span>
     <sub>C</sub>) and the angle determined by the numerical aperture (
     <span class="italic">θ</span>
     <sub>NA</sub>) are indicated. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Schematic of angle-resolved photoluminescence spectroscopy on a Fourier imaging system. 
     <span class="bold">d</span>, 
     <span class="bold">e</span> Measured radiation patterns of QRs highlighted in 
     <span class="bold">f</span>. 
     <span class="bold">f</span> A scanning photoluminescence image used to locate single QRs. Scale bar: 2 µm. 
     <span class="bold">g</span>, 
     <span class="bold">h</span> Calculated radiation patterns of QRs with their azimuthal angles adjusted to match those in 
     <span class="bold">d</span> and 
     <span class="bold">e</span>. 
     <span class="bold">i</span>
     <span class="bold">k</span>-vector resolved emission profiles from experimentally measured (dots) and calculated (curve) radiation patterns
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11225_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e631" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
