<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Higher-order laser scanning microscopy</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To consolidate our conclusion of the uniaxial, in-plane nature of the TDMs in CdSe QRs, we apply a second approach based on higher-order laser scanning microscopy to study the absorption in QRs. This approach has been used to study TDMs of organic molecules
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, and semiconductor
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> and metallic nanoparticles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. When an individual particle is raster scanned through the focus of a higher-order Bessel–Gauss laser beam, its excitation pattern is characteristic of its TDMs at the excitation wavelength. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a, b</a> shows the calculated transverse and longitudinal field components within the focal region of a radially polarized laser beam according to the parameters used in our experiment. The corresponding field intensity profiles are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c, d</a>. When a uniaxial TDM lies horizontally in the sample plane, it interacts mainly with the transverse component of the radially polarized laser beam, leading to an excitation pattern consisting of two bright off-axis lobes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e</a>). In the case that the uniaxial dipole lies perpendicularly to the sample plane, primarily the longitudinal component of the radially polarized laser beam interacts with the dipole, giving rise to an intense spot in the center. The relatively weak interaction between the transverse component of the laser beam and the vertical dipole results in a weak ring around the intense spot (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3f</a>). Comparison between the calculated and experimentally measured excitation patterns enables the determination of the dimensionalities and orientations of the TDMs. Excitation patterns of individual CdSe QRs scanned through radially polarized laser beams exclusively show two bright off-axis lobes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3g</a>). The intensity profiles from the experimentally measured patterns and calculated patterns of a horizontally lying uniaxial dipole show a reasonable agreement (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3h</a>). These results confirm our conclusion about the uniaxial, in-plane nature of the TDMs in CdSe QRs. We note that the TDMs studied here are the intrinsic properties of the QRs given their specific composition and geometry, while their emission polarization may not be uniaxial due to the renormalization effect caused by the differences in the dielectric constants of the QRs and their surrounding environment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Higher-order laser mode scanning microscopy of single CdSe quantum rings. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Numerically simulated transverse and longitudinal components of a radially polarized Bessel-Gauss laser beam. 
     <span class="bold">c, d</span> The corresponding intensity profiles of the transverse 
     <span class="bold">c</span> and longitudinal 
     <span class="bold">d</span> electromagnetic components. 
     <span class="bold">e, f</span> Calculated excitation patterns of a uniaxial TDM lying horizontally 
     <span class="bold">e</span> or vertically 
     <span class="bold">f</span> on the sample plane. 
     <span class="bold">g</span> Experimentally measured excitation patterns of individual CdSe QRs. 
     <span class="bold">h</span> Calculated intensity profiles of a horizontally lying uniaxial TDM (curve) and measured intensity profiles from the excitation patterns of a single CdSe QR (dot). The dimensions of 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">e</span>, 
     <span class="bold">f</span> are 1.27 × 1.27 µm
     <span class="sup">2</span>. The dimensions of 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span> are 2.53 × 2.53 µm
     <span class="sup">2</span>. The scale bars in 
     <span class="bold">g</span> are 1 µm
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11225_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e749" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
