<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optical transition dipole moments are key parameters in determining the interactions between optical emitters and external electromagnetic fields. Controlled orientation and alignment of TDMs have led to optoelectronic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span> and quantum photonic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> devices with unprecedented performance. The properties of TDMs are determined by the emitters’ electronic structures, which are closely related to their compositions, dimensions, and geometries. For instance, TDMs in zero-dimensional semiconductor quantum dots and two-dimensional nanoplatelets and transition-metal dichalcogenides have shown anisotropic two-dimensional distributions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, whereas those in one-dimensional nanorods and nanowires are uniaxial
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In semiconductor quantum rings (QRs), charge carriers are confined in the radial direction. This quantum confinement effect, in combination with the unique ring geometry, has led to the observation of geometry-dependent photon antibunching
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> and angular momentum-dependent emission in QRs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, which may enable a new class of quantum photon sources capable of high-density information coding for quantum communication
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> and quantum imaging techniques
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. The Aharonov-Bohm effect in QRs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> may also provide a promising avenue for single photon trapping, storage, and release by the use of an electric field
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. To explore these intriguing quantum photonic properties of QRs, a critical first step required for their realization and application in quantum information science is a detailed understanding of their intrinsic TDMs. Moreover, the study of TDMs in a topological ring structure is fundamentally interesting as QRs represent a crossover between one- and two-dimensional structures due to their peculiar annular geometry.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we investigate the dimensionality and orientation of the TDMs in CdSe QRs using single particle optical spectroscopy. We find that despite their two-dimensional annular shape, CdSe QRs exhibit an in-plane linear distribution. Our empirical tight binding calculations show that this uniaxial TDM is caused by the broken rotational symmetry in the QR geometries.</p>
</sec>
