<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum ring geometry and optical spectra</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CdSe QRs with emission wavelengths at around 675 nm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a–c</a>) were synthesized following our previously published method
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Their average outer ring diameters (OD
  <sub>1</sub> and OD
  <sub>2</sub>) along two perpendicular axes are 13.3 ± 1.1 nm and 9.9 ± 1.0 nm, respectively, with certain degrees of lateral elongation visible (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> for statistics). The corresponding average inner ring diameters, ID
  <sub>1</sub> and ID
  <sub>2</sub>, are 6.1 ± 0.9 nm and 3.8 ± 0.7 nm, respectively. Hence, the average thickness of the rings varies from 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 3.6 nm along the long axis to 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 3.0 nm along the short axis. The average height 
  <span class="italic">h</span> of the QRs was around 5.0 nm. Emissive QRs dispersed on substrates were located by raster scanning samples through the focus of a laser beam. Time-dependent measurements of single QR spectra show photoluminescence blinking and spectral shift (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1e</a>), both of which are characteristic of single quantum emitters and often attributed to charge carrier trapping at surface states
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Ensemble and single particle characterization of CdSe quantum rings. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> TEM images of the CdSe QRs. Scale bars in 
     <span class="bold">a</span> and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> represent 50 nm and 5 nm, respectively. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Absorption and emission spectra of CdSe QR ensembles. The vertical dashed line indicates the excitation wavelength for the single particle measurements. The inset is a schematic of the ring geometry. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> A scanning photoluminescence image of single QRs. Scale bar: 1 µm. 
     <span class="bold">e</span> A representative time-dependent spectral sequence of a single QR
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11225_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e489" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
