<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Single quantum ring optical spectroscopy and imaging</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To prepare samples for single particle optical measurements, the stock solutions of QRs were diluted by hexane and spin coated onto quartz or glass cover slips. Optical measurements of single QRs were performed on home-built confocal laser scanning microscopes at room temperature. The angle-resolved photoluminescence spectroscopy was performed on a Fourier imaging system (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). In this method, to inhibit photoluminescence blinking of the QRs, a layer of polystyrene was deposited onto the QRs. This was considered within the dipole distribution simulations by adjusting the refractive index of the upper half-space to 
  <span class="italic">n</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 1.1, since the presence of the polystyrene thin film will increase the effective refractive index experienced by the QRs. The lower half-space refractive index 
  <span class="italic">n</span>
  <sub>2</sub> was defined by the glass cover slide, index matching oil and objective and given with 
  <span class="italic">n</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 1.52. A continuous wave HeNe laser with a wavelength of 633 nm was focused by a microscope objective (NA = 1.4) to excite the samples. Emission from the QRs was collected by the same objective and sent to a cooled charge-coupled device (CCD) after spectral filtering. A Bertrand lens was used to form an image of the back focal plane on the CCD. The higher-order laser scanning microscopy of the QRs were performed using similar excitation conditions, except that the Gaussian laser beam was converted into a higher-order radially polarized beam and a microscope objective with NA = 1.49 was used. Emission from the QRs collected by the objective was focused onto an avalanche photon diode to form confocally scanned images.
 </p>
</sec>
