<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical modeling of quantum rings</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The two-dimensional infinite potential well calculations were performed using a discrete variable representation with a sinc basis
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Two ovals, defined by the parameters OD
  <sub>1</sub>, OD
  <sub>2</sub>, ID
  <sub>1</sub>, and ID
  <sub>2</sub> (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>), were defined. Any points in the discretized space in between these two ovals had a potential of zero; any point outside had a potential set arbitrarily high, defining a Hamiltonian matrix. This matrix was diagonalized using the parallel eigenvalue solver package SLEPc
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span> for the eigenstates with eigenvalues closest to zero.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To calculate the energy levels and wavefunctions of the CdSe QRs, we started with a large supercell of zinc-blend CdSe atoms with lattice constant 6.052 Å. We then defined an ideal three-dimensional generalized torus, where any slice along 
  <span class="italic">z</span> was defined by two ovals in the 
  <span class="italic">x</span>, 
  <span class="italic">y</span> plane. In the middle of the ring along the 
  <span class="italic">z</span> dimension, these two ovals were defined by the parameters OD
  <sub>1</sub>, OD
  <sub>2</sub>, ID
  <sub>1</sub>, and ID
  <sub>2</sub>. Towards the edges of the ring in the 
  <span class="italic">z</span> plane (defined by the height of the ring, 
  <span class="italic">h</span>), the parameters of the two ovals changed such that a slice along the 
  <span class="italic">x</span> or 
  <span class="italic">y</span> planes results in an oval. Any atom which fell inside of this three-dimensional geometry was kept; any atom outside of the ring was discarded. After cutting out the ring, we iteratively looped through all atoms and removed any atoms which had only a single bond until all atoms had at least two bonds. This may result in unequal numbers of Cd and Se in the QRs, but since we are not doing total energy calculations, a slight nonstoichiometry should not alter our calculation results. Using this set of atoms, we solved for the band-edge states using the empirical tight-binding method within the code QNANO
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Within the empirical tight-binding method, a set of orbitals was defined for each atom. The parameters of these orbitals were fit to density functional theory calculations of bulk systems. The method solved for the eigenstates near the band-edge using the basis of these parameterized orbitals.
 </p>
</sec>
