<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two new planar chiral macrocyclic hosts 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> and 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span> were synthesized by grafting two fluorophore pigments (DPA or Py) on pillar[5]arene through CuAAC “click” reaction. The new macrocyclic compounds showed strong absorptions in the visible range and high fluorescence quantum yield, e.g., 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> showed absorption at 350–410 nm and a quantum yield of 89.5% which is comparable to the monomer 
  <span class="bold">DPA-6</span>. On the other hand, 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span> with two perylene (Py) pigments grafted on the pillar[5]arene showed intense absorption at 385–460 nm and a quantum yield of 46.4%. The rotation of phenolic units was inhibited by introducing two bulky fluorophores in one of the phenolic units of pillar[5]arene, and the enantiomers were isolated by chiral HPLC. The absolute configurations of each fraction were determined by circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy. The first fraction showing negative CD signals was assigned to the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> conformer and the second fraction showing positive CD signals was assigned to the 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> conformer. Aggregation behaviors of the enantiopure chiral pillar[5]arene derivatives were investigated by adding water into the THF solution. 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> and 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span> showed an enhancement of the CD signals by adding water due to restriction of the conformers’ rotations by aggregation. 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> showed a fluorescence enhancement when less than 50% of water was added, while 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span> showed emission quenching and excimer emission when adding water into the THF solution. This work presented a new strategy for achieving versatile planar chiral hosts, and these hosts will have potential applications in various fields such as supramolecular sensing, host–guest recognition and triplet–triplet annihilation upconversion.
 </p>
</sec>
