<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optical properties</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the fact that the Py and DPA units are too large to enter the cavity of the pillar[5]arene, we expected that the oxygen-through-annulus rotation is blocked in 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> and 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span>, giving rise to two pairs of enantiomeric pillar[5]arene derivatives. The racemic mixtures of 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> and 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span> were respectively separated by chiral high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>, injection of a 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> solution onto a DAICEL CHIRALPAK IA chiral HPLC column afforded two well-separated peaks of almost equal areas at 8.8 min and 10.0 min, respectively, demonstrating that 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> was the racemic mixture of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> and 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> configuration. The two fractions were collected separately and re-injected into the chiral column to confirm the enantiomeric purity and to check if racemization of the enantiomers takes place in solution at room temperature. In both cases, only the original peak was detected and the peak for the antipodal enantiomer was not detected, indicating that no racemization of the enantiomer of 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> takes place at room temperature (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a> and c). 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span> showed a similar phenomenon (Figure S22a,b and c). These results demonstrated that the bulky substituents DPA or perylene effectively prevent the ring rotations, and therefore making the separation of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> and 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> conformers possible.
 </p>
 <div id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Chiral HPLC traces of 
    <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span>, (b), (c) the first and second fractions of 
    <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span>, detected by UV at 295 nm. Conditions: column, DAICEL CHIRALPAK IA; mobile phase: hexane/dichloromethane 35:65; flow rate = 4.0 mL/min; temperature 25 °C). (d) CD and (e) UV–vis spectra of racemic 
    <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span>, the first and second fractions (10 μM) in CHCl
    <sub>3</sub> at 25 °C.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="Beilstein_J_Org_Chem-15-1601-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a> and e show the circular dichroism (CD) and UV–vis spectra of each fraction for 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span>. The CD signals of both fractions observed at 270–320 nm are perfect mirror images, thus confirming that the two fractions contain a pair of enantiomers. The positive Cotton effect observed at ca. 310 nm was assigned to the 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> configured enantiomer whereas the negative Cotton effect at ca. 310 nm was assigned to the corresponding 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> configured isomer, based on calculations as well as single-crystal X-ray diffraction published recently [
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">20</a>]. Thus, the absolute configuration of the first fraction was assigned to be 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> and the second fraction was assigned to the 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> isomer. Unexpectedly, no induced CD signals of DPA units at 360–420 nm were observed though 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> showed a strong absorption (with ε &gt; 10
  <span class="sup">4</span> M
  <span class="sup">−1</span> cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>) in this region. The same is true for 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span> (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>, Figure S22d and e). We attributed the absence of induced CD signals to the long distances of the fluorophores to the chiral center and therefore chirality transfer is non-effective [
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supramolecular assembly usually leads to different photophysical properties than homogeneous solutions. We have demonstrated that solvents play a critical role in chiral recognition and chiral photoreactions [
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">44</a>–
  <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">51</a>]. We therefore further investigated the solvent-induced aggregation behaviors of the chirally pure conformers by adding different proportions of water into their THF solutions. Taking the 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>p</sub>
  </span> conformers for example, the aggregation of 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> is apparently divided into two stages (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). By adding 50% water to THF, the UV–vis absorption wavelength of 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> did not change but the CD signals were obviously enhanced. This is most probably due to the formation of aggregates and the rotation of the phenolic units in pillar[5]arene host was inhibited in the aggregates. The aggregation behavior was further investigated by dynamic light scattering (DLS) analyses, and revealed the formation of nanoparticles with 615 nm in average diameter after the addition of 50% water (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). Increasing the amount of water to 70% or 90% led to a bathochromic shift of the UV–vis absorption and a raise of the baseline, indicating particles of larger size were formed. The CD signals continuously increased accompanied with a red-shifting of the wavelength, thus demonstrating that the DPA pigments started to aggregate in solutions with a water content of more than 50%. The π–π stacking of the anthracene core in DPA is responsible for the red-shift of the absorption. For 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span>, however, adding water to the THF solution led to a continuous red-shifting of the UV–vis spectra and increasing of CD signal, which is reasonable, as the planar structure of Py tends more to get aggregated in water by π–π stacking. Aggregates with an average diameter of 531 nm are formed in 60% water (Figure S23, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>) [
  <a rid="R52" ref-type="bibr" href="#R52">52</a>]. Exciton coupling CD (ECCD) signals were not observed for both compounds, even when adding more than 90% water, demonstrating that the chromophores DPA or Py units were not asymmetrically oriented in the aggregates.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) CD, (b) UV–vis and (c) fluorescence spectra of the 
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <span class="bold">
     <sub>P5A-DPA</sub>
    </span> (20 μM) in THF and THF/H
    <sub>2</sub>O solvent mixtures; inset: the normalized fluorescence spectrum. (d) DLS measurements of the aggregated 
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <span class="bold">
     <sub>P5A-DPA</sub>
    </span> obtained from the mixture of THF/H
    <sub>2</sub>O 1:1 (v/v).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="Beilstein_J_Org_Chem-15-1601-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, by adding water into the THF solution of 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span>, the fluorescence intensity firstly increased by 3 times at 50% water and then decreased when the water content was increased to 70% (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). We attributed the enhanced emission of 
  <span class="bold">P5A-DPA</span> in the presence of less than 50% water to an inhibited rotation of the 9,10-phenyl groups in the DPA units, which reduced the inactivation of the excited state through non-radiative transition [
  <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">53</a>]. However, when increasing the amount of water, the fluorescence starts to decrease due to the π–π stacking of DPA, which led to aggregation-caused quenching (ACQ), as was demonstrated by UV–vis absorption and CD studies. For compound 
  <span class="bold">P5A-Py</span>, however, the fluorescence intensity continuously decreased when adding water into the THF solutions, and at 70% water content, a new emission peak at 540 nm was observed which was assigned to the excimer emission of Py (Figure S23, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>) [
  <a rid="R54" ref-type="bibr" href="#R54">54</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
