<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the following, we compare our result with recent studies on strong coupling of single emitters using plasmonic nanocavities. To date, most strong coupling studies have relied on multiple (
  <span class="italic">n</span>) emitters in the form of J-aggregates (
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
   <span class="italic">43</span>
  </a>) to induce a large collective effect (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m11" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">g</span>
      <span class="mo">∝</span>
      <div class="msqrt">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">n</span>
        <span class="mo">/</span>
        <span class="mi">V</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>). However, multiple emitters are impracticable for applications in quantum gates (
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
   <span class="italic">44</span>
  </a>) and entanglement (
  <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">
   <span class="italic">45</span>
  </a>) because they exhibit an equidistant energy spectrum that is identical to a classical system. This means that the nonlinear optical properties of multiple emitters are qualitatively different than the single emitter case (
  <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
   <span class="italic">46</span>
  </a>). However, the observation of peak splitting in scattering spectra from single emitters (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>) is not sufficient to ensure strong coupling, as other effects such as Fano-like interference can lead to nearly identical spectral features (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
   <span class="italic">43</span>
  </a>). Probing strong coupling plexciton emission in the form of, e.g., PL of a single emitter overcomes these issues and provides unambiguous evidence of strong coupling for applications in quantum information and photonic quantum devices. However, the recent work using PL to probe strong coupling of a single QD coupled to a plasmonic slot structure (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>) led to convoluted spectra with large background and competing interactions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, our approach of TESC uses a combination of several enabling features that allow us to induce, image, and control single-emitter plexciton PL at room temperature with the following beneficial attributes. First, on the basis of the inverse geometry (
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">
   <span class="italic">47</span>
  </a>), instead of a nanogap in the tip itself, we induce the nanocavity between the tip and the sample, which provides tunable coupling and ultrasmall mode volumes (section S6). Second, with the tilted tip and thus spectrally controlled SPP, the field enhancement is further increased by suppressing the overdamped resonance of a conventional surface-normal oriented tip (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>). Third, near-field coupling and polarization transfer to the tip with its few-femtosecond radiative lifetime (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>) at the subnanometer gap between the tip and QD outcompetes the otherwise dominant nonradiative damping of a QD near a metallic surface (
  <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">
   <span class="italic">48</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
