<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="se0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="pr0010" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tremendous enhancement in the research on low-dimensional semiconductor systems (LDSS) e.g. quantum wells (QWLs), quantum wires (QWRs) and quantum dots (QDs) has been envisaged over the last couple of decades. The said enhancement can be justified from two different but highly related angles; technological and pedagogical. The technological angle deals with the widespread application of LDSS in the manufacture of high-output microelectronic and optoelectronic devices such as QD lasers, solar cells, single electron transistors and quantum computers. Simultaneously, the pedagogical angle involves rejuvenation of many fundamental concepts of quantum mechanics. Sudden rise in the level of delicacy of LDSS physics occurs with the introduction of impurity (dopant). The increased delicacy has its roots in the newly formed interaction between the original LDSS confinement potential and the dopant potential. The resultant effective confinement potential discernibly modifies the nonlinear optical (NLO) properties of LDSS from that of a dopant-free condition. LDSS possess special status for displaying enhanced NLO properties. Thus, the modulation of NLO properties of LDSS by impurity is quite interesting and accentuates rigorous research works 
  <a rid="br0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0010">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0020">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0030" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0030">[3]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0040" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0040">[4]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0050">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0060">[6]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0070">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0080">[8]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0090">[9]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0100" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0100">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0110" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0110">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0120" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0120">[12]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0130">[13]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0140" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0140">[14]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0150" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0150">[15]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0160" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0160">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0170" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0170">[17]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0180" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0180">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0190" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0190">[19]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0200">[20]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0210" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0210">[21]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0220" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0220">[22]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0230" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0230">[23]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0240" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0240">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0250" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0250">[25]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0260" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0260">[26]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0270" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0270">[27]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0280" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0280">[28]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0290" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0290">[29]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0300" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0300">[30]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0310">[31]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0320" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0320">[32]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0330" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0330">[33]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0340" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0340">[34]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0350" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0350">[35]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0360" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0360">[36]</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="pr0020" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Presence of 
  <span class="italic">noise</span> markedly affects the efficacy of LDSS-based devices. Noise can make its entry to the system by using some external ‘modes’ or ‘pathways’, among which 
  <span class="italic">additive</span> and 
  <span class="italic">multiplicative</span> are the two most common ones. These two pathways can be distinguished depending on how noise gets engaged with the system coordinates. Noise, thus introduced, conspicuously changes the physical properties of the system through the alteration of the effective confinement potential. Importantly, such change in the physical properties of LDSS has been found to be dependent on the mode of introduction of noise mentioned before. Therefore, exploration of noise-induced modulations of the physical properties of LDSS draws sincere attention.
 </p>
 <p id="pr0030" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently we have studied the influence of noise-binding energy interplay on a magnetic property viz. diamagnetic susceptibility (DMS) of doped QDs 
  <a rid="br0370" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0370">[37]</a>. Current study endeavors to carry out an in-depth scrutiny of how the 
  <span class="italic">interplay between noise and binding energy (BE)</span> can fine-tune three important NLO properties of 2-d 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M2" altimg="si1.svg" class="math">
    <span class="mi">G</span>
    <span class="mi">a</span>
    <span class="mi">A</span>
    <span class="mi">s</span>
   </div>
  </div> QD viz. 
  <span class="italic">electro-optical effect (EOE)</span>
  <a rid="br0380" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0380">[38]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0390" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0390">[39]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0400" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0400">[40]</a>, 
  <span class="italic">third-order nonlinear optical susceptibilities (TONOS)</span>
  <a rid="br0410" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0410">[41]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0420" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0420">[42]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0430" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0430">[43]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0440" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0440">[44]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0450" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0450">[45]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0460" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0460">[46]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0470" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0470">[47]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0480" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0480">[48]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0490" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0490">[49]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0500" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0500">[50]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0510" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0510">[51]</a> and 
  <span class="italic">total optical dielectric function (TODF)</span>
  <a rid="br0520" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0520">[52]</a>. Thus, the present study shows some new innovation with respect to our previous study 
  <a rid="br0370" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0370">[37]</a>. Among the mentioned NLO properties EOE and TONOS stand for the second-order and third-order nonlinear phenomena, respectively. TODF deserves importance since an extended inspection which commences from it culminates into understanding the effective optical properties of the dot-matrix composite systems because of dielectric mismatch. In this context BE of LDSS deems importance as any alteration in BE noticeably affects the physical properties of LDSS, including the NLO properties 
  <a rid="br0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0050">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0130">[13]</a>, 
  <a rid="br0190" ref-type="bibr" href="#br0190">[19]</a>. Thus, such study appears significant even from a technological viewpoint. In the present work the 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M3" altimg="si2.svg" class="math">
    <span class="mi">x</span>
    <span linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after" class="mo">−</span>
    <span class="mi">y</span>
   </div>
  </div> confinement is described by harmonic oscillator potential and the 
  <span class="italic">z</span>-confinement is offered by a vertical magnetic field. In addition, an electric field of strength 
  <span class="italic">F</span> is applied to the system along 
  <span class="italic">x</span> and 
  <span class="italic">y</span>-directions. The QD is doped with 
  <span class="italic">Gaussian impurity</span> and at the same time is subjected to 
  <span class="italic">Gaussian white noise</span> applied via 
  <span class="italic">additive</span> and 
  <span class="italic">multiplicative</span> pathways (modes). The study makes a close scrutiny of how the interplay between BE and noise engineers the above NLO properties with substantial thrust on the influence of the noise mode.
 </p>
</sec>
