<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2D electronic measurements and experimental conditions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Details of the experimental setup have already been described in earlier reports from our group.
  <a rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit32">32</a> Briefly, an all-reflective 2D spectrometer based on a diffractive optic (Holoeye) with a phase stability of 
  <span class="italic">λ</span>/160 has been used for these measurements.
  <a rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit34">34</a> ∼16 fs pulses for the 2D electronic measurements have been generated by compressing the laser beam from a home-built nonlinear optical parametric amplifier (NOPA) to the Fourier transform limit using the combination of a prism pair and a deformable mirror (OKO Technologies). The NOPA is pumped by a commercial femtosecond laser Pharos from Light Conversion. The temporal profile of the compressed beam was characterized by frequency-resolved optical grating (FROG) measurements and the obtained FROG traces were analyzed using a commercial program FROG3 (Femtosecond Technologies). A broadband spectrum so obtained carried a linewidth of ∼100 nm (FWHM) and was centered at 13 000 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> which covered the polaron peak, P
  <sub>2</sub> of PBTTT at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>) as well as the second vibronic feature at 769 nm (∼13 000 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>) corresponding to the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. An additional component is the Sciencetech spectrometer model 9055 which is coupled to CCD linear array camera (Entwicklungsburo Stresing). The 2D spectra for each waiting time 
  <span class="italic">T</span> were collected by scanning the delay time 
  <span class="italic">τ</span> = 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>1</sub> – 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>2</sub> in the range of [–128 fs, 128 fs] with a delay step of 1 fs. At each delay step, 200 spectra were averaged to reduce the noise ratio. The waiting time 
  <span class="italic">T</span> = 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>3</sub> – 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>2</sub> was linearly scanned in the range of 1 ps with steps of 5 fs. The energy of the excitation pulse is attenuated to 10 nJ with 1 kHz repetition rates for all the measurements. Three pulses are focused on the sample with the spot size of ∼80 μm and the photon echo signal is generated at the phase-matching direction. A fresh sample solution was prepared for each time-resolved measurement. The sample was filtered using a 0.2 μm filter to minimize light scattering, and then sealed in a 1 mm quartz cell (Starna). To avoid the possibility of sample degradation, the cell in the 2D setup was placed on a precise 2D translator and moved at a speed of ∼20 cm s
  <span class="sup">–1</span> in both directions. Absorption spectrum of the sample was measured before and after the measurements using a Shimadzu spectrometer (UV-2600), and no noticeable change was observed.
 </p>
</sec>
