<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Organic semiconductors have attracted enormous attention due to the advantage of convenient large area processing 
  <span class="italic">via</span> spin coating or printing techniques, and due to their potential in designing custom-tailored molecules to tune optoelectronic properties for organic electronics.
  <a rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit1">1</a> To gain control over the intrinsic charge carrier concentration in organic semiconductors, doping with small molecules and ions is commonly used. Conjugated semiconducting polymers have shown remarkable conductivities as high as ∼105 S cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> in a solid pellet of polyacetylene
  <a rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit2">2</a> and ∼2000 S cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> in solution-processed polythiophenes.
  <a rid="cit3" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit3">3</a> Recent experiments have revealed the unforeseen potential of doping and have resolved various issues in organic semiconductors beyond its traditional role of increasing conductivities. This includes organic light emitting diodes,
  <a rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit4">4</a>,
  <a rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit5">5</a> solar cells,
  <a rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit6">6</a> thermoelectric generators
  <a rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit7">7</a>,
  <a rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit8">8</a> and thin film transistors.
  <a rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit9">9</a> However, despite the initial successes of the doped materials, it remained difficult to precisely ascertain the dominating mechanisms, which should guide the further improvement of the materials' performance.
  <a rid="cit10" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit10">10</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To obtain higher conductivities, empirical efforts have been developed for selecting appropriate molecular dopants, which are compatible with the network of conducting polymers as organic semiconductors. The choice of the complementary dopant and polymer combination is mainly determined by energy level alignment which is favorable for the charge transfer. Usually, the highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) of the donor lies higher in energy than the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO) of the acceptor, which works in most cases with few exceptions.
  <a rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit11">11</a> For p-type doping, the successful donor:acceptor (D:A) pair configuration is a polymer:dopant pair. However, the roles are inverted for n-type doping. To achieve doped conducting polymer films over a desired substrate, a convenient approach is based on a processable solution in which a dopant and a polymer material are co-deposited from a solution mixture 
  <span class="italic">via</span> spin coating.
  <a rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit12">12</a> This technique of D:A mixing in solution leads to the formation of either an ion-pair, where a duplex of interacting charges is formed by electron transfer, or, of a ground state charge transfer complex, where frontier molecular orbitals of the polymer and the dopant hybridize to generate a new set of bonding and antibonding orbitals.
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a> How the small-molecule dopants are incorporated in order to achieve these fundamental interaction mechanisms has been an active area of research.
  <a rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit14">14</a>,
  <a rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit15">15</a> Amongst these two interaction mechanisms, ion-pair formation has been identified as the dominant effect, which is operative in doped organic semiconductors. The doping efficiency (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, the number of free charge carriers created per dopant molecule) is completely determined by these prevailing interactions. The strength of the Coulomb interaction within the ion-pairs thereby determines the binding energy of the charge carriers generated after the doping process. Thus, it becomes important to decipher the origin and strength of the dominating interactions in the course of the doping process. Interestingly, the optical signatures and dynamics for the ion-pair formation process can even be observed in the solution mixture used for spin-casting.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> Although there have been numerous attempts to decipher the nano-morphologies and molecular structures of the doped polymer films using solid-state NMR,
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> IR/Raman spectroscopy,
  <a rid="cit17" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit17">17</a> small-angle neutron or X-ray scattering,
  <a rid="cit18" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit18">18</a>,
  <a rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit19">19</a> electron microscopy
  <a rid="cit20" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit20">20</a> and inelastic neutron spectroscopy,
  <a rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit21">21</a> there is minimal understanding of the strength of the dominant intermolecular interactions prevailing in the precursor solutions, which dictate the incumbent film properties. A direct determination of the intermolecular interaction strength of the ion pair in solution is needed to formulate the guidelines to gain systematic control over the molecular design for doped organic semiconductor to improve the doping efficiency.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to develop a specific molecular basis for rational tailoring of molecular interactions in ion pairs within doped polymer materials, we have explored the electronic structure of p-doped thiophene-based conjugated polymer, PBTTT (poly(2,5-bis(3-dodecylthiophen-2-yl)thieno[3,2-
  <span class="italic">b</span>]thiophene)) in chlorobenzene as a model system. The dopant used in our studies is tetrafluoro-tetracyano-quinodimethane (F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ). We employed ultrafast nonlinear two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy to probe the electronic interactions amongst the ion pair in the precursor solution mixture. The use of 2D methods provides a means to directly determine the inhomogeneous distribution of ion pair interactions and equally important the degree of interaction as measured by the effect of electronic coupling on the homogeneous lineshape. Our measurements prove the presence of strong electronic coupling within the ion pair already in solution and this distribution corresponds to a spectrally well resolved state. We do not observe a broad distribution of interactions as might be expected for well solvated species in which solvation energies overcome Coulomb interactions. In addition, the electronic coupling between the dopant and polymer strongly perturbs electronic structure of the dopant anion, which is inferred from its modulated decay dynamics. We have developed a theoretical model, which allows us to extract the value of the electronic coupling strength to be ∼250 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>, which is unexpectedly large. Likewise, it retrieves an intermolecular distance of ∼4.5 Å within the ion-pair distribution. The lineshape indicates a relatively narrow distribution about this charge separated pairs. Using this combination of experimental and theoretical results, a structural model of the ion pair in the precursor solution is established and compared with the postulated model in spin casted films by solid-state NMR
  <a rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit21">21</a> to reveal the retained memory of the precursor solution interactions in the films. We conclude that already at the level of the precursor solution, the electronic interaction in the ion pair is fixed and the film inherits this property, which becomes the decisive parameter for the electronic conductivity in the films. Yet, strategies are available for controlling chemical processing at the level of the precursor solution.
 </p>
</sec>
