<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and discussion</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ: a model system of ion-pair formation in doped organic semiconductors
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent studies of doped PBTTT by F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ have revealed promising values of electrical conductivity from this pair.
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a>,
   <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a>
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(b)</a> represents the molecular structures of polymer PBTTT and dopant F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ. Polymer PBTTT consists of a thieno [3,2-
   <span class="italic">b</span>] thiophene (TT) core having two fused thiophene rings with 6Ï electrons in each monomeric unit. These TT units are in conjugation with thiophene bridges in the backbone which manifests a broad π–π* absorption in the range of 350 to 640 nm with an evident shoulder at 580 nm as shown in the ESI (Fig. S1
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>).
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> Dopant F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ on the other hand shows a strong dipolar excitation between 350 to 550 nm in chlorobenzene (blue trace in Fig. S1, ESI
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The solution mixture of dopant and polymer in chlorobenzene (dielectric constant = 5.6) has been prepared using the protocol reported by Chabinyc and co-workers (see Methods section for details).
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> Black color solution so obtained has 10 wt% of dopant to polymer (molar ratio = 0.25), which corresponds to ∼4 PBTTT repeat units per F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ.
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> This solution exhibits a distinct structural band in the range of 650 to 1000 nm as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a> as brown spheres (also in Fig. S1, ESI
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The measured absorption spectrum of the molecular system shows three peaks at 689 nm, 769 and 869 which are characteristic features of F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion's HOMO to LUMO transition (D
   <sub>0</sub> → D
   <sub>1</sub>).
   <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a> These pronounced vibronic structures in F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion arises from the Franck–Condon displacements along the C
   <div name="DOUBLE BOND, LENGTH AS M-DASH" description="double bond, length as m-dash" class="private-char">
    <span id="z.dbdRxuNV" format="PBM" resolution="300" x-size="34" y-size="34" xml:space="preserve" class="glyph-data">
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
	</span>
   </div>C stretching vibrational mode of ∼1500 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>.
   <a rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit31">31</a> The broadening of these vibronic features is caused by the overlapping PBTTT positive polaron features. Molecular dopants are known to interact with the polymer matrix 
   <span class="italic">via</span> two possible fundamental interaction mechanisms, 
   <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, ion-pair and ground state charge transfer complex formation.
   <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a> Since the PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ pair shows diagnostic electronic transitions for the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion in the solution mixture, we can conclude that PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ forms an ion-pair in solution. Our conclusion is also supported by the fact that the electron affinity of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ is higher than the ionization energy of the polymer so that one electron can be transferred from the HOMO of the PBTTT polymer to the LUMO of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(a)</a>.
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> In the absorption profile of PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, the spectral feature for PBTTT cation is rendered invisible due to the overlap with the features stemming from the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion.
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a>,
   <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a> The optical transitions associated with the PBTTT cation and the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion are calculated on a constructed model of the ion-pair (details have been mentioned in Theoretical modeling section) by means of density functional theory (DFT) using CAM-B3LYP with the diffuse basis set of cc-pvdz, which revealed the transition dipole moments of the PBTTT and F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ ions' electronic transitions with the magnitude of 3.3 and 6.5 Debye, respectively, in the spectral range of 650 to 950 nm (for details, see the ESI
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The feature at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>) corresponds to the P2 electronic transition associated with the PBTTT cation (blue circles in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>). Thus, the optical absorption spectrum of PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in chlorobenzene is a superposition of contributions from F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anions and PBTTT positive polarons which signifies the presence of ion-pair formation in the solution phase. These electronic transitions of PBTTT
   <span class="sup">+</span>F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
   <span class="sup">–</span> in chlorobenzene can be capitalized to explore the intermolecular electronic interactions in the ion-pair.
  </p>
  <div id="fig1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">PBTTT/F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ: a model system for the ion-pair in p-doped organic semiconductors. (a) Unperturbed energy diagram depicting the electronic states of PBTTT and F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, which are involved in the formation of the ion-pair. Electron transfer (ET) from PBTTT to F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ is favored by the sizable energy offset between the ionization energy (IE) of PBTTT (–5.1 eV) and the electron affinity (EA) of F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ (–5.2 eV). The values of the IE and EA of F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ and PBTTT are used from literature report.
     <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> (b) Chemical structures of the polymer PBTTT and the dopant, F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, used in this study. (c) Experimental (brown spheres) and calculated (blue circles) absorption spectra of the PBTTT
     <span class="sup">+</span>F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
     <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair at room temperature. The vibronic features in the experimental absorption spectrum in chlorobenzene are diagnostic for the F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion (D
     <sub>0</sub> → D
     <sub>1</sub>). The blue filled curve represents the laser spectrum used in the two-dimensional electronic spectroscopic measurements which covers the polaron peak, P
     <sub>2</sub> of PBTTT at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
     <span class="sup">–1</span>) as well as the second vibronic feature at 769 nm (∼13 000 cm
     <span class="sup">–1</span>) corresponding to the F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion.
    </div>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="c8sc00758f-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy (2DES) measurements</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2DES is a powerful nonlinear optical spectroscopic technique which provides a correlation between the excitation (
   <span class="italic">ω</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">τ</span>
   </sub>) and the probing wavelength (
   <span class="italic">ω</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">τ</span>
   </sub>) presenting connectivity in different electronic transitions to reveal the electronic coupling between corresponding chromophores.
   <a rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit25">25</a>–
   <a rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit27">27</a> This method also provides a direct means to separate inhomogeneous broadening effects from the 2D lineshape to enable a determination of the underlying distribution of nuclear configurations giving rise to the inhomogeneous lineshape. To unveil the interplay of the different electronic transitions and their couplings in PBTTT
   <span class="sup">+</span>F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
   <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair, we have carried out 2DES measurements at room temperature for different waiting times. The details of the experimental set up and the measurement conditions are described in the Methods section. PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in chlorobenzene is excited by an ultrashort laser pulse with the pulse width of 16 fs and the associated spectrum is shown as the blue curve in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(c)</a>. In order to avoid the interference with the 0–0 transition of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion, the frequency window of the laser spectrum has been judiciously chosen to cover two specific transitions corresponding to the polaron peak of PBTTT at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>) and the second vibronic feature at 769 nm (∼13 000 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>) of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. Measured 2D spectra (real part) for selected waiting times are shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>. Interestingly, the measured 2D spectra for different waiting times show several diagonal and off-diagonal features, which represent the underlying optical transitions and the coupling between them. To identify the individual features, we have marked the diagonal and off-diagonal peaks in the 2DES spectrum for 
   <span class="italic">T</span> = 50 fs by (A, B, C) and (D, E, F, I), respectively. The diagonal peak A corresponds to the 0–0 transition between the ground and excited state of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. Since this transition is only weakly absorbed within the laser spectrum as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a> (blue filled curve), it does not show an appreciable magnitude in the 2DES spectra. The diagonal peak B at 
   <span class="italic">ω</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">τ</span>
   </sub> = 12 250 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span> is a signature of the PBTTT positive polaron.
   <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a>,
   <a rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit28">28</a> Peak C at 
   <span class="italic">ω</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">τ</span>
   </sub> = 13 000 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span> is a strong positive bleach feature and corresponds to the transition to the higher vibrational level of the excited state, D
   <sub>1</sub> of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. It is worth mentioning here that unlike the linear absorption spectrum of PBTTT
   <span class="sup">+</span>F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
   <span class="sup">–</span> in chlorobenzene in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>, 2DES is able to resolve the features corresponding to the PBTTT positive polaron as peak B despite its weak transition dipole strength. In addition to the diagonal peaks, 2DES spectra also display clear off-diagonal features. The off-diagonal peaks D and E demonstrate the existence of a noticeable electronic coupling between the transitions corresponding to B and C. Thus, these off-diagonal features are direct evidence of the electronic interaction between the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion and the PBTTT cation. The other set of off-diagonal peaks F and I manifests vibronic coupling between the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion's transitions corresponding to A and C. The absence of any signal at the position F is probably caused by the additional overlapping excited-state absorption features. It is important to realize that the diagonal and off-diagonal peaks are clearly resolved in the 2D spectra even at room temperature. The specific shape of the 2D spectrum with well defined off diagonal couplings shows a small inhomogeneity of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ within the environment of the polymer as a host. The small inhomogeneity of the underlying transition is a direct reflection of the exceptionally homogeneous intermolecular interactions of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion through the polymer backbone. Thus, the 2DES spectra clearly resolve the electronic coupling between the polymer cation and the dopant anion within the ion-pair, which are homogeneously interacting in the solution.
  </p>
  <div id="fig2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Experimental 2D electronic spectra (real part) of the PBTTT
     <span class="sup">+</span>F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
     <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair in chlorobenzene at the selected evolution times. (a) Red and blue peaks represent the photo-induced increase and decrease of the transmission due to the ground-state bleach and the excited-state absorption, respectively. The diagonal and off-diagonal peaks are clearly resolved even at room temperature. They are labeled in the spectrum for 
     <span class="italic">T</span> = 50 fs by capital letters (A, B, C) and (D, E, F, I), respectively. The 2D spectra for early time points show a rich structure and they decay rapidly within the initial 
     <span class="italic">T</span> = 100 fs, which manifests the decay of the electronic wave packet from the excited state surface back to the ground state 
     <span class="italic">via</span> the conical intersection. The spectra are normalized to the maximum of the F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion bleach signal. (b) Signature of electronic coherence in 2D correlation map. The off-diagonal peaks at (12 250, 13 000) and (13 000, 12 250) cm
     <span class="sup">–1</span> demonstrate the presence of electronic coherence in the excitonically coupled electronic states of the PBTTT
     <span class="sup">+</span>F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
     <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair in chlorobenzene. (c) Ultrafast decay dynamics and frequency analysis. The red curves show the decay kinetics of the selected peaks (B–E) which correspond to the different location in the 2D electronic spectra shown in (a). All the kinetic traces have been fitted to a bi-exponential function shown as black traces.
    </div>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="c8sc00758f-f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dynamics of the different states can be observed by the time evolution of the 2D electronic spectra, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>. At 
   <span class="italic">T</span> = 40 fs, the diagonal peaks (B and C) and the off-diagonal peaks (D and E) are clearly evident with strong intensities. Additionally, negative features corresponding to excited-state absorption can also be seen in different frequency regions, which overlap with the strong off-diagonal features. With the time evolution, we observe an increase in the magnitude of the off-diagonal peak I as shown in the 2DES spectrum for 
   <span class="italic">T</span> = 50 fs in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>. It clearly signifies the vibronic coupling between the A and C transitions of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. From the waiting time 
   <span class="italic">T</span> = 100 fs, we can observe a rapid decrease in the magnitude of the different spectral features constituting the 2D maps. In fact, the 2D map at 
   <span class="italic">T</span> = 500 fs shows only one diagonal peak C corresponding to the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion with an extremely small magnitude. Verlet and co-workers have shown that the lower energy excited state in this F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion relaxes within 200 fs 
   <span class="italic">via</span> a conical intersection.
   <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a> Based on this, we can conclude here that in the PBTTT
   <span class="sup">+</span>F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
   <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair, the electronic wave packet on the excited state surface of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion undergoes a fast decay back to the ground state 
   <span class="italic">via</span> the conical intersection.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To gain further insight into the electronic interaction amongst the ions, we performed a 2D correlation analysis of the residuals obtained by subtracting the underlying global kinetics from the real part of the measured 2D spectra (see the ESI
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> for the details of the analysis). The 2D correlation map so obtained is shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(b)</a>. It clearly shows two symmetric off-diagonal peaks at (12 250, 13 000) and (13 000, 12 250) cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>, which perfectly complements the electronic energy gap of the transitions in the PBTTT
   <span class="sup">+</span>F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
   <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair. Earlier reports from different groups have demonstrated that the existence of positive correlations in this 2D correlation analysis is a unique signature of electronic coherence.
   <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a>,
   <a rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit30">30</a> Based on this phase correlation, we confirm the presence of electronic coherence in coupled PBTTT
   <span class="sup">+</span>F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
   <span class="sup">–</span> in solution. However, we do not observe any evidence of long-lived electronic coherence or that coherence would be prolonged by the vibronic coupling. This is possibly due to the presence of fast decay channels for the excited state wave packet to relax back to the ground state. Secondly, we can quantify the static disorder of 350 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>, which the polaron experiences (see ESI
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> for details). This inhomogeneous broadening gives a relative measure of the coupling of the electronic transitions to the bath. Based on this degree of coupling and resulting site distribution, we can attribute the fast decoherence due to this relative strong interaction with the bath. In addition, the off-diagonal blue peaks manifest the vibronic coupling of 0–1 transitions to the higher ones for the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, the kinetics of the decay of the photoexcited ions can also be modulated by the presence of interacting counter-ions, such that the dynamics will reflect the perturbed electronic structure of the constituent ions. To quantify the deactivation dynamics of the dopant F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion within the ion-pair in chlorobenzene, we have carried out a detailed analysis of the kinetics of selected diagonal and off-diagonal peaks. The results are shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(c)</a>. Each kinetic trace has been fitted with two exponential decay functions and the retrieved time-constants are mentioned in the respective kinetic curves. All the traces clearly show one fast decay component with a time constant of &lt;40 fs along with the other longer decay time component of ∼500 fs. It is important to point out that Verlet and co-workers have reported a decay time constant of ∼200 fs for the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion in the gas phase.
   <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a> Although there has been no report on excited state lifetimes of the D
   <sub>1</sub> state in solution for the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion, transient absorption measurements of the TCNQ anion have revealed an increased decay time constant of ∼2 ps (alongwith a minor component of ∼20 ps) for the D
   <sub>1</sub> state in the solution phase as compared to 650 fs in the gas phase
   <a rid="cit23" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit23">23</a> In our study, we observe a bi-exponential decay with an ultrafast decay with a time constant of ∼30 fs for the D
   <sub>1</sub> state of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion within the ion-pair. This ultrafast decay component hints towards new possible relaxation pathway(s) for the excited state of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion in the solution mixture. In addition, peak B which corresponds to the polymer polaron, also shows an ultrafast decay time constant of 40 fs along with a slower component of ∼0.5 ps. Thus, the presence of a strong electronic interaction between ion-pairs greatly modulates the decay dynamics of the constituting ions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical modeling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand the experimental data on the quantitative level, we have modeled the optical absorption and 2D electronic spectra of the PBTTT
   <span class="sup">+</span>F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
   <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair. In order to calculate these spectra, we have constructed a model which is shown as the unperturbed energy diagram in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(a)</a>. For simplification, we assume that the vibrational mode of 1500 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span> corresponding to C
   <div name="DOUBLE BOND, LENGTH AS M-DASH" description="double bond, length as m-dash" class="private-char">
    <span id="z.dbdm7H0J" format="PBM" resolution="300" x-size="34" y-size="34" xml:space="preserve" class="glyph-data">
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
	</span>
   </div>C stretching in the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion is harmonic. As discussed earlier, Franck–Condon displacements along this mode cause pronounced vibronic signatures in the absorption spectrum. The vibronic coupling strength (given by the Huang–Rhys factor, 
   <span class="italic">S</span> = 0.5) was estimated from the absorption spectrum of the TCNQ anion reported earlier.
   <a rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit31">31</a> To include the contribution of the observed positive polaron peak B marked in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>, we have added one electronic state with the site energy of 12 250 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span> in our model, which is assumed to describe the P
   <sub>2</sub> state of the PBTTT cation. In order to attain the small magnitude of peak B as observed in the absorption and the 2D spectra, a large static disorder (
   <span class="italic">Δ</span> = 350 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>) is included for the polymer chain of PBTTT. The bold arrow labeled as ‘CI’ in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(a)</a> indicates the deactivation pathway of the electronic wave packet from the excited state back to the ground state 
   <span class="italic">via</span> the conical intersection. We model this deactivation dynamics in terms of a Lindblad master equation with appropriate decay rates. To calculate the absorption and 2D electronic spectra, we assume that cation and anion of the ion-pair interact due to the parallel π-stacking, which was earlier proposed by Chabinyc and co-workers for PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in films.
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> It is important to mention here that Sirringhaus and co-workers have proposed a different orientation of the dopant in doped-polymer matrix obtained by solid-state diffusion method.
   <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a> For solution processed films, π-stacking is the dominant interaction mechanism as shown by Chabinyc and co-workers using a combination of solid-state NMR and synchrotron X-ray scattering.
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> To account for the dipolar environment, the system-bath model has been developed which include the dipole–dipole interactions between ion-pair and solvent. Further details on the model can be found in the ESI.
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>
  </p>
  <div id="fig3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Theoretical model used for calculating the 2DES spectra. (a) The energy diagram of the proposed model. The vibrational dynamics of F
     <sub>4</sub>TCNQ is described by a harmonic oscillator. The polaron formation is modeled by one electronic state which is strongly coupled to the lattice vibrations. (b) Simulated 2D electronic spectra for different waiting times. (c) Comparison of the experimental and the simulated decay dynamics. (d) Proposed molecular configuration of the ion-pair with an intermolecular distance of ∼4.5 Å. For the modeling, cation and anion of ion-pair interact vai π-stacking interaction as proposed by Chabinyc and co-workers.
     <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> To treat the dipolar environment properly, the solvent has been modeled as a thermal bath of harmonic oscillators and the dipole–dipole interaction between the ion-pair and solvent has been included in the system-bath interaction.
    </div>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="c8sc00758f-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the model, we have calculated the absorption spectrum shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(c)</a> (blue circles). We observe that the positions for all peaks agree with the experimental absorption spectrum. Moreover, we further examine the validity of the model by calculating 2D electronic spectra and comparing them to the experimental data. The calculated 2D electronic spectra for different waiting times are shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(b)</a>. The obtained 2D maps clearly reproduce the experimentally observed diagonal and off-diagonal features along with the population kinetics for the excited states. For comparison, we have examined the decay traces at different points of the calculated 2D spectra and compared them with experimental decays, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(c)</a>. The calculated kinetic traces show a fast decay component with a time constant of ∼50 fs, together with an additional slow decay component as also observed in the experimental kinetic traces. This further confirms the validity of our model of the ion-pair. Based on these simulations, we successfully retrieve a strong electronic coupling of ∼250 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span> amongst the ions of the ion-pair. It is worth mentioning that in spite of a strong electronic coupling, we do not observe any evidence of long-lived electronic coherence in our simulations (details are discussed in Section V of the ESI and in Fig. S3
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>).
   <a rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit32">32</a> Using the results of our calculations, we can easily retrieve the distance between the cation and the anion of the ion-pair in the precursor solution obtained by quantum chemistry calculations. The intermolecular distance in the ion-pair is calculated to be ∼4.5 Å, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(d)</a> (details of the structure and calculations are provided in the ESI
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for the molecular doping process</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular doping in organic semiconductors is achieved by three principle methods: (1) solution processing, where the dopant is co-deposited with the polymer from the solution; (2) solution sequential processing, where the dopant is spin-casted on top of a pre-deposited polymer film; and, (3) solid-state diffusion, where the dopant is evaporated on top of a pre-deposited polymer film by spin coating. Ion-pair formation is attained at different stages in these methods. In the solution processing method, the ion-pair can be observed in the precursor solution itself whereas in the other methods, it is attained after diffusion of the dopant inside the pre-ordered polymer lamellar microstructure. Our study reveals that the distance between the constituent ions in the precursor solution is ∼4.5 Å which is close to the values of ∼4.0 Å observed in solid-state NMR measurements for solution processed films.
   <a rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit21">21</a> We can infer that the dopant interaction with the polymer is essentially not modified during the evolution of the doped-polymer film microstructure from the precursor solution. Thus, our measurements provide direct evidence of a strong electronic coupling amongst the ions of the ion-pair in the p-doped organic semiconductor in solution. This strong electronic coupling is a manifestation of coulombic interaction that renders the charge carriers on the polymer matrix to be bound. Thus, the strong electronic coupling between dopant and polymer contributes to the origin of poor doping efficiency, which, in turn, necessitates the use of higher dopant concentration to achieve a substantial free carrier concentration. But at higher doping ratios, the Fermi level is shown to be pinned by tailing states in the transport gap which leads to the saturation effects.
   <a rid="cit33" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit33">33</a> Our results emphasize that in order to obtain a high doping efficiency by a desired dopant:polymer interaction for solution processed films, control lies at the stage of the precursor solution. Thus, it will be important to formulate a quantitative model of the structure–function relationship, which takes the inter-ionic interactions into account in order to predict charge mobilities in doped organic semiconductors. To better formulate this structure–function relationship, we will extend our studies to additional polymer-dopant systems in future. Definite tests of this concept will involve specific comparisons of doping efficiencies correlated to experimentally determined electronic couplings as a quantitative measure of the inter-ionic interactions.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
