<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical modeling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand the experimental data on the quantitative level, we have modeled the optical absorption and 2D electronic spectra of the PBTTT
  <span class="sup">+</span>F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
  <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair. In order to calculate these spectra, we have constructed a model which is shown as the unperturbed energy diagram in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(a)</a>. For simplification, we assume that the vibrational mode of 1500 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> corresponding to C
  <div name="DOUBLE BOND, LENGTH AS M-DASH" description="double bond, length as m-dash" class="private-char">
   <span id="z.dbdm7H0J" format="PBM" resolution="300" x-size="34" y-size="34" xml:space="preserve" class="glyph-data">
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
	</span>
  </div>C stretching in the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion is harmonic. As discussed earlier, Franck–Condon displacements along this mode cause pronounced vibronic signatures in the absorption spectrum. The vibronic coupling strength (given by the Huang–Rhys factor, 
  <span class="italic">S</span> = 0.5) was estimated from the absorption spectrum of the TCNQ anion reported earlier.
  <a rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit31">31</a> To include the contribution of the observed positive polaron peak B marked in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>, we have added one electronic state with the site energy of 12 250 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> in our model, which is assumed to describe the P
  <sub>2</sub> state of the PBTTT cation. In order to attain the small magnitude of peak B as observed in the absorption and the 2D spectra, a large static disorder (
  <span class="italic">Δ</span> = 350 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>) is included for the polymer chain of PBTTT. The bold arrow labeled as ‘CI’ in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(a)</a> indicates the deactivation pathway of the electronic wave packet from the excited state back to the ground state 
  <span class="italic">via</span> the conical intersection. We model this deactivation dynamics in terms of a Lindblad master equation with appropriate decay rates. To calculate the absorption and 2D electronic spectra, we assume that cation and anion of the ion-pair interact due to the parallel π-stacking, which was earlier proposed by Chabinyc and co-workers for PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in films.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> It is important to mention here that Sirringhaus and co-workers have proposed a different orientation of the dopant in doped-polymer matrix obtained by solid-state diffusion method.
  <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a> For solution processed films, π-stacking is the dominant interaction mechanism as shown by Chabinyc and co-workers using a combination of solid-state NMR and synchrotron X-ray scattering.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> To account for the dipolar environment, the system-bath model has been developed which include the dipole–dipole interactions between ion-pair and solvent. Further details on the model can be found in the ESI.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Theoretical model used for calculating the 2DES spectra. (a) The energy diagram of the proposed model. The vibrational dynamics of F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ is described by a harmonic oscillator. The polaron formation is modeled by one electronic state which is strongly coupled to the lattice vibrations. (b) Simulated 2D electronic spectra for different waiting times. (c) Comparison of the experimental and the simulated decay dynamics. (d) Proposed molecular configuration of the ion-pair with an intermolecular distance of ∼4.5 Å. For the modeling, cation and anion of ion-pair interact vai π-stacking interaction as proposed by Chabinyc and co-workers.
    <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> To treat the dipolar environment properly, the solvent has been modeled as a thermal bath of harmonic oscillators and the dipole–dipole interaction between the ion-pair and solvent has been included in the system-bath interaction.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c8sc00758f-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the model, we have calculated the absorption spectrum shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(c)</a> (blue circles). We observe that the positions for all peaks agree with the experimental absorption spectrum. Moreover, we further examine the validity of the model by calculating 2D electronic spectra and comparing them to the experimental data. The calculated 2D electronic spectra for different waiting times are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(b)</a>. The obtained 2D maps clearly reproduce the experimentally observed diagonal and off-diagonal features along with the population kinetics for the excited states. For comparison, we have examined the decay traces at different points of the calculated 2D spectra and compared them with experimental decays, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(c)</a>. The calculated kinetic traces show a fast decay component with a time constant of ∼50 fs, together with an additional slow decay component as also observed in the experimental kinetic traces. This further confirms the validity of our model of the ion-pair. Based on these simulations, we successfully retrieve a strong electronic coupling of ∼250 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> amongst the ions of the ion-pair. It is worth mentioning that in spite of a strong electronic coupling, we do not observe any evidence of long-lived electronic coherence in our simulations (details are discussed in Section V of the ESI and in Fig. S3
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>).
  <a rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit32">32</a> Using the results of our calculations, we can easily retrieve the distance between the cation and the anion of the ion-pair in the precursor solution obtained by quantum chemistry calculations. The intermolecular distance in the ion-pair is calculated to be ∼4.5 Å, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(d)</a> (details of the structure and calculations are provided in the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
