<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample preparation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chlorobenzene solvent and F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. Polymer PBTTT with 
   <span class="italic">M</span>
   <sub>w</sub> of 40 000–80 000 was purchased from Lumtec, Taiwan. All the materials and solvent were used as received. Blend of PBTTT and F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ was prepared using earlier reported protocol
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> with slight modification. Firstly, 10 mg ml
   <span class="sup">–1</span> of orange-red colored solution of F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ was prepared in chlorobenzene. Since the high concentration solution of F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ precipitates at room temperature, we heated the solution to 150 °C for 30 min and then kept at 110 °C. The red color solution of PBTTT in chlorobenzene was prepared using the same temperature conditions by adding 10 mg of PBTTT in 1 ml of chlorobenzene. On addition of the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ solution and PBTTT solution at 110 °C, the color of the solution changes to wine red indicating the formation of ion-pairs in chlorobenzene which was further confirmed by absorption measurements.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2D electronic measurements and experimental conditions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Details of the experimental setup have already been described in earlier reports from our group.
   <a rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit32">32</a> Briefly, an all-reflective 2D spectrometer based on a diffractive optic (Holoeye) with a phase stability of 
   <span class="italic">λ</span>/160 has been used for these measurements.
   <a rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit34">34</a> ∼16 fs pulses for the 2D electronic measurements have been generated by compressing the laser beam from a home-built nonlinear optical parametric amplifier (NOPA) to the Fourier transform limit using the combination of a prism pair and a deformable mirror (OKO Technologies). The NOPA is pumped by a commercial femtosecond laser Pharos from Light Conversion. The temporal profile of the compressed beam was characterized by frequency-resolved optical grating (FROG) measurements and the obtained FROG traces were analyzed using a commercial program FROG3 (Femtosecond Technologies). A broadband spectrum so obtained carried a linewidth of ∼100 nm (FWHM) and was centered at 13 000 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span> which covered the polaron peak, P
   <sub>2</sub> of PBTTT at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>) as well as the second vibronic feature at 769 nm (∼13 000 cm
   <span class="sup">–1</span>) corresponding to the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. An additional component is the Sciencetech spectrometer model 9055 which is coupled to CCD linear array camera (Entwicklungsburo Stresing). The 2D spectra for each waiting time 
   <span class="italic">T</span> were collected by scanning the delay time 
   <span class="italic">τ</span> = 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>1</sub> – 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>2</sub> in the range of [–128 fs, 128 fs] with a delay step of 1 fs. At each delay step, 200 spectra were averaged to reduce the noise ratio. The waiting time 
   <span class="italic">T</span> = 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>3</sub> – 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>2</sub> was linearly scanned in the range of 1 ps with steps of 5 fs. The energy of the excitation pulse is attenuated to 10 nJ with 1 kHz repetition rates for all the measurements. Three pulses are focused on the sample with the spot size of ∼80 μm and the photon echo signal is generated at the phase-matching direction. A fresh sample solution was prepared for each time-resolved measurement. The sample was filtered using a 0.2 μm filter to minimize light scattering, and then sealed in a 1 mm quartz cell (Starna). To avoid the possibility of sample degradation, the cell in the 2D setup was placed on a precise 2D translator and moved at a speed of ∼20 cm s
   <span class="sup">–1</span> in both directions. Absorption spectrum of the sample was measured before and after the measurements using a Shimadzu spectrometer (UV-2600), and no noticeable change was observed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2D spectra have been retrieved from the measured photon-echo (PE) signals using the earlier reported procedure.
   <a rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit26">26</a> Briefly, the PE-traces were extracted from the heterodyne signals and transformed along the delay axis 
   <span class="italic">τ</span> using numerical Fourier transforms which provides frequency axis, 
   <span class="italic">ω</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">τ</span>
   </sub>. The observation axis of the spectra corresponding to spectrometer's wavelength scale, were interpolated to the equally-spaced frequencies 
   <span class="italic">ω</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">τ</span>
   </sub>. Using the “invariant theorem”,
   <a rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit26">26</a> phasing of the obtained 2D spectra was performed which provide the correct delay of the local oscillator (LO)-filter used. Phasing of the PE heterodyne signal was performed based on the PP signal at the particular waiting time. The stability of the 2D measurements has been examined by the LO delay.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical calculations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The charge-neutral molecular systems, PBTTT and F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ are initially optimized by semi-empirical methods and the obtained structures are further optimized by density functional theory. The subsequent molecular structures of the PBTTT cation and the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion are obtained by using CAM-B3LYP with the diffuse basis of cc-pvdz. The associated optical transitions are calculated and the transition dipole moments of the PBTTT cation and the F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion are obtained with the magnitude of 3.3 and 6.5 Debye, respectively. The optimized molecular structures are shown in the ESI as Fig. S2.
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> To further quantify the experimental results, we assume that cation and anion of the ion-pair interact in the parallel π-stacking orientation, which was earlier proposed by Chabinyc and co-workers for PBTTT/F
   <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in films.
   <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> We have calculated the absorption and the 2D electronic spectra using a model shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(a)</a>. The first-order correlation function of the transition dipole is calculated by the time non-local (TNL) master equation.
   <a rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit35">35</a>,
   <a rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit36">36</a> In our system-bath model, dipolar solvent has been modeled as a thermal bath of harmonic oscillators and the dipole–dipole interaction between ion-pair and solvent has been taken into account as the system-bath interaction. In order to calculate the 2D spectra, time-dependent master equations are calculated using TNL method and the photon-echo signal is obtained by selecting the phase-matching direction.
   <a rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit37">37</a> Complete details of the calculations are given in the ESI.
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
