<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy (2DES) measurements</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2DES is a powerful nonlinear optical spectroscopic technique which provides a correlation between the excitation (
  <span class="italic">ω</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">τ</span>
  </sub>) and the probing wavelength (
  <span class="italic">ω</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">τ</span>
  </sub>) presenting connectivity in different electronic transitions to reveal the electronic coupling between corresponding chromophores.
  <a rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit25">25</a>–
  <a rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit27">27</a> This method also provides a direct means to separate inhomogeneous broadening effects from the 2D lineshape to enable a determination of the underlying distribution of nuclear configurations giving rise to the inhomogeneous lineshape. To unveil the interplay of the different electronic transitions and their couplings in PBTTT
  <span class="sup">+</span>F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
  <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair, we have carried out 2DES measurements at room temperature for different waiting times. The details of the experimental set up and the measurement conditions are described in the Methods section. PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in chlorobenzene is excited by an ultrashort laser pulse with the pulse width of 16 fs and the associated spectrum is shown as the blue curve in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(c)</a>. In order to avoid the interference with the 0–0 transition of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion, the frequency window of the laser spectrum has been judiciously chosen to cover two specific transitions corresponding to the polaron peak of PBTTT at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>) and the second vibronic feature at 769 nm (∼13 000 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>) of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. Measured 2D spectra (real part) for selected waiting times are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>. Interestingly, the measured 2D spectra for different waiting times show several diagonal and off-diagonal features, which represent the underlying optical transitions and the coupling between them. To identify the individual features, we have marked the diagonal and off-diagonal peaks in the 2DES spectrum for 
  <span class="italic">T</span> = 50 fs by (A, B, C) and (D, E, F, I), respectively. The diagonal peak A corresponds to the 0–0 transition between the ground and excited state of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. Since this transition is only weakly absorbed within the laser spectrum as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a> (blue filled curve), it does not show an appreciable magnitude in the 2DES spectra. The diagonal peak B at 
  <span class="italic">ω</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">τ</span>
  </sub> = 12 250 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> is a signature of the PBTTT positive polaron.
  <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a>,
  <a rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit28">28</a> Peak C at 
  <span class="italic">ω</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">τ</span>
  </sub> = 13 000 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span> is a strong positive bleach feature and corresponds to the transition to the higher vibrational level of the excited state, D
  <sub>1</sub> of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. It is worth mentioning here that unlike the linear absorption spectrum of PBTTT
  <span class="sup">+</span>F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
  <span class="sup">–</span> in chlorobenzene in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>, 2DES is able to resolve the features corresponding to the PBTTT positive polaron as peak B despite its weak transition dipole strength. In addition to the diagonal peaks, 2DES spectra also display clear off-diagonal features. The off-diagonal peaks D and E demonstrate the existence of a noticeable electronic coupling between the transitions corresponding to B and C. Thus, these off-diagonal features are direct evidence of the electronic interaction between the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion and the PBTTT cation. The other set of off-diagonal peaks F and I manifests vibronic coupling between the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion's transitions corresponding to A and C. The absence of any signal at the position F is probably caused by the additional overlapping excited-state absorption features. It is important to realize that the diagonal and off-diagonal peaks are clearly resolved in the 2D spectra even at room temperature. The specific shape of the 2D spectrum with well defined off diagonal couplings shows a small inhomogeneity of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ within the environment of the polymer as a host. The small inhomogeneity of the underlying transition is a direct reflection of the exceptionally homogeneous intermolecular interactions of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion through the polymer backbone. Thus, the 2DES spectra clearly resolve the electronic coupling between the polymer cation and the dopant anion within the ion-pair, which are homogeneously interacting in the solution.
 </p>
 <div id="fig2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Experimental 2D electronic spectra (real part) of the PBTTT
    <span class="sup">+</span>F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
    <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair in chlorobenzene at the selected evolution times. (a) Red and blue peaks represent the photo-induced increase and decrease of the transmission due to the ground-state bleach and the excited-state absorption, respectively. The diagonal and off-diagonal peaks are clearly resolved even at room temperature. They are labeled in the spectrum for 
    <span class="italic">T</span> = 50 fs by capital letters (A, B, C) and (D, E, F, I), respectively. The 2D spectra for early time points show a rich structure and they decay rapidly within the initial 
    <span class="italic">T</span> = 100 fs, which manifests the decay of the electronic wave packet from the excited state surface back to the ground state 
    <span class="italic">via</span> the conical intersection. The spectra are normalized to the maximum of the F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion bleach signal. (b) Signature of electronic coherence in 2D correlation map. The off-diagonal peaks at (12 250, 13 000) and (13 000, 12 250) cm
    <span class="sup">–1</span> demonstrate the presence of electronic coherence in the excitonically coupled electronic states of the PBTTT
    <span class="sup">+</span>F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
    <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair in chlorobenzene. (c) Ultrafast decay dynamics and frequency analysis. The red curves show the decay kinetics of the selected peaks (B–E) which correspond to the different location in the 2D electronic spectra shown in (a). All the kinetic traces have been fitted to a bi-exponential function shown as black traces.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c8sc00758f-f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dynamics of the different states can be observed by the time evolution of the 2D electronic spectra, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>. At 
  <span class="italic">T</span> = 40 fs, the diagonal peaks (B and C) and the off-diagonal peaks (D and E) are clearly evident with strong intensities. Additionally, negative features corresponding to excited-state absorption can also be seen in different frequency regions, which overlap with the strong off-diagonal features. With the time evolution, we observe an increase in the magnitude of the off-diagonal peak I as shown in the 2DES spectrum for 
  <span class="italic">T</span> = 50 fs in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(a)</a>. It clearly signifies the vibronic coupling between the A and C transitions of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion. From the waiting time 
  <span class="italic">T</span> = 100 fs, we can observe a rapid decrease in the magnitude of the different spectral features constituting the 2D maps. In fact, the 2D map at 
  <span class="italic">T</span> = 500 fs shows only one diagonal peak C corresponding to the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion with an extremely small magnitude. Verlet and co-workers have shown that the lower energy excited state in this F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion relaxes within 200 fs 
  <span class="italic">via</span> a conical intersection.
  <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a> Based on this, we can conclude here that in the PBTTT
  <span class="sup">+</span>F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
  <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair, the electronic wave packet on the excited state surface of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion undergoes a fast decay back to the ground state 
  <span class="italic">via</span> the conical intersection.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To gain further insight into the electronic interaction amongst the ions, we performed a 2D correlation analysis of the residuals obtained by subtracting the underlying global kinetics from the real part of the measured 2D spectra (see the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> for the details of the analysis). The 2D correlation map so obtained is shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(b)</a>. It clearly shows two symmetric off-diagonal peaks at (12 250, 13 000) and (13 000, 12 250) cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>, which perfectly complements the electronic energy gap of the transitions in the PBTTT
  <span class="sup">+</span>F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
  <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair. Earlier reports from different groups have demonstrated that the existence of positive correlations in this 2D correlation analysis is a unique signature of electronic coherence.
  <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a>,
  <a rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit30">30</a> Based on this phase correlation, we confirm the presence of electronic coherence in coupled PBTTT
  <span class="sup">+</span>F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
  <span class="sup">–</span> in solution. However, we do not observe any evidence of long-lived electronic coherence or that coherence would be prolonged by the vibronic coupling. This is possibly due to the presence of fast decay channels for the excited state wave packet to relax back to the ground state. Secondly, we can quantify the static disorder of 350 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>, which the polaron experiences (see ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> for details). This inhomogeneous broadening gives a relative measure of the coupling of the electronic transitions to the bath. Based on this degree of coupling and resulting site distribution, we can attribute the fast decoherence due to this relative strong interaction with the bath. In addition, the off-diagonal blue peaks manifest the vibronic coupling of 0–1 transitions to the higher ones for the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, the kinetics of the decay of the photoexcited ions can also be modulated by the presence of interacting counter-ions, such that the dynamics will reflect the perturbed electronic structure of the constituent ions. To quantify the deactivation dynamics of the dopant F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion within the ion-pair in chlorobenzene, we have carried out a detailed analysis of the kinetics of selected diagonal and off-diagonal peaks. The results are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2(c)</a>. Each kinetic trace has been fitted with two exponential decay functions and the retrieved time-constants are mentioned in the respective kinetic curves. All the traces clearly show one fast decay component with a time constant of &lt;40 fs along with the other longer decay time component of ∼500 fs. It is important to point out that Verlet and co-workers have reported a decay time constant of ∼200 fs for the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion in the gas phase.
  <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a> Although there has been no report on excited state lifetimes of the D
  <sub>1</sub> state in solution for the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion, transient absorption measurements of the TCNQ anion have revealed an increased decay time constant of ∼2 ps (alongwith a minor component of ∼20 ps) for the D
  <sub>1</sub> state in the solution phase as compared to 650 fs in the gas phase
  <a rid="cit23" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit23">23</a> In our study, we observe a bi-exponential decay with an ultrafast decay with a time constant of ∼30 fs for the D
  <sub>1</sub> state of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion within the ion-pair. This ultrafast decay component hints towards new possible relaxation pathway(s) for the excited state of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion in the solution mixture. In addition, peak B which corresponds to the polymer polaron, also shows an ultrafast decay time constant of 40 fs along with a slower component of ∼0.5 ps. Thus, the presence of a strong electronic interaction between ion-pairs greatly modulates the decay dynamics of the constituting ions.
 </p>
</sec>
