<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ: a model system of ion-pair formation in doped organic semiconductors
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent studies of doped PBTTT by F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ have revealed promising values of electrical conductivity from this pair.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a>,
  <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(b)</a> represents the molecular structures of polymer PBTTT and dopant F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ. Polymer PBTTT consists of a thieno [3,2-
  <span class="italic">b</span>] thiophene (TT) core having two fused thiophene rings with 6Ï electrons in each monomeric unit. These TT units are in conjugation with thiophene bridges in the backbone which manifests a broad π–π* absorption in the range of 350 to 640 nm with an evident shoulder at 580 nm as shown in the ESI (Fig. S1
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>).
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> Dopant F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ on the other hand shows a strong dipolar excitation between 350 to 550 nm in chlorobenzene (blue trace in Fig. S1, ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The solution mixture of dopant and polymer in chlorobenzene (dielectric constant = 5.6) has been prepared using the protocol reported by Chabinyc and co-workers (see Methods section for details).
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> Black color solution so obtained has 10 wt% of dopant to polymer (molar ratio = 0.25), which corresponds to ∼4 PBTTT repeat units per F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> This solution exhibits a distinct structural band in the range of 650 to 1000 nm as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a> as brown spheres (also in Fig. S1, ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The measured absorption spectrum of the molecular system shows three peaks at 689 nm, 769 and 869 which are characteristic features of F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion's HOMO to LUMO transition (D
  <sub>0</sub> → D
  <sub>1</sub>).
  <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a> These pronounced vibronic structures in F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion arises from the Franck–Condon displacements along the C
  <div name="DOUBLE BOND, LENGTH AS M-DASH" description="double bond, length as m-dash" class="private-char">
   <span id="z.dbdRxuNV" format="PBM" resolution="300" x-size="34" y-size="34" xml:space="preserve" class="glyph-data">
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 1111111111111111111111111111111111
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
 0000000000000000000000000000000000
	</span>
  </div>C stretching vibrational mode of ∼1500 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>.
  <a rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit31">31</a> The broadening of these vibronic features is caused by the overlapping PBTTT positive polaron features. Molecular dopants are known to interact with the polymer matrix 
  <span class="italic">via</span> two possible fundamental interaction mechanisms, 
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, ion-pair and ground state charge transfer complex formation.
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a> Since the PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ pair shows diagnostic electronic transitions for the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion in the solution mixture, we can conclude that PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ forms an ion-pair in solution. Our conclusion is also supported by the fact that the electron affinity of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ is higher than the ionization energy of the polymer so that one electron can be transferred from the HOMO of the PBTTT polymer to the LUMO of the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1(a)</a>.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> In the absorption profile of PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, the spectral feature for PBTTT cation is rendered invisible due to the overlap with the features stemming from the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a>,
  <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a> The optical transitions associated with the PBTTT cation and the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion are calculated on a constructed model of the ion-pair (details have been mentioned in Theoretical modeling section) by means of density functional theory (DFT) using CAM-B3LYP with the diffuse basis set of cc-pvdz, which revealed the transition dipole moments of the PBTTT and F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ ions' electronic transitions with the magnitude of 3.3 and 6.5 Debye, respectively, in the spectral range of 650 to 950 nm (for details, see the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The feature at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>) corresponds to the P2 electronic transition associated with the PBTTT cation (blue circles in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>). Thus, the optical absorption spectrum of PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in chlorobenzene is a superposition of contributions from F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anions and PBTTT positive polarons which signifies the presence of ion-pair formation in the solution phase. These electronic transitions of PBTTT
  <span class="sup">+</span>F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
  <span class="sup">–</span> in chlorobenzene can be capitalized to explore the intermolecular electronic interactions in the ion-pair.
 </p>
 <div id="fig1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">PBTTT/F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ: a model system for the ion-pair in p-doped organic semiconductors. (a) Unperturbed energy diagram depicting the electronic states of PBTTT and F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, which are involved in the formation of the ion-pair. Electron transfer (ET) from PBTTT to F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ is favored by the sizable energy offset between the ionization energy (IE) of PBTTT (–5.1 eV) and the electron affinity (EA) of F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ (–5.2 eV). The values of the IE and EA of F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ and PBTTT are used from literature report.
    <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> (b) Chemical structures of the polymer PBTTT and the dopant, F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ, used in this study. (c) Experimental (brown spheres) and calculated (blue circles) absorption spectra of the PBTTT
    <span class="sup">+</span>F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ
    <span class="sup">–</span> ion-pair at room temperature. The vibronic features in the experimental absorption spectrum in chlorobenzene are diagnostic for the F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion (D
    <sub>0</sub> → D
    <sub>1</sub>). The blue filled curve represents the laser spectrum used in the two-dimensional electronic spectroscopic measurements which covers the polaron peak, P
    <sub>2</sub> of PBTTT at 815 nm (∼12 250 cm
    <span class="sup">–1</span>) as well as the second vibronic feature at 769 nm (∼13 000 cm
    <span class="sup">–1</span>) corresponding to the F
    <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c8sc00758f-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
