<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for the molecular doping process</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular doping in organic semiconductors is achieved by three principle methods: (1) solution processing, where the dopant is co-deposited with the polymer from the solution; (2) solution sequential processing, where the dopant is spin-casted on top of a pre-deposited polymer film; and, (3) solid-state diffusion, where the dopant is evaporated on top of a pre-deposited polymer film by spin coating. Ion-pair formation is attained at different stages in these methods. In the solution processing method, the ion-pair can be observed in the precursor solution itself whereas in the other methods, it is attained after diffusion of the dopant inside the pre-ordered polymer lamellar microstructure. Our study reveals that the distance between the constituent ions in the precursor solution is ∼4.5 Å which is close to the values of ∼4.0 Å observed in solid-state NMR measurements for solution processed films.
  <a rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit21">21</a> We can infer that the dopant interaction with the polymer is essentially not modified during the evolution of the doped-polymer film microstructure from the precursor solution. Thus, our measurements provide direct evidence of a strong electronic coupling amongst the ions of the ion-pair in the p-doped organic semiconductor in solution. This strong electronic coupling is a manifestation of coulombic interaction that renders the charge carriers on the polymer matrix to be bound. Thus, the strong electronic coupling between dopant and polymer contributes to the origin of poor doping efficiency, which, in turn, necessitates the use of higher dopant concentration to achieve a substantial free carrier concentration. But at higher doping ratios, the Fermi level is shown to be pinned by tailing states in the transport gap which leads to the saturation effects.
  <a rid="cit33" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit33">33</a> Our results emphasize that in order to obtain a high doping efficiency by a desired dopant:polymer interaction for solution processed films, control lies at the stage of the precursor solution. Thus, it will be important to formulate a quantitative model of the structure–function relationship, which takes the inter-ionic interactions into account in order to predict charge mobilities in doped organic semiconductors. To better formulate this structure–function relationship, we will extend our studies to additional polymer-dopant systems in future. Definite tests of this concept will involve specific comparisons of doping efficiencies correlated to experimentally determined electronic couplings as a quantitative measure of the inter-ionic interactions.
 </p>
</sec>
