<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical calculations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The charge-neutral molecular systems, PBTTT and F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ are initially optimized by semi-empirical methods and the obtained structures are further optimized by density functional theory. The subsequent molecular structures of the PBTTT cation and the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion are obtained by using CAM-B3LYP with the diffuse basis of cc-pvdz. The associated optical transitions are calculated and the transition dipole moments of the PBTTT cation and the F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ anion are obtained with the magnitude of 3.3 and 6.5 Debye, respectively. The optimized molecular structures are shown in the ESI as Fig. S2.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> To further quantify the experimental results, we assume that cation and anion of the ion-pair interact in the parallel π-stacking orientation, which was earlier proposed by Chabinyc and co-workers for PBTTT/F
  <sub>4</sub>TCNQ in films.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> We have calculated the absorption and the 2D electronic spectra using a model shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3(a)</a>. The first-order correlation function of the transition dipole is calculated by the time non-local (TNL) master equation.
  <a rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit35">35</a>,
  <a rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit36">36</a> In our system-bath model, dipolar solvent has been modeled as a thermal bath of harmonic oscillators and the dipole–dipole interaction between ion-pair and solvent has been taken into account as the system-bath interaction. In order to calculate the 2D spectra, time-dependent master equations are calculated using TNL method and the photon-echo signal is obtained by selecting the phase-matching direction.
  <a rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit37">37</a> Complete details of the calculations are given in the ESI.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>
 </p>
</sec>
