<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electronic density</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dipole moment calculations presented in the three theoretical models showed closer values between the B3lyp/6-311++G(d,p) and B3lyp/6-31+G(d,p) models. The data generated for all alkaloids using the B3lyp/6-311++G(d,p) model did result in significant differences because of the markedly close values of parameters; differences in the house of 0.2 debye, PILO (7.3 debye), EPI (5.8 debye), EPIIS (5.7 debye), ISOP (5,3 debye), and MAC (4.5 debye) are presented in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s007" href="#pone.0198476.s007">S7 Table</a>. These values also suggest a similar solubility potential.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the electron density in each molecule, it was observed that redder regions are more negative and therefore more polar; this was observed in the imidazolic ring by the N1 atom and in the O = C group of the dihydrofuran ring in all the alkaloids (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0198476.g006" href="#pone.0198476.g006">Fig 6</a>). These regions with higher electronic density also represented sites with a higher probability of chemical interactions, described in molecular docking.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0198476.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0198476.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Electronic density of alkaloids.</div>
   <p>a) epiisopiloturine, b) epiisopilosine, c) isopilosine, d) pilosine, and e) macaubine, using the theoretical model B3lyp/6-311++G(d,p). The colors represent red (negative) and blue (positive).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0198476.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
