<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spectral analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The infrared spectra are shown in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s008" href="#pone.0198476.s008">S8 Table</a>. Similarities can be observed in the vibrational frequencies between the EPI, EPIIS, ISOP, and PILO alkaloids, which demonstrate the isomeric conformations (Figs (a) and (b) in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s010" href="#pone.0198476.s010">S2 Fig</a>. The symmetric carbonyl stretching (C = O) showed a strong peak in the regions of 1785 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>, 1846 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>, 1838 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>, and 1845 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> for EPI, EPIIS, ISOP, and PILO, respectively. A deformation in the dihydrofuran ring represented the second highest intensity, at a frequency between 1075 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> and 1162 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> in all alkaloids. This was followed by C-N stretching and C-H group deformation, which occurred at frequencies between 1404 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> and 1455 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>, respectively, in all alkaloids. The OH group showed a strong peak in the region of 3783 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> to 3830 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>. This peak was absent in MAC, because it does not contain an OH group in its structure (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s008" href="#pone.0198476.s008">S8 Table</a>). The lowest values of the IR frequencies were identified in PILO, which corroborated the results presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0198476.g002" href="#pone.0198476.g002">Fig 2</a> that demonstrated a lower stability for this alkaloid (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s008" href="#pone.0198476.s008">S8 Table</a>). For the IR and Raman parameters, the theoretical model B3lyp/6-31+G(d,p) was highly similar to the B3lyp/6-311++G(d,p), and the B3lyp/Sdd model indicated a more distant wavenumber than these two models (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s011" href="#pone.0198476.s011">S3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s012" href="#pone.0198476.s012">S4</a> Figs).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental IR data for the EPI alkaloid have been previously described [
  <a rid="pone.0198476.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0198476.ref019">19</a>], including C = O stretching in dihydrofuran (1769 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>), C-C stretching in imidazole (1568 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>), symmetric stretching N-C-N in imidazole (1524 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>), and C-C stretching in benzene (1472 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span>), which showed a greater similarity to our theoretical parameters compared with those used by the author, which supported the use of the same theoretical model. This difference might have resulted from the optimization of the chemical structure of EPI used differently in both works.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The theoretical 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR spectra of the EPI, EPIIS, ISOP, PILO, and MAC alkaloids are shown in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s013" href="#pone.0198476.s013">S5 Fig</a>, as well as the chemical shift patterns (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s006" href="#pone.0198476.s006">S6 Table</a>). The 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR spectrum of EPI shows the peaks related to the CH
  <sub>3</sub> and CH
  <sub>2</sub> groups (C2 and C4) at 33–37 ppm and CH (C8) at 85 ppm, where the latter exhibits a hydroxyl group, unlike C4. The C1 and C3 (143–151 ppm) of the imidazole ring were displaced, owing to the resonance of the aromatic ring. In addition, the resonance peaks at 131–134 ppm related to CH bonds (C10, C11, C12, C13, and C14) in benzene were observed to be slightly less displaced than the C1 and C3 of the imidazole aromatic ring. Finally, a downfield shift for C6 in the dihydrofuran ring was observed, which was displaced by the binding to the oxygen atom, whereas the CH
  <sub>2</sub> (C15) directly bound to the CO (carbonyl group) and C7 (CH) were protected by the ring. As the EPI, EPIIS, ISOP and PILO alkaloids exhibit isomerism, similarities were observed in the values of the displacement patterns (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s013" href="#pone.0198476.s013">S5 Fig</a>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0198476.s006" href="#pone.0198476.s006">S6 Table</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental results of 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR of EPI, EPIIS, ISOP, PILO, and MAC presented in previous studies [
  <a rid="pone.0198476.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0198476.ref016">16</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0198476.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0198476.ref019">19</a>] describe patterns of displacement similar to that obtained in our calculations, with peaks of (179, 137, 32, 125–128 ppm) for EPI, (180, 139, 31, 126–129 ppm) for EPIIS, (179, 139, 31, 127–129 ppm) for ISOP, (179, 139, 31, 127–129 ppm) for PILO, and (178, 135, and 33 ppm) for MAC.
 </p>
</sec>
