<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rapid development of medicine as well as increasing numbers of patients suffering from cancer causes a need for new types of biomaterials with advanced properties. Special attention is focused on materials with fluorescent properties which can be applied as powerful diagnostic tools as well as elements of controlled drug delivery and release systems. Some of them can also act as theragnostic agents or as cell-labelling agents. Although numerous fluorescent dyes have already been developed, there is still a lack of biomaterials which are non-cytotoxic, water soluble and characterized by strong photoluminescence and reasonable stability [
  <a rid="B1-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-nanomaterials-09-00274">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-nanomaterials-09-00274">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-nanomaterials-09-00274">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-nanomaterials-09-00274">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the most promising nanomaterials are quantum dots (QD)s which can be prepared from various sources. QDs are nanoparticles of quasi-spherical shape with a size below 10 nm and luminescent properties [
  <a rid="B5-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-nanomaterials-09-00274">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-nanomaterials-09-00274">6</a>]. QDs with metallic or semi-metallic cores can be toxic. In some cases QDs may lose their luminesce properties (photobleaching) or can change from a fluorescent state to a non-fluorescent state temporarily (photoblinking). Therefore, currently scientists are working on carbon-based QDs which can be applied in medicine and pharmacy due to their good biocompability as well as water-dispersity [
  <a rid="B2-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-nanomaterials-09-00274">2</a>,
  <a rid="B5-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-nanomaterials-09-00274">5</a>]. Carbon quantum dots (CQDs), unlike other C-based materials such as carbon nanotubes, graphenes, fullerenes, nanodiamonds and carbon nanohorns, are much simpler and cheaper to produce and do not exhibit cytotoxicity. They can be described as a carbogenic cores with surface functional groups. Usually, they consist of amorphous to a nanocrystalline cores with sp2 carbon. CQDs exhibit polar nature and can be easily modified due to the presence of various functional groups on their surfaces such as hydroxyl, carboxyl, ester, ether or amino. Most importantly, carbon quantum dots can be prepared according to Green Chemistry principles without using toxic reagents [
  <a rid="B7-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-nanomaterials-09-00274">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-nanomaterials-09-00274">8</a>]. As raw materials, almost any kind of bio-waste rich in C atoms can be applied, such as tea leaves, coffee grounds or fruit peels. The replacement of toxic reactants with natural substrates helps to obtain biocompatible CQDs. Thus, they can be described as materials with very high potential in biomedical applications.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon quantum dots are prone to chemical and physical modifications with inorganic, organic polymeric or biological species. What is important, their photoluminescent properties are not only size- and shape-dependent. Edge shapes, surface ligands and defects also play significant roles in determining their final characteristics. Another extra-ordinary feature of CQDs is that their photoluminescence depends on excitation wavelength. Thus, when CQDs are excited by UV to VIS-their emission wavelengths range from the UV to the near-IR region [
  <a rid="B9-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-nanomaterials-09-00274">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-nanomaterials-09-00274">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nanomaterials-09-00274">11</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CQDs can be prepared by two general methods. The first one is called top-down. The second one is named bottom-up. In this method CQDs are obtained as a result of the carbonization process. Top-down methods are harsher as these require high temperatures and pressures [
  <a rid="B12-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nanomaterials-09-00274">12</a>]. As raw materials graphite powder or multi-walled carbon nanotubes can be used. The best-known top-down methods include arc-discharge, laser ablation and electrochemical methods. Nevertheless, the purification and functionalization of CQDs involves complicated and time-consuming steps, which makes them less interesting, both from a scientific and commercial point of view [
  <a rid="B13-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-nanomaterials-09-00274">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the contrary, bottom-up methods are known to be much more eco-friendly as these often use as raw materials small biomolecules such as fructose or glucose rich in carbon atoms. These methods require application of external sources of energy including microwave heating, ultrasounds or conventional heating. For instance, microwave-assisted conditions enable very fast preparation of CQDs using polyhydroxy carbonates and some functionalizing agents in less than 10 min [
  <a rid="B8-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-nanomaterials-09-00274">8</a>]. It is known, that functionalization of the carbon quantum dots enhances their photoluminescence properties which enables the preparation of the nanomaterials with tailored properties. Such functionalization can be achieved by controlling their surface states. One of the most common methods is implementation of the amino groups through passivation reactions. Numerous reports suggest that general mechanism of the passivation using agents involve terminal-NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups filling the surface defects of the CQDs. Another way of quantum yield improvement is doping of the CQDs with nitrogen atoms. Nevertheless, scientists are still facing problems with the preparation of carbon quantum dots which are not only biocompatible and non-cytotoxic but also characterized by good photostability and high quantum yield [
  <a rid="B8-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-nanomaterials-09-00274">8</a>,
  <a rid="B14-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nanomaterials-09-00274">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nanomaterials-09-00274">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-nanomaterials-09-00274">16</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chitosan is a biopolymer obtained from chitin by deacetylation reactions. It contains amino glucose and 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-acetylaminoglucose mers linked by glycosidic bonds. Due to its biocompability, biodegradability as well as its lack of cytotoxicity it is widely applied in medicine and pharmacy as a three-dimensional scaffold in wound dressings or elements of controlled drug delivery and release systems. Since this polymer is not only rich in C atoms but it also contains numerous -OH and-NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups which make it an interesting raw material for CQDs preparation for biomedical applications.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Until now, there have been numerus attempts at modifying CQDs. Nevertheless, simple and controllable functionalization and doping of CQDs are still crucial issues, especially in the field of life sciences, where very good photoluminescence properties must be followed by the lack of cytotoxicity [
  <a rid="B10-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-nanomaterials-09-00274">10</a>,
  <a rid="B14-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nanomaterials-09-00274">14</a>,
  <a rid="B17-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-nanomaterials-09-00274">17</a>]. The application of microwave radiation enables generation of high temperatures in very short periods of time due to the local hot points and high intensity of radiation. Aforementioned heating method enables crosslinking of various polymers monomers due to high local temperatures which may be followed by the carbonization [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>]. Therefore, the use of microwave field leads to the fast obtainment of CQDs which would not be created under conventional heating. However, the efficiency of microwave fields is correlated with the ability of mixture components to absorb this kind of radiation. There are reports of CQDs preparation using monomers containing COOH and NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups. Nevertheless, the application of compounds such as diethylamine or tris(2-aminoethyl)amine may lead to the cytotoxicity of the prepared nanomaterials [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00274">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00274">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00274">21</a>,
  <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00274">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>,
  <a rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-nanomaterials-09-00274">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-nanomaterials-09-00274">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of the following research was to obtain a new kind of chitosan-based carbon quantum dots according to Green Chemistry principles with low cytotoxicity that could be used to prepare biomaterials. Although there are some papers considering application of chitosan as a raw material, none of them reports functionalization using amino acids in the field microwave radiation [
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>]. It this paper, a novel type of CQDs from chitosan was prepared by means of microwave processing. CQDs were simultaneously functionalized by functional groups containing nitrogen applying biocompatible compounds naturally occurring in human body. The obtained nanomaterials were characterized by UV-VIS spectroscopy and spectro-fluorimetry. The spectra confirmed preparation of two kinds of nanomaterials including nanodots and low-molecular fluorescent by-products. Moreover, quantum yield was determined and proved very good photoluminescence properties of the CQDs. Additionally, cytotoxicity of the chitosan CQDs was investigated confirming biocompability of the prepared nanodots.
 </p>
</sec>
