<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. FT-IR Analysis of Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the chemical structure of the prepared CQDs verification, the FT-IR analysis was carried out (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f001">Figure 1</a>). FT-IR spectra present pure chitosan as well as CQD-3, CQD-4, CQD-9 and CQD-10 samples (the CQDs with the highest quantum yield). Pure chitosan spectrum exhibits a band typical for free hydroxyl groups at 3301 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> coming from 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-acetylaminoglucose and amino glucose mers. A band characteristic for aliphatic groups is visible at 2933 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and 2871 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. A band with the maximum at 1662 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> confirms the presence of 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-acetylated units. Moreover, bands typical for free NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups coming from deacetylated units are visible at 1595 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and 1165 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. Finally, a band typical for glycosidic bonds between chitosan mers at 1094 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> as well as a band coming from pyranose ring at 893 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> can be observed. The FT-IR spectra of CQDs-3, CQDs-4, CQDs-8 and CQDs-10 are significantly different from pure chitosan spectrum which confirms polymer transformation into carbon quantum dots. It can be noticed, that bands typical for chitosan chain structure coming from pyranose rings and glycosidic bonds have disappeared. At the same time, some new bands typical for aromatic structures have appeared (CQDs-3- 1516 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 1508 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 1520 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 1508 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively). The bands characteristic for unsubstituted C=C bonds have arisen at CQDs-3- 3009 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 3004 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 3042 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 3009 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively. On the other hand, bands typical for hydroxyl groups are still present (CQDs-3- 3435 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 3443 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 3360 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 3448 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively) and so do bands coming from –CH
  <sub>2</sub>– groups (CQDs-3- 2929 and 2854 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 2942 and 2841 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 2946 and 2845 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 2933 and 2858 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively). An increased intensity of the bands typical for free amino groups can be observed (CQDs-3- 1591 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 1587 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 1616 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 1600 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively) which confirms the 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-doping of the carbon core. The spectra also exhibit bands typical for free carboxyl groups (CQDs-3- 1717 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 1716 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 1713 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 1721 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively) which have arisen as a result of the modifying agents (amino acids) thermal degradation. The presence of aforementioned functional groups of polar nature (NH
  <sub>2</sub>, OH, COOH) is responsible for water-solubility of the carbon quantum dots [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
