<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Spectroscopic Studies on Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon quantum dots mainly feature two absorption bands: a π-π* electron transfer band which appears when double C=C bonds are present in the carbon skeleton and a n-π* electron transfer which arises when C=O groups are present. What is important, intensity of these bands is variable. In the first kind of CQDs the bands are intense and the peaks visibly stand out from the base-line spectrum; in the other case, these bands are almost invisible. Carbon quantum dots have spherical structure and are built up from sheets of carbon atoms combined in the crystalline structure. Absorption properties which are correlated with fluorescence are caused by a disturbance of the graphite crystalline structure as a result the incorporation of N and O atoms. Higher crystalline structure disorder and number of chromophores chemically bonded with carbon core leads to the improvement of absorption properties of the nanoparticles. The disturbance of the crystalline structure leads to the increased possibility of the appearance of the additional absorption bands coming not only from the carbon core but also attached particles modifying CQDs structure [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00274">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00274">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00274">21</a>,
  <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00274">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f002">Figure 2</a> presents UV-VIS spectra of the prepared CQDs as well as permeates obtained during nanomaterials purification from low-molecular-weights side-products. Spectra given in panel (a) refer to carbon nanoparticles prepared from chitosan using lysine as a modifying agent and by applying increasing carbonization times under microwave irradiation. It can be noticed that the shorter carbonization time (5–3 min), the stronger intensity of the absorption band of the generated CQDs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One can notice, that CQDs-1 samples do not feature any clear bands, while in CQD-2 samples an absorption band appears at 271 nm. In the CQD-3 samples, an absorption band is visible at 291 nm. The appearance of the strong absorption band suggests the formation of a chromophore system which emits strong fluorescence as a result of radiation deactivation [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00274">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00274">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00274">21</a>,
  <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00274">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f002">Figure 2</a> shows that all permeates (P1-P3) have different absorption characteristics which confirms the presence of two fractions of products during carbonization process. Moreover, it proves that the obtained CQDs were completely purified. The spectra given in the panel (b) were observed on CQDs obtained during chitosan carbonization in the presence of glutamic acid. These are completely different from those of the previous samples (CQDs1-3). A lowering of the reaction time caused the disappearance of the strong absorption band visible at 263 nm (CQDs-4). In the case of CQDs-5 samples this band has shifted to 277 nm and it has almost completely disappeared in samples CQD-6. Based on the spectra of P4-P6 permeates, it can be concluded that both CQD-4-6 samples as well as P4-P6 permeates had similar chromophore systems in their structure, since their bands had similar shape. Panel (c) presents absorption spectra for CQDs prepared from chitosan functionalized with cysteine—an amino acid containing sulphur and nitrogen atoms. These spectra do not feature strong bands with the exception of the CQD-9 sample which was carbonized for 3 min and which features two clear bands at 259 nm and 302 nm. At the same time, one can notice that the permeate of this sample (P9) exhibited the most pronounced difference in the ability of radiation absorption.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the impact of amino acid functionalization on chitosan CQD properties, CQDs were also modified with casein hydrolysate. The hydrolysate was dried and added to the reaction mixture. Panel (d) shows the absorption bands of the obtained samples and their permeates. It can be noticed that a strong absorption band is present only in the case of CQD-12 samples at 256 nm. On the other hand, permeates P10-P12 exhibited strong absorption bands at 255–258 nm which suggests that conjugated systems of N=N bonds in the low-molecular products were created. The obtained spectra correlate with the data of other researchers, who obtained chitosan-based nanomaterials. Nevertheless, the intensity of absorption bands may be misleading in the case of not fully purified CQDs [
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
