<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot3-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Fluorescence Studies on Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f003" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f003">Figure 3</a> presents fluorescence spectra of the prepared samples. Panel (a) shows fluorescence spectra observed on primary CQDs solutions diluted to 50 mL volume using distilled water. It can be noticed, that an increase in carbonization duration leads to the formation of larger amounts of CQDs, which can be confirmed by the strong fluorescence emission intensity of the CQDs-1 sample. In the all three cases (CQDs1-3) similar radiation emission maxima can be noticed at 440 nm and 478 nm. On this basis, it can be concluded that although the carbonization time has an impact on the number density of CQDs, it does not influence their photoluminescence properties. In the case of samples modified with glutamic acid (panel (b)) it can be observed that their luminescence properties are highly dependent on the carbonization reaction duration. By applying longer synthesis times as well as higher carbonization temperatures, quantum dots with emission maxima shifted to longer wavelengths are obtained. It can be observed, that a decrease in the carbonization duration fluorescence emission maxima shift from 525 nm through 498 nm up to 496 nm. Thus, it can be concluded that CQDs with different luminescent characteristics are obtained. Nanomaterials which emit radiation at an excitation wavelength of 365 nm yield higher emission intensity in the yellow region of the spectrum (CQDs-4). All three samples (CQDs4-6) show similar fluorescence emission intensities. Carbon quantum dots prepared from chitosan modified with cysteine (panel (c)) exhibit a strong correlation of fluorescence emission maxima with the carbonization duration. In the case of samples carbonized for 5 min (CQDs-7) as well as for 3 min (CQDs-9) it can be noticed that the emission maxima have shifted to a higher wavelength of 497 nm. When the duration time is shortened nanomaterials with blue fluorescence are obtained. What is interesting, CQD-8 samples exhibit two emission fluorescence bands in the region of lower wavelengths at 417 nm and 440 nm respectively. The samples prepared from casein hydrolysate (CQDs-10-12) have almost identical fluorescence spectra which do not depend on the carbonization duration. However, they differ in the fluoresce intensity. In the case of the CQDs-10-12 samples three characteristic bands at 440 nm, 491 nm and 500 nm are visible. The obtained fluorescence spectra are typical for carbon quantum dots and correspond to the other researchers results [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>,
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>]. 
 </p>
</sec>
