<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot4-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Quantum Yield, Size and Morphology of Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the determination of the quantum yield of the prepared bionanomaterials, a comparative method was applied with quinine sulphate solutions (0.1 M) in sulphuric acid serving as a reference medium. During measurements standard solutions were prepared as well as samples of different concentrations (0–0.100 A (Absorbance)). The results are given in 
  <a rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-t002" ref-type="table" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-t002">Table 2</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results show that the highest fluorescence quantum yield was noticed in the case of the sample prepared from chitosan and functionalized by lysine (CQDs-3) and carbonized for 3 min in the microwave radiation field. The quantum yield for this sample is 11.5%. Another sample with very good quantum yield (7.4%) was obtained through chitosan carbonization with glutamic acid as a modifying agent (CQDs-4). In this second case a long carbonization time was applied (5 min). The quantum yields are higher than in the case of CQDs prepared by other researchers (4.34%) using chitosan under harsher conditions without any additional modifying agents (300 °C, 2 h) [
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>]. There are reports considering obtainment of chitosan nanomaterials by hydrothermal method (180 °C, 12 h) of better fluorescence properties, however the authors did not perform dialysis process. Thus, it was not confirmed that high fluorescence yield can be assign to CQDs, only high- and low-molecular fluorescent compounds [
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>]. Interestingly, the lowest quantum yields were obtained for carbon quantum dots modified with cysteine as well as with amino acid/peptide mixtures (casein hydrolysate). These results are unexpected, since it was expected that the introduction of a high amount of S and N atoms into the reaction mixture will result in a higher quantum yield due to the introduction of the new chromophore systems containing sulphur atoms. Moreover, the application of various amino acids with different chemical structure did not result in the expected formation of numerous chromophore systems with high fluorescence intensity. This effect is quite surprising, since cyclic and aromatic amino acids such as proline, phenylalanine, tyrosine or tryptophan were used. Overall, it can be concluded that the application of isolated amino acids containing two nitrogen atoms (lysine) gave the best results and lysine can be considered as the best functionalizing agent. The quantum yields can be correlated with the size of the obtained nanoparticles (
  <a rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-t002" ref-type="table" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-t002">Table 2</a>). 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f004" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f004">Figure 4</a> presents results of DLS analysis for the samples with the highest fluorescence quantum yield. It can be noticed that the fluorescence properties are hardly correlated with the nanoparticles size. Carbon dots diameters are corresponding to the carbonization time. It may be assumed, that the longer reaction duration caused more intense degradation of the polymeric chains followed by formation of the smaller particles. The other factor affecting nanoparticles sizes is the type of modifying agent which was applied. The application of simpler functionalizers enabled preparation of smaller particles. It correlates with the results of other researchers, who obtained nanodots of size below 9 nm from chitosan using acetic acid as only additional component [
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>]. It may be assumed, that modifying substances could vary in the ability of microwave radiation absorption thus affecting the mechanism of carbon quantum dots formation. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f005" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f005">Figure 5</a> presences microphotographs of the CQDs with the highest fluorescence quantum yield. It can be noticed that all of the nanoproducts have spherical shape and their size is correlated with DLS results. The morphology as well as size of the chitosan nanomaterials correlates with other researchers data. Therefore, it can be stated that prepared nanomaterials are confirmed to be carbon quantum dots [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>,
  <a rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-nanomaterials-09-00274">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-nanomaterials-09-00274">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f006" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f006">Figure 6</a> presents solutions of chitosan-based quantum dots with different concentrations leading to absorbances of A = 0.02; 0.04; 0.06; 0.08; 0.10 respectively. The samples were kept in darkness. For fluorescence excitation a mercury lamp with an emission maximum of 365 nm was used. The figure shows that the highest fluorescence intensity exhibit CQD-3 and CQD-4 samples.
 </p>
</sec>
