<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot5-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Cytotoxicity Study</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f007" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f007">Figure 7</a> presents the results of the XTT assay. It can be noticed that all evaluated samples were non-cytotoxic, since cell viability was no less than 94% as compared to the control sample–cells cultured at standard conditions as well as the raw chitosan (102%). Such results suggest that although nanomaterials may penetrate cell membranes these do not affect in any significant manner cell cycles such as glycolysis [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>]. It can be noticed that the differences in the cell viability hardly depend on the functionalization agents of the CQDs. The lack of cytotoxicity can be explained by the application of non-toxic raw materials as well as efficient purification from unreacted residues. As reported, carbon-based quantum dots are not toxic to cells, however their functionalization may negatively affect this property [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>]. The application of biocompatible functionalizing agents and the introduction of cells-friendly -NH
  <sub>2</sub> groups resulted in the preparation of nanomaterials suitable for biomedical applications. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f008" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f008">Figure 8</a> presents microphotographs of human dermal fibroblasts after 48 h culture in the presence of these samples. It can be noticed that all cells are flattened and have standard morphology. Cultured fibroblasts are of typical spindle-like shape. No granules in the cytoplasm can be observed. The cells nuclei are flat and oval. Therefore, it can be stated that the presence of carbon quantum dots does not have any negative impact on the cultured cells. Overall, all investigated nanomaterials can be ascribed as being not cytotoxic and biocompatible [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
  <a rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-nanomaterials-09-00274">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-nanomaterials-09-00274">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
