<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. FT-IR Analysis of Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the chemical structure of the prepared CQDs verification, the FT-IR analysis was carried out (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f001">Figure 1</a>). FT-IR spectra present pure chitosan as well as CQD-3, CQD-4, CQD-9 and CQD-10 samples (the CQDs with the highest quantum yield). Pure chitosan spectrum exhibits a band typical for free hydroxyl groups at 3301 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> coming from 
   <span class="italic">N</span>-acetylaminoglucose and amino glucose mers. A band characteristic for aliphatic groups is visible at 2933 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 2871 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. A band with the maximum at 1662 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> confirms the presence of 
   <span class="italic">N</span>-acetylated units. Moreover, bands typical for free NH
   <sub>2</sub> groups coming from deacetylated units are visible at 1595 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 1165 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. Finally, a band typical for glycosidic bonds between chitosan mers at 1094 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> as well as a band coming from pyranose ring at 893 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> can be observed. The FT-IR spectra of CQDs-3, CQDs-4, CQDs-8 and CQDs-10 are significantly different from pure chitosan spectrum which confirms polymer transformation into carbon quantum dots. It can be noticed, that bands typical for chitosan chain structure coming from pyranose rings and glycosidic bonds have disappeared. At the same time, some new bands typical for aromatic structures have appeared (CQDs-3- 1516 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 1508 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 1520 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 1508 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively). The bands characteristic for unsubstituted C=C bonds have arisen at CQDs-3- 3009 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 3004 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 3042 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 3009 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively. On the other hand, bands typical for hydroxyl groups are still present (CQDs-3- 3435 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 3443 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 3360 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 3448 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively) and so do bands coming from –CH
   <sub>2</sub>– groups (CQDs-3- 2929 and 2854 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 2942 and 2841 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 2946 and 2845 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 2933 and 2858 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively). An increased intensity of the bands typical for free amino groups can be observed (CQDs-3- 1591 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 1587 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 1616 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 1600 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively) which confirms the 
   <span class="italic">N</span>-doping of the carbon core. The spectra also exhibit bands typical for free carboxyl groups (CQDs-3- 1717 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-4- 1716 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-8- 1713 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, CQDs-10- 1721 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> respectively) which have arisen as a result of the modifying agents (amino acids) thermal degradation. The presence of aforementioned functional groups of polar nature (NH
   <sub>2</sub>, OH, COOH) is responsible for water-solubility of the carbon quantum dots [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
   <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Spectroscopic Studies on Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon quantum dots mainly feature two absorption bands: a π-π* electron transfer band which appears when double C=C bonds are present in the carbon skeleton and a n-π* electron transfer which arises when C=O groups are present. What is important, intensity of these bands is variable. In the first kind of CQDs the bands are intense and the peaks visibly stand out from the base-line spectrum; in the other case, these bands are almost invisible. Carbon quantum dots have spherical structure and are built up from sheets of carbon atoms combined in the crystalline structure. Absorption properties which are correlated with fluorescence are caused by a disturbance of the graphite crystalline structure as a result the incorporation of N and O atoms. Higher crystalline structure disorder and number of chromophores chemically bonded with carbon core leads to the improvement of absorption properties of the nanoparticles. The disturbance of the crystalline structure leads to the increased possibility of the appearance of the additional absorption bands coming not only from the carbon core but also attached particles modifying CQDs structure [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
   <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00274">19</a>,
   <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00274">20</a>,
   <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00274">21</a>,
   <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00274">22</a>,
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>]. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f002">Figure 2</a> presents UV-VIS spectra of the prepared CQDs as well as permeates obtained during nanomaterials purification from low-molecular-weights side-products. Spectra given in panel (a) refer to carbon nanoparticles prepared from chitosan using lysine as a modifying agent and by applying increasing carbonization times under microwave irradiation. It can be noticed that the shorter carbonization time (5–3 min), the stronger intensity of the absorption band of the generated CQDs.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One can notice, that CQDs-1 samples do not feature any clear bands, while in CQD-2 samples an absorption band appears at 271 nm. In the CQD-3 samples, an absorption band is visible at 291 nm. The appearance of the strong absorption band suggests the formation of a chromophore system which emits strong fluorescence as a result of radiation deactivation [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
   <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00274">19</a>,
   <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00274">20</a>,
   <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00274">21</a>,
   <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00274">22</a>,
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>]. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f002">Figure 2</a> shows that all permeates (P1-P3) have different absorption characteristics which confirms the presence of two fractions of products during carbonization process. Moreover, it proves that the obtained CQDs were completely purified. The spectra given in the panel (b) were observed on CQDs obtained during chitosan carbonization in the presence of glutamic acid. These are completely different from those of the previous samples (CQDs1-3). A lowering of the reaction time caused the disappearance of the strong absorption band visible at 263 nm (CQDs-4). In the case of CQDs-5 samples this band has shifted to 277 nm and it has almost completely disappeared in samples CQD-6. Based on the spectra of P4-P6 permeates, it can be concluded that both CQD-4-6 samples as well as P4-P6 permeates had similar chromophore systems in their structure, since their bands had similar shape. Panel (c) presents absorption spectra for CQDs prepared from chitosan functionalized with cysteine—an amino acid containing sulphur and nitrogen atoms. These spectra do not feature strong bands with the exception of the CQD-9 sample which was carbonized for 3 min and which features two clear bands at 259 nm and 302 nm. At the same time, one can notice that the permeate of this sample (P9) exhibited the most pronounced difference in the ability of radiation absorption.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the impact of amino acid functionalization on chitosan CQD properties, CQDs were also modified with casein hydrolysate. The hydrolysate was dried and added to the reaction mixture. Panel (d) shows the absorption bands of the obtained samples and their permeates. It can be noticed that a strong absorption band is present only in the case of CQD-12 samples at 256 nm. On the other hand, permeates P10-P12 exhibited strong absorption bands at 255–258 nm which suggests that conjugated systems of N=N bonds in the low-molecular products were created. The obtained spectra correlate with the data of other researchers, who obtained chitosan-based nanomaterials. Nevertheless, the intensity of absorption bands may be misleading in the case of not fully purified CQDs [
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Fluorescence Studies on Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f003" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f003">Figure 3</a> presents fluorescence spectra of the prepared samples. Panel (a) shows fluorescence spectra observed on primary CQDs solutions diluted to 50 mL volume using distilled water. It can be noticed, that an increase in carbonization duration leads to the formation of larger amounts of CQDs, which can be confirmed by the strong fluorescence emission intensity of the CQDs-1 sample. In the all three cases (CQDs1-3) similar radiation emission maxima can be noticed at 440 nm and 478 nm. On this basis, it can be concluded that although the carbonization time has an impact on the number density of CQDs, it does not influence their photoluminescence properties. In the case of samples modified with glutamic acid (panel (b)) it can be observed that their luminescence properties are highly dependent on the carbonization reaction duration. By applying longer synthesis times as well as higher carbonization temperatures, quantum dots with emission maxima shifted to longer wavelengths are obtained. It can be observed, that a decrease in the carbonization duration fluorescence emission maxima shift from 525 nm through 498 nm up to 496 nm. Thus, it can be concluded that CQDs with different luminescent characteristics are obtained. Nanomaterials which emit radiation at an excitation wavelength of 365 nm yield higher emission intensity in the yellow region of the spectrum (CQDs-4). All three samples (CQDs4-6) show similar fluorescence emission intensities. Carbon quantum dots prepared from chitosan modified with cysteine (panel (c)) exhibit a strong correlation of fluorescence emission maxima with the carbonization duration. In the case of samples carbonized for 5 min (CQDs-7) as well as for 3 min (CQDs-9) it can be noticed that the emission maxima have shifted to a higher wavelength of 497 nm. When the duration time is shortened nanomaterials with blue fluorescence are obtained. What is interesting, CQD-8 samples exhibit two emission fluorescence bands in the region of lower wavelengths at 417 nm and 440 nm respectively. The samples prepared from casein hydrolysate (CQDs-10-12) have almost identical fluorescence spectra which do not depend on the carbonization duration. However, they differ in the fluoresce intensity. In the case of the CQDs-10-12 samples three characteristic bands at 440 nm, 491 nm and 500 nm are visible. The obtained fluorescence spectra are typical for carbon quantum dots and correspond to the other researchers results [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>,
   <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>]. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot4-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Quantum Yield, Size and Morphology of Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the determination of the quantum yield of the prepared bionanomaterials, a comparative method was applied with quinine sulphate solutions (0.1 M) in sulphuric acid serving as a reference medium. During measurements standard solutions were prepared as well as samples of different concentrations (0–0.100 A (Absorbance)). The results are given in 
   <a rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-t002" ref-type="table" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-t002">Table 2</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results show that the highest fluorescence quantum yield was noticed in the case of the sample prepared from chitosan and functionalized by lysine (CQDs-3) and carbonized for 3 min in the microwave radiation field. The quantum yield for this sample is 11.5%. Another sample with very good quantum yield (7.4%) was obtained through chitosan carbonization with glutamic acid as a modifying agent (CQDs-4). In this second case a long carbonization time was applied (5 min). The quantum yields are higher than in the case of CQDs prepared by other researchers (4.34%) using chitosan under harsher conditions without any additional modifying agents (300 °C, 2 h) [
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>]. There are reports considering obtainment of chitosan nanomaterials by hydrothermal method (180 °C, 12 h) of better fluorescence properties, however the authors did not perform dialysis process. Thus, it was not confirmed that high fluorescence yield can be assign to CQDs, only high- and low-molecular fluorescent compounds [
   <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>]. Interestingly, the lowest quantum yields were obtained for carbon quantum dots modified with cysteine as well as with amino acid/peptide mixtures (casein hydrolysate). These results are unexpected, since it was expected that the introduction of a high amount of S and N atoms into the reaction mixture will result in a higher quantum yield due to the introduction of the new chromophore systems containing sulphur atoms. Moreover, the application of various amino acids with different chemical structure did not result in the expected formation of numerous chromophore systems with high fluorescence intensity. This effect is quite surprising, since cyclic and aromatic amino acids such as proline, phenylalanine, tyrosine or tryptophan were used. Overall, it can be concluded that the application of isolated amino acids containing two nitrogen atoms (lysine) gave the best results and lysine can be considered as the best functionalizing agent. The quantum yields can be correlated with the size of the obtained nanoparticles (
   <a rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-t002" ref-type="table" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-t002">Table 2</a>). 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f004" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f004">Figure 4</a> presents results of DLS analysis for the samples with the highest fluorescence quantum yield. It can be noticed that the fluorescence properties are hardly correlated with the nanoparticles size. Carbon dots diameters are corresponding to the carbonization time. It may be assumed, that the longer reaction duration caused more intense degradation of the polymeric chains followed by formation of the smaller particles. The other factor affecting nanoparticles sizes is the type of modifying agent which was applied. The application of simpler functionalizers enabled preparation of smaller particles. It correlates with the results of other researchers, who obtained nanodots of size below 9 nm from chitosan using acetic acid as only additional component [
   <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>]. It may be assumed, that modifying substances could vary in the ability of microwave radiation absorption thus affecting the mechanism of carbon quantum dots formation. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f005" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f005">Figure 5</a> presences microphotographs of the CQDs with the highest fluorescence quantum yield. It can be noticed that all of the nanoproducts have spherical shape and their size is correlated with DLS results. The morphology as well as size of the chitosan nanomaterials correlates with other researchers data. Therefore, it can be stated that prepared nanomaterials are confirmed to be carbon quantum dots [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00274">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00274">25</a>,
   <a rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-nanomaterials-09-00274">26</a>,
   <a rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-nanomaterials-09-00274">27</a>,
   <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>]. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f006" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f006">Figure 6</a> presents solutions of chitosan-based quantum dots with different concentrations leading to absorbances of A = 0.02; 0.04; 0.06; 0.08; 0.10 respectively. The samples were kept in darkness. For fluorescence excitation a mercury lamp with an emission maximum of 365 nm was used. The figure shows that the highest fluorescence intensity exhibit CQD-3 and CQD-4 samples.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot5-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Cytotoxicity Study</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f007" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f007">Figure 7</a> presents the results of the XTT assay. It can be noticed that all evaluated samples were non-cytotoxic, since cell viability was no less than 94% as compared to the control sample–cells cultured at standard conditions as well as the raw chitosan (102%). Such results suggest that although nanomaterials may penetrate cell membranes these do not affect in any significant manner cell cycles such as glycolysis [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>]. It can be noticed that the differences in the cell viability hardly depend on the functionalization agents of the CQDs. The lack of cytotoxicity can be explained by the application of non-toxic raw materials as well as efficient purification from unreacted residues. As reported, carbon-based quantum dots are not toxic to cells, however their functionalization may negatively affect this property [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>]. The application of biocompatible functionalizing agents and the introduction of cells-friendly -NH
   <sub>2</sub> groups resulted in the preparation of nanomaterials suitable for biomedical applications. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-f008" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-f008">Figure 8</a> presents microphotographs of human dermal fibroblasts after 48 h culture in the presence of these samples. It can be noticed that all cells are flattened and have standard morphology. Cultured fibroblasts are of typical spindle-like shape. No granules in the cytoplasm can be observed. The cells nuclei are flat and oval. Therefore, it can be stated that the presence of carbon quantum dots does not have any negative impact on the cultured cells. Overall, all investigated nanomaterials can be ascribed as being not cytotoxic and biocompatible [
   <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00274">18</a>,
   <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00274">23</a>,
   <a rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-nanomaterials-09-00274">26</a>,
   <a rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-nanomaterials-09-00274">27</a>,
   <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00274" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00274">28</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
