<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Materials</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chitosan was purchased from Vanson, Everett, WA, USA (300,000 g/mol). Sodium hydroxide, lysine, glutamic acid, cysteine, hydrochloric acid were purchased from Sigma Aldrich, Poznań, Poland. Casein hydrolysate was prepared from natural casein as a result of the mineralization reaction with hydrochloric acid under microwave-assisted conditions. XTT (2,3-Bis-(2-Methoxy-4-Nitro-5-Sulfophenyl)-2H-Tetrazolium-5-Carboxanilide) assay, human dermal fibroblasts (HDF), fibroblast growth medium (FGM) were purchased from Sigma Aldrich, Poland. Multi-hole plates were purchased from Nest, Gdańsk, Poland. </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Methods</div>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot1-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1. Chitosan-Based Carbon Quantum Dots Synthesis and Functionalization</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chitosan-based CQDs were prepared in microwave radiation fields using a Prolabo Synthwave 402 reactor according to data given in 
    <a rid="nanomaterials-09-00274-t001" ref-type="table" href="#nanomaterials-09-00274-t001">Table 1</a>. CQDs were simultaneously functionalized by N-doping with amino acids and casein hydrolysate as modifying agents. Briefly, for the CQDs synthesis and modification chitosan (0.25 g), HCl (0.10 mL) and appropriate functionalizing agents were placed into the reaction vessel and subjected to microwave radiation (300 W). 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The post-reaction mixture was diluted with distilled water and treated in an ultrasonic bath for 10 min. Next, the mixture was filtrated on filter paper to remove large particles. Thereafter, the mixture was neutralized to pH = 7 using NaOH solution and filtrated by membrane filters (0.22 µm). In the next step, the obtained CQDs were purified using dialysis tubing (MWCO 500-1000) method to separate nanomaterials from other by-products such as low molecular weight molecules. Dialysis was conducted for 4 days. The solvent was exchanged daily. The prepared solutions were diluted with distilled water and used for the experiments.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot2-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy (FT-IR) Analysis</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All FT-IR analyses were carried out using IR Nicolet 6700 Thermo Scientific spectrometer (USA). For the analysis the samples were evaporated and placed in KBr pellet. The range was between 400 and 4000 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span> with 32 scans and the resolution was 4 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span>.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot3-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.3. Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS) Analysis</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All DLS analyses were performed using Zeta-Sizer Nano.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot4-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.4. Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) Analysis</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All SEM analyses were performed using FEI QUANTA 650 FEG. Microphotographs were taken under the pressure of 50 Pa and HV of 10.00 kV.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot5-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.5. Chitosan-Based Carbon Quantum Dot Spectroscopic Characterization</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the measurements an Aligent 8453 spectrophotometer was used. Spectra of the perpmeates obtained during the dialysis were measured. </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot6-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.6. Chitosan-Based Caron Quantum Dot Spectrofluorimetric Characterization</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fluorescence measurements were performed using an Ocean Optics 2000 spectro-fluorimeter for non-diluted CQD solutions. Measurements were conducted using cuvettes with an optical length of 1 cm with the integration time of 10,000 ms. Fluorescence excitation was performed with an UV light-emitting diode with an emission maximum at 365 nm using distilled water as a blank probe.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot7-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.7. Quantum Yield Determination of Chitosan-Based Carbon Quantum Dots</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The quantum yield of the obtained products was determined according to Equation (1):
    <div id="FD1-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="disp-formula">
     <span class="label">(1)</span>
     <div id="mm1" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">Q</span>
         <span class="mi">s</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">Q</span>
         <span class="mi">r</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mo">(</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="mfrac">
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span class="mi">A</span>
             <span class="mi">r</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span class="mi">A</span>
             <span class="mi">s</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mo">(</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="mfrac">
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span class="mi">E</span>
             <span class="mi">s</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span class="mi">E</span>
             <span class="mi">r</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
        <div class="msup">
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mo">(</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="mfrac">
             <div class="mrow">
              <div class="msub">
               <span class="mi">η</span>
               <span class="mi">s</span>
              </div>
             </div>
             <div class="mrow">
              <div class="msub">
               <span class="mi">η</span>
               <span class="mi">r</span>
              </div>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">)</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mn">2</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">,</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Q</span> = Fluorescence quantum yield; 
    <span class="italic">ŋ</span> = Refractive index of the solvent; 
    <span class="italic">A</span> = Absorbance of the solution; 
    <span class="italic">E</span> = Integrated fluorescence intensity of emitted light; Subscripts ‘
    <span class="italic">r</span>’ and ‘
    <span class="italic">s</span>’ refer to the reference and unknown fluorophore respectively.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fluorescence quantum yield was determined by comparison to quinine sulphate (dissolved in 0.1 M sulphuric acid solution) standard solutions, which exhibited a fluorescence quantum yield of 0.54 at 365 nm.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot8-nanomaterials-09-00274" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.8. Cytotoxicity of the Prepared Chitosan-Based CQDs</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cytotoxicity of the prepared CQDs was investigated by a fast and sensitive XTT assay method. Experiments were carried out using primary cells - human dermal fibroblasts (HDF). XTT test enable determination of the cell viability by enzymatic reactions in which viable cells convert water-soluble XTT salt into a water-soluble, orange formazan product. For the experiments all vessels were sterilized using an autoclave. HDF were cultured in ready to use complete fibroblast growth medium. The medium was changed every two days. Cell culture was performed for 5 days. HDF were cultured at 37 °C, 5% CO
    <sub>2</sub> and 95% humidity. For the CQDs testing 96-hole plates were used. The cell culture with CQDs solutions lasted 48 h. Each experiment was repeated 5 times. The morphology of the cultured cells was investigated using an inverted microscope under 40× magnification.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
