<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec3-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous work on triggered release of active TGF-β, aside from magnetic activation, has focused on the use of carbon nanotubes that are photo-irradiated to activate TGF-β [
  <a rid="B32-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijms-20-03190">32</a>] Carbon nanotubes have the ability to generate heat when exposed to ultra-violet (UV) or NIR light. NIR light has the ability to penetrate human tissues with minimal damage. By conjugating carbon nanotubes to the LAP molecule of the SLC, that group was able to achieve remote activation of latent TGF-β. The main problem with NIR light, however, is that its penetration depth is limited to 1–2 cm. Not only does this greatly limit the physiological range wherein such a technique may be used, it also presents further complications when scaling up from small animal experiments. As such, there is a need for an external trigger capable of targeted activation at deep tissue sites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results reported here were directed towards the development of a non-invasive technique, similar to carbon nanotubes, to control the release of active TGF-β—and, eventually, other bioactive molecules—in order to minimize deleterious off-target effects. Local injection of active TGF-β at specific sites initiates a cascade of positive and negative effects in many cell types, including unwanted cellular proliferation and tumor growth. Thus, by binding its latent form to SPIONs, we gain the ability to noninvasively release the active form at local sites by focusing fields to specific targets, thereby allowing us to better mitigate and control negative effects. The SPIONs couple to the external field, and allow us to alter the energy landscape of the conjugated protein. Because the human body is largely transparent to magnetic fields and the limits of field strength and frequency are well studied, this technique will potentially give us greater control over cell signaling at most target sites in the body. Carbodiimide chemistry was used to attach latent TGF-β through a zero-linked reaction by reacting open carboxyl groups, by hydrolytic conversion to maleic acid on the SPIONs, to the open primary amine containing side groups. These side groups have been sequenced [
  <a rid="B33-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijms-20-03190">33</a>] and are confirmed to have asparagine, glutamine, and arginine. These side chain groups are stabilized into specific tertiary structure/domains and remain an unlikely site for binding, so it is most likely the N-terminus of the protein that is being conjugated. Conjugation to the SPIONs was observed in FTIR-ATR, where the new existing peak of 1650 was observed. 1650 is highly suggestive of covalent carbonyl carbon to a secondary amine.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The magnetic properties of the SPIONS both pre- and post-conjugation were tested in the SQUID magnetometer. Interestingly, the values for saturation magnetization and magnetic diameter were nominally higher for the conjugated particles than they were for the unconjugated particles, however, further studies will be needed to determine the significance of these results. Similarly, both TEM and DLS provided data that seemingly agree with each other: The aggregations that are seen in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03190-f002" href="#ijms-20-03190-f002">Figure 2</a>c in DLS were confirmed in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03190-f003" href="#ijms-20-03190-f003">Figure 3</a>c/d of TEM. This suggests that there is some amount of crosslinking occurring wherein latent TGF-β binds to multiple NHS-active SPIONs. This could have some effects on the stability of the SLC, and may lead to the high background release seen in the control groups of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-03190-f006" href="#ijms-20-03190-f006">Figure 6</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to test the release of active TGF-β, an ELISA specific to the active form of TGF-β with low cross-reactivity to latent TGF-β was used. It was verified that thermal activation of the latent complex occurred at a temperature of 80 °C, however, neither thermal nor magnetic release appeared to have impacted the structure of the active form of TGF-β, as shown in the ELISA results. Given that the temperature of the conjugated magnetic nanoparticle suspension failed to reach the necessary temperature for thermal activation, these results point towards a more direct mechanism of energy transfer than simple heat radiation, perhaps via lattice vibrations.</p>
</sec>
