<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot3-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Particle Characterization</div>
 <sec id="sec4dot3dot1-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.1. Fourier Transmission Infrared Attenuated Total Reflectance Spectroscopy (FTIR-ATR)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Liquid samples were placed upright in a lateral magnetic separator (Dobson Laboratory, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA) until the separated magnetic nanoparticles gathered on the lateral side of each upright Eppendorf pipette tube ( Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). After separation, the supernatants were decanted and the particles were resuspended in phosphate buffered saline (PBS). This wash was repeated three times. Prior to use of FTIR-ATR, the particles were sonicated for 10 min in order to ensure a homogenous suspension. A 10 uL aliquot was taken and dried by heating and placed onto the NICOLET 6700 detector (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). No further preparation was needed, since FTIR-ATR only requires dried-solid samples. A background of air was taken before measurements, and isopropanol was used to clean the detector between samples.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot3dot2-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.2. Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental groups were tested against the control groups, all of which were tested against a diluted (1:10) solution of unhydrolyzed SPIONs (0.5 mg/mL). These were measured using a Brookhaven 90Plus Nano Particle Sizer (Brookhaven Instruments, Holtsville, NY, USA ).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot3dot3-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.3. Transmission Electron Microscopy</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-resolution transmission electron microscopy (HR-TEM) imaging of the particles was performed using a FEI Tecnai F20 transmission electron microscope operated at 200 kV and equipped with a Gatan UltraScan 1000P digital camera (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Specimens for HR-TEM imaging were prepared by drop casting the particles suspended in PBS onto Cu grids with a &lt;2 nm thick C film supported by a thicker, lacy C film (Ted Pella #01824, (Redding, CA, USA), and allowing the grids to dry in air on a warm hotplate. All HR-TEM imaging was performed on particles located on unsupported (&lt;2 nm thick) regions of the C film to minimize the distortion to the images resulting from the presence of the film.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot3dot4-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.4. Superconducting Quantum Interference Device (SQUID) Magnetometry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both experimental and control groups (100 µL of particles in suspension) were collected into PTFE sample holders and placed into the quantum design magnetic property measurement system 3 (superconducting quantum inference device (MPMS-3-SQUID San Diego, CA, USA). Magnetization curves for each group were obtained at room temperature. By fitting the magnetization curve to the Langevin function [
   <a rid="B34-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijms-20-03190">34</a>], it is possible to determine the magnetic diameter as well as the geometric deviation; doing this relies on the assumption that the magnetic domains are spherical, as well as the assumption that said magnetic domains possess a magnetization equivalent to bulk magnetite (86.6 emu/g) [
   <a rid="B35-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijms-20-03190">35</a>]. We also deduced the saturation magnetization by measuring the maximum magnetization on the magnetization curves [
   <a rid="B36-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijms-20-03190">36</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
