<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec4dot1-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Hydrolysis of SPION to Open Conjugation Sites</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to maximize induced heating, SPIONs with high specific absorption rates (SAR) (Sigma Aldrich #900042, St. Louis, MO, USA) were used. According to their material safety data sheets, the components of these particles (aside from their iron oxide content) include maleic anhydride polymer with methoxyethane and water [
   <a rid="B34-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijms-20-03190">34</a>]. The rate of hydrolysis, prior to laboratory use, of the maleic anhydride to maleic acid is unknown. Thus, we subjected the particles to a rigorous washing in effort to maximize the conversion.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The particle stock solution was first diluted to a working concentration of 0.5 mg/mL, mixed with deionized water, and 190 proof ethanol as a mutual solvent, to a final ratio of 1 part particles, 2 parts water, and 7 parts ethano. The resulting mixture was then heated under reflux conditions for a period of 8 h. Verification of hydrolysis was confirmed via on the NICOLET 6700 FTIR-ATR apparatus (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot2-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. Carbodiimide Conjugation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrolyzed SPIONs were diluted to a concentration of 0.5 mg/mL. A total 20 mg of both NHS and EDC were added, and the solution was left to incubate for 1 h before the particles underwent magnetic separation. After magnetic separation, the supernatant was decanted and the particles were washed with deionized water. This wash step was repeated three times before the particles were resuspended in PBS and latent TGF-β (2.5 ng/mL) was added. The solution was left to incubate for 1 h before the particles underwent magnetic separation and were washed three times with a PBS solution, wherein the pH was raised to 9 via dropwise addition of NaOH. The particles were washed with pH 9 PBS three times, after which they were resuspended and stored in pH 7 PBS. These wash steps were found to be necessary in order to properly quench the EDC/NHS reaction without altering any existing functional groups, thereby maintaining the integrity of the protein.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot3-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Particle Characterization</div>
  <sec id="sec4dot3dot1-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.1. Fourier Transmission Infrared Attenuated Total Reflectance Spectroscopy (FTIR-ATR)</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Liquid samples were placed upright in a lateral magnetic separator (Dobson Laboratory, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA) until the separated magnetic nanoparticles gathered on the lateral side of each upright Eppendorf pipette tube ( Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). After separation, the supernatants were decanted and the particles were resuspended in phosphate buffered saline (PBS). This wash was repeated three times. Prior to use of FTIR-ATR, the particles were sonicated for 10 min in order to ensure a homogenous suspension. A 10 uL aliquot was taken and dried by heating and placed onto the NICOLET 6700 detector (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). No further preparation was needed, since FTIR-ATR only requires dried-solid samples. A background of air was taken before measurements, and isopropanol was used to clean the detector between samples.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot3dot2-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.2. Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS)</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental groups were tested against the control groups, all of which were tested against a diluted (1:10) solution of unhydrolyzed SPIONs (0.5 mg/mL). These were measured using a Brookhaven 90Plus Nano Particle Sizer (Brookhaven Instruments, Holtsville, NY, USA ).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot3dot3-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.3. Transmission Electron Microscopy</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-resolution transmission electron microscopy (HR-TEM) imaging of the particles was performed using a FEI Tecnai F20 transmission electron microscope operated at 200 kV and equipped with a Gatan UltraScan 1000P digital camera (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Specimens for HR-TEM imaging were prepared by drop casting the particles suspended in PBS onto Cu grids with a &lt;2 nm thick C film supported by a thicker, lacy C film (Ted Pella #01824, (Redding, CA, USA), and allowing the grids to dry in air on a warm hotplate. All HR-TEM imaging was performed on particles located on unsupported (&lt;2 nm thick) regions of the C film to minimize the distortion to the images resulting from the presence of the film.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot3dot4-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3.4. Superconducting Quantum Interference Device (SQUID) Magnetometry</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both experimental and control groups (100 µL of particles in suspension) were collected into PTFE sample holders and placed into the quantum design magnetic property measurement system 3 (superconducting quantum inference device (MPMS-3-SQUID San Diego, CA, USA). Magnetization curves for each group were obtained at room temperature. By fitting the magnetization curve to the Langevin function [
    <a rid="B34-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijms-20-03190">34</a>], it is possible to determine the magnetic diameter as well as the geometric deviation; doing this relies on the assumption that the magnetic domains are spherical, as well as the assumption that said magnetic domains possess a magnetization equivalent to bulk magnetite (86.6 emu/g) [
    <a rid="B35-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijms-20-03190">35</a>]. We also deduced the saturation magnetization by measuring the maximum magnetization on the magnetization curves [
    <a rid="B36-ijms-20-03190" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijms-20-03190">36</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot4-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4. ELISA of Activated TGF-β</div>
  <sec id="sec4dot4dot1-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4.1. Magnetic Release of Active Transforming Growth Factor-β</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to test the magnetic activation of the latent TGF-β, an enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) specific to active TGF-β was used, following the manufacturer’s procedure (Duoset
    <span class="sup">®</span>, R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA). The results were measured via a UV/Vis spectrophotometer (PERKIN-ELMER LAMBDA 800, (Waltham, MA, USA), with absorbance measured at 450 nm. In order to correct for optical imperfections within the plate, absorbance was measured at 540 and 570 nm and subtracted from the 450 absorbance measurement. From the correlation of optical density to protein concentration, a standard curve was created.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following the conjugation of latent TGF-β to magnetic nanoparticles, magnetic activation by way of magnetic hyperthermia was attempted. First, the particles were magnetically separated and resuspended in PBS. The particles were then split into two groups. The first group was designated for magnetic release. This sub-group would undergo magnetic hyperthermia in a radio frequency alternating magnetic field using an Ambrell Easy Heat (
    <span class="italic">f</span> = 350 kHz/H = 40 kA/m) apparatus (Rochester, NY, USA). The second sub-group was used as a control, wherein the samples were kept at room temperature, away from the presence of an alternating magnetic field. For each group, three samples were tested via ELISA, using the given protocol. A two-tailed, unpaired homoscedastic t-test was performed in order to determine significance.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot4dot2-ijms-20-03190" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4.2. Heat Controls</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It became necessary to verify the integrity of the latent TGF-β, and to test whether or not it was possible to release the active TGF-β from the small latent complex using only heat. To this end, latent TGF-β was split into two groups: an experimental group that would be heated on an AccuBlock Digital Dry Bath (Labnet International, Inc., USA) at 80 °C for 10 min, and a control group kept at room temperature. The resulting release of active TGF-β was then quantified via ELISA.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
