<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The World Health Organization (WHO) labels cancer as one of the most pressing health challenges in the world. Statistical data from the National Cancer Institute (NCI) show that one in two (three) men (women) will develop this disease. Cancer is a leading cause of death, accounting for over 8.8 million casualties and 14.1 million cases diagnosed worldwide in 2015, numbers that are expected to increase in the coming years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. It is characterized by an uncontrolled growth of cells in the body, with the potential to invade or spread to its other parts with the formation of metastases. It is induced by mutations in the genome of a cell population, which changes the normal function of various classes of protein families, such as cytokines, cell surface receptors, signal transducers and transcription factor, making it one of the most difficult and complex disease to treat
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. The more widely the cancer spreads, the harder it becomes to eradicate. In 2013, oncology was ranked on the top therapeutic class by worldwide sales, amounting to $73 billion
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. However, though highly expensive, the treatment suffers several fails due to a defense mechanisms developed by some malignant cells, mainly those related to the activation of drug resistance processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although these mutations provide a selective vantage to populations of cancer cells, they also increase their divergences from the normal one, which can allow the recognition by the immune system cells, such as the T lymphocytes (T cells) and B cells
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Nevertheless, tumors also evolved to deceive immune cells, including the ability to activate co-inhibitory signaling pathways on T cells by immune checkpoint proteins, such as the cytotoxic T-lymphocite protein 4 (CTLA-4) and the programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1), leading to a state of immune tolerance
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The molecular identification of cancer antigens helped the creation of new approaches for effective therapies, giving rise to a new era of treatment in which our own immune system evade the block created by malignant cells and fights against them. Among these new treatments, the immune checkpoint therapy has been clinically validated as an effective treatment for many cancer types
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. The blockade of the ligand-receptor interaction of these immune checkpoint molecules can directly increase the function of the T-cells, whereas it has been shown as a way to release the immune system to unleash anti-tumor immune response
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The receptor PD-1 (
  <span class="italic">Pdcd1</span> gene on chromossome 2) is an immune cell-specific surface inhibitor, mainly expressed in the late effector phase on activated CD4
  <span class="sup">+</span>/CD8
  <span class="sup">+</span> T cells, B cells, monocytes, natural killer T cells, and antigen-presenting cells (APC), including dendritic cells
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. It is a transmembrane glycoprotein of the Ig superfamily, accounting for 288 amino-acids, displaying four domains including a single V-set immunoglobulin superfamily (IgSF) domain, a stalk, a transmembrane domain and a cytoplasmic domain, which contains two tyrosine-based immunoreceptor signaling motifs: the inhibitory motif (ITIM) and the switch one (ITSM)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. Due to its relevance for immune system maintenance, a number of crystallographic structures have been published related to the human extracellular domain of PD-1, in apo form or bound to several ligands, making possible to recognize its overall structural architecture
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. A comparison among them allow us to describe the PD-1 extracellular domain in a canonical IgV-type topology containing a 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-sandwich arrangement formed by front and back 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-strand faces of interacting domains, GFCC’ and ABED 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-sheets, respectively (for a review see ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Together with its ligants PD-L1/PD-L2, the receptor PD1 form a family of immune checkpoint proteins that act as co-inhibitory factors, which can halt or limit the development of the T cell response. Through interactions with them, the protein PD-1 affects negatively the function of the T and B cells by inhibiting their immune check, ensuring that the immune system is activated only at the appropriate time in order to minimize the possibility of chronic autoimmune inflammation, leading to a decrease of the cytokine production and antibody formation. On the other hand, tumor cells exploit this immune-checkpoint pathway as a mechanism to evade detection and inhibit the immune response, preventing the immune system from killing cancer cells. Many types of cells can express PD-L1, including tumor cells and immune cells after exposure to cytokines, while PD-L2 is expressed mainly on dendritic cells in normal tissues, making the PD-1/PD-L1 interaction more suitable to cancer therapies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. Thus, the search for antibodies that block the interaction between the receptor PD-1 and its ligands has been seen as a major therapeutic advancement in oncology, once it shows response often durable without causing serious toxicity effects in most people
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently, a number of cancer immunotherapy agents that target the PD-1 receptor have been developed. Among them, two antibody-based agents targeting PD-1 were approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (US-FDA) and other agencies around the world, namely the nivolumab and pembrolizumab drugs. Pembrolizumab is a humanized monoclonal antibody, belonging to the immunoglobulin IgG4 subclass with potential immune checkpoint inhibitory and antineoplastic activities. Upon administration, it blocks the interaction between the programmed cell death protein PD-1 on T cells with its ligands which results in the activation of T-cell-mediated immune responses against tumor cells
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. It was the first anti-PD-1 agent to be approved by the FDA, being nowadays used to treat some cancer types where cells express PD-L1, including advanced melanoma, advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), recurrent or metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma, classical Hodgkin lymphoma (cHL), and counting, the list being increasing with the release of new clinical trials
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although these antibodies are associated with substantial benefits, the immune checkpoint blockade can lead to inflammatory side-effects. Besides, there is a necessity for new drugs targeting PD-1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Thus, obtain a deep understanding of the human PD-1/therapeutic antibody complex is essential for our knowledge about its inhibition mechanism and the design of improved anti-PD-1 therapeutics. In this sense, it has been shown that patients making use of pembrolizumab has presented better results and fewer side-effects than those using the nivolumab drug, turning the former a suitable candidate to provide new compounds based on its structure.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To push this field forward, we intend here to investigate the pembrolizumab recognition surface on PD-1 under a quantum mechanical-based point of view. Our main goal is the supply of enough information at the binding interface that substantially contribute to the affinity and specificity between the receptor (PD-1) and the therapeutic antibody (pembrolizumab). For this task, we take into account the crystallographic structure of the antigen-binding fragment (Fab) of pembrolizumab in complex with the extracellular domain of human PD-1 (PD-1
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ECD</span>
  </sub>) determined at a resolution of 2.00 Å
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, as depicted in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, with the structural segments of the receptor PD-1 labeled with different letters. Afterwards, it is submitted to a fragmentation scheme based on the molecular fractionation with conjugate caps (MFCC) method
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Our results are the first attempt to outline the pembrolizumab/PD-1 interaction based in quantum mechanics, given an individual residue-residue interaction energy, which could be useful for the development of new pharmaceutical drugs targeting PD-1, and a key tool to avoid the onset of a number of cancerous tumors.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structural representation of the antigen-binding fragment (Fab) of pembrolizumab (PDB ID:5GGS) in complex with the extracellular domain of human PD-1 receptor. Here, HC and LC means heavy-chain and light-chain, respectively.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_20325_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e362" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
