<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Computational Studies on (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(Im
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </span>Pr
  <sub>2</sub>)(CO) (
  <span class="bold">6</span>)
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">N-Heterocyclic carbene ligands are typically viewed as pure σ-donors with minimal π-acceptor properties. There is, however, both experimental and computational evidence suggesting that certain electron-rich metals may engage in back-bonding to the NHC ligand.(
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13" href="#ref13">13</a>) There are also literature reports that suggest that in some cases NHC ligands are capable of π-donation to metals.(
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14" href="#ref14">14</a>) In order to further study the structural dynamic properties of (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(NHC)L systems, we performed a series of quantum chemistry calculations on 
  <span class="bold">6</span>. The aim of this study was to identify the relative contributions arising from electronic and steric effects that determine the specific conformation of the NHC ligand in (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(NHC)L complexes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A full geometry optimization was initially performed on 
  <span class="bold">6</span>, and the resulting optimized structure (
  <span class="bold">6</span>-
  <span class="italic">calc</span>, Figure 
  <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">6</a>) was remarkably similar to the X-ray crystal structure (Figure 
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">4</a>). The geometry-optimized carbene carbon−cobalt bond is 1.902 Å compared to the X-ray crystal structure (1.898 Å). Similarly, the two C−Co−C−N dihedral angles are {−90.164°, 91.177°} and {−86.635°, 89.295°} for the DFT-optimized geometries and the X-ray crystal structures, respectively. Using the geometry-optimized structure, the molecular orbitals for the two interacting fragments (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(CO) and NHC were calculated and analyzed. Figure 
  <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">6</a> shows the principal molecular orbitals involved in the binding interaction between the (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(CO) and NHC ligand in the bound complex structure. The primary interaction is between the NHC HOMO and the (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(CO) LUMO, and, as is well understood, the carbene carbon acts as a strong σ-donor. Analysis of the other molecular orbitals shows no further significant electronic interaction effects. Most notably, the unoccupied molecular orbitals for the NHC ligand are extremely diffuse and are located on the opposite side of the ligand of the (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(CO)-interaction site, confirming that NHC is a poor π-acceptor (
  <a rid="notes-1" href="#notes-1">Figures S1 and S2</a>). Additionally, analysis of the NHC HOMO−1 molecular orbital reveals that the carbene carbon is also a poor π-donor.
 </p>
 <div id="fig6" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Orthogonal views of the molecular orbitals defining the primary electronic interaction between (η
    <span class="sup">5</span>-C
    <sub>5</sub>H
    <sub>5</sub>)Co(CO) and Im
    <span class="sup">
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </span>Pr
    <sub>2</sub> in 
    <span class="bold">6</span>-
    <span class="italic">calc</span>. The positive and negative phases of the Im
    <span class="sup">
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </span>Pr
    <sub>2</sub> HOMO are depicted in green and purple; the phases of the (η
    <span class="sup">5</span>-C
    <sub>5</sub>H
    <sub>5</sub>)Co(CO) LUMO are depicted in yellow and pink. Two contour plots are displayed for each normalized MO, the solid surface is the contour at ±0.1, and the transparent surface is the contour at ±0.05.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="om-2010-00680c_0011" id="gr8" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of the individual molecular orbitals suggests that the specific orientation of the Im
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </span>Pr
  <sub>2</sub> ligand in the complex is determined predominantly, if not solely, by steric effects. In order to substantiate this result, a series of partial geometry optimizations were performed on 
  <span class="bold">6</span>-
  <span class="italic">calc</span> in which the C−Co−C−N dihedral angle was treated as a constraint and systematically varied from −80° to −190° (see 
  <a rid="sec4.2" href="#sec4.2">Methods</a> for more details). The upper panel of Figure 
  <a rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#fig7">7</a> shows the energy of the system as a function of the C−Co−C−N dihedral angle. The energy barrier for rotation of the Co−Im
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </span>Pr
  <sub>2</sub> bond is found to be 13.3 kcal/mol, which is in extremely good agreement with the simulated NMR data result of 13.6 kcal/mol. As the Im
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </span>Pr
  <sub>2</sub> ligand is rotated away from the optimal geometry (at −90.164°), the system exhibits many structural distortions: The carbene carbon−cobalt bond length increases from 1.902 Å to 1.960 Å (as shown in the lower panel of Figure 
  <a rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#fig7">7</a>). The O−C−Co angle distorts away from a near-linear geometry (178.7°) to 170.2° as the CO group tilts away from the rotating Im
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </span>Pr
  <sub>2</sub> ligand. Similarly, steric interaction between the Im
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </span>Pr
  <sub>2</sub> and C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub> ligands causes the C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub> ring to tilt relative to the cobalt atom (see 
  <a rid="notes-1" href="#notes-1">Supporting Information</a> for more details).
 </p>
 <div id="fig7" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Variation of the enthalpy (upper panel) and Co−C(carbene) interatomic distance (lower panel) of 
    <span class="bold">6</span>-
    <span class="italic">calc</span> as a function of the C−Co−C−N dihedral angle.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="om-2010-00680c_0012" id="gr9" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed structural distortions of the complex discussed above provide further evidence that steric effects determine the preferential geometry of the NHC ligand predominantly. This result is confirmed by a second, identical set of QC calculations performed on (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(ImMe
  <sub>2</sub>)(CO), where ImMe
  <sub>2</sub> is the 1,3-dimethylimidazol-2-ylidene ligand (data not shown). The energy barrier to rotation about the Co−ImMe
  <sub>2</sub> bond is found to be only 8.7 kcal/mol, which represents a 35% decrease in the energy barrier to rotation compared to the more bulky Im
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </span>Pr
  <sub>2</sub> ligand. The results of this study suggest that the specific orientation of the NHC ligand in (η
  <span class="sup">5</span>-C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)Co(NHC)CO systems is determined solely by steric interactions. This is obviously also true for extremely bulky NHC ligands, such as the mesityl-substituted NHC ligand in 
  <span class="bold">15</span>. The QC-optimized geometry of this system afforded a C−Co−C−N dihedral angle of 57.3° compared to the X-ray crystal structure (46.4°). This 10° discrepancy between the theoretical and experimental result is the product of an exceedingly shallow potential energy well about the optimal geometry. We consider that this is due to the large inherent flexibility of this particular NHC ligand; however crystal packing effects and possible errors in the treatment of the dispersion forces in the DFT calculations cannot be ruled out.
 </p>
</sec>
