<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Technical Validation</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Validation of geometry consistency</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To validate the consistency of the relaxed B3LYP geometries, we have used them to generate the corresponding InChI
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>
   </span> strings with Corina and Open Babel (Version 2.3.0 2011)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>
   </span>. InChI corresponds to ‘IUPAC International Chemical Identifier’. The resulting strings have been compared to the InChI strings obtained from the initial Cartesian coordinates (generated by Corina using the original GDB-17 SMILES strings). See 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a> for a flow-chart of this consistency check. Out of the 134k molecules, 3,054 molecules did not pass this test. This is due to the fact that SMILES and InChI representations are not unique because transformation of Cartesian coordinates to string based chemical identifiers is prone to implementation specific artifacts. For molecules with same topology, small differences in interatomic distances, bond and dihedral angles can lead to different molecular graphs encoded by the string. To quantify this artifact, the distribution of Coulomb-matrix distances
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">13</a>
   </span>, 
   <span class="italic">D</span>
   <sub>IJ</sub> [Hartree], using the Manhattan or L1 metric, between Corina generated Cartesian coordinates (see 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>) and B3LYP coordinates is on display in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a> for all the 3,054 molecules.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consider, for example, molecule indexed 58 in the 134k set, which is among the 3,054 molecules for which the consistency check failed. Its original GDB-17 SMILES corresponds to NC(=N)C#N, and Cartesian coordinates can be generated using Corina. When feeding back these coordinates to Open Babel to perform the inverse task of reproducing the initial SMILES string, [NH]C(=[NH2])C#N is obtained instead. By contrast, performing first a geometry relaxation of the Corina generated Cartesian coordinates using PM7 followed by B3LYP, and only then parsing through Open Babel, recovers the original SMILES string. In this case, 
   <span class="italic">D</span>
   <sub>IJ</sub> using the Coulomb-matrices of Corina and B3LYP geometries is rather small (~27 Ha) when compared to distances between geometries of other failed molecules, see distance distribution plot in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>. By contrast, failed molecules with large 
   <span class="italic">D</span>
   <sub>IJ</sub> between Corina and B3LYP geometries, see 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>, correspond to molecules for which the B3LYP relaxation induces dramatic distortion with significant alteration and rearrangement of covalent bonding patterns. As a result, parsing back these geometries with Open Babel yields different SMILES strings. Note that all the 6,095 constitutional isomers of C
   <sub>7</sub>H
   <sub>10</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub> for which G4MP2 calculations have been performed, passed this geometry consistency check, shown as a flow-chart in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Validation of quantum chemistry results</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All 134k molecules have been modeled using B3LYP/6-31G(2df,p) based DFT. Previously, B3LYP has been validated for several subsets, containing up to a few hundred small molecules. These benchmarks are of limited use since they are not necessarily sufficiently representative for gauging B3LYP’s performance in general. In the case of DFT’s systematic errors this issue is particularly pertinent
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">22</a>
   </span>. Experimental data assembled in the NIST database is very sparse by comparison to our 134k organic molecules made up of CHONF atoms. Consequently, we have performed additional benchmark calculations for a subset of 100 randomly selected molecules using high level theories G4MP2
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">12</a>
   </span>, G4
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>
   </span>, and CBS-QB3
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The predictive power of the G4MP2 method is widely considered to be on par with experimental uncertainties. For example, comparison to the G3/05 test set
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>
   </span> with 454 experimental energies (including enthalpies of formation, ionization potentials, electron affinities, proton affinities, and hydrogen bond energies) of small molecules yields MAE, and RMSE of 1.0, and 1.5 kcal/mol, respectively
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">12</a>
   </span>. For the same properties and molecules, the slightly more accurate, and considerably more expensive method G4
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">12</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>
   </span> yields errors of MAE=0.8 kcal/mol, RMSE=1.2 kcal/mol. G4MP2 has been shown to deviate only by 1.4 kcal/mol from 261 bond dissociation enthalpies computed with the highly accurate W1w composite procedure
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a>
   </span> for the BDE261 data set
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>
   </span>. Consequently, we believe these calculations to be sufficiently suitable to validate the quality of the B3LYP energetics predictions. Various resulting deviations are summarized in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>. For the 100 molecules, the mean absolute error of B3LYP heats of atomization amounts to no more than 5 kcal/mol.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
