<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental Sections</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis of N-CDs quantum dots</div>
  <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental procedure of N-CDs fabrication have been reported elsewhere in the literature and here cited with minor modifications
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. Typically 4 mmol citric acid and 12 mmol urea were dissolved together in 20 ml distilled water, and then poured into a 100 ml Teflon lined hydrothermal reaction vessel. The reaction take place at 200 °C and kept for 8 hours. Then Cool to ambient temperature and adjusting the pH to 7. Centrifuge to get a dark yellowish N-CDs solution. The solution was put in a dialysis tube (keep molecular weight: 500 Da~3500 Da) for 4 days in the dark (changed deionized water every 8 h). Concentration to 20 mL.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis of N-CDs/P25 composites</div>
  <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">N-CDs/P25 was synthesized via a hydrothermal deposition process. Typically, 0.2 g P25 was put into certain volume of as-prepared N-CDs solution and added 40 mL more water, mixed and transferred to a dried Teflon-lined hydrothermal reaction vessel, heated to 200 °C and kept for 6 hours. After cooling down the mixture were then centrifuged at 8000r/min to collect the final product. The samples were named according to the added volume of N-CDs as (2 mL)N-CDs/P25, (4 mL)N-CDs/P25, (6 mL)N-CDs/P25, (8 mL)N-CDs/P25 and (10 mL)N-CDs/P25</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photocatalytic performance evaluation</div>
  <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The photodegradation of Rhodamine B (RhB) were chosen as model reaction to evaluation the photocatalytic activities of the as synthesized material under visible light irradiation. Xenon lamp with a &lt;400 nm cutoff filter was used as the photo source to mimic the nature solar irradiation. Generally, a 150 mL quartz reactor were equipped with a thermostat to keep the degradation temperature at 28 °C, in which put 10 mg/L RhB100 mL. Into the RhB solution added 50 mg catalysts. Keep the mixture in the dark for 30 min to make sure the catalysts saturated with the adsorption of RhB. Turn on the lamp to start the photocatalytic reaction and accumulate the irradiation time. To trace the dynamic concentration changes of the RhB 3 mL of the mixture each time was taken out from the reactant at regular intervals. The concentration was obtained by UV-VIS measurements.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
