<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TiO
  <sub>2</sub> are the most widely explored semiconductor photocatalysts in environmental pollutants treatment and solar-energy conversion area in these latest decades for their superior photocatalytic activity, nontoxicity, long-term stability and low cost
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Degussa (Evonik) P25 is a biphasic titanium dioxide that owns especially high photocatalytic activity due to its special biphasic interfacial heterojunction structure
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. It contains more than 80% anatase with a minor amount of rutile (15%) and a small amount of amorphous phase with approximately 20 nm particle size
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Interfaces between rutile and anatase phase facilitate charge carrier separation and retard the charge recombination between electron trapping sites within the mixed phase so as to improve photocatalytic activity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>; Therefore P25 is prevailing used in laboratory for photocatalytic reaction systems. However, P25 have its own inherent weakness, for example, the large band gap limited its response wavelengths in the UV region, lower absorption volume and slower electronic mobility limited its energy conversion efficiency
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. A strategy we can take is the combination of the photoactive P25 nanoparticle with visible light adsorptive conductor. Not only does this provide visible light sensitizer and electron trapping sites, extend its photoresponse wavelength to visible region, it also ensures relative fast electronic transportation to the reaction interface that is beneficial to charge separation, enhance the conversion efficiency
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon quantum dots (CDs) are zero dimensional nanocarbon material less than 10 nm in diameter, formed by crystalline graphitic sp
  <span class="sup">2</span>-bonded carbon atoms, which have a quantum confinement effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Apart from its unique electronic attributes, the quasi-spherical nanocarbon material possess several other attractive advantages, such as the large specific surface area, high stability, low toxicity, simple synthetic routes and the strong and tunable fluorescence emission properties
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. Based on those novel properties, therefore, the couple of P25 and CDs is anticipated to simultaneously have high photo activity, excellent adsorptivity, good electronic mobility and good cost-efficiency, therefore enhancing the photocatalytic decomposition abilities of pollutants
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. Herein we demonstrated a facile route to prepare a chemically bonded N-doping carbon quantum dots/P25 composite via hydrothermal method that is illustrated in Scheme 1. The as-prepared composites own several advantages over other catalysts: the enhanced adsorptive ability of pollutants, fast charge conductivity and separation, extended light absorption range. The factors of particle size, chemical composition, and the CDs content in N-CDs/P25 that may influence the catalytic performance were systematically discussed. The as synthesized N-CDs/P25 composites show higher photocatalytic activity in the degradation of Rhodamine B (RhB) over the commercial P25 catalysts under visible light illumination. Finally based on trapping control experiment and Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR) measurements, we proposed one feasible visible-light driven degradation mechanism.
 </p>
</sec>
