<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experiments</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General Procedures</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="sup">1</span>H NMR spectra were measured using a JEOL ECA400II (400 MHz) system in solutions of acetone-
   <span class="italic">d</span>
   <sub>6</sub>. The residual protons of acetone-
   <span class="italic">d</span>
   <sub>6</sub> were used as an internal standard for measurements. Electrospray ionization-mass spectroscopy (ESI-MS) was performed using a Shimadzu LCMS-2010A system with acetonitrile as the mobile phase. UV-vis absorption spectra were measured with a JASCO V-565 spectrophotometer. Emission spectra were measured using a Horiba Fluorolog-3-21 spectrofluorometer equipped with a NIR-PMT R5509-43 near infrared detector. A Horiba FluoroCube time-correlated single-photon counting system was used to obtain emission lifetimes. The excitation light source was a NanoLED-515L pulse lamp (510 nm). A HAMAMATSU absolute PL quantum yield spectrometer C9920-02 was used to determine emission quantum yields. The samples were degassed by Ar-bubbling of solutions for 30 min prior to measuring emissions. Emission quenching experiments were performed on solutions containing the complexes and five different concentrations of BIH. The quenching rate constants 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>q</sub> were calculated from linear Stern-Volmer plots for the emission from the 
   <span class="sup">3</span>MLCT excited state of the photosensitizing complexes and their lifetimes. The redox potentials of the complexes were measured in an Ar-saturated DMA solution containing Et
   <sub>4</sub>NBF
   <sub>4</sub> (0.1 M) as a supporting electrolyte using cyclic voltammetric techniques performed with an ALS CHI-720Dx electrochemical analyzer with a glassy carbon disk working electrode (3 mm diameter), a Ag/AgNO
   <sub>3</sub> (10 mM) reference electrode, and a Pt counter electrode. The supporting electrolyte was dried under vacuum at 100°C for 1 day prior to use. The scan rate was 200 mV·s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photocatalytic Reactions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photocatalytic reactions were performed in DMA–TEOA (5:1 v/v) solutions containing the photosensitizer (50 μM), 
   <span class="bold">Re</span> (50 μM), and BIH (0.2 M). After the solution was purged with CO
   <sub>2</sub> for 20 min, the solution was irradiated. For TON measurements, the mixed solution (2 mL) in an 11 mL test tube (i.d. 8 mm) was irradiated in a merry-go-round apparatus using λ
   <sub>ex</sub> &gt; 620 nm light from a halogen lamp equipped with a Rhodamin B (0.2% w/v, 
   <span class="italic">d</span> = 1 cm) solution filter or λ
   <sub>ex</sub> &gt; 500 nm light from a high-pressure Hg lamp equipped with a uranyl glass and a K
   <sub>2</sub>CrO
   <sub>4</sub> (30% w/w, 
   <span class="italic">d</span> = 1 cm) solution filter. During irradiation, the temperature of the solution was maintained at 25°C using an EYELA CTP-1000 constant-temperature system. For quantum yield measurements, the mixed solution in a quartz cubic cell (11 mL, light pass length: 1 cm) was irradiated in a Shimadzu photoreaction quantum yield evaluation system QYM-01 using 600 nm or 480 nm light from a 300 W Xe lamp equipped with a 600 nm or 480 nm (FWHM: 10 nm) bandpass filters. The temperature of the solution was controlled during irradiation at 25 ± 0.1°C using an IWAKI CTS-134A constant-temperature system. The gaseous products of photocatalysis, i.e., CO and H
   <sub>2</sub>, were analyzed by GC-TCD (GL science GC323). A capillary electrophoresis system (Agilent 7100) was used to analyze HCOOH. HPLC analyses for BIH and BI
   <span class="sup">+</span> were conducted using a JASCO 880-PU pump, a Develosil ODS-UG-5 column (250 × 4.6 mm), a JASCO 880–51 degasser, and a JASCO UV-2070 detector. The column temperature was maintained at 30°C using a JASCO 860-CO oven. The mobile phase was a 6:4 (v/v) mixture of acetonitrile and a NaOH–KH
   <sub>2</sub>PO
   <sub>4</sub> buffer solution (50 mM, pH 7) with a flow rate of 0.5 mL·min
   <span class="sup">−1</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electrochemical Spectroscopy</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electrochemical spectroscopy to determine the molar absorptivity of OERS was performed using a JASCO PU-980 pump and an EC Frontier flow-type electrolysis cell VF-2 equipped with a carbon felt working electrode (18 mm diameter), a Ag/AgNO
   <sub>3</sub> (10 mM) reference electrode, and a Pt wire counter electrode in an Ar-saturated acetonitrile solution of 
   <span class="bold">Ru(pic)</span> (0.5 mM) and Et
   <sub>4</sub>NBF
   <sub>4</sub> (0.1 M) as a supporting electrolyte. Applied potential was controlled using an ALS CHI-720Dx electrochemical analyzer and UV-vis absorption spectra were measured using a Photal MCPD-9800 spectrometer (Otsuka Electronics) and a flow-type transmission cell (light pass length: 1.5 mm) (Ishitani et al., 
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">1994</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum Yields for One-Electron Reduction of Photosensitizers</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A 4-mL DMA–TEOA (5:1 v/v) solution of the photosesnsitizer (0.1 mM) and BIH (0.2 M) in a quartz cubic cell (light pass length: 1 cm) was purged with Ar for 20 min, and then irradiated with the 500-W Xe lamp combined with a 480-nm (FWHM = 10 nm) bandpass filter (Asahi Spectra Co.), ND filter, and a 5-cm-long H
   <sub>2</sub>O solution filter. UV–vis absorption spectral changes during irradiation were measured using a Photal MCPD-9800 spectrometer (Otsuka Electronics). The light intensity was determined as 5.0 × 10
   <span class="sup">−9</span> einstein·s
   <span class="sup">−1</span> using a K
   <sub>3</sub>Fe(C
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>4</sub>)
   <sub>3</sub> actinometer.(Hatchard and Parker, 
   <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">1956</a>) The amount of OERS of 
   <span class="bold">Ru(pic)</span> was calculated using the molar absorption coefficient of OERS (500–700 nm) obtained by electrochemical spectroscopy.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
