<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General Procedures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="sup">1</span>H NMR spectra were measured using a JEOL ECA400II (400 MHz) system in solutions of acetone-
  <span class="italic">d</span>
  <sub>6</sub>. The residual protons of acetone-
  <span class="italic">d</span>
  <sub>6</sub> were used as an internal standard for measurements. Electrospray ionization-mass spectroscopy (ESI-MS) was performed using a Shimadzu LCMS-2010A system with acetonitrile as the mobile phase. UV-vis absorption spectra were measured with a JASCO V-565 spectrophotometer. Emission spectra were measured using a Horiba Fluorolog-3-21 spectrofluorometer equipped with a NIR-PMT R5509-43 near infrared detector. A Horiba FluoroCube time-correlated single-photon counting system was used to obtain emission lifetimes. The excitation light source was a NanoLED-515L pulse lamp (510 nm). A HAMAMATSU absolute PL quantum yield spectrometer C9920-02 was used to determine emission quantum yields. The samples were degassed by Ar-bubbling of solutions for 30 min prior to measuring emissions. Emission quenching experiments were performed on solutions containing the complexes and five different concentrations of BIH. The quenching rate constants 
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>q</sub> were calculated from linear Stern-Volmer plots for the emission from the 
  <span class="sup">3</span>MLCT excited state of the photosensitizing complexes and their lifetimes. The redox potentials of the complexes were measured in an Ar-saturated DMA solution containing Et
  <sub>4</sub>NBF
  <sub>4</sub> (0.1 M) as a supporting electrolyte using cyclic voltammetric techniques performed with an ALS CHI-720Dx electrochemical analyzer with a glassy carbon disk working electrode (3 mm diameter), a Ag/AgNO
  <sub>3</sub> (10 mM) reference electrode, and a Pt counter electrode. The supporting electrolyte was dried under vacuum at 100°C for 1 day prior to use. The scan rate was 200 mV·s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
