<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Redox photosensitizers, which absorb visible light and facilitate the electron transfer process, play a key role in various photochemical reactions, such as CO
  <sub>2</sub> reduction (Takeda et al., 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">2017</a>; Tamaki and Ishitani, 
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">2017</a>), water oxidation (Fukuzumi et al., 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2016</a>), hydrogen evolution (Schulz et al., 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">2012</a>), and organic synthesis (Prier et al., 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">2013</a>). Effective photosensitizers should be endowed with three important properties, including (1) visible-light absorption, (2) a long lifetime in the excited state to initiate the electron transfer process, and (3) reducing and/or oxidizing power that is strong enough to donate electrons or holes to the catalyst. In particular, the utilization of visible-light over a wider range of wavelengths is important both to utilize sunlight efficiently and avoid the internal filter effect and side reactions that are commonly caused by the light-absorption of catalysts and/or electron donor/acceptor. Ru(II) complexes coordinated with three diimine ligands, [Ru(N
  <span class="sup">∧</span>N)
  <sub>3</sub>]
  <span class="sup">2+</span> (N
  <span class="sup">∧</span>N = diimine ligand) are the most widely used redox photosensitizers in various photochemical redox reactions because these types of complexes exhibit strong absorption in the visible-light region and have a long lifetime in their triplet metal-to-ligand charge-transfer (
  <span class="sup">3</span>MLCT) excited states (Juris et al., 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">1988</a>; Thompson et al., 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, one of the disadvantages of [Ru(N
  <span class="sup">∧</span>N)
  <sub>3</sub>]
  <span class="sup">2+</span>-type photosensitizers is the limited access to the wavelength region of visible light, e.g., λ
  <sub>abs</sub> &lt; 560 nm in the cases of N
  <span class="sup">∧</span>N = 2,2′-bipyridine (bpy) and 4,4′-dimethyl-2,2′-bipyridine (dmb), and these complexes cannot utilize visible light having lower energy (λ &gt; 560 nm). To overcome this, ligand-modified Ru(II) photosensitizers have been reported. For example, Ru(II) complexes have an extended π-system for photodynamic therapy (Zhang et al., 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">2017</a>) and multinuclear Ru(II) complexes by conjugated bridging ligand are used for hydrogen evolution (Tsuji et al., 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">2018</a>). However, these modifications lower the reducing power of photosensitizers and limit the choice of catalyst especially for the reduction of CO
  <sub>2</sub>. On the other hand, we have reported an osmium(II) analog, i.e., [Os(N
  <span class="sup">∧</span>N)
  <sub>3</sub>]
  <span class="sup">2+</span>, which could function as a redox photosensitizer utilizing a much wider wavelength range of visible light (λ
  <sub>abs</sub> &lt; 700 nm) due to its singlet-to-triplet direct excitation (S-T absorption) and drive photocatalytic CO
  <sub>2</sub> reduction by red-light irradiation (λ
  <sub>ex</sub> &gt; 620 nm) in the combination with rhenium(I) catalyst unit (Tamaki et al., 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">2013b</a>), whereas the high toxicity of Os
  <span class="sup">VIII</span>O
  <sub>4</sub> inhibits the wider application of osmium complexes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, we developed a novel ruthenium(II) redox photosensitizer that can utilize a wider wavelength range of visible light than [Ru(N
  <span class="sup">∧</span>N)
  <sub>3</sub>]
  <span class="sup">2+</span>. In the photocatalytic system for CO
  <sub>2</sub> reduction, a photosensitizer mediates an electron from a sacrificial electron donor to a catalyst. Since the positive shift of the LUMO level of redox photosensitizer should limit the choice of a catalyst for reducing CO
  <sub>2</sub>, for the expansion of the useable wavelength range, we try to decrease the energy-gap between HOMO and LUMO by the negative shift of the HOMO level, while maintaining the LUMO level. We introduced anionic electron-donating picolinate instead of a diimine ligand into a ruthenium complex (Norrby et al., 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">1997</a>; Couchman et al., 
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1998</a>). [Ru(dmb)
  <sub>2</sub>(pic)]
  <span class="sup">+</span> (
  <span class="bold">Ru(pic)</span>; Hpic = picolinic acid) was synthesized, and we investigated its photophysical properties and functions as a redox photosensitizer using [Ru(dmb)
  <sub>3</sub>]
  <span class="sup">2+</span> (
  <span class="bold">Ru(dmb)</span>) as a reference redox photosensitizer and Re(dmb)(CO)
  <sub>3</sub>Br (
  <span class="bold">Re</span>) as a catalyst for the reduction of CO
  <sub>2</sub> (Hawecker et al., 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">1983</a>; Gholamkhass et al., 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">2005</a>; Tamaki et al., 
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2016</a>). 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F8" href="#F8">Chart 1</a> shows structures and abbreviations of the metal complexes used.
 </p>
 <div id="F8" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Chart 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Structures and abbreviations of complexes used.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fchem-07-00327-g0008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
