<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photocatalytic Reactions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photocatalytic reactions were performed in DMA–TEOA (5:1 v/v) solutions containing the photosensitizer (50 μM), 
  <span class="bold">Re</span> (50 μM), and BIH (0.2 M). After the solution was purged with CO
  <sub>2</sub> for 20 min, the solution was irradiated. For TON measurements, the mixed solution (2 mL) in an 11 mL test tube (i.d. 8 mm) was irradiated in a merry-go-round apparatus using λ
  <sub>ex</sub> &gt; 620 nm light from a halogen lamp equipped with a Rhodamin B (0.2% w/v, 
  <span class="italic">d</span> = 1 cm) solution filter or λ
  <sub>ex</sub> &gt; 500 nm light from a high-pressure Hg lamp equipped with a uranyl glass and a K
  <sub>2</sub>CrO
  <sub>4</sub> (30% w/w, 
  <span class="italic">d</span> = 1 cm) solution filter. During irradiation, the temperature of the solution was maintained at 25°C using an EYELA CTP-1000 constant-temperature system. For quantum yield measurements, the mixed solution in a quartz cubic cell (11 mL, light pass length: 1 cm) was irradiated in a Shimadzu photoreaction quantum yield evaluation system QYM-01 using 600 nm or 480 nm light from a 300 W Xe lamp equipped with a 600 nm or 480 nm (FWHM: 10 nm) bandpass filters. The temperature of the solution was controlled during irradiation at 25 ± 0.1°C using an IWAKI CTS-134A constant-temperature system. The gaseous products of photocatalysis, i.e., CO and H
  <sub>2</sub>, were analyzed by GC-TCD (GL science GC323). A capillary electrophoresis system (Agilent 7100) was used to analyze HCOOH. HPLC analyses for BIH and BI
  <span class="sup">+</span> were conducted using a JASCO 880-PU pump, a Develosil ODS-UG-5 column (250 × 4.6 mm), a JASCO 880–51 degasser, and a JASCO UV-2070 detector. The column temperature was maintained at 30°C using a JASCO 860-CO oven. The mobile phase was a 6:4 (v/v) mixture of acetonitrile and a NaOH–KH
  <sub>2</sub>PO
  <sub>4</sub> buffer solution (50 mM, pH 7) with a flow rate of 0.5 mL·min
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
