<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, we have demonstrated a non-destructive, inkjet-printable, smart-phone readable, AI decodable, unclonable, and fluorescence security label. Such security labels with various 2D patterns composed of red, green, or blue emission arrays were fabricated through inkjet printing using II–VI semiconductor core-shell quantum dots as model ink. The surface modification of the print substrates with randomly arranged PMMA nanoparticles is crucial for the successful inkjet printing of the unclonable security labels. The polymer nanoparticles on the print substrates were acted as stochastic pinning points at the three-phase contact lines of the ink droplets for the quantum dot deposition, forming physically unclonable flower-like dot patterns. This non-deterministic pattern formation process guarantees the unclonability of the fabricated security labels. By utilizing the RGB emission core-shell quantum dots, full-color security labels can be generated.</p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fabricated security labels are invisible in the ambient environment but can be visualized by naked eyes when irradiated with UV light, which offers an easy way for the preliminary verification. A more reliable authentication strategy by using AI techniques has been developed. Covert and unclonable flower-like dot patterns with different sharpness, brightness, rotations, amplifications, and the mixture of these parameters have been successfully decoded within seconds using the authentication strategy developed here. The overall cost per security labels has been estimated to be approximately US$ 0.011 (see Supplementary Note 2). The anti-counterfeiting technology described in this work is a good step closer to commercial applications that are low cost, mass-producible, nondestructive, diverse full-color pattern design capability, unclonable, and convenient for authentication. Applications of this technology span the full range from established to emerging-technology industries, including pharmaceutics, food security, and nanotechnology. Compared with intrinsic surface topography of material itself (like scratch patterns, fiber weave, etc.), our current system shows advantages in fluorescent and multi-color information, multi-level security, convenient for authentication, and well-designed patterns. The possibility of covert but easily detectable labeling through the use of a portable mini microscope and AI technique (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>) will ensure the security and trackability of sensitive substances and equipment, which will lead to a promising approach in sensitive industries such as the nuclear one.
 </p>
</sec>
