<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials</div>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Poly(methyl methacrylate) (PMMA, average Mw ~996,000 g mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, from Sigma-Aldrich), polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP, average Mw ~40,000×
   <span class="italic">g</span> mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), chlorobenzene (99.8% pure, from J&amp;K Scientific), CdO (AR grade, from Aladdin), ZnO (99.7%, from Shijiazhuang hongda zinc industry co. LTD), zinc acetate dehydrate (AR grade, from Aladdin), oleic acid (OA, 90%, from Alfa aeser), 1-octadecene (ODE, 98%, from Toyata), Se powder (99.999%, from Alfa aeser), sulfur powder (99.95%, from Aladdin), 1-Dodecanethiol (DDT, ≥ 98%, from Chevron Phillips Chemical), toluene (for synthesizing quantum dots, AR grade, from Guangdong Guanghua Sci-Tech Co., Ltd), and ethanol (AR grade, from Guangdong Guanghua Sci-Tech Co., Ltd) were received and used without further purification. Sticky-gel film with gel thickness of 1.5 mm and retention level of X4 was purchased from Gel-Pak company. Toluene (for dissolving PMMA) was purchased from Sinopharm Chemical Reagents and further dried by distillation over sodium.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis of core-shell quantum dots</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For a typical synthesis of CdSe/CdS/CdZnS red emission quantum dots: 7 mmol of CdO, 10 mL of OA and 25 mL of ODE were mixed in a 250 mL round flask. The mixture was heated to 160 °C, degassed for 15 min, then filled with N
   <sub>2</sub> gas and further heated to 310 °C. Subsequently, Se precursor was injected swiftly into the flask. Then the reaction was cooled to 300 °C and remained at this temperature for 5 min. To grow the CdS shell, S source was injected dropwise to react with the remaining cadmium ions for 20 min. For the growth of CdZnS shell, keep the reaction temperature and dropwise injected the pre-prepared shelling materials, the shelling process last for ~30 mins. After the reaction, the temperature was naturally cooled down to room temperature. The synthesized quantum dots were finally purified using toluene and ethanolfor several times and finally dispersed in n-octylcyclohexane. For ZnCdSe/CdZnS green emission quantum dots: 35 mmol of ZnO, 25 mL of OA, and 20 mL of ODE were mixed in a 250 mL round flask. The mixture was heated to 160 °C, degassed for 15 min, then filled with N
   <sub>2</sub> gas and further heated to 300 g to get a clear solution. The solution was cooled to 200 °C, at which Se and Cd stock precursors were quickly injected into the flask sequentially. Then the temperature was elevated to 310 °C and remained at this temperature for 30 min to form alloyed CdZnSe core. For the growth of the CdZnS shell, S source and Cd source were dropwise injected into the flask repeatedly while keeping temperature at 270 °C. After the precursor injection, the temperature was kept unchanged for 30 min to 1 h, and then naturally cooled down to room temperature. For the synthesis ZnCdS/CdZnS blue emission quantum dots with composition gradient, the procedure is the same as that for the green emission quantum dots, except using S stock solution instead of Se solution as the anion precursor. At the elevated temperature, the S precursor was injected into the mixture of the Zn precursor and Cd precursor in a round bottom flask, forming the blue emitting ZnCdS cores. The shell materials (S source and Cd source) were added afterwards drop-wisely, and the reaction was allowed to proceed from 30 min to 1 h for the shell growth. The synthesized of green and blue quantum dots were purified and prepared with similar process as above.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fabrication of quantum-dot security labels</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a typical procedure, the precursors of surface modification layer were prepared by adding solutes into chlorobenzene, toluene, and DMSO for common PMMA (4 mg ml
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), designed PMMA (4 mg ml
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), and PVP (4 mg ml
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) layer respectively, and stirring vigorously for 12 h at 60 °C before use The quantum dot inks were dispersed in n-octylcyclohexane at a concentration of 20 mg ml
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. Indium-tin-oxide (ITO)-coated glass substrates were cleaned with ultrasonication successively in deionized (DI) water, acetone, isopropanol, and DI water. Then, nitrogen stream was used to dry the substrates, followed by 10 min oxygen plasma treatment. The pre-prepared precursors of surface modification layer were deposited on the substrates by spin coating, and then were heated at 120 °C for 30 min. The quantum-dot inks were printed on the substrates with a Microfab JETLAB II equipped with a 30-μm diameter piezoelectric-driven inkjet nozzle and a motorized stage with the accuracy of 5 μm. Driving voltage waveforms to the inkjet printing nozzle and the flying single droplet are shown in Supplementary Figs. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">20</a> and 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">21</a>. All the processes were operated in the ambient environment. If every single macroscopic pattern has 1000 unclonable flower-like points, we can achieve 1600 macroscopic patterns in 5 min with our single-nozzle printing machine. The time of drying is ~5 min for each batch of security label. The as-fabricated security labels were covered with gel films by tearing of their polycarbonate coversheet and then stick their gel material on the labels for stability test (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characterization</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The surface morphology of the PMMA films and quantum-dot patterns were characterized with atomic force microscopy (AFM, Bruker Multimode 8) and scanning electronic microscope (SEM, FEI, Nova Nano SEM 230). The UV−Vis absorption spectra were tested with a UV/Vis/NIR spectrophotometer (Shimadzu, UV-3600). The transmission electronic microscopy (TEM) image of quantum dots was recorded using JEOL JEM-2100F microscope. The steady-state photoluminescence (PL) spectra were collected with a Hitachi F-4600 fluorescence spectrophotometer, by exciting the samples using a Xe lamp coupled with a monochromator. Time-resolved PL measurement was collected by using fluorescence lifetime measurement system (HORIBA scientific). Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectra were recorded with a Nicolet 50 FTIR spectrometer at room temperature. The PL microscopic images of quantum dot patterns morphology were characterized by using a fluorescent microscope (Olympus BX51M). For pattern readout with a smartphone microscope, the portable microscope was linked to a small WiFi box by a USB line, which allows for the smartphone to control the microscope for real-time imaging (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum yield of quantum dots</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results are obtained by comparing integrated PL intensities using the standard procedure
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span>. The quantum yield (QYs) of blue, green, and red emission quantum dots were measured relative to Coumarin 480 (QY 99% in ethanol) with excitation at 350 nm, Coumarin 480 (QY 99% in ethanol) with excitation at 370 nm and rhodamine 6 G (QY 95% in ethanol) with excitation at 450 nm, respectively. Solutions of quantum dots in toluene were optically matched at the excitation wavelength. Fluorescence spectra of quantum dots and dye were taken under identical spectrometer conditions in triplicate and averaged. The optical density was kept below 0.06 at the 
   <span class="italic">λ</span>
   <sub>max</sub>, and the integrated intensities of the emission spectra, corrected for differences in index of refraction and concentration, were used to calculate the quantum yields using the expression.
   <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">1</span>
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\mathrm{QY}}\;{\mathrm{of}}\;{\mathrm{quantum}}\;{\mathrm{dots}} = {\mathrm{QY}}_R \times \frac{I}{{I_R}} \times \frac{{A_R}}{A} \times \frac{{n^2}}{{n_R^2}}$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" class="math">
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">QY</span>
      <span width="0.16em" class="mspace"/>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">of</span>
      <span width="0.16em" class="mspace"/>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">quantum</span>
      <span width="0.16em" class="mspace"/>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">dots</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">QY</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">R</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">I</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">I</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">R</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">A</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">R</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">A</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msup">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">n</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msubsup">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">n</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">R</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10406_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>where QY is the quantum yield, 
   <span class="italic">I</span> is the measured integrated PL emission intensity, 
   <span class="italic">n</span> is refractive index (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1.496 for toluene; 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1.361 for ethanol) and 
   <span class="italic">A</span> is the optical density at the excitation wavelength.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Deep learning</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the deep learning networks employed in our paper are based on the TensorFlow backend. The code used are run in software Pycharm 2017.3. To generate a large enough training set from theoretical image(s) for Alexnet model, a data augmentation procedure to the original synthetic image(s) is applied. For a typical process, one lower-left dot representing a security label is captured as an image. Such a clear image was rotated by a step of 0.72° for 360° using an algorithm, producing a set of 500 training images. The input images were resized to 512 × 384 using pixel area relation for training. Plots of accuracy on the training and validation data sets over training epochs (from http://host:6006) can be found in the Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">19</a>. The training images do not need to be stored and are not stored in this case; The storage requirement is mainly determined by the neural network itself, about 200 M Bytes here. For the AI technology we used, the learning process takes 2 h. The computer used for deep CPU is equipped with the CPU (Intel(R) Core(TM) i7–6700 CPU @3040 GHz), the GPU (NVIDIA GTX 1080), the RAM (32.0 GB), and HDD Capability (1 TB). The computer rated power is 350 W/h.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Registration and validation methodology</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We created a file named as gn (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1, 2, 3, …) per security label to store the corresponding 500 training images prior to the training process. The training images stored in the file gn are named as gn_000, gn_001, …, gn_500. Many files from these security labels composed a database. After the 500 training images of a security label were learnt by AI, their structural information was remembered and linked to the file name gn (e.g., g1). Then the training images will be deleted. When consumers randomly take a picture of a real security label and sent it to the AI, the AI can automatically recall the accurately corresponding relationship and output the indexing name with a detailed match score. According our results, if the captured image from the end-user is clear enough, the match score of the image of true security label is more than 99% (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4t</a>). On the other hand, if the image (from a fake label) has never been learned, the engine will give a lower match score (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4u</a>). The authentication process takes about 2 s. Deep learning, as a black box that nobody actually knows how it works in details up to now, is an advantage for unclonable anti-counterfeiting technique because it is a tamper proof.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
