<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inkjet printing of unclonable quantum dot security labels</div>
  <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fabrication process of unclonable security labels by inkjet printing are illustrated in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Three types of commercially available II–VI semiconductor core-shell quantum dots (CdSe/CdS/CdZnS, ZnCdSe/CdZnS, and ZnCdS/CdZnS) that emitted red, green, and blue light were chosen as model inks owing to their high fluorescent quantum yield and outstanding stability (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). These quantum dots were synthesized using a well-established chemical route
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>, in which high boiling point oleic acid and 1-octadecen were used as a capping agent and solvent, respectively (see Methods for details). Typical low-magnification transmission electron microscopy (TEM) and high-resolution TEM micrographs present an extremely narrow particle size distribution and high crystallinity of the synthesized quantum dots (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a, b</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). The particle sizes of the red, green, and blue emission quantum dots are 6.5 ± 2 nm, 10.5 ± 3 nm, and 11.0 ± 2.5 nm, respectively. Generally, for quantum dots, the relationship between size and emissive wavelength accords with quantum confinement effect — that a small size corresponds to a larger band gap and emits short-wavelength fluorescence
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span>. In this case, the emission wavelength of red, green and blue quantum dots shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> was determined by the composition rather than the size of quantum dots (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1c</a>)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
   </span>. The Fourier-transform infrared absorption peaks at 2923 and 2854 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, corresponding to C–C and C–H stretching modes of the -CH
   <sub>2</sub>- group, reveals the presence of oleic acid on the quantum dot surface (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. The surface ligands are of importance for the preparation of highly dispersed and stable quantum dot inks as they can stabilize the quantum dots in non-polar solvents for months at room temperature. In this work, n-octylcyclohexane with low evaporation rate at ambient environment was adopted as model solvent for ink preparation. The low evaporation rate of the jetted ink droplet leads to a slow movement of the three-phase contact line on the print substrate, which allows us to dynamically study the quantum dot deposition behavior. Photographs of twenty jetted single droplets show almost identical shape both before contacting a print substrate and at the early stage after the contact (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>).
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Outline of formation processes of unclonable security labels by inkjet printing. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Typical TEM/HRTEM images (left), particle size distributions (middle), and ink for inkjet printing (right) of red core-shell quantum dots (QDs). 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Surface modification of a substrate with partly dissolved PMMA solution by spin coating. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> Substrate with random-distributed pinning points of PMMA nanoparticles on PMMA film after spin coating. 
      <span class="bold">d</span> Inkjet printing of prepared QDs ink on the modified substrate. 
      <span class="bold">e</span> Pinning process of QDs droplet contact line at random pinning points. 
      <span class="bold">f</span> Residual central ink teared in to several smaller droplets in the final evaporation process. 
      <span class="bold">g</span> A resulting security label composed of flower-like dot patterns, which are protected with a thin, optically transparent sticky gel film
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10406_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e485" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to inkjet printing, the print indium-tin-oxide (ITO)-coated glasses were cleaned by sonication in various solvents (see Methods for detailed sonication cleaning procedure), treated with oxygen plasma and then spin-coated with a partly-dissolved poly(methyl methacrylate) (PMMA)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span> nanoparticle colloid, forming a randomly distributed PMMA nanoparticle array on a PMMA layer (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b, c</a>). The surface cleaning and oxygen plasma treatment were utilized to remove the dusts and generate a super wettable surface for the PMMA nanoparticle coating, while the surface decoration with PMMA nanoparticles were used to create randomly arranged pinning points for the quantum dot deposition during the subsequent inkjet printing process. Such randomly arranged pinning points are critical for the successful inkjet printing of unclonable security labels (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>). Representative dark-field and atomic force microscopy images revealed the presence of randomly distributed PMMA nanoparticles with particle size in the range of a few nanometers to a few micrometers on the print substrates (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). Following the surface modification of the print substrates, they were subjected to the inkjet printing to produce 2D graphic security labels. The inkjet printing was conducted by continuously jetting the quantum dot ink droplets with size of ~130 μm on the print substrates (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>). The interval between two adjacent ink droplets is 200 μm. If each macroscopic security label contains 1000 flower-like points, we can achieve 1600 security labels in 5 min (i.e., the drying time of each batch of security label) with our single-nozzle printing machine. Each droplet represents a pixel of the inkjet-printed security labels after being completely dried. The PMMA nanoparticles on the poorly wettable PMMA film were acted as stochastic pinning points at the three-phase contact lines of the ink droplets. With the evaporation of solvent, the three-phase contact line continually slides and shrinks at the smooth PMMA areas owing to the poor wettability of the surface but is captured by some pinning points. Consequently, the pinning points stretch and pin the contact line, distorting the fluid convex and forming irregular quantum dot ink pattern (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1e</a>). During the solvent evaporation process, the quantum dot concentration increases gradually. When the quantum dot concentration reached their saturation point, they started to deposit at the stochastic PMMA pinning points on the three-phase contact line, forming a unique flower-like dot pattern (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1f</a>). With the shrinking of droplet, the volume-smaller droplet is more liable to be tortured by pinning points, thus splitting into several smaller sub-droplets (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). Due to the small space between these sub-droplets and some stochastic external factors (such as airflow), they experienced merging and splitting irregularly before eventual drying (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1f</a>). This non-deterministic, random pattern formation process was recorded by a camera to monitor the shape evolution of a droplet as a function of time (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). Such a non-deterministic pattern formation process makes it impossible to reproduce the flower-like dot patterns, which were used as PUF codes in our security labels. The fabricated security labels were then covered with a thin, optically transparent, sticky gel film to protect them being damaged during the real circulation (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1g</a>). If without the PMMA nanoparticles on the print substrates, the accumulated quantum dots induced by solvent evaporation directly deposited on the self-pinned three-phase contact line, producing a coffee-ring-like pattern (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6a</a>). However, if the print substrates were coated with a continuous, smooth, poorly wettable PMMA layer, the three-phase contact line of the droplets are incline to shrink and slide towards to the center, rather than pinned on substrates, bringing the quantum dots to center of the droplet. When the solvent is completely evaporated, a central bump pattern, i.e., a hilly accumulation with diameter much smaller than the initial wetted diameter of the ink droplet, is generated (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6b</a>). In the absence of the stochastic PMMA pinning points, either a uniform coffee ring or central bump pattern was formed, which was determined by the wettability property of the print substrates. These deterministic pattern formation processes ensure the reproducibility of the patterns under the same conditions.
  </p>
  <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The miniaturized dark-field and fluorescence microscopes integrated with smartphones have been developed for single nanoparticle imaging
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. Such small, affordable, portable microscopes were utilized by consumers to authenticate the inkjet-printed security labels. The magnification-adjustable objective lens of the portable microscope used here is covered with a cylindrical metal shell that creates a small dark imaging environment by blocking the ambient light (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>). The portable microscope is able to quickly (typically within one second), accurately and nondestructively readout the produced flower-like dot patterns, which show different geometries as expected (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unlimited colorful pattern design capability</div>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ideal fluorescent security labels require the ink materials having strong fluorescence intensity, which guarantees the high fluorescence brightness. The prepared quantum dot inks exhibit a narrow fluorescence emission peak with maximum intensity at 459 nm, 532 nm, and 631 nm, respectively, when excited at 375 nm (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). The full-width at half-maximum (FWHM) of these blue, green and red emission quantum dots is 20 nm, 24 nm, and 28 nm, respectively. They also bear a high fluorescence quantum yield of 75, 90, and 80%, respectively. The time-resolved fluorescence decays of the blue, green, and red emission quantum dots show their lifetime of 27.5 ns, 17.0 ns, and 7.6 ns (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>), respectively, in consistent with consistent with previous reports
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>. According to the Commission Internationale de I’éclairage (CIE) 1931 color coordinate triangle, the quantum dots achieved a wide color gamut of 124% of the National Television System Committee (NTSC) standard (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a>), better than phosphor (color gamut: 85.6%)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>, implying outstanding full-color fluorescence properties for security label applications.
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Optical characterization. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Fluorescence spectra and 
      <span class="bold">b</span> time-resolved fluorescence decay measurements of red, green, and blue emission quantum dot (QD) inks excited at 375 nm. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> Transmittance spectra of ITO coated glass substrates before and after inkjet printing of red, green, and blue emission Fuzhou University logos (Inset: photographs of the four samples under ambient light). 
      <span class="bold">d</span>–
      <span class="bold">i</span> Fluorescence images of red, green, and blue emission 
      <span class="bold">d</span>–
      <span class="bold">f</span> Fuzhou University logos and 
      <span class="bold">g</span>–
      <span class="bold">i</span> two-dimensional QR codes and bar codes. The Fuzhou University logos, QR codes and bar codes, composed of thousands of dot patterns (pixels), are adapted with permission of the Fuzhou University. The scale bar is 1 cm
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10406_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e613" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Complex Fuzhou University logos composed of red, green, or blue emission arrays were inkjet-printed on indium tin oxide (ITO) coated glass slides using the printing strategy described in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. The print substrates with Fuzhou University logos maintained transparent (Insert of Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>). That is, the inkjet-printed logos are invisible by naked eyes under the ambient conditions. The transmittance curves of the printed ITO glass slides are almost identical to the pristine print substrate (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>), further confirming the covert characteristic of the fabricated security labels. When irradiated with UV light, bright red, green and blue photoluminescence photographs of the university logos were observed by the naked eyes (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d–f</a>). Any other 2D macroscale patterns with sharp corners, for example, QR codes and bar codes (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2g–i</a>), can also be produced using our inkjet printing technique. The property that these images are only seen upon UV excitation offers the first layer of security realized by naked eye authentication of macroscopic patterns; and the PUF nature of the flower-like patterns is the second more secure layer.
  </p>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By tuning RGB ink component ratios, fine tonal variations from red to green were obtained (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>). In principle, the full palette of colors could be achieved with elaborate control of the RGB ink components. Alternatively, the full-color security labels can be generated by creating individual color pixels including red, green, and blue sub-pixels, which has been widely used in display
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span> and color images
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span>. The inkjet printing strategy developed here offers us an opportunity to extend the ink to other fluorescent materials, e.g., lanthanide complexes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span>, carbon dots
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span>, and up-conversion nanoparticles
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
   </span>, etc. and the print substrates to flexible ones, such as plastics (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>). Although the 2D macroscale security labels shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d-i</a> contained thousands of discrete points (or pixels), the printing process is completed within a few minutes using our single-nozzle printing machine.
  </p>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> displays fluorescence micrographs of three batches of inkjet-printed macroscopic letters FZU (i.e., the acronym of Fuzhou University) that are composed of red, green, or blue emission arrays. At the macroscopic level, the printed FZU letters were seemingly identical (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a–c</a>). However, under the microscopic level, they were completely different from each other, as every fluorescent pixel of the letters showed a unique, random and unrepeatable flower-like geometry (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d–i</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). Further scanning electron microscope and energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy characterizations verify that the unique flower-like micropattern obtained from optical imaging systems is consistent with quantum dot deposition zones (see Supplementary Figs. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>2–
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">14</a>). By carefully comparing all the pixels within the letters (i.e., the same sample), no identical flower-like micropatterns were found. A copy of the red, green, and blue fluorescence counterparts of the FZU letters shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> fabricated under the same conditions also shows entirely different geometries of the corresponding pixels (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">15</a>). The encoding capacity of the inkjet-printed security labels that relies on the encoding capacity (defined as l) and the number (defined as m) of the PUF patterns (i.e., flower-like pixels) within the security labels can be described as l
   <span class="sup">m</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
   </span>. Recently, Carro-Temboury et al. established a universal binary-bit model for the estimation of the encoding capacity of PUF pattern
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
   </span>. According to Carro-Temboury’s model, the encoding capacity of a red flower-like PUF pattern, l, is calculated to be 4.7 × 10
   <span class="sup">202</span> (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>6 and Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> for calculation details). Therefore, for a security label composed of 1000 red flower-like PUF patterns, its encoding capacity will be larger than 10
   <span class="sup">202,000</span>. This indicates that the inkjet-printed security labels are unclonable even by the manufacturer. Moreover, the fabricated security labels have been frequently exposed to UV light over the period of 2 months. No obvious decrease of the fluorescence brightness is observed, revealing that security labels have excellent chemical and photo stabilities (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17</a>).
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Security labels with physically unclonble flower-like patterns. Typical fluorescence images of inkjet-printed macroscopic letters FZU composed of 
      <span class="bold">a</span> red, 
      <span class="bold">b</span> green, and 
      <span class="bold">c</span> blue emission dot patterns (the scale bar is 4000 μm), 
      <span class="bold">d</span>–
      <span class="bold">f</span> their local enlarged images (the scale bar is 500 μm), and 
      <span class="bold">g</span>–
      <span class="bold">i</span> further enlarged images (the scale bar is 100 μm). All the samples are printed under the same conditions. The FZU patterns are identical on macroscale but completely different at the microscale (i.e., every dot pattern is unique)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10406_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e764" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Deep learning decoding mechanism</div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conventional security labels with macroscale features, for instance, QR codes or bar codes are convenient for authentication with naked eyes, but easy to be counterfeited. Advanced security labels that carry complex, random nano/microscale features (PUF keys) are formidable to be faked. The decoding of such security labels relies on a similar character extraction, recognition, and comparison analysis that a real fingerprint does
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
   </span>. Such machine learning algorithms for pattern recognition, enhancement, and identification are widely employed for the authentication of the PUF-based security labels
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
   </span>. A general drawback of the machine learning approach is time consuming and having a high level of false positives of up to 20%
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
   </span>. Furthermore, conventional classification can only be used in the PUF that can be transformed to private keys; for flower-like patterns, it does not work. To deal with this problem, deep learning, an artificial intelligence (AI) technique, was introduced to validate the fabricated unclonable security labels, which pushes anti-counterfeiting technology to a higher dimension.
  </p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although AI has been recently applied into organic chemistry synthesis and TEM image analysis
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first time to use AI for security label authentication. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> demonstrates a typical authentication procedure of the inkjet-printed security labels through deep learning. First of all, each quantum dot security label on a commercial product is imaged using an advanced fluorescence microscope (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>, step 1). Only one image is taken from each security label and represents one PUF code. Simply, randomly shifting and rotating the image creates a large number of images for an AI to learn the characteristic features of the security label. Once the images are trained on AI, they are categorized in a very general manner (e.g., classes associated with geometry of the security labels) and then stored as a database in a deep learning engine for the subsequent authentication using (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>, step 2). This is done by the manufacturer. When the consumers receive the products, they can simply use their portable mini-microscope-connected smartphones to readout the PUF codes by taking photos of the security labels (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>, step 3), which are automatically sent to the deep learning engine for validation (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>, step 4). The deep learn engine immediately feeds back the authentication results (real or fake) to the users (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>, step 5).
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Deep learning decoding mechanism. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Schematic illustrating the authentication process: 1: image capture and database generation from the goods by the manufacturers, 2: image learning by AI, 3: Image capture from the goods by the consumers using their smart phones, 4: image recognition and comparing by AI, and 5: authentication outcome feedback to the consumers. 
      <span class="bold">b</span>–
      <span class="bold">g</span> A library of six single dot pattern security labels, 
      <span class="bold">h</span>–
      <span class="bold">m</span> six fluorescence images taken from 
      <span class="bold">b</span> (referred as to genuine product) with different brightness, sharpness, rotation angles, magnifications, and the mixture of the above-mentioned factors, and 
      <span class="bold">n</span>–
      <span class="bold">s</span> six fluorescence images from security labels that are not in the database shown in panel 
      <span class="bold">b</span>–
      <span class="bold">g</span> (referred as to fake products). 
      <span class="bold">t</span>, 
      <span class="bold">u</span> Recognition rates of labels (h1–h6) and (i1–i6) by the authenticating way of deep learning. Labels (g1–g6), (h1–h6), and (i1–i6) correspond to the labels in figure (
      <span class="bold">b</span>–
      <span class="bold">g</span>), (
      <span class="bold">h</span>–
      <span class="bold">m</span>), and (
      <span class="bold">n</span>–
      <span class="bold">s</span>) respectively. The color scales from blue to red stand for the matching score (ranging from 0 to 100%) of the captured pictures with the labels
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10406_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e881" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To experimentally demonstrate the above authentication process, six quantum-dot security labels (named as g
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">n</span>
   </sub>, 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1, 2, ···, 6) were randomly chosen to establish a security label database (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b–g</a>). Five hundred fluorescence images of each security label (e.g., g
   <sub>1</sub>) obtained by randomly shifting and rotating a same image (i.e., g
   <sub>1</sub>) are provided to AI for learning and classifying. The selected 72 out of the 500 images from g
   <sub>1</sub> show the exact same geometrical characteristics of the security label (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">18</a>). The 500 images were divided into two parts: 80% for learning and 20% for validation. After every learning cycle (the parts for learning), the images for validation were sent to AI engine to test, providing a train accuracy plot. After about 1000 learning cycles, they can be recognized with accuracy fluctuating between 97 and 100% when being sent to AI for validation again (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">19</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For decoding, a security label that represented a genuine product (i.e., from the pre-established database) was imaged at various sample rotation angles, magnification, focusing degrees, and the mixture of the above-mentioned factors (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4h–m</a>). We try to cover all possible deviations from the imaging equipment, imaging conditions, personnel habits of users that may happen in a real authentication scenario. None of the images shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4h–m</a> (named as h
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">n</span>
   </sub>, 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1, 2, ···, 6) has ever been previously learnt by AI. The image h
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">n</span>
   </sub> is fed into the trained AI for validation. The authentication outputs show the accuracy of h
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">n</span>
   </sub> (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1, 2, ···, 6) is 0.999, 0.758, 0.999, 0.909, 0.999, and 0.999, respectively (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4t</a>). The relatively low accuracy of h
   <sub>2</sub> and h
   <sub>4</sub> are attributed to their over-indistinct characteristics, for which parts of details are lost during imaging, implying sharpness exerting a much higher impact on authentication accuracy than other variations, such as brightness, location, rotation angle, and amplification factor. The threshold of the accuracy at a value of 0.5 is then set to distinguish the real and fake security labels. For comparison, six fake security labels named as i
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">n</span>
   </sub> (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1, 2, ···, 6) were sent to AI for authentication in the same way (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4n–s</a>). The corresponding accuracy is almost zero for all the fake security labels (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4u</a>). By simply comparing the accuracy on the test with the threshold, the deep learning machine can immediately provide the authentication outcomes (real: accuracy ≥0.5, fake: accuracy &lt;0.5) to the customers. Regarding to the rate of false positives, we achieved the false positives rate of 0 using the match score of 0.5 as the threshold when sampling 100 security labels (see Supplementary Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). It only takes seconds or even less to finish the whole authentication process.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
