<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fabrication of quantum-dot security labels</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a typical procedure, the precursors of surface modification layer were prepared by adding solutes into chlorobenzene, toluene, and DMSO for common PMMA (4 mg ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), designed PMMA (4 mg ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), and PVP (4 mg ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) layer respectively, and stirring vigorously for 12 h at 60 °C before use The quantum dot inks were dispersed in n-octylcyclohexane at a concentration of 20 mg ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. Indium-tin-oxide (ITO)-coated glass substrates were cleaned with ultrasonication successively in deionized (DI) water, acetone, isopropanol, and DI water. Then, nitrogen stream was used to dry the substrates, followed by 10 min oxygen plasma treatment. The pre-prepared precursors of surface modification layer were deposited on the substrates by spin coating, and then were heated at 120 °C for 30 min. The quantum-dot inks were printed on the substrates with a Microfab JETLAB II equipped with a 30-μm diameter piezoelectric-driven inkjet nozzle and a motorized stage with the accuracy of 5 μm. Driving voltage waveforms to the inkjet printing nozzle and the flying single droplet are shown in Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">20</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">21</a>. All the processes were operated in the ambient environment. If every single macroscopic pattern has 1000 unclonable flower-like points, we can achieve 1600 macroscopic patterns in 5 min with our single-nozzle printing machine. The time of drying is ~5 min for each batch of security label. The as-fabricated security labels were covered with gel films by tearing of their polycarbonate coversheet and then stick their gel material on the labels for stability test (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
