<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inkjet printing of unclonable quantum dot security labels</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fabrication process of unclonable security labels by inkjet printing are illustrated in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Three types of commercially available II–VI semiconductor core-shell quantum dots (CdSe/CdS/CdZnS, ZnCdSe/CdZnS, and ZnCdS/CdZnS) that emitted red, green, and blue light were chosen as model inks owing to their high fluorescent quantum yield and outstanding stability (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). These quantum dots were synthesized using a well-established chemical route
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, in which high boiling point oleic acid and 1-octadecen were used as a capping agent and solvent, respectively (see Methods for details). Typical low-magnification transmission electron microscopy (TEM) and high-resolution TEM micrographs present an extremely narrow particle size distribution and high crystallinity of the synthesized quantum dots (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a, b</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). The particle sizes of the red, green, and blue emission quantum dots are 6.5 ± 2 nm, 10.5 ± 3 nm, and 11.0 ± 2.5 nm, respectively. Generally, for quantum dots, the relationship between size and emissive wavelength accords with quantum confinement effect — that a small size corresponds to a larger band gap and emits short-wavelength fluorescence
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. In this case, the emission wavelength of red, green and blue quantum dots shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> was determined by the composition rather than the size of quantum dots (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1c</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. The Fourier-transform infrared absorption peaks at 2923 and 2854 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, corresponding to C–C and C–H stretching modes of the -CH
  <sub>2</sub>- group, reveals the presence of oleic acid on the quantum dot surface (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. The surface ligands are of importance for the preparation of highly dispersed and stable quantum dot inks as they can stabilize the quantum dots in non-polar solvents for months at room temperature. In this work, n-octylcyclohexane with low evaporation rate at ambient environment was adopted as model solvent for ink preparation. The low evaporation rate of the jetted ink droplet leads to a slow movement of the three-phase contact line on the print substrate, which allows us to dynamically study the quantum dot deposition behavior. Photographs of twenty jetted single droplets show almost identical shape both before contacting a print substrate and at the early stage after the contact (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Outline of formation processes of unclonable security labels by inkjet printing. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Typical TEM/HRTEM images (left), particle size distributions (middle), and ink for inkjet printing (right) of red core-shell quantum dots (QDs). 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Surface modification of a substrate with partly dissolved PMMA solution by spin coating. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Substrate with random-distributed pinning points of PMMA nanoparticles on PMMA film after spin coating. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> Inkjet printing of prepared QDs ink on the modified substrate. 
     <span class="bold">e</span> Pinning process of QDs droplet contact line at random pinning points. 
     <span class="bold">f</span> Residual central ink teared in to several smaller droplets in the final evaporation process. 
     <span class="bold">g</span> A resulting security label composed of flower-like dot patterns, which are protected with a thin, optically transparent sticky gel film
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10406_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e485" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to inkjet printing, the print indium-tin-oxide (ITO)-coated glasses were cleaned by sonication in various solvents (see Methods for detailed sonication cleaning procedure), treated with oxygen plasma and then spin-coated with a partly-dissolved poly(methyl methacrylate) (PMMA)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> nanoparticle colloid, forming a randomly distributed PMMA nanoparticle array on a PMMA layer (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b, c</a>). The surface cleaning and oxygen plasma treatment were utilized to remove the dusts and generate a super wettable surface for the PMMA nanoparticle coating, while the surface decoration with PMMA nanoparticles were used to create randomly arranged pinning points for the quantum dot deposition during the subsequent inkjet printing process. Such randomly arranged pinning points are critical for the successful inkjet printing of unclonable security labels (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>). Representative dark-field and atomic force microscopy images revealed the presence of randomly distributed PMMA nanoparticles with particle size in the range of a few nanometers to a few micrometers on the print substrates (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). Following the surface modification of the print substrates, they were subjected to the inkjet printing to produce 2D graphic security labels. The inkjet printing was conducted by continuously jetting the quantum dot ink droplets with size of ~130 μm on the print substrates (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>). The interval between two adjacent ink droplets is 200 μm. If each macroscopic security label contains 1000 flower-like points, we can achieve 1600 security labels in 5 min (i.e., the drying time of each batch of security label) with our single-nozzle printing machine. Each droplet represents a pixel of the inkjet-printed security labels after being completely dried. The PMMA nanoparticles on the poorly wettable PMMA film were acted as stochastic pinning points at the three-phase contact lines of the ink droplets. With the evaporation of solvent, the three-phase contact line continually slides and shrinks at the smooth PMMA areas owing to the poor wettability of the surface but is captured by some pinning points. Consequently, the pinning points stretch and pin the contact line, distorting the fluid convex and forming irregular quantum dot ink pattern (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1e</a>). During the solvent evaporation process, the quantum dot concentration increases gradually. When the quantum dot concentration reached their saturation point, they started to deposit at the stochastic PMMA pinning points on the three-phase contact line, forming a unique flower-like dot pattern (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1f</a>). With the shrinking of droplet, the volume-smaller droplet is more liable to be tortured by pinning points, thus splitting into several smaller sub-droplets (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). Due to the small space between these sub-droplets and some stochastic external factors (such as airflow), they experienced merging and splitting irregularly before eventual drying (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1f</a>). This non-deterministic, random pattern formation process was recorded by a camera to monitor the shape evolution of a droplet as a function of time (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). Such a non-deterministic pattern formation process makes it impossible to reproduce the flower-like dot patterns, which were used as PUF codes in our security labels. The fabricated security labels were then covered with a thin, optically transparent, sticky gel film to protect them being damaged during the real circulation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1g</a>). If without the PMMA nanoparticles on the print substrates, the accumulated quantum dots induced by solvent evaporation directly deposited on the self-pinned three-phase contact line, producing a coffee-ring-like pattern (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6a</a>). However, if the print substrates were coated with a continuous, smooth, poorly wettable PMMA layer, the three-phase contact line of the droplets are incline to shrink and slide towards to the center, rather than pinned on substrates, bringing the quantum dots to center of the droplet. When the solvent is completely evaporated, a central bump pattern, i.e., a hilly accumulation with diameter much smaller than the initial wetted diameter of the ink droplet, is generated (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6b</a>). In the absence of the stochastic PMMA pinning points, either a uniform coffee ring or central bump pattern was formed, which was determined by the wettability property of the print substrates. These deterministic pattern formation processes ensure the reproducibility of the patterns under the same conditions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The miniaturized dark-field and fluorescence microscopes integrated with smartphones have been developed for single nanoparticle imaging
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Such small, affordable, portable microscopes were utilized by consumers to authenticate the inkjet-printed security labels. The magnification-adjustable objective lens of the portable microscope used here is covered with a cylindrical metal shell that creates a small dark imaging environment by blocking the ambient light (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>). The portable microscope is able to quickly (typically within one second), accurately and nondestructively readout the produced flower-like dot patterns, which show different geometries as expected (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
