<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis of core-shell quantum dots</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For a typical synthesis of CdSe/CdS/CdZnS red emission quantum dots: 7 mmol of CdO, 10 mL of OA and 25 mL of ODE were mixed in a 250 mL round flask. The mixture was heated to 160 °C, degassed for 15 min, then filled with N
  <sub>2</sub> gas and further heated to 310 °C. Subsequently, Se precursor was injected swiftly into the flask. Then the reaction was cooled to 300 °C and remained at this temperature for 5 min. To grow the CdS shell, S source was injected dropwise to react with the remaining cadmium ions for 20 min. For the growth of CdZnS shell, keep the reaction temperature and dropwise injected the pre-prepared shelling materials, the shelling process last for ~30 mins. After the reaction, the temperature was naturally cooled down to room temperature. The synthesized quantum dots were finally purified using toluene and ethanolfor several times and finally dispersed in n-octylcyclohexane. For ZnCdSe/CdZnS green emission quantum dots: 35 mmol of ZnO, 25 mL of OA, and 20 mL of ODE were mixed in a 250 mL round flask. The mixture was heated to 160 °C, degassed for 15 min, then filled with N
  <sub>2</sub> gas and further heated to 300 g to get a clear solution. The solution was cooled to 200 °C, at which Se and Cd stock precursors were quickly injected into the flask sequentially. Then the temperature was elevated to 310 °C and remained at this temperature for 30 min to form alloyed CdZnSe core. For the growth of the CdZnS shell, S source and Cd source were dropwise injected into the flask repeatedly while keeping temperature at 270 °C. After the precursor injection, the temperature was kept unchanged for 30 min to 1 h, and then naturally cooled down to room temperature. For the synthesis ZnCdS/CdZnS blue emission quantum dots with composition gradient, the procedure is the same as that for the green emission quantum dots, except using S stock solution instead of Se solution as the anion precursor. At the elevated temperature, the S precursor was injected into the mixture of the Zn precursor and Cd precursor in a round bottom flask, forming the blue emitting ZnCdS cores. The shell materials (S source and Cd source) were added afterwards drop-wisely, and the reaction was allowed to proceed from 30 min to 1 h for the shell growth. The synthesized of green and blue quantum dots were purified and prepared with similar process as above.
 </p>
</sec>
