<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TC-RFWM spectroscopy allows overcoming the hindrances that have so far prevented experimental access to systems exhibiting a high density of states. Perturbations identified by this method can be used as gateways for experimental access into otherwise inaccessible regions, including the near-dissociation regime of the ground state. These mixed states oscillate between high- and low-vibrational quanta for large and small internuclear distances, respectively. While at short distance, a model based on the linear combination of atomic orbitals is appropriate, ligand-field theory might be better suited to address the behaviour at long range
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. The large size of the 4s and 4p orbitals serves to de-shield the atomic-ion cores from each other, leading to a positive point charge perturbing the 3d structures on the other atom. This relates to the foundational concept of “oxidation state”, which could be more properly thought of as the charge on one atom as seen by the atom to which it is bound (Field, R. W. (personal communication (2019))). The features of the nonlinear method open a wide field for future experiments on transition metal systems. The presented data also provide reference data to test new quantum chemical methods for computational handling of systems with a high density of states. Such insights lead to fundamental understanding of the complex electronic structure of transition metal clusters that govern their functionality. Ion-pair states, respectively, the states that originate from their avoided crossings with other states, affect almost all regions of the potential energy landscape of the copper dimer. Considering the commonness of perturbation-facilitated mixing between these and other quantum states, it is unlikely that other transition metal systems, which usually exhibit an even higher density of states, can be understood based on the assumption of pure states and the usage of the Born-Oppenheimer approximation. Even for the copper dimer itself, a glance behind the veil of overlapping lines exposed not only a complex network of perturbations, but also vibronic bands displaying interesting properties to access regions of the energy map beyond the possibilities of more conventional spectroscopic methods.
 </p>
</sec>
