<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the biochemical logic of the universal reliance on NAD(P)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While myriad natural electron carriers are known to support cellular redox reactions, NAD(P) has the prime role in almost all organisms, participating in most (&gt;50%) known redox reactions [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref008">8</a>]. The standard redox potential of NAD(P) is ~ -330 mV (pH = 7, I = 0.25), but as [NADPH]/[NADP] can be higher than 50 and [NADH]/[NAD] can be lower than 1/500, the physiological range of the NAD(P) reduction potential is between -380 mV and -250 mV [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref035">35</a>,
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref047">47</a>–
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref051">51</a>]. Most cellular redox reactions are therefore constrained to a limited reduction potential range determined by the physicochemical properties and physiological concentrations of NAD(P). By examining the fundamental trends of redox potentials of the different oxidoreductase groups we will show that NAD(P) is well-matched to the redox transformations most commonly found in cellular metabolism.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g003" href="#pcbi.1006471.g003">Fig 3</a> demonstrates that the reduction potentials of activated acids (activated G1) and carbonyls (G2 and G3) are very similar, such that NAD(P) can support both the oxidation and reduction of nearly all redox couples in these classes. Although the distributions associated with these redox reactions are not entirely contained in the NAD(P) reduction potential range (marked in grey), the reduction potential of a redox pair can be altered by modulating the concentrations of the oxidized and reduced species. As the concentrations of metabolites usually lie between 1 μM and 10 mM [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref035">35</a>,
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref052">52</a>], the reduction potential of a redox pair can be offset from its standard value by up to 
  <div id="pcbi.1006471.e003" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pcbi.1006471.e003.jpg" id="pcbi.1006471.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M3" class="math">
     <span class="mo">±</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
       <span class="mi">T</span>
       <span class="mi">l</span>
       <span class="mi">n</span>
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="msup">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mn">10</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mn">4</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">n</span>
       <span class="mi">F</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">≅</span>
     <span class="mo">±</span>
     <span class="mn">120</span>
     <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
     <span class="mi">m</span>
     <span class="mi">V</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> (assuming two electrons are transferred). Therefore, NAD(P) can support reversible redox reactions of compound pairs with E’
  <span class="sup">m</span> as low as −380 − 120 = −500 
  <span class="italic">mV</span> and as high as −250 + 120 = −130 
  <span class="italic">mV</span> (indicated by the light grey regions in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g003" href="#pcbi.1006471.g003">Fig 3</a>), a range that encompasses almost all activated acids (activated G1) and carbonyls (G2 and G3 reactions). Outside this range, however, NAD(P)(H) can only be used in one direction of the redox transformation–either oxidation or reduction, but not both. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g003" href="#pcbi.1006471.g003">Fig 3</a> shows that NAD(P)H can support irreversible reductions of hydroxycarbons to hydrocarbons and NAD(P) supports irreversible oxidation of carbonyls to carboxylic acids.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, we focus on a small set of redox reactions found in the extended central metabolic network that is shared by almost all organisms: (i) The TCA cycle, operating in the oxidative or reductive direction [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref053">53</a>], as a cycle or as a fork [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref054">54</a>], being complete or incomplete [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref054">54</a>], or with some local bypasses (e.g., [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref055">55</a>]); (ii) glycolysis and gluconeogenesis, whether via the EMP or ED pathway [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref056">56</a>], having fully, semi or non-phosphorylated intermediates [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref057">57</a>]; (iii) the pentose phosphate cycle, working in the oxidative, reductive or neutral direction; and (iv) biosynthesis of amino-acids, nucleobases and fatty acids. As schematically shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g005" href="#pcbi.1006471.g005">Fig 5</a>, and listed in Supplementary Dataset S2, the ≈ 60 redox reactions that participate in the extended central metabolism almost exclusively belong to one of the following groups: (i) reduction of an activated carboxylic acid to a carbonyl or the reverse reaction oxidizing the carbonyl (9 reactions, G1); (ii) reduction of a carbonyl to a hydroxycarbon or its reverse oxidation (20 reactions, G2); (iii) reduction of a carbonyl to an amine or its reverse oxidation (18 reactions, G3); (iv) irreversible oxidation of carbonyls to un-activated carboxylic acids (5 reactions, G1 in the direction of oxidation); and (v) irreversible reduction of hydroxycarbon to hydrocarbons (4 reactions, G4). Only two central metabolic reactions (marked in magenta background in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g005" href="#pcbi.1006471.g005">Fig 5</a>) oxidize hydrocarbons to hydroxycarbons (G4, in the direction of oxidation) and require a reduction potential higher than that of NAD(P): oxidation of succinate to fumarate and oxidation of dihydroorotate to orotate (While formally being oxidation of hydrocarbon to hydroxycarbon, the oxidations of prephenate to 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate and of arogenate to tyrosine present a special case since they create a highly stable aromatic ring and hence have enough energy to donate their electrons directly to NAD(P)). Similarly, the extended central metabolic network does not demand the low reduction potential required for the reduction of un-activated carboxylic acids (G1).
 </p>
 <div id="pcbi.1006471.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006471.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">A schematic showing the location of different types of oxidoreductase reactions (oxidoreductase groups 1 to 4) within the extended central metabolic network.</div>
   <p>We highlight reactions (purple) where a hydrocarbon is oxidized to a hydroxycarbon (G4 reactions, in the direction of oxidation) which generally cannot be sustained by NAD(P) as redox cofactor. See Supplementary Dataset 2 for full set of redox reactions in extended central metabolic network. G6P, Glucose-6-phosphate; F6P, Fructose-6-phosphate; DHAP, Dihydroxyacetone phosphate; GAP, Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate; Gly1P; Glycerol 1-phosphate; 6PG, 6-Phosphogluconolactone; R5P, Ribulose 5-phosphate; E4P, Erythrose 4-phosphate; 3PG, 3-Phosphoglycerate; PEP, Phosphoenolpyruvate; PYR, Pyruvate; AcCoA, Acetyl coenzyme A; 2KG, 2-Ketoglutaric acid; OA, Oxaloacetate.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pcbi.1006471.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reduction potential range associated with NAD(P) therefore perfectly matches the vast majority of reversible redox reactions in extended central metabolism–i.e., reduction of activated carboxylic acids and reduction of carbonyls (orange, purple and blue distributions in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g003" href="#pcbi.1006471.g003">Fig 3</a>)–and can also support the common irreversible redox transformations of extended central metabolism–i.e., reduction of hydroxycarbons and oxidation of carbonyls to un-activated carboxylic acids (green and red distributions in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g003" href="#pcbi.1006471.g003">Fig 3</a>). Cells typically rely on secondary redox carriers like quinones and ferredoxins (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g003" href="#pcbi.1006471.g003">Fig 3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1006471.s001" href="#pcbi.1006471.s001">S1 Table</a>), to support less common reactions, i.e., oxidation of hydrocarbons and reduction of un-activated carboxylic acids.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Why is the reduction potential of NAD(P) lower than the E’
  <span class="sup">m</span> of most carbonyls (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g003" href="#pcbi.1006471.g003">Fig 3</a>)? As biosynthesis of an NAD(P) derivative with higher reduction potential presents no major challenge [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref058">58</a>], why does this lower potential persist? We suggest that this redox offset plays an important role in reducing the concentrations of cellular carbonyls by making their reduction to hydroxycarbons favorable. It is well known that carbonyls are reactive towards macromolecules, as they spontaneously cross-link proteins, inactivate enzymes and mutagenize DNA [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref059">59</a>,
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref060">60</a>]. As the reduction potential of NAD(P) is lower than most carbonyls, the redox reactions in category G2 (or G3) prefer the direction of reduction, thus ensuring that carbonyls are kept at lower concentrations than their corresponding hydroxycarbons (or amines). Assuming a value of 
  <span class="italic">E</span>′ = −330 
  <span class="italic">mV</span> for NAD(P) and taking the average E’
  <span class="sup">m</span> of the G2 reactions (&lt;
  <span class="italic">E</span>′
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </span>&gt; ≅ −225 
  <span class="italic">mV</span>) results in an estimated equilibrium concentration ratio 
  <div id="pcbi.1006471.e004" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pcbi.1006471.e004.jpg" id="pcbi.1006471.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M4" class="math">
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">[</span>
       <span class="mi">h</span>
       <span class="mi">y</span>
       <span class="mi">d</span>
       <span class="mi">r</span>
       <span class="mi">o</span>
       <span class="mi">x</span>
       <span class="mi">y</span>
       <span class="mi">c</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">r</span>
       <span class="mi">b</span>
       <span class="mi">o</span>
       <span class="mi">n</span>
       <span class="mo">]</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">[</span>
       <span class="mi">c</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">r</span>
       <span class="mi">b</span>
       <span class="mi">o</span>
       <span class="mi">n</span>
       <span class="mi">y</span>
       <span class="mi">l</span>
       <span class="mo">]</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mi">e</span>
     <span class="mi">x</span>
     <span class="mi">p</span>
     <span class="mo">(</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <span class="mi">E</span>
       <span class="mi">’</span>
       <span class="mo">[</span>
       <span class="mi">N</span>
       <span class="mi">A</span>
       <span class="mi">D</span>
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <span class="mi">P</span>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
       <span class="mo">]</span>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <span class="mo">&lt;</span>
       <span class="mi">E</span>
       <div class="msup">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">’</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">m</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">&gt;</span>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
       <span class="mi">n</span>
       <span class="mi">F</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
       <span class="mi">T</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">)</span>
     <span class="mo">≅</span>
     <span class="mn">3500</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, thus ensuring very low levels of the carbonyl species. While we do not have many measurements to confirm this prediction, we note one central example: in 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">coli</span>, the concentration of oxaloacetate is 1–4 μM [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref061">61</a>], while the concentration of its conjugated hydroxyacid, malate, is 2–3 mM [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref052">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For ketoacids and open-ring sugars (which are especially reactive due to the free carbonyl) this effect is even more pronounced as both have especially high reduction potentials (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g004" href="#pcbi.1006471.g004">Fig 4</a>). Indeed, the reduction potential of ketoacids is so high that the reverse, oxidative reaction is usually supported by electron donors with a higher potential than NAD(P), for example, quinones, flavins, and even O
  <sub>2</sub> (e.g., lactate oxidase, glycolate oxidase). Interestingly, the reactions of category G2 that are supported by known enzymes in the KEGG database (75% of reactions in this category) have significantly lower E’
  <span class="sup">m</span> than the remaining reactions, which are not known to be catalyzed by natural enzymes (
  <span class="italic">Δ</span> &lt;
  <span class="italic">E</span>′
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </span>&gt; ≅ 20 
  <span class="italic">mV</span>,
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.005). As such, we suggest that the G2 transformations that are known to be enzyme-catalyzed are mainly those that are amenable to redox coupling with NAD(P) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g004" href="#pcbi.1006471.g004">Fig 4D</a>). Within the subset of G2 transformations found in KEGG, those that use redox cofactors other than NAD(P) (such as cytochromes, FAD, O
  <sub>2</sub>, or quinones) have higher E’
  <span class="sup">m</span> values (
  <span class="italic">Δ</span> &lt;
  <span class="italic">E</span>′
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </span>&gt; ≅ 20 
  <span class="italic">mV</span>, not significant 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.03) than those that use NAD(P) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006471.g004" href="#pcbi.1006471.g004">Fig 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we note that the reduction potential of NADP and activated carboxylic acids (activated G1) overlap almost completely, such that we would not expect NAD(P) to have a strong effect on the ratio between the concentrations of carbonyls and activated acids. This is to be expected as both carbonyls and activated carboxylic acids are reactive–e.g., acetylphosphate and glycerate bisphosphate acetylates proteins spontaneously [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref062">62</a>] and acyl-CoA’s S-acetylates cellular peptides non-enzymatically [
  <a rid="pcbi.1006471.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1006471.ref063">63</a>]. As such, there is no sense in driving the accumulation of carbonyls at the expense of activated carboxylic acids or vice-versa–neither approach would ameliorate non-specific toxicity.
 </p>
</sec>
