<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Encouraged by the efficiency of natural photosynthesis,
  <a rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit1">1</a> numerous research groups have focused on mimicking its key steps. In particular, a great many studies explored molecular donor–acceptor compounds,
  <a rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit2">2</a>–
  <a rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit27">27</a> in which the primary photoinduced charge separation was frequently enabled by a covalently linked photosensitizer.
  <a rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit5">5</a>,
  <a rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit6">6</a>,
  <a rid="cit10" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit10">10</a>–
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a>,
  <a rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit19">19</a>,
  <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a> Optimizing the primary charge separation is without any doubt one basic requirement for the realization of much more complex artificial systems allowing solar fuel production through multiphoton-driven charge accumulation.
  <a rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit28">28</a>–
  <a rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit31">31</a> However, the great majority of previous studies on charge-separated states merely investigated their qualitative formation after light absorption and their lifetimes, but systematic quantum yield investigations
  <a rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit12">12</a>,
  <a rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit14">14</a>,
  <a rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit32">32</a> are scarce. In direct consequence, the factors governing the charge-separated state (CSS) formation efficiencies are still poorly understood. Even less explored are the processes that occur upon further excitation of CSSs with a second photon, such as detrimental light-induced charge recombination,
  <a rid="cit33" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit33">33</a>,
  <a rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit34">34</a> although their deep understanding is of pivotal importance for the efficient accumulation of redox equivalents.
  <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a>,
  <a rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit30">30</a>,
  <a rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit35">35</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The molecular design of our compounds (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1a</a>) is such that about 2.0 eV are stored (in CH
  <sub>3</sub>CN) in the final CSS after absorption of a single visible photon (energies of the photons used for excitation, 2.6 to 3.0 eV). A comparison with CSS energies of other triads revealed that the stored energy typically amounts to about 1.5 eV upon visible light excitation,
  <a rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit9">9</a>–
  <a rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit12">12</a>,
  <a rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit36">36</a> and in two recent CSS studies stored energies between 1.7 and 1.8 eV were declared as highly energetic.
  <a rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit4">4</a>,
  <a rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit5">5</a> Recently, we reported on the distance dependence of thermal charge recombination in the compounds from 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1a</a> in comparison to two series of other molecular triads.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> The unusually high CSS energy of the two specific triads in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1a</a> prompted us to perform a complete quantitative photophysical investigation including new multi-photon excitation studies, geared at understanding light-induced charge recombination. We optimized our laser setup such that it permits one- and two-pulse laser experiments with sensitive and quantitative detection of reaction intermediates, as well as homogeneous excitation in the detection volume (a detailed description of our setup is given in the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). That setup allows us to gain insights that are far beyond those obtained in former investigations of photoinduced electron transfer in donor–acceptor compounds and CSS formation.
 </p>
 <div id="sch1" fig-type="scheme" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Scheme 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">(a) Structure of molecular triads. (b) Schematic representation of the mechanism for light-induced (
    <span class="italic">hν</span>
    <sub>1</sub>) formation of a CSS in a molecular electron donor-photosensitizer-electron acceptor triad together with thermal (
    <span class="italic">τ</span>) and light-induced (
    <span class="italic">hν</span>
    <sub>2</sub>) charge recombination.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c9sc01381d-s1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The triads under study contain a triarylamine (TAA) donor and an anthraquinone (AQ) moiety as an acceptor. Symmetrical addition of 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-xylene units to the central bipyridine moiety enabled us to elongate the triad and to perform distance-dependent studies (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1a</a>). After visible-light excitation of the iridium photosensitizer, a CSS is formed. As indicated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1b</a>, charge recombination between oxidized donor and reduced acceptor can either occur 
  <span class="italic">via</span> well-known thermal charge recombination with characteristic lifetimes (
  <span class="italic">τ</span>; central part)
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> or through poorly-understood light-induced recombination pathways (
  <span class="italic">hν</span>
  <sub>2</sub>; left part). Since it is desirable to use high-energy CSSs for demanding (photo)chemical processes,
  <a rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit4">4</a> we considered the following aspects in our study: (i) the photoactive system should store as much energy as possible (Section 2.1), (ii) long lifetimes of the CSS are essential for the applicability of the photoactive system for subsequent (photo)reactions (Section 2.2), (iii) high quantum yields for light-induced charge separation are desirable (Section 2.3), (iv) the energy efficiency of photon usage is an important factor, and it is desirable to convert a very large fraction of the photon energy into chemical energy (Sections 2.1 and 2.3), and (v) the absorption of a second visible photon should ideally not induce light-driven charge recombination, which usually represents a detrimental CSS decay pathway (Section 2.4). In particular, that last aspect is underexplored given its importance for accumulative multi-electron transfer,
  <a rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit37">37</a>–
  <a rid="cit44" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit44">44</a> and, as noted above, quantitative factors of CSS formation are often neglected in studies of donor–sensitizer–acceptor compounds.
  <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a>,
  <a rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit30">30</a>,
  <a rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit35">35</a>
 </p>
</sec>
