<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CSS formation and energetic considerations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photoexcitation of our Ir-based sensitizer into its metal-to-ligand charge transfer (MLCT) absorption band between 390 and 450 nm produces, after intersystem crossing, its triplet state.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> However, comparison of the UV-Vis spectrum of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1a</a>, green trace) with 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1a</a>, violet trace) and 
  <span class="bold">Ir-Ref</span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1a</a>, red trace; see ESI page S8
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> for molecular structure) shows an unexpectedly high extinction coefficient in the blue for the shorter triad. That observation suggests that this triad exhibits not only an MLCT transition in this spectral range, but there is also an intraligand charge transfer (CT). We postulated earlier that this intraligand CT occurs between the TAA donor and the bipyridine ligand of the photosensitizer and that the increase of the distance between those two moieties in the 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> triad decreases the contribution of the intraligand CT significantly,
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> which is now further substantiated by DFT-calculations (see ESI, page S6
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The population of additional CT transitions is obviously not limited to our system, as the comparison of the UV-Vis absorption spectra within other series of triads suggests, where exclusively the molecules with the shortest distance show additional shoulders in the UV-Vis absorption spectra.
  <a rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit11">11</a>,
  <a rid="cit45" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit45">45</a> The same effect can also be observed in dyads with a short TAA-bipyridine distance,
  <a rid="cit46" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit46">46</a> while AQ-bipyridine dyads show no differences in the absorption behavior, even with short intramolecular distances.
  <a rid="cit47" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit47">47</a>
 </p>
 <div id="fig1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">(a) UV-Vis absorption spectra of 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-AQ
    </span> (green), 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>2</sub>-AQ
    </span> (violet), 
    <span class="bold">Ir-Ref</span> (red, see Fig. S3
    <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> for molecular structure) and the bipyridine-containing free ligand of the longer triad (black) in CH
    <sub>3</sub>CN at 293 K. The highlighted region indicates the wavelength range used for photoexcitation. (b) Cyclic voltammogram for 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-AQ
    </span> in dry and deoxygenated CH
    <sub>3</sub>CN. TBAPF
    <sub>6</sub> (0.1 M) was used as an electrolyte and a scan rate of 0.1 V s
    <span class="sup">–1</span> was applied. (c) Averaged energy of relevant excited states and relevant intermediates for 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-AQ
    </span> and 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>2</sub>-AQ
    </span> in CH
    <sub>3</sub>CN. Energies were estimated using the redox potentials from Table S1 and eqn (S1).
    <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>
    <span class="italic">E</span>
    <sub>00</sub> for the Ir sensitizer is 2.61 eV (
    <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">ref. 16</a>) whereas 
    <span class="italic">E</span>
    <sub>00</sub> for AQ˙
    <span class="sup">–</span> was estimated from its long wavelength absorption band.
    <a rid="cit49" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit49">49</a> (d) Transient UV-Vis absorption spectrum of 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-AQ
    </span> in deoxygenated CH
    <sub>3</sub>CN at 293 K. A 20 μM solution was excited at 440 nm with laser pulses of 
    <span class="italic">ca</span>. 10 ns duration; detection occurred by integration over a period of 200 ns immediately afterwards.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c9sc01381d-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amount of stored energy in the CSS (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>CSS</sub>) is equivalent to the driving force (–Δ
  <span class="italic">G</span>0CR) of the thermal charge recombination process of the photoexcited triads under study. The driving force can be derived from the redox potentials of AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> and TAA˙
  <span class="sup">+</span> in the respective triad (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1b</a> and ESI, page S5
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>), which results in a –Δ
  <span class="italic">G</span>0CR value of 1.99 eV for the shorter 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> triad and 1.96 eV for 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span>, 
  <span class="italic">i</span>.
  <span class="italic">e</span>., both triads can store 
  <span class="italic">ca</span>. 2.0 eV in their CSSs (in CH
  <sub>3</sub>CN). The maximal excitation wavelength for detectable CSS formation in the 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> triad is 450 nm, whereas the CSS of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> can be generated with wavelengths up to 
  <span class="italic">ca</span>. 470 nm due to the higher extinction coefficients resulting from the superposition of Ir-based MLCT and intraligand CT transitions (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1a</a> and Section 2.3 for details). Excitation with longer wavelengths is preferred to maximize energy efficiencies (
  <span class="italic">η</span>), which we define as the ratios of 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>CSS</sub> and the photon energies at the maximum excitation wavelength usable for CSS formation under our conditions. With the photon energies at the above-mentioned limiting wavelengths, energy efficiencies of 71% (longer triad) and 75% (shorter triad) thus result. These values are close to the upper limit of already reported high-energy CSSs where a visible photon was absorbed to form the respective CSS.
  <a rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit4">4</a>,
  <a rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit5">5</a>,
  <a rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit11">11</a>,
  <a rid="cit48" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit48">48</a> The energy efficiencies for the triads under study also compare very favorably with a reported two-photon process, which stores the same amount of energy as our triads.
  <a rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit28">28</a> Based on the redox potentials from the cyclic voltammograms of the triads (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1b</a> and ESI, page S5
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>), an energy level scheme for excited states and relevant intermediates of the triads 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> and 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> was calculated (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1c</a>). The shown energies are averaged over both triads. Excitation of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> (
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 470 nm) mainly results in an intraligand CT from the TAA unit to the bipyridine ligand of the Ir sensitizer since there is a significant oscillator strength for this excitation (see ESI, page S6
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). Electron transfer from the reduced bipyridine to the AQ unit finally gives the long-lived CSS. By contrast, the absorption of a higher energy photon (
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 450 nm) by 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> mainly excites an MLCT transition. The final CSS can then be generated by (i) reductive quenching of the excited Ir chromophore by the TAA moiety, followed by an electron transfer from the reduced Ir photosensitizer to the AQ unit, or (ii) oxidative quenching of the excited Ir sensitizer by the AQ unit, followed by an electron transfer from the TAA moiety to the Ir
  <span class="sup">IV</span> species. The formed final CSS in both triads can then undergo thermal charge recombination into the ground state. In addition, the final CSS can also be selectively photoexcited by absorption of a second visible photon (
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 532 nm) inducing rapid reverse electron transfer as discussed in Section 2.4.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The formation of the final CSS was detected immediately after photoexcitation by transient absorption spectroscopy (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1d</a> and S5 of the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The transient absorption spectrum of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1d</a>) clearly shows the spectroscopic signatures of the anticipated CSS. The one-electron oxidized TAA unit exhibits bands at 370 and 720 nm whereas the AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> species is characterized by bands at 370 and 570 nm.
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> For 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span>, the same spectroscopic signatures can be observed though the TAA˙
  <span class="sup">+</span> signal shifts from 720 to 
  <span class="italic">ca</span>. 700 nm (see ESI, Fig. S5
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
