<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Light-induced charge recombination</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the ultimate aim of achieving photoinduced charge accumulation in molecular systems without sacrificial additives, many sophisticated compounds have been prepared, but in the last decade only a handful of investigations succeeded in overcoming the associated difficulties.
  <a rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit31">31</a>,
  <a rid="cit77" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit77">77</a>–
  <a rid="cit80" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit80">80</a> Starting from the first CSS, a key problem is the light-induced charge recombination upon excitation of intermediate electrons/holes with a second photon (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1b</a>), which is competitive with the desired accumulation of redox equivalents.
  <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a>,
  <a rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit30">30</a> Given that CSSs typically exhibit intense absorptions over a broad wavelength range, selective photosensitizer excitation is even more difficult under conditions of solar (broadband) irradiation than it is under well-defined lab (monochromatic) conditions. However, this is currently a heavily underexplored area given its importance for accumulative multi-electron transfer.
  <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a>,
  <a rid="cit33" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit33">33</a>,
  <a rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit35">35</a>,
  <a rid="cit78" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit78">78</a>,
  <a rid="cit81" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit81">81</a> The molecular triads investigated in this study do not permit charge accumulation, but they are well-suited for studying light-induced charge recombination processes and for quantum yield determinations of this undesired side reaction, which lay the grounds for structural optimizations to avoid that detrimental process.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two-pulse two-color laser flash photolysis is the ideal experimental technique to investigate consecutive photoreactions, both for purely intramolecular reactions
  <a rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit34">34</a>,
  <a rid="cit60" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit60">60</a>,
  <a rid="cit82" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit82">82</a>–
  <a rid="cit84" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit84">84</a> and reaction sequences with intervening bimolecular processes.
  <a rid="cit81" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit81">81</a>,
  <a rid="cit85" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit85">85</a>–
  <a rid="cit87" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit87">87</a> This holds also true for the mechanism shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1b</a>: the first (violet or blue) pulse serves to produce the desired CSS, and the ensuing second (green) pulse
  <a rid="cit88" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit88">88</a> investigates the fate of this intermediate upon absorption of another photon. In line with the absorption spectra displayed in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1a</a>, the latter pulse (532 nm) alone has no effect on the ground states of the triads, which was verified by control experiments. Hence, that pulse selectively excites the CSSs in our systems with AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> being the main absorbing species at 532 nm (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1d</a> and page S4 of the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). The two-pulse experiments on 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> are summarized in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a>. Initial experiments with an interpulse delay of 240 ns (the pulse sequence is shown at the top of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5b</a>) and monitoring at the maximum of the CSS, 720 nm, revealed a green-light induced CSS bleach of about 24%, as is evidenced in the main plot of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5a</a>. The rather long interpulse delay allows sensitive monitoring of the CSS absorption spectrum between the two pulses (200 ns integration time, green spectrum in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5b</a>), and its comparison with the spectrum observed after the green pulse (gray spectrum in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5b</a>). Comparing the spectra presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5b</a>, we found that all (positive) absorption peaks in the gray spectrum are less intense by about 39%, and even the ground state bleach at 320 nm recovers accordingly; in other words, the normalized spectra are completely identical (normalization not shown). A correction of the ∼39% signal decrease observed in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5b</a> for the thermal CSS recombination, which also takes place during spectral detection, gave essentially the same result for the light-induced recombination (23%) as extracted from kinetic traces (24%, see above). Moreover, the kinetics of thermal charge recombination are unaffected by the second pulse (Fig. S6 of the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). Hence, all these two-pulse experiments on 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> unambiguously establish that charge recombination is the only green-light-induced process observable on the nanosecond timescale.
 </p>
 <div id="fig5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Observing and quantifying the light-induced charge recombination in 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-AQ
    </span> (20 μM in deoxygenated CH
    <sub>3</sub>CN) using two-pulse experiments with the general pulse sequence displayed at the top of panel (b). (a) Main plot: kinetic traces for the CSS of the triad at 720 nm with the second laser pulse blocked (green) or unblocked (gray). Inset: relative CSS bleaching at different intensities of the second laser (gray), together with the intensity dependence of the green-light induced [Ru(bpy)
    <sub>3</sub>]
    <span class="sup">2+</span> bleach (orange) used as reference for the charge recombination quantum yield (
    <span class="italic">φ</span>
    <sub>2</sub>) determination. The fit parameters 
    <span class="italic">a</span> for the saturation curves (1 – exp[–
    <span class="italic">I</span>
    <sub>532</sub>/
    <span class="italic">a</span>]) are 150 mJ (orange) and 463 mJ (gray). (b) Main plot: transient absorption spectrum of 
    <span class="bold">TAA-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
     <sub>1</sub>-AQ
    </span> before (green) and after (gray) the second laser pulse in a representative two-pulse experiment. The inset shows a kinetic transient absorption measurement under identical conditions (the detection windows used for recording the transient absorption spectra of the main plot have been highlighted). For details, see text.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c9sc01381d-f5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the sensitive and isolated detection of light-induced charge recombination, its quantum yield determination became a realistic target. Starting from the experimental conditions presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5a</a>, we analyzed the CSS bleach at six different intensities of the second laser while keeping all other parameters unchanged. The intensity dependent relative recombination yields were extracted by independent fitting of pre- and post-pulse signals and extrapolation to the time of the second laser pulse, 
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 240 ns (inset of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5a</a>, gray data points). For a reliable quantum yield determination, we applied the same method as in a recent investigation on a second-pulse induced photoreaction.
  <a rid="cit60" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit60">60</a> Briefly, we again employed [Ru(bpy)
  <sub>3</sub>]
  <span class="sup">2+</span> in water as reference system (compare, Section 2.3) and quantified the relative green-light induced ground state bleach upon excitation with laser pulses spanning a similar intensity range (inset of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Fig. 5a</a>, orange data points). To minimize experimental uncertainties associated with single-point actinometry,
  <a rid="cit61" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit61">61</a> we fitted both intensity dependencies with a saturation function that is valid for monophotonic photoreactions.
  <a rid="cit60" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit60">60</a>,
  <a rid="cit89" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit89">89</a> By analyzing the fit parameters with the extinction coefficients (at 532 nm) of the respective absorbing species (CSS of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span>, 15 500 M
  <span class="sup">–1</span> cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>, see page S4 of the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a> for details; [Ru(bpy)
  <sub>3</sub>]
  <span class="sup">2+</span>, 720 M
  <span class="sup">–1</span> cm
  <span class="sup">–1</span>),
  <a rid="cit62" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit62">62</a> a quantum yield for the light-induced charge recombination (
  <span class="italic">φ</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) of 1.5% was finally obtained.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar two-pulse experiments were carried out with 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> (Section 4.2 of the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). Owing to the shorter CSS lifetime of that triad (Section 2.2), single-wavelength transient absorption kinetic traces are much more sensitive than spectral measurements with (short) detection time windows. However, during kinetic traces recorded at both the AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> and the TAA˙
  <span class="sup">+</span> absorption maximum with a 45 ns interpulse delay, we did not observe any noticeable second-pulse induced absorption change, although at 532 nm the CSS of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> absorbs slightly more strongly than that of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> (see ESI page S4
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>). Taking into account the reduced detection sensitivity for these measurements on the short-lived CSS in this triad, we estimate an upper limit of 0.2% for the green-light induced charge recombination of this compound.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that the green pulse is mainly absorbed by the anthraquinone radical anion part of the CSS (page S4 of the ESI
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" href="#fn1">†</a>), we assume that the following mechanism explains the widely differing quantum yields for light-induced charge recombination in our triads (1.5 
  <span class="italic">vs.</span> 0.2%). Excitation of AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> at 532 nm (2.33 eV) produces – after ultrafast internal conversion – the lowest excited doublet state *AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span>, whose energy lies ∼1.15 eV above the electronic ground state of AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> (estimated from its long wavelength absorption band).
  <a rid="cit49" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit49">49</a> Isolated *AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> is known to rapidly deactivate back to AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span>: averaging over the available literature values gave a lifetime as short as ∼40 ps,
  <a rid="cit49" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit49">49</a>,
  <a rid="cit90" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit90">90</a>,
  <a rid="cit91" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit91">91</a> and we expect a similar natural lifetime of *AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> in our triads. Based on structural and energetic considerations, we regard the electron transfer to the bipyridine (bpy) moiety as the most-likely reaction pathway competing with photophysical deactivation. Once the bipyridine radical anion is formed, recombination with the adjacent TAA˙
  <span class="sup">+</span> could account for the observed ground-state regeneration through light-induced charge recombination (see also 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1c</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With a driving force of about 0.85 eV for the reaction between *AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> and bpy (see energies of the pertinent states in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Fig. 1c</a>), a conventional distance dependence of the electron transfer rates is expected, 
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, a rate constant decrease with increasing distances.
  <a rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit9">9</a>,
  <a rid="cit92" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit92">92</a>,
  <a rid="cit93" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit93">93</a> With the above-mentioned quantum yields of light-induced charge recombination and a rate of ∼1/40 ps for photophysical deactivation, reasonable rate constants for the intermolecular electron transfer between *AQ˙
  <span class="sup">–</span> and bpy on the order of 4 × 10
  <span class="sup">8</span> s
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span>) and &lt;5 × 10
  <span class="sup">7</span> s
  <span class="sup">–1</span> (
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span>) can be estimated, if we simply assume that this intramolecular reaction is rate-limiting. The reasoning of the preceding paragraph could thus explain that green-light-induced charge recombination of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>1</sub>-AQ
  </span> is more efficient than that of 
  <span class="bold">TAA-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-Ir-ph
   <sub>2</sub>-AQ
  </span> by about one order of magnitude. Moreover, it is worth emphasizing that a quantum yield of 1.5% for an undesired pathway starting from a CSS is not negligible, since it could clearly outperform the quantum yield of desired charge accumulation (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span>, 0.5% in 
  <a rid="cit77" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit77">ref. 77</a>). Although our triads are well-suited test systems to understand (biphotonic) light-induced recombination processes, we consider the probability of a (second) photon absorption by the CSSs of our triads with (sub)microsecond lifetimes as very unlikely under sunlight conditions. This is borne out by previous publications on intensity-dependent photoreactions with intermediates possessing nanosecond
  <a rid="cit94" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit94">94</a> to microsecond
  <a rid="cit60" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit60">60</a> lifetimes, whose efficient biphotonic ionization was only feasible with pulsed lasers or collimated laser diodes providing light power densities &gt;1 kW cm
  <span class="sup">–2</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiments of this section illustrate the wealth of information that is accessible by quantitative two-pulse experiments on molecular triads, and that electron transfer rate distance dependencies could also help understand light-induced recombination processes.</p>
</sec>
