<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chirp pulse Fourier transform microwave (CP-FTMW) spectroscopy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the broadband CP-FTMW spectra obtained with neon as a carrier gas, we assigned two PVE–MeOH complexes with significantly different intensities. Complex 1 is about ten times more intense than complex 2. The experimental rotational constants (
  <a rid="T3" ref-type="table" href="#T3">Table 3</a>) for the two isomers agree the best with the values calculated for the OH–O’ isomer (as also indicated in the FTIR and the IR–UV investigations, which are, however, unable to distinguish OH–O from OH–O’) and the OH–P isomer, respectively. The identification of the two complexes to the OH–O’ and the OH–P isomers is guided by the absolute and relative values of the B and C rotational constants. Generally, the rotational constants calculated at the SCS-CC2/def2-TZVP level of theory agree somewhat better with the experimental values than the B3LYP-D3(BJ)/def2-TZVP values (note that we compare experimental 
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <sub>0</sub> rotational constants with theoretical 
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <sub>e</sub> rotational constants here). For the OH–P complex, however, we find that the B3LYP-D3(BJ)/def2-TZVP level of theory provides a better prediction of the magnitudes of the dipole-moment components. Experimentally, we only observe a-type transitions for this complex, which points to rather low values for μ
  <sub>b</sub> and μ
  <sub>c</sub>. SCS-CC2 calculations predict all three dipole-moment components to be of comparable magnitude. At the B3LYP-D3(BJ) level, μ
  <sub>a</sub> is predicted to be significantly stronger than μ
  <sub>b</sub> and μ
  <sub>c</sub>. This change in magnitude for the dipole-moment components for different levels of calculation is more often observed for weakly bound complexes because the exact arrangement of the two monomers with respect to each other can have a major influence on the dipole-moment components. Also note that in none of the spectroscopic experiments, we observe the OH–E isomer that is also predicted to be of relatively low energy (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span>
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Experimental rotational constants of the two observed complexes, using neon as carrier gas, that are assigned to the OH–O’ and the OH–P isomers, respectively. The experimental rotational parameters for the OH–O’ isomer (called Exp 1) are the results of a fit to a rigid-rotor asymmetric Hamiltonian including solely the A lines of the internal rotation splitting. Rotational parameters of a global fit (XIAM) including both A and E levels due to internal rotation for the OH–O’ isomer are presented in the Table S9 of 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1">Complex 1
     <span class="break"/>(OH–O’ isomer)
    </td>
    <td colspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1">Complex 2
     <span class="break"/>(OH–P isomer)
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="5" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1">
     <span class="hr"/>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 1</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCS-CC2/def2-TZVP</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exp 1</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCS-CC2/def2-TZVP</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="5" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1">
     <span class="hr"/>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <span class="italic">A</span> [MHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1466.59120(26)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1501.94</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1275.7623(49)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1297.89</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <span class="italic">B</span> [MHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">697.48965(11)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">697.58</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">818.45271(73)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">818.01</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <span class="italic">C</span> [MHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">572.109900(95)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">589.94</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">640.2184(11)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">646.81</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆
     <sub>J</sub> [kHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72697(62)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070(14)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆
     <sub>JK</sub> [kHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6669(26)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19(10)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">∆
     <sub>K</sub> [kHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6217(62)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ
     <sub>J</sub> [kHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15121(11)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">δ
     <sub>K</sub> [kHz]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5783(29)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A state transition</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 (49/104/60)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(20/0/0)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dipole moment (D) (μ
     <sub>a</sub>/μ
     <sub>b</sub>/μ
     <sub>c</sub>)
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2/1.9/1.2</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8/0.4/0.8</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">σ [kHz]</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
   </tr>
  </table>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rotational spectra of the two isomers are qualitatively different. For the OH–O’ isomer (complex 1), we observe a characteristic line splitting into so-called A and E components (cf. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>) arising from internal rotation of the methyl group of methanol, similar to the case of the DPE–MeOH complex. For the OH–P isomer (complex 2), no line splitting due to internal rotation was observed. This is consistent with the higher barrier for this motion due to the secondary interactions of the methyl group with PVE (cf. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>A section of the experimental 2–8 GHz spectrum using a mixture of PVE and MeOH (3 million acquisitions). The upper experimental trace in black is compared with simulations, based on fitted parameters that can be assigned to the OH–O’ isomer (complex 1, red) for the PVE–MeOHcomplex. The observed complex has a clear splitting pattern due to the internal rotation of the methyl group of methanol, labeled with A and E. The experimental 
    <span class="sup">13</span>C positions (blue atoms) (r
    <sub>s</sub> substitution structure) deduced from a Kraitchman analysis are compared to the calculated structure at the SCS-CC2/def2-TZVP level of theory and further confirm the observation of the OH–O’ isomer.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="Beilstein_J_Org_Chem-14-1642-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two different ways of analyzing the rotational spectrum of the OH–O’ isomer (complex 1) were performed. In 
  <a rid="T3" ref-type="table" href="#T3">Table 3</a>, the results from a fit to an asymmetric-top Hamiltonian of only the A state species of the internal rotation splitting pair, which is often a good approximation, is summarized (Exp 1). In addition, we used the program XIAM to perform a global fit including both A and E lines. This global fit does not only provide the rotational constants, but also parameters of the internal rotor, in this case the methyl group. This includes the barrier height for internal rotation as well as the geometrical arrangement of the rotor with respect to the overall rotating molecule, as also discussed for the DPE–MeOH complex [
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">19</a>]. For PVE–MeOH, the barrier height was determined to be 261 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, as summarized in Table S9 of 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>. This value is in agreement to barrier heights observed for other complexes with methanol [
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">19</a>]. It is somewhat lower than in the case of free methanol (373 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and also lower than the calculated barrier height of 341 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span> Table S9, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>). This somewhat lower methyl group internal rotation barrier for the OH–O’ isomer could point to a softening of the C–O bond of methanol due to the hydrogen bond. The DID plots in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a> also indicate that the methyl group is basically free from other interactions, so that no additional hindering is expected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, the transition intensities for the OH–O’ isomer are strong enough (with a signal-to-noise (SNR) of about 500:1 to 600:1 for the stronger transitions) to assign rotational transitions arising from all nine singly substituted 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C isotopologues in natural abundance (about 1%, cf
  <span class="italic">.</span> Figure S3, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>). The additional data sets of rotational constants are summarized in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a> (Table S12) together with line lists of the main isotopologues (Tables S10–S11) and the 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C isotopologues (Tables S13–S21). They allow us, using Kraitchman’s equations, to determine the carbon substitution structure, 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>s</sub>, of the complexes, which are the positions of the respective substituted carbon atoms with respect to the center of mass of the complex and thus the carbon backbone structure. The obtained 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>s</sub> structure for complex 1 (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>) further confirms the assignment of complex 1 as the OH–O’ isomer, where the methyl group of the methanol moiety points towards the phenyl ring.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As mentioned, the OH–O’ isomer is about ten times more intense than the OH–P isomer. The intensity observed in CP-FTMW spectroscopy directly depends on the number of molecules, i.e., the population of the respective isomers, as well as the square of the transition dipole moments. Since the μ
  <sub>a</sub> values for the two isomers differ by a factor of two (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span> Table S11 in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>), the OH–P isomer can be considered to be about 2.5 times less populated than the OH–O’ isomer, as an upper estimate. Taking the predicted energy difference of 0.8 kJ/mol for granted, this ratio would correspond to a plausible [
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">18</a>] conformational freezing temperature of 100 K. A three-fold lower or three-fold higher conformational temperature appears unlikely, and thus a tentative experimental energy penalty for OH–P relative to OH–O’ ranges from 0.3 to 2 kJ/mol. This contradicts both inexpensive approaches (B3LYP-D3 and SCS-CC2 with def2-TZVP) and suggests that these methods somewhat underestimate the stability of OH∙∙∙O contacts.
 </p>
</sec>
