<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Computational Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various input structures for the PVE–MeOH complex were generated by using the MMFF94s force field [
  <a rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" href="#R57">57</a>] as implemented in Avogadro [
  <a rid="R58" ref-type="bibr" href="#R58">58</a>]. Afterwards, geometry optimizations were performed by applying the Berny optimization algorithm of Gaussian 09 [
  <a rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" href="#R56">56</a>] with energies and gradients obtained from Turbomole 7.0 [
  <a rid="R59" ref-type="bibr" href="#R59">59</a>]. The DFT functional B3LYP with Grimme's two-body D3 corrections and Becke–Johnson damping [
  <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">45</a>] was used in combination with the def2-TZVP basis set based on the documented performance of this level of theory for the similar diphenyl ether–methanol system [
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">19</a>]. Furthermore, the obtained structures were re-optimized with the SCS-CC2 method using the def2-TZVP basis set, both in the electronic ground (S
  <sub>0</sub>) and first excited state (S
  <sub>1</sub>). The ricc2 module in Turbomole 7.0 requires an auxiliary Coulomb fitting basis set (cbas) for the resolution-of-identity approximation (RI) for which def2-TZVP-cbas was chosen [
  <a rid="R60" ref-type="bibr" href="#R60">60</a>]. All obtained geometries were confirmed as minima by harmonic frequency calculations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the relative stability of the different conformers found on the potential hypersurface, density fitted explicitly correlated local coupled cluster with singles and doubles excitations and perturbative triples (DF-LCCSD(T0)-F12) calculations were carried out [
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">47</a>]. In order to converge the energies relative to the one particle basis, the VTZ-F12 and VQZ-F12 basis sets [
  <a rid="R61" ref-type="bibr" href="#R61">61</a>–
  <a rid="R62" ref-type="bibr" href="#R62">62</a>] were used together with a Schwenke style basis set extrapolation, as proposed in [
  <a rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" href="#R63">63</a>]. The orbitals were Pipek–Mezey [
  <a rid="R64" ref-type="bibr" href="#R64">64</a>] localized and orbital domains determined by natural population analysis with a threshold of TNPA = 0.03 [
  <a rid="R65" ref-type="bibr" href="#R65">65</a>]. Defaults were used for the pair classification, with all pairs included in the F12 treatment. Furthermore, the intermolecular pairs were classified as strong (meaning that they were treated at the highest level of theory). The latter method will be denoted as LCCSD(T0)-F12/CBS[T:Q]. In all correlated calculations the 1s electrons were removed from the treatment (frozen-core approximation). Furthermore, we analyzed the relative impact of dispersion interactions in the different complexes through a local orbital analysis of the CCSD (connected) doubles energy terms. The latter discussion is complemented with dispersion interaction density (DID) plots [
  <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>]. The coupled cluster calculations were carried out with Molpro 2015.1 [
  <a rid="R66" ref-type="bibr" href="#R66">66</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
