<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electronically excited state spectrum</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the investigation of the electronically excited state by using the UV/IR/UV technique, a two-color R2PI signal is required. For this reason, the one-color R2PI signal was suppressed by attenuating the laser power of the excitation laser. On the other hand, higher pulse energies were used for the ionizing laser. The latter was set to 31847 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for the UV/IR/UV experiment in order to yield the best two-color R2PI signal. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6</a> shows the recorded UV/IR/UV spectrum for the PVE–MeOH mass trace.
 </p>
 <div id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>UV/IR/UV spectrum of PVE–MeOH in the range of 3520–3750 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span>; excitation laser: 36741 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span>, ionizing laser: 31847 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span>, carrier gas helium; the lower trace shows the calculated OH stretching frequencies at the SCS-CC2/def2-TZVP level for the optimized S
    <sub>0</sub> and S
    <sub>1</sub> structure of the OH–O’ isomer scaled by 0.9635.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="Beilstein_J_Org_Chem-14-1642-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to temporally overlapping laser pulses, the spectrum contains transitions from the S
  <sub>0</sub> state, the electronically excited (S
  <sub>1</sub>, at 3637 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and also the ionic D
  <sub>0</sub> state (at 3667 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>). This could not be avoided, as the lifetime of the excited state, which is estimated to be in the order of 5–7 ns, is shorter than the laser pulse-widths of 7–10 ns. The OH stretching vibration at 3637 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> originating from the electronically excited state of the PVE–MeOH complex is blue-shifted compared to the ground state, which indicates a decrease of the hydrogen bond strength in the S
  <sub>1</sub> compared to the S
  <sub>0</sub> state. A comparison with SCS-CC2 calculations shows a good agreement of a blue-shifted OH stretching frequency at 3642 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span> Table S2, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>, scaled by 0.9635) compared to the ground state at 3619 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span>
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>) for the OH–O’ isomer, which is also reflected in an increase of the H∙∙∙O hydrogen bond distance from 2.068 to 2.168 Å from S
  <sub>0</sub> to S
  <sub>1</sub> state geometry. This destabilization of the OH∙∙∙O hydrogen bond is further reflected in the calculated binding energies of the PVE–MeOH complex obtained at the SCS-CC2/def2-TZVP level, which are reduced by 0.9 kJ/mol regarding 
  <span class="italic">D</span>
  <sub>0</sub> and 1.6 kJ/mol regarding 
  <span class="italic">D</span>
  <sub>e</sub> in the S
  <sub>1</sub> state compared to the S
  <sub>0</sub> state for OH–O’ (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span> Table S3, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>). The spectral shift can be explained by regarding the HOMO and LUMO orbitals involved in the S
  <sub>1</sub>←S
  <sub>0</sub> transition, which is predicted to be mainly a π–π* transition with a small charge transfer contribution from the ether oxygen to the phenyl ring. The latter leads to a slightly decreased electron density at the binding site for the methanol molecule and therefore weakens the hydrogen bond. These findings are in line with observations in previous studies on diphenyl ether–alcohol complexes [
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">20</a>–
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In principle, as the OH–O’ isomer has been identified in the S
  <sub>0</sub> state, the observation of a respective OH∙∙∙O-bound structure can be expected in the S
  <sub>1</sub> state as well. However, the OH–P isomers are predicted to be significantly stabilized in the S
  <sub>1</sub> state (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span> Table S2, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>). Nevertheless, due to the predicted red-shifts of the OH stretching frequencies of the OH–P isomers (indicating an increased hydrogen bond strength compared to the S
  <sub>0</sub> state), their presence, i.e., by a rearrangement reaction from the OH–O’ isomer, can be excluded. By exciting the electronic origin of the OH–O’ isomer the formation of OH–E isomers can also be excluded as their expected excitation energies are higher than the one for OH–O’ and in addition they are energetically less stable (cf
  <span class="italic">.</span> Table S2, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
