<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental Setup</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FTIR setup</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the FTIR experiments, the so-called filet-jet setup, as described in detail in [
   <a rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" href="#R49">49</a>], was used. In this setup, the scans of a Bruker IFS 66 v/s spectrometer (80 kHz, resolution 2 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) are synchronized to a pulsed supersonic expansion through a 600 × 0.2 mm
   <span class="sup">2</span> slit nozzle. Using two separate cooled saturators, low concentrations (&lt;0.1%) of PVE (Sigma-Aldrich, 97%, used as purchased) and methanol (Sigma-Aldrich, ≥99.8%, used as purchased) were added to the carrier gas helium (Linde, 99.996%) and premixed at a pressure of 0.75 bar in a 67 L reservoir before being expanded through the slit nozzle. The pulsed operation with waiting times of 30–90 s between 150 ms long pulses combined with a buffer volume of 12–23 m
   <span class="sup">3</span> and a pumping capacity of 500–2500 m
   <span class="sup">3</span>/h resulted in background pressures of less than 0.1 mbar before expansions. This facilitated measurements of clusters of methanol and PVE in the zone of silence of the expansion at an average distance of 10 mm to the nozzle. A calcium fluoride beam splitter, lenses and windows were used in combination with a 150 W tungsten filament and an optical filter (4200–2450 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) to maximize the signal-to-noise ratio in the OH stretching range of the vibrational spectra. For the final spectra, 150 to 775 pulses were co-added to further improve signal-to-noise.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">IR/UV setup</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental setup for the IR/UV experiments is described in detail elsewhere [
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">29</a>,
   <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">50</a>], thus only a brief description is given here. All experiments were carried out in a molecular beam apparatus consisting of a differentially pumped linear time-of-flight (TOF) mass spectrometer with a pulsed valve (Series 9 and pulse driver Iota One, General Valve, 500 µm orifice) for skimmed jet expansion. PVE was synthesized according to the procedure reported in [
   <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">51</a>] (cf. 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a> for details). MeOH (Sigma-Aldrich, ≥99.7%) and PVE were both supplied via separate cooled reservoirs (approx. −8 °C and −13 °C, respectively) and co-expanded with the carrier gas neon (2.5–3.0 bar).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the one- and two-color R2PI, the IR/R2PI and the UV/IR/UV experiments up to three tunable nanosecond laser systems were necessary, including two independent UV laser systems and one IR laser system. The UV laser radiation is obtained via second harmonic generation in a BBO crystal using the output of a dye laser (Cobra-Stretch and PrecisionScan, Sirah). They are pumped by the second harmonic (532 nm) of a Nd:YAG laser (SpitLight 600 and SpitLight 1000, Innolas). The IR laser radiation in the range of 3520–3750 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> is generated by difference frequency mixing (DFM) in a LiNbO
   <sub>3</sub> crystal using the fundamental (1064 nm) of a seeded Nd:YAG laser (Quanta-Ray Pro-230, Spectra-Physics) and the output of a further dye laser (PrecisionScan, Sirah), which is pumped by the second harmonic (532 nm) of the same Nd:YAG laser. Amplification of the resulting IR radiation is obtained by an optical parametric amplification (OPA) process in a further LiNbO
   <sub>3</sub> crystal using the output of the DFM process and the fundamental (1064 nm) of the Nd:YAG laser.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the IR/R2PI spectra, the IR laser was fired 50 ns prior to the UV excitation laser, whereas for the UV/IR/UV spectra the IR laser was fired 2.0–3.0 ns after the UV excitation laser. The time delay between UV excitation and ionizing laser was 4.0–4.5 ns.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CP-FTMW setup</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rotational spectroscopy measurements were performed with the Hamburg chirped-pulse Fourier transform microwave (CP-FTMW) spectrometer COMPACT covering the 2–8 GHz frequency range, which has been described in detail in [
   <a rid="R52" ref-type="bibr" href="#R52">52</a>]. The molecules were seeded into a supersonic expansion with neon as the carrier gas by using a pulse nozzle (Parker General Valve, Series 9, 0.9 mm diameter orifice) equipped with a heatable reservoir close to the valve orifice, operating at 8 Hz. PVE was synthesized as described above and used without further purification.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The liquid sample was held in the reservoir at room temperature, which resulted in sufficient vapor pressure (standard boiling point of about 155 °C) for recording the rotational spectrum. MeOH was kept in a separate reservoir. PVE–MeOH clusters were generated by first flowing the carrier gas (neon) through the reservoir containing methanol that was external to the chamber, followed by picking up PVE vapor. After supersonic expansion into vacuum using neon at 3 bar, the molecular jet was polarized with a 4 µs chirp spanning 2–8 GHz. The chirp was generated with an arbitrary waveform generator, amplified to 300 W with a traveling wave tube amplifier, and transmitted into the vacuum chamber via a horn antenna. Following excitation, 40 µs of the free induction decay (FID) of the macroscopic ensemble of polarized molecules was recorded. The fast frame capability [
   <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">53</a>] of the Tektronix DPO 71254C was used in which eight consecutive excitation chirps, each followed by 40 µs during which the FID could be collected, were recorded and averaged. This resulted in an effective repetition rate of 64 Hz.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the spectrum of the PVE–MeOH dimer, 3 million FIDs were co-added. A resulting signal-to-noise ratio of about 500:1 to 600:1 for the stronger transitions of the dominant complex allowed us to determine the positions of the carbon atoms with respect to the center of mass of the overall complex (see below) exploiting the presence of 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C isotopologues in natural abundance and using the Kraitchman approach [
   <a rid="R54" ref-type="bibr" href="#R54">54</a>]. Fourier transformation of the averaged time domain FID, recorded at point spacings of 10 ps, resulted in a frequency domain rotational spectrum with frequency resolution of 25 kHz.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The assignment was performed with the program JB95 [
   <a rid="R55" ref-type="bibr" href="#R55">55</a>], then the fits to an asymmetric-rotor Hamiltonian were performed using SPFIT/SPCAT. The experimental results were complemented by and compared with the results of electronic structure calculations. B3LYP-D3/aug-cc-pVTZ calculations were performed using the Gaussian 09, rev. D.01 program suite [
   <a rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" href="#R56">56</a>] to guide the assignment.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Computational Methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various input structures for the PVE–MeOH complex were generated by using the MMFF94s force field [
   <a rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" href="#R57">57</a>] as implemented in Avogadro [
   <a rid="R58" ref-type="bibr" href="#R58">58</a>]. Afterwards, geometry optimizations were performed by applying the Berny optimization algorithm of Gaussian 09 [
   <a rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" href="#R56">56</a>] with energies and gradients obtained from Turbomole 7.0 [
   <a rid="R59" ref-type="bibr" href="#R59">59</a>]. The DFT functional B3LYP with Grimme's two-body D3 corrections and Becke–Johnson damping [
   <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">45</a>] was used in combination with the def2-TZVP basis set based on the documented performance of this level of theory for the similar diphenyl ether–methanol system [
   <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">19</a>]. Furthermore, the obtained structures were re-optimized with the SCS-CC2 method using the def2-TZVP basis set, both in the electronic ground (S
   <sub>0</sub>) and first excited state (S
   <sub>1</sub>). The ricc2 module in Turbomole 7.0 requires an auxiliary Coulomb fitting basis set (cbas) for the resolution-of-identity approximation (RI) for which def2-TZVP-cbas was chosen [
   <a rid="R60" ref-type="bibr" href="#R60">60</a>]. All obtained geometries were confirmed as minima by harmonic frequency calculations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the relative stability of the different conformers found on the potential hypersurface, density fitted explicitly correlated local coupled cluster with singles and doubles excitations and perturbative triples (DF-LCCSD(T0)-F12) calculations were carried out [
   <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">47</a>]. In order to converge the energies relative to the one particle basis, the VTZ-F12 and VQZ-F12 basis sets [
   <a rid="R61" ref-type="bibr" href="#R61">61</a>–
   <a rid="R62" ref-type="bibr" href="#R62">62</a>] were used together with a Schwenke style basis set extrapolation, as proposed in [
   <a rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" href="#R63">63</a>]. The orbitals were Pipek–Mezey [
   <a rid="R64" ref-type="bibr" href="#R64">64</a>] localized and orbital domains determined by natural population analysis with a threshold of TNPA = 0.03 [
   <a rid="R65" ref-type="bibr" href="#R65">65</a>]. Defaults were used for the pair classification, with all pairs included in the F12 treatment. Furthermore, the intermolecular pairs were classified as strong (meaning that they were treated at the highest level of theory). The latter method will be denoted as LCCSD(T0)-F12/CBS[T:Q]. In all correlated calculations the 1s electrons were removed from the treatment (frozen-core approximation). Furthermore, we analyzed the relative impact of dispersion interactions in the different complexes through a local orbital analysis of the CCSD (connected) doubles energy terms. The latter discussion is complemented with dispersion interaction density (DID) plots [
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>]. The coupled cluster calculations were carried out with Molpro 2015.1 [
   <a rid="R66" ref-type="bibr" href="#R66">66</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
