<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FTIR spectroscopy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of an FTIR exploration of the conformational diversity of this system are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>. Besides methanol monomer, methanol dimer and a signal clearly attributed to a larger cluster, only a single, reasonably narrow absorption at 3625 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> is observed. It can be attributed to mixed dimers of MeOH with PVE and allows for a single rigorous conclusion, due to the linearity of the technique and the comparable IR absorption cross section of all predicted dimer conformations (cf. 
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a> and Table S1, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Supporting Information File 1</a>): the global minimum structure and any other, higher lying isomers which are initially formed and impeded from relaxation to the global minimum due to broad or high interconversion barriers must have their OH stretching fundamental at 3625 ± 5 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> or be significantly less abundant.
 </p>
 <div id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>FTIR spectra of the supersonic expansion of methanol (MeOH) and phenyl vinyl ether (PVE) at different concentrations in helium. The spectra are spread out along the ordinate to improve visualization. Only one dominant mixed dimer band is visible in the spectra, lying at 3625 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span> (marked MeOH + PVE) between the methanol monomer at 3686 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span> (MeOH) and methanol dimer at 3575 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span> ((MeOH)
    <sub>2</sub>). By comparing the spectrum at the top with the other two spectra recorded at reduced concentrations of methanol (middle) or methanol and PVE (bottom), the further downshifted band at 3466 cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span> can be attributed to a higher cluster, probably a methanol-rich mixed trimer ((MeOH)
    <sub>2</sub> + PVE (?)), due to its scaling with the variation of the concentrations.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="Beilstein_J_Org_Chem-14-1642-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If one were to trust the relative harmonic wavenumber predictions from the preceding subsection (cf. 
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>), this would imply a single docking motif, as different docking motifs are predicted to lead to larger spectral separations. However, different extents of anharmonicity do not allow to completely ruling out overlapping docking motifs. Therefore, conformationally selective methods are desirable to investigate this possibility. Finally, the actual docking site has to be identified by structural or electronic excitation spectroscopy.
 </p>
</sec>
