<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The balance of different noncovalent interactions is crucial for chemical and biochemical processes as it controls molecular recognition and aggregation [
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">1</a>–
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">6</a>]. In order to gain a deeper understanding of these processes, knowledge on exact structural arrangements and the respective role of different intermolecular forces such as electrostatic, dispersion and induction forces is needed. Thus, experimental examination as well as the precise prediction of a preferred molecular docking site for different molecules is of crucial importance. Despite the remarkable progress made in experiments and theory/computational chemistry, there is still a need for improvement and benchmarking [
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many aromatic solute–solvent complexes have been studied in the gas phase (cf. [
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">8</a>–
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">10</a>] and references therein). Studied systems involving methanol as attached solvent molecule include the works on benzene–methanol clusters by the Zwier group [
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">11</a>] and on fluorobenzene–methanol clusters by the Brutschy group [
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">12</a>], to mention only two examples. Complexes of aromatic ethers with polar solvent molecules are of special interest due to the presence of different competing hydrogen bond acceptor sites. An extensive study on diphenoxyethane–water clusters was performed by the Zwier group [
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">13</a>–
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">15</a>] including studies in the excited S
  <sub>1</sub> and S
  <sub>2</sub> states. Concerning aggregates of aromatic ethers with alcohols, there is a work of Pietraperzia et al. [
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">16</a>] on the anisole–phenol complex in which an OH∙∙∙O structure was identified. In a systematic study by the Suhm group on complexes of anisole derivatives with methanol, a balance between OH∙∙∙O and OH∙∙∙π structures being very sensitive to the substitution pattern at the anisole moiety was identified [
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">17</a>–
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">18</a>]. In previous multi-spectroscopic studies by the Schnell, Suhm and Gerhards groups on diphenyl ether (DPE)–solvent complexes [
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">19</a>–
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">22</a>], the influence of different attached solvent molecules on the structural preference was compared. It could be shown that the balance between OH∙∙∙π- and OH∙∙∙O-bound structures is very sensitive to the size of the attached alcohol. Torsional balances in solution have been used to probe aromatic OH∙∙∙π interactions and to show that these interactions remain important at room temperature [
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In such aromatic solute–solvent systems, one frequently encounters hydrogen bonds formed towards oxygen or nitrogen lone pairs, or R–H∙∙∙π binding motifs (R = O, N, C, S,…) involving aromatic π systems. Less often, R–H∙∙∙π bound complexes are found involving nonconjugated, localized C=C double bonds. Exceptions include the ethene–methanol complex [
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">24</a>] as well as bulky olefin–
  <span class="italic">tert</span>-butyl alcohol complexes [
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">25</a>] investigated by jet FTIR spectroscopy. The observed OH stretching red-shifts compared to the free alcohols are small, indicating a comparatively weak hydrogen bond, which is also reflected in calculated binding energies [
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">24</a>–
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the herein presented work, we now extend our overall multi-spectroscopic study to mixed aromatic olefinic ethers: in the case of phenyl vinyl ether (PVE), there is an ethenyl moiety replacing one of the phenyl rings compared to DPE. This introduces a localized π system along with the delocalized phenyl π system as hydrogen bond acceptor sites. Thereby, the complexity of the system is increased, as now three qualitatively different basic binding motifs have to be regarded instead of only two for DPE. This also provides an enhanced challenge for theory, with no clear preference for one of the motifs to be expected. As shown, e.g., in the case of DPE–
  <span class="italic">t</span>-BuOH [
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">20</a>], there is a need for benchmarking systems in order to improve and develop better theoretical approaches especially for non-covalently bound complexes. The study on PVE–MeOH is meant to present a further benchmark system, probably even more challenging than DPE–
  <span class="italic">t</span>-BuOH.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For an experimental elucidation of structural arrangements and energetic preferences, investigations on a molecular level are required on isolated molecular aggregates, allowing for an ideal comparison with gas phase calculations. This can be achieved by molecular beam experiments, which can be combined with a variety of spectroscopic techniques. For our multi-spectroscopic studies, we utilize FTIR spectroscopy, mass- and isomer-selective IR/UV techniques (IR/R2PI, for methodical developments, cf., e.g., [
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">8</a>,
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">26</a>–
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">29</a>] and UV/IR/UV spectroscopy, cf., e.g., [
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">30</a>–
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">43</a>]) and chirped-pulse Fourier transform microwave (CP-FTMW) spectroscopy. Comparing spectroscopic results with quantum-chemical calculations is often mandatory for the interpretation of experiments. Furthermore, such comparison enables a critical evaluation of the approximations used, comparing the relative stability of different binding motifs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, the first structural investigation on the complex of phenyl vinyl ether with methanol is presented. An established multi-spectroscopic approach [
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">19</a>–
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">20</a>] is used, coupling FTIR, IR/UV and microwave spectroscopy with theoretical treatments including dispersion-corrected density functional theory (DFT-D3) [
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">44</a>–
  <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">45</a>], spin-component-scaled approximated coupled cluster-singles-doubles (SCS-CC2) [
  <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">46</a>] as well as explicitly correlated local coupled cluster theory (LCCSD(T0)-F12) [
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">47</a>] calculations, the latter allowing for a quantification and visualization of London dispersion interactions [
  <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>]. The aim of the presented study is the unambiguous experimental identification of the preferred binding site of a first methanol solvent molecule to the multivalent hydrogen bond scaffold of phenyl vinyl ether, followed by a classification of theoretical methods in terms of success or failure to predict this preference. Visualization of possible reasons for the subtle preference is a valuable additional asset.
 </p>
</sec>
