<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6620477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">46277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-46277-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Preparation of the heterojunction catalyst N-doping carbon quantum dots/P25 and its visible light photocatalytic activity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Ning</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Hongqin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9371-6988</contrib-id><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Huigang</given-names></name><address><email>zdwhg@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0574 8737</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413273.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry, </institution><institution>Zhejiang Sci-Tech University, </institution></institution-wrap>Hangzhou, 310018 P. R. China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>9971</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">N-doping carbon quantum dots were successfully loaded on P25 nanoparticles (denoted as N-CDs/P25) by facile hydrothermal process, and their morphology and chemical structure were systematically studied. The carrier of N-CDs can significantly broaden the photoresponse range of the P25 to the visible region, accelerate charge transportation and separation. Application of the N-CDs/P25 material for the photocatalytic decomposition of Rhodamine B (RhB) gave improved activity relative to P25. The best degradation activity obtained at 6mL N-CDs/P25 under visible light irradiation, which shows a 13.06 fold photocatalytic activity over P25. Radical trapping control experiment and Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR) measurements have been applied to explore the photodegradation dynamic and visible-light driven degradation mechanism. This work provides new insights into the fabrication of N-doping carbon quantum dots/TiO<sub>2</sub> composite and is promising to open new possibilities in the application of carbon-TiO<sub>2</sub> composites as the photocatalysts in the environmental protection issues.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Nanoparticles</kwd><kwd>Pollution remediation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100004731</institution-id><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province (Zhejiang Provincial Natural Science Foundation)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>LZ17B030001</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Huigang</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100005156</institution-id><institution>Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung (Alexander von Humboldt Foundation)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">TiO<sub>2</sub> are the most widely explored semiconductor photocatalysts in environmental pollutants treatment and solar-energy conversion area in these latest decades for their superior photocatalytic activity, nontoxicity, long-term stability and low cost<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Degussa (Evonik) P25 is a biphasic titanium dioxide that owns especially high photocatalytic activity due to its special biphasic interfacial heterojunction structure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. It contains more than 80% anatase with a minor amount of rutile (15%) and a small amount of amorphous phase with approximately 20&#x02009;nm particle size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Interfaces between rutile and anatase phase facilitate charge carrier separation and retard the charge recombination between electron trapping sites within the mixed phase so as to improve photocatalytic activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>; Therefore P25 is prevailing used in laboratory for photocatalytic reaction systems. However, P25 have its own inherent weakness, for example, the large band gap limited its response wavelengths in the UV region, lower absorption volume and slower electronic mobility limited its energy conversion efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. A strategy we can take is the combination of the photoactive P25 nanoparticle with visible light adsorptive conductor. Not only does this provide visible light sensitizer and electron trapping sites, extend its photoresponse wavelength to visible region, it also ensures relative fast electronic transportation to the reaction interface that is beneficial to charge separation, enhance the conversion efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Carbon quantum dots (CDs) are zero dimensional nanocarbon material less than 10&#x02009;nm in diameter, formed by crystalline graphitic sp<sup>2</sup>-bonded carbon atoms, which have a quantum confinement effect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Apart from its unique electronic attributes, the quasi-spherical nanocarbon material possess several other attractive advantages, such as the large specific surface area, high stability, low toxicity, simple synthetic routes and the strong and tunable fluorescence emission properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Based on those novel properties, therefore, the couple of P25 and CDs is anticipated to simultaneously have high photo activity, excellent adsorptivity, good electronic mobility and good cost-efficiency, therefore enhancing the photocatalytic decomposition abilities of pollutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Herein we demonstrated a facile route to prepare a chemically bonded N-doping carbon quantum dots/P25 composite via hydrothermal method that is illustrated in Scheme 1. The as-prepared composites own several advantages over other catalysts: the enhanced adsorptive ability of pollutants, fast charge conductivity and separation, extended light absorption range. The factors of particle size, chemical composition, and the CDs content in N-CDs/P25 that may influence the catalytic performance were systematically discussed. The as synthesized N-CDs/P25 composites show higher photocatalytic activity in the degradation of Rhodamine B (RhB) over the commercial P25 catalysts under visible light illumination. Finally based on trapping control experiment and Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR) measurements, we proposed one feasible visible-light driven degradation mechanism.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Experimental Sections</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Synthesis of N-CDs quantum dots</title><p id="Par4">Experimental procedure of N-CDs fabrication have been reported elsewhere in the literature and here cited with minor modifications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Typically 4&#x02009;mmol citric acid and 12&#x02009;mmol urea were dissolved together in 20&#x02009;ml distilled water, and then poured into a 100&#x02009;ml Teflon lined hydrothermal reaction vessel. The reaction take place at 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and kept for 8&#x02009;hours. Then Cool to ambient temperature and adjusting the pH to 7. Centrifuge to get a dark yellowish N-CDs solution. The solution was put in a dialysis tube (keep molecular weight: 500&#x02009;Da~3500&#x02009;Da) for 4 days in the dark (changed deionized water every 8&#x02009;h). Concentration to 20&#x02009;mL.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Synthesis of N-CDs/P25 composites</title><p id="Par5">N-CDs/P25 was synthesized via a hydrothermal deposition process. Typically, 0.2&#x02009;g P25 was put into certain volume of as-prepared N-CDs solution and added 40&#x02009;mL more water, mixed and transferred to a dried Teflon-lined hydrothermal reaction vessel, heated to 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and kept for 6&#x02009;hours. After cooling down the mixture were then centrifuged at 8000r/min to collect the final product. The samples were named according to the added volume of N-CDs as (2&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25, (4&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25, (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25, (8&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25 and (10&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Photocatalytic performance evaluation</title><p id="Par6">The photodegradation of Rhodamine B (RhB) were chosen as model reaction to evaluation the photocatalytic activities of the as synthesized material under visible light irradiation. Xenon lamp with a &#x0003c;400&#x02009;nm cutoff filter was used as the photo source to mimic the nature solar irradiation. Generally, a 150&#x02009;mL quartz reactor were equipped with a thermostat to keep the degradation temperature at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, in which put 10&#x02009;mg/L RhB100 mL. Into the RhB solution added 50&#x02009;mg catalysts. Keep the mixture in the dark for 30&#x02009;min to make sure the catalysts saturated with the adsorption of RhB. Turn on the lamp to start the photocatalytic reaction and accumulate the irradiation time. To trace the dynamic concentration changes of the RhB 3&#x02009;mL of the mixture each time was taken out from the reactant at regular intervals. The concentration was obtained by UV-VIS measurements.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p id="Par7">The synthetic route for N-CDs/P25 composites is depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Firstly citric acid was carbonized with hydrothermal process to form N-doped CDs and was purified through centrifugation and dialysis. Then mixed the N-CDs solution and P25 with hydrothermal reaction, Ti-OH on the surface of P25 dehydrates easily with the C-OH groups on the N-CDs surfaces, chemically formation of the N-CDs/P25 composites.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Illustration of procedures for preparation of the photocatalysts N-CDs/P25 by hydrothermal deposition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e337"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">XRD were carried out to study the crystallographic phase structures of the as prepared catalysts. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the measured XRD measurements of N-CDs, P25 and N-CDs/P25 respectively. The bottom curve at 21 tin Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> occurs a broad peak, which is assigned as the (002) crystal plane of graphite. The measured interlamellar spacing of as-synthesized N-CDs is bigger than that of graphite. the nitrogen-containing groups introduced into the interlayer space may account for this effects.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>XRD spectra of N-CDs, P25 and N-CDs/P25. &#x025c6; stands for anatase, &#x025c7; for rutile.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e354"/></fig></p><p id="Par9">Meanwhile the composites (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25 in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows that no N-CDs peak was detected; this may be attributed to the situation that the C quantum dots is greatly scattered on P25 nanoparticles. In addition the low doping content of C quantum dots is another factor that caused the disappearance of N-CDs signals in the XRD measurement.</p><p id="Par10">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> also shows, the diffraction pattern for (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25 and P25 are identical, matching well with the standard mixture phase of anatase and rutile-phase TiO<sub>2</sub> (JCPDS No. 84-1286 and No. 88-1175), indicating the coexists of the anatase and rutile phase in the N-CDs/P25 catalysts, the incorporation of N-CDs on the surface of TiO<sub>2</sub> haven&#x02019;t change the crystal structure of P25 powders.</p><p id="Par11">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref> shows that the size of N-CDs nanoparticles is uniform and high dispersed. The particle size is approximately 3&#x02009;nm in diameter. Inset of Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref> is the N-CDs nanoparticles&#x02019; high resolution image, it indicates that the lattices of N-CDs is 0.242&#x02009;nm. Reference assigned these lattices to the N-CDs sp<sup>2</sup> clusters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref> shows the TEM image of pure P25, the average diameter is about 20&#x02013;30&#x02009;nm. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref> is the TEM measurement of the N-CDs/P25 catalysts; it demonstrates that the N-CDs are highly dispersed on P25. This uniformly distribution may result from our superiority of hydrothermal deposition procedure: crucial homogeneously filled hydro vapor pressure and the monodispersed spatial confined P25 surfaces.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>TEM measurements of (<bold>a</bold>) N-CDs (Inset is the high resolution image) (<bold>b</bold>) P25 (<bold>c</bold>) N-CDs/P25 (Inset is the high resolution image).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e410"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) measurement was carried out for N-CDs and N-CDs/P25 to determine the valence states of the related elements, and the results are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Survey scan in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref> suggests that the samples of our synthesized N-CDs or N-CDs/P25 both contain Oxygen, Nitrogen and Carbon elements. XPS of N-CDs/P25 indicates the existence of Ti 2p coming from TiO<sub>2</sub>. Moreover, inset of Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref> shows the wide scan oxidation state of the Ti in N-CDs/P25. Two distinct bands located at 459.08&#x02009;eV and 465.08&#x02009;eV are assigned to the Ti2p3/2 and Ti2p1/2 signals in the Ti<sup>4+</sup> valence state, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Because of the small size of CDs (&#x0003c;3&#x02009;nm), the XPS can reach more than the whole CDs particles, so the collected XPS spectrum origins from the whole catalysts, rather than the surface alone.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>XPS characterization of N-CDs and N-CDs/P25. (<bold>a</bold>) full survey scan XPS pattern, (<bold>b</bold>) C 1&#x02009;s narrow scan XPS spectra and (<bold>c</bold>) O 1&#x02009;s narrow scan high resolution XPS spectra (<bold>d</bold>) N 1&#x02009;s narrow scan XPS spectra.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e453"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">The XPS spectra and deconvoluted fitted peaks for C,O and N were shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b&#x02013;d</xref>, respectively. The C 1&#x02009;s XPS spectrum shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref> was deconvoluted fitted as four peaks: The binding energy observed at 285.88&#x02009;eV was attributed to C&#x02013;O group, binding energy at 288.78&#x02009;eV was assigned as the C=O carbonyl group, energy at 285.18&#x02009;eV ascribed to C-N, the peak at 284.58&#x02009;eV comes from the C&#x02013;H/C=C/C&#x02013;C group. The above deconvoluted fitted spectra indicate that N-CDs and N-CDs/P25 composites are rich of O element and N element. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows that the intensity of O signal in the C XPS spectrum decreased for N-CDs/P25 relative to N-CDs, which means that P25 have been covered by N-CDs. The XPS pattern of O 1&#x02009;s shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref> indicates the great difference between N-CDs and N-CDs/P25. N-CDs in top panel of Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref> shows, the binding energy at 533.59&#x02009;eV ascribed to the C-O and -OH, deconvoluted peak at 532.07&#x02009;eV were related to carbonyl group, after integration with P25, as bottom panel shows, these peaks were shifted towards lower order values. 529.68&#x02009;eV for Ti-O, 530.08&#x02009;eV for carbonyl group, 532.08&#x02009;eV for C-O and -OH, respectively. The above comparisons in XPS spectra demonstrate the strong interaction between the TiO<sub>2</sub> and C after the solvothermal process and further confirm the successful integration of N-CDs on P25. The N 1&#x02009;s peaks detected at 400.08 and 401.78&#x02009;eV in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref> demonstrate that N element presents primary in N-H (401.78&#x02009;eV) or N-C(400.08&#x02009;eV) style, respectively, either on the N-CDs or N-CDs/P25. Specifically there is no C&#x02212;Ti peak detected, which means N-CDs integrated to P25 were not directly trough C&#x02013;Ti bond, but takes the form of Ti-O-C.</p><p id="Par14">200&#x02013;800&#x02009;nm absorption spectrum of N-CDs solution and the pictures of N-CDs illuminated under visible light and 365&#x02009;nm light are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>. &#x003c0;&#x02013;&#x003c0;* transition of C=C bonds absorbs strong band center around 228&#x02009;nm region wavelength and n&#x02013;&#x003c0;* transitions of C=O and C=N bonds shows weak wide absorption ranging from 280&#x02009;nm to 450&#x02009;nm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Any excitation light sited between this wide absorption range can resonant with the electron and excite it to the S1 state, so light wavelength from 280&#x02009;nm to 450&#x02009;nm can excite to produce the photoluminescent emission of the N-CDs. It is well known that N-doping carbon quantum dots-based materials have one characteristic property, that is, fluorescence spectra is dependent on the excitation wavelength<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The N-CDs dispersion displays yellow color by nature light irradiation but blue color by a 365&#x02009;nm light illumination as is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> right panel.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>UV-vis Spectra (<bold>a</bold>) Absorption spectrum of N-CDs dispersion (Include the pictures of N-CDs dispersion taken under nature solar light and 365&#x02009;nm light illumination respectively). (<bold>b</bold>) Comparison of UV-vis diffuse reflectance spectra of various as prepared N-CDs/P25 nanoparticles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e508"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref> demonstrates the UV-vis DRS spectra of P25 and N-CDs/P25 catalysts. They all show strong absorption in the UV region, while only the N-CDs/P25 have medium absorption band across the whole visible light region, among which (6&#x02009;mL) N-CDs/P25 has the highest visible light absorption intensity. Obviously the absorption edge for N-CDs/P25 shows a red shift relative to P25. This phenomenon of visible region absorption band and absorption edge red shift can be explained by the fact of N-doping CDs deposition on the catalysts, decreased the light reflection.</p><p id="Par16">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref> shows a series of fluorescence spectra of as synthesized N doping C quantum dots pictured by different excitation wavelengths with their intensity normalized. The broad fluorescence spectra range from 350&#x02009;nm to 550&#x02009;nm. In addition, the emission spectra show typical excitation laser wavelength dependent property, which suggests its complicate energy band composition, either in ground state or excited band. The XPS detected carbonyl and C-N groups in N-CDs will influence the energy band structures of C-dots sp<sup>2</sup> kernel and introduce additional energy stage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. These multiple electronic structures mix together and result in multiple electronic transition possibilities, broaden the absorption range. The probability of each transition is depends on the excitation wavelength. The excited electrons come back to their own ground state with radiative transition, producing multiple fluorescence emissions. The weights of excited resonant electrons satisfy Gaussian distribution, centered with excitation laser wavelength. The weight of each transition is dependent on the excitation laser, correspondingly the weight of each fluorescence emissions also changes with the excitation wavelength, result in the wavelengths dependent properties. It is well known that doping of the N element in C dots can reduce the band gap. Furthermore, the chemical linking of N to C will introduce additional energy level that can trap the e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02013;h<sup>+</sup> pairs, thus prolong the lifetime of separate e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02013;h<sup>+</sup> pairs, spare enough time for separated e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> conduct to other chemical reaction path. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref> demonstrates that the fluorescence intensity of P25 decreases after the doting of N-CDs, it means the doting process have altered the electron radiative path and quenched the fluorescence.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Emission fluorescence spectra of N-CDs in water excited with series laser wavelengths, Intensity were normalized for better comparison. (<bold>b</bold>) Fluorescence spectra of P25 and (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e559"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">Rhodamine B(RhB) is one kind of the important dyes that has been popular applied in industrial application, which forms the pollutions to environments. In this article the degradation of RhB was chosen as the model reaction. The photocatalytic performance was compared among N-CDs<bold>/</bold>P25 photocatalysts, N-CDs and P25. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> shows the concentration changes of RhB with degradation time. No RhB self degradation was observed under visible light irradiation(400~780&#x02009;nm). In addition there is no obvious RhB degradation either under visible light irradiation over N-CD catalysts. Approximately 30% concentration decrease was observed over P25 within 90&#x02009;minutes. In contrast, the N-CDs/P25 catalysts showed higher visible-light degradation activity. Specially the RhB were completely removed by (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25 within 90&#x02009;minutes. It is interestingly to stress that the RhB removal activity increases with the series of N-CDs from 2&#x02009;mL to 6&#x02009;mL. However, further increasing the loading content will decrease the catalytic performance. The linear fitting of ln(C/C<sub>0</sub>) versus time (see in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>) based on the simplified Langmuir-Hinshelwood model suggests that the RhB removal dynamics obeys a first order kinetic. The apparent rate constant (k) obtained from the linear fitting were shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8b</xref>. The highest k is obtained from (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/TNS catalyst, approximately k&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.029&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which is 13.06 folds photocatalytic activity improvement over P25 (k&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00385&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The obtained apparent rates constants suggest that there is a optimal N-CDs loading content on P25 for optimize the photocatalytic performance. The integration of N-CDs on P25 gives the photocatalysts several prominent features: improved catalysts adaptability, increased adsorption ability of pollutants, extension of light absorption edge to visible region and prolonged lifetime of photo generated electron-hole pair.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The dynamic photocatalytic degradation of RhB vs time with the visible light illumination.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e596"/></fig><fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Kinetic fitting using First order reaction function. (<bold>b</bold>) The obtained apparent k for as-prepared photocatalysts with different N-CDs content.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e611"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">To better understanding the photodegradation mechanism, especially to know what kind of reactive mediums that triggered the light induced degradation and which one be responsible for the whole kinetic photodegradation process, another experiment should be done by introducing specific radical scavenger in reaction system before the photo reaction starts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Generally tert-Butanol (TBA) can trap OH radicals, benzoquinone (BQ) can capture O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> radicals, EDTA-2Na is a holes scavengers and AgNO<sub>3</sub> is an electrons scavenger. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> shows that, the RhB degradation under visible light irradiation was significantly suppressed when BQ(O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> scavenger) or EDTA-2Na(holes scavenger) was added to the reactant. In contrast, the RhB degradation was slightly suppressed when TBA was added. This indicated that the <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${}^{.}{\rm{O}}_{2}^{-}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mprescripts/><mml:none/><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> radical&#x000b7;OH radical and h<sup>+</sup> could be the mostly possible reactive species in the photo degradation process.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Active species capture experiment for (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25 by the addition of different scavenges.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig9_HTML" id="d29e670"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">Moreover the electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) measurements were performed to demonstrate the reactive radicals that may take charges of the degradation of RhB. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10a</xref> shows the DMPO spin trapping spectra of (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25 dispersed in water upon continuous laser illumination, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10b</xref> shows the compared spectra dispersed in CH<sub>3</sub>OH. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10a</xref> indicates no characteristic signals, which suggests no DMPO-<inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${}^{\cdot }{\rm{O}}{\rm{H}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:none/><mml:none/><mml:mprescripts/><mml:none/><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> adducts in water solution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10b</xref> shows four signals with equal intensity. These pattern of signals are typical feature for the 5,5-dimethyl-1-pyrrolidone-2-oxyl (&#x02022;DMPO-X, ie O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;&#x02022;</sup>/&#x02022;OOH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>), demonstrating the formation of DMPO-<inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${}^{\cdot }{\rm{O}}_{2}^{-}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mprescripts/><mml:none/><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. This experiment verifies that <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${}^{\cdot }{\rm{O}}_{2}^{-}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mprescripts/><mml:none/><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo></mml:mmultiscripts></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the most important active redicals that created with continuous laser illumination and take charge of the photo degradation process, which is in consistency with the scavenges experiments shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>.<fig id="Fig10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>EPR spins trapping spectra for N-CDs/P25 in water (a panel) and in methanol (b panel) under visible light irradiation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig10_HTML" id="d29e775"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">The CVs photogram of N-CDs were shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11a</xref>. The electrochemical behavior is reversible. From the Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11a</xref> we can get the reduction potential value is &#x02212;0.61&#x02009;V. with the equation E<sub>LUMO</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;e (E<sub>red</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;4.4) we can get the LUMO energy is &#x02212;3.79&#x02009;V, which is in consistency with the reference reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Based on the UV&#x02013;VIS DRS spectra shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and LUMO energy, the HOMO energy can be known E<sub>HOMO</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;6.81&#x02009;V. Z-scheme can be drawn based on the energy data, according to the further active trapping results (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11b</xref>). The visible light induced dynamic pathway of electron can be described using Z-scheme heterojunction structures as following: the N-CDs electron in HOMO was excited to LUMO by visible light irradiation. Meanwhile, P25 can absorber the 400&#x02009;nm light and the electrons are excited to the CB state due to the weak absorption &#x0201c;tail&#x0201d;. Moreover the RhB dye self-sensitization on surface of photocatalysts also lowered the band gap of p25 and favors the visible light absorption. In sum, the ground electrons on both sides could be excited by visible light to produce e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>h<sup>+</sup> separation couple. Then the produced e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> in LUMO orbital can annihilate the h<sup>+</sup> in VB of P25, the e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> in CB of P25 and the h<sup>+</sup> carriers in HOMO of CDs were spatially separated. This process favors the e<sup>&#x02212;</sup> accumulation on P25 rather radiative transition to VB. Because no h<sup>+</sup> are remaining on P25, much longer lifetimes of the hot electrons on the CB could be expected, thus increase the probability to reduce the O<sub>2</sub> adsorbed on the P25 and helps the photo degradation of RhB. In the meantime, the h<sup>+</sup> carriers of N-CDs HOMO orbital may attack directly the dye pollutions, or react with H<sub>2</sub>O to form <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${}^{\cdot }{\rm{O}}{\rm{H}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">O</mml:mi><mml:none/><mml:none/><mml:mprescripts/><mml:none/><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Sum up, the Z-scheme heterojunction structure favors the separation of the photo induced electron&#x02013;hole pairs, with the enhanced photocatalytic activity for N-CDs/P25.<fig id="Fig11"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) cyclic Voltammetry curves (CVs) of N-CDs. (<bold>b</bold>) The proposed photo induced electron dynamic pathway of N-CDs/P25 with vis-light irradiation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig11_HTML" id="d29e872"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">The stability and recyclability of the catalysts have been carried out and the results have been shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>. The degradation efficiency of RhB exhibits high stability after 5 successive continuously recycles of the catalysts under identical conditions. Intrinsic biphasic structure of P25, the application of most affinity force size of the N-CDs and the strong interaction between the P25 and N-CDs heterojunction may account for this superior catalytic stability.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>The catalysts stability measurement of (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/P25.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46277_Fig12_HTML" id="d29e886"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par22">Overall, the TiO<sub>2</sub> nanoparticles loaded with N doping carbon quantum dots-N-CDs/P25 composites-were synthesis using hydrothermal method to extend their photoresponse range and improve photocatalytic stability. Our results showed that the precipitation of N-CDs on P25 could considerably enhance the visible-light photocatalytic activity of P25. The screened best catalyst is (6&#x02009;mL)N-CDs/TNS, its degradation rate constant was found to be 13.06 folds of pure P25. TEM confirmed the as prepared N-CDs/P25 composites structure; the N-CDs are spherical and highly dispersed with a mean size of approximately 3&#x02009;nm. UV-vis DRS spectra verified the efficient absorption edge extension from UV to visible light region. XPS measurements proved that the N-CDs have been chemically bonded to P25 by C-O-Ti. The high photocatalytic can be attributed to the synergistic effects of the Z-scheme structure, the biphasic heterojunction of P25, the extension of visible light absorption edge, and the prolonged e<sup>&#x02212;</sup>h<sup>+</sup> separation lifetime. The as-prepared N-CDs/P25 catalyst is anticipated to be applied in photocatalysis water treatment, photocatalytic synthesis, solar cells and sensors etc.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The research was funded by the Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang province, China (LZ17B030001) and National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 21873084 and 21473161).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Ning Xu and Hongqin Huang synthesize the photo catalysts and the catalysts characterization. Hao Ouyang conducted the photodegradation experiment. Huigang Wang wrote the main manuscript text and responsible for the whole research work.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par23">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shayegan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghighat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TiO<sub>2</sub> photocatalyst for removal of volatile organic compounds in gas phase - A review</article-title><source>Chemical Engineering Journal</source><year>2018</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>2408</fpage><lpage>2439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2017.09.153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalan</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaparatne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amirbahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripp</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>P25 titanium dioxide coated magnetic particles: Preparation, characterization and photocatalytic activity</article-title><source>Applied Catalysis B-Environmental</source><year>2016</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2016.01.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unprecedentedly enhanced solar photocatalytic activity of a layered titanate simply integrated with TiO<sub>2</sub> nanoparticles</article-title><source>Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>30920</fpage><lpage>30925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c6cp05635k</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27711734?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27711734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phongamwong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel visible-light-sensitized Chl-Mg/P25 catalysts for photocatalytic degradation of rhodamine B</article-title><source>Applied Catalysis B-Environmental</source><year>2017</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2017.02.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajashekhar</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Devi</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphic phase transformation of Degussa P25 TiO<sub>2</sub> by the chelation of diaminopyridine on TiO62- octahedron: Correlation of anatase to rutile phase ratio on the photocatalytic activity</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Catalysis a-Chemical</source><year>2013</year><volume>374</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcata.2013.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayarangamuthu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>K-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low Frequency Ultrasonication of Degussa P25 TiO<sub>2</sub> and Its Superior Photocatalytic Properties</article-title><source>Journal of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>4399</fpage><lpage>4404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1166/jnn.2016.10994</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27483763?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27483763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeredla</surname><given-names>Rakesh R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Huifang</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An investigation of nanostructured rutile and anatase plates for improving the photosplitting of water</article-title><source>Nanotechnology</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>055706</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0957-4484/19/05/055706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21817620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rui</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of TiO<sub>2</sub> Degussa P25 with anatase and rutile crystalline phases for methane combustion</article-title><source>Chemical Engineering Journal</source><year>2014</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2014.01.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on Morphological Distribution of Photogenerated Superoxide Radicals Produced by Different Crystal Titanium Dioxide</article-title><source>Chinese Journal of Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2017</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1882</fpage><lpage>1887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11895/j.issn.0253-3820.171378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anatase and rutile in evonik aeroxide P25: Heterojunctioned or individual nanoparticles?</article-title><source>Catalysis Today</source><year>2018</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cattod.2017.06.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Prajapat</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly photoactive Au-TiO<sub>2</sub> nanowires for improved photo-degradation of propiconazole fungicide under UV/sunlight irradiation</article-title><source>Solar Energy</source><year>2017</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.solener.2017.02.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganeshraja</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One-pot synthesis visible-light-active TiO<sub>2</sub> photocatalysts at low temperature by peroxotitanium complex</article-title><source>Journal of Alloys and Compounds</source><year>2018</year><volume>765</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jallcom.2018.06.227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Facile in-suit synthesis of Ag/AgVO<sub>3</sub> one-dimensional hybrid nanoribbons with enhanced performance of plasmonic visible-light photocatalysis</article-title><source>Applied Catalysis B-Environmental</source><year>2015</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2014.08.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sillenite-type Bi<sub>12</sub>MnO<sub>20</sub> photocatalyst: UV, visible and infrared lights responsive photocatalytic properties induced by the hybridization of Mn 3d and O 2p orbitals</article-title><source>Applied Catalysis B-Environmental</source><year>2017</year><volume>219</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2017.07.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of Charge Separation and Frontier Orbital Structure in Graphitic Carbon Nitride and Graphene Quantum Dots</article-title><source>Chemphyschem</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2534</fpage><lpage>2539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cphc.201800451</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30019383?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30019383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>TTY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>F-X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Graphene quantum dots (GQDs) and its derivatives for multifarious photocatalysis and photoelectrocatalysis</article-title><source>Catalysis Today</source><year>2018</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cattod.2018.01.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OD/2D interface engineering of carbon quantum dots modified Bi<sub>2</sub>WO<sub>6</sub> ultrathin nanosheets with enhanced photoactivity for full spectrum light utilization and mechanism insight</article-title><source>Applied Catalysis B-Environmental</source><year>2018</year><volume>222</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2017.10.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>KQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving the Efficiency of Carbon Quantum Dots as a Visible Light Photosensitizer by Polyamine Interfacial Modification</article-title><source>Acta Phys.-Chim. Sin.</source><year>2018</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3866/pku.whxb201710162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>Yong-Qiang</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Shao-Zhao</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Guoyang</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Jiangtao</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yating</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Jieshan</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrochemical and Capacitive Properties of Carbon Dots/Reduced Graphene Oxide Supercapacitors</article-title><source>Nanomaterials</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>212</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nano6110212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Core-shell Ag<sub>2</sub>CrO<sub>4</sub>/N-GQDs@g-C<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub> composites with anti-photocorrosion performance for enhanced full-spectrum-light photocatalytic activities</article-title><source>Applied Catalysis B-Environmental</source><year>2018</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2018.08.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>KQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3D carbon quantum dots/graphene aerogel as a metal-free catalyst for enhanced photosensitization efficiency</article-title><source>Applied Catalysis B-Environmental</source><year>2018</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcarb.2018.03.108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>K-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z-R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent progress in carbon quantum dots: synthesis, properties and applications in photocatalysis</article-title><source>Journal of Materials Chemistry A</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3717</fpage><lpage>3734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c6ta08660h</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functionalization of TiO<sub>2</sub> with graphene quantum dots for efficient photocatalytic hydrogen evolution</article-title><source>Superlattices and Microstructures</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.spmi.2016.04.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent developments of graphene-TiO<sub>2</sub> composite nanomaterials as efficient photoelectrodes in dye-sensitized solar cells: A review</article-title><source>Renewable &#x00026; Sustainable Energy Reviews</source><year>2018</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2017.09.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The endeavour to advance graphene-semiconductor composite-based photocatalysis</article-title><source>Crystengcomm</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c5ce01712b</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagliaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial photosynthesis over graphene-semiconductor composites</article-title><source>Are we getting better? Chemical Society Reviews</source><year>2014</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>8240</fpage><lpage>8254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c4cs00213j</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25200332?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25200332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly luminescent S, N co-doped graphene quantum dots with broad visible absorption bands for visible light photocatalysts</article-title><source>Nanoscale</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>12272</fpage><lpage>12277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c3nr04402e</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24150696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24150696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Qu, D. <italic>et al</italic>. Formation mechanism and optimization of highly luminescent N-doped graphene quantum dots. <italic>Scientific Reports</italic><bold>4</bold>, 10.1038/srep05294 (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction of carbon quantum dots/single crystal TiO<sub>2</sub> nanosheets with exposed {001} and {101} facets and their visible light driven catalytic activity</article-title><source>Rsc Advances</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3532</fpage><lpage>3541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c8ra10311a</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strongly green-photoluminescent graphene quantum dots for bioimaging applications</article-title><source>Chemical Communications</source><year>2011</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>6858</fpage><lpage>6860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c1cc11122a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21584323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21584323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anatase TiO<sub>2</sub> single crystals with a large percentage of reactive facets</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>453</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>U634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06964</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18509440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18509440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tuning the surface charge of graphene for self-assembly synthesis of a SnNb2O6 nanosheet-graphene (2D-2D) nanocomposite with enhanced visible light photoactivity</article-title><source>Nanoscale</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6335</fpage><lpage>6345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c4nr00116h</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24817377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24817377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z-R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of Bi<sub>2</sub>WO<sub>6</sub> as a highly selective visible-light photocatalyst toward oxidation of glycerol to dihydroxyacetone in water</article-title><source>Chemical Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1820</fpage><lpage>1824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c3sc50285f</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontmorin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>RCB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sillanpaa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability of 5,5-dimethyl-1-pyrroline-N-oxide as a spin-trap for quantification of hydroxyl radicals in processes based on Fenton reaction</article-title><source>Water Research</source><year>2016</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2016.04.053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27132196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27132196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, A. S. W., Cummings, K. B., Rothling, H. P., Buettner, G. R. &#x00026; Chignell, C. F. <italic>J. Magn. Reson</italic>. <bold>79</bold>, 140 (1988).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L-s</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large, Solution-Processable Graphene Quantum Dots as Light Absorbers for Photovoltaics</article-title><source>Nano Letters</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1869</fpage><lpage>1873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl101060h</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20377198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20377198</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>