<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ACS//DTD ACS Journal DTD v1.02 20061031//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ACSJournal-v102.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.02?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName acs2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Cent Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Cent Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">oc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">acscii</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACS Central Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2374-7943</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2374-7951</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6535778</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31139726</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A New Magnetic Topological Quantum Material Candidate
by Design</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><name><surname>Pletikosic</surname><given-names>Ivo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Huibo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#x02225;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><name><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>Hung-Ju</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">&#x022a5;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Xitong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath6"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Ruidan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath7"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Guangqiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath8"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Tay-Rong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">&#x022a5;</xref><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">&#x029eb;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath9"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Shuang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">#</xref><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">&#x02207;</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">&#x025cb;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath10"><name><surname>Valla</surname><given-names>Tonica</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath11"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Weiwei</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath12"><name><surname>Cava</surname><given-names>Robert J.</given-names></name><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Department
of Chemistry, <institution>Louisiana State University</institution>, Baton Rouge, Louisiana 70803, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Department
of Chemistry, <institution>Princeton University</institution>, Princeton, New Jersey 08540, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Condensed
Matter Physics and Materials Science, <institution>Brookhaven
National Laboratory</institution>, Upton, New York 11973, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>&#x02225;</label>Neutron
Scattering Division, <institution>Oak Ridge National
Laboratory</institution>, Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>&#x022a5;</label>Department
of Physics, <institution>National Cheng Kung University</institution>, Tainan 70101, <country>Taiwan</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>#</label>International
Center for Quantum Materials, School of Physics, <institution>Peking University</institution>, Beijing 100871, <country>People&#x02019;s Republic
of China</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>&#x02207;</label><institution>Collaborative
Innovation Center of Quantum Matter</institution>, Beijing 100871, <country>People&#x02019;s
Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>&#x025cb;</label>CAS
Center for Excellence in Topological Quantum Computation, <institution>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, Beijing 100190, <country>People&#x02019;s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><label>&#x029eb;</label>Center for Quantum
Frontiers of Research &#x00026; Technology (QFort), Tainan 701, <country>Taiwan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>weiweix@lsu.edu</email>.</corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>rcava@princeton.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>04</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>22</day><month>05</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>900</fpage><lpage>910</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>02</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 American Chemical
Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>American Chemical
Society</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open access article published under an ACS AuthorChoice <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/page/policy/authorchoice_termsofuse.html">License</ext-link>, which permits copying and redistribution of the article or any adaptations for non-commercial purposes.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0013" id="ab-tgr1"/></p><p>Magnetism, when combined with an
unconventional electronic band
structure, can give rise to forefront electronic properties such as
the quantum anomalous Hall effect, axion electrodynamics, and Majorana
fermions. Here we report the characterization of high-quality crystals
of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, a new quantum material specifically
designed to engender unconventional electronic states plus magnetism.
EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> has a layered, Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub>-type structure. Ferromagnetic interactions dominate the Curie&#x02013;Weiss
susceptibility, but a transition to antiferromagnetic ordering occurs
near 30 K. Neutron diffraction reveals that this is due to two-dimensional
ferromagnetic spin alignment within individual Eu layers and antiferromagnetic
alignment between layers&#x02014;this magnetic state surrounds the
Sn&#x02013;P layers at low temperatures. The bulk electrical resistivity
is sensitive to the magnetism. Electronic structure calculations reveal
that EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> might be a strong topological insulator,
which can be a new magnetic topological quantum material (MTQM) candidate.
The calculations show that surface states should be present, and they
are indeed observed by angle-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy (ARPES)
measurements.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="short"><p>The layered quantum material
EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> is designed, synthesized, and characterized.
This new material is
an ideal platform for studying the interplay of magnetism with topological
electronic states.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>oc9b00202</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>oc-2019-00202n</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The
design and discovery of new quantum materials with desired
electronic and magnetic functionality, especially materials where
quantum effects result in topological electronic properties, is a
new challenge and one of the frontiers of research in materials chemistry
and materials physics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> There is a crucial
need for the discovery of new materials that in particular harness
the topological quantum states of matter, to increase our understanding
of these newly recognized electronic states and to realize their potential
in devices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> In this context, topological insulators
(TIs), which support fundamentally different surface (i.e., &#x0201c;topologically
protected&#x0201d;) and bulk electronic states, are of particular interest.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> When additional quantum phases such as superconductivity,
magnetism, or charge density waves are also present, new electronic
properties can arise due to their interactions with the surface states.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> Currently, the study of such systems in materials physics frequently
focuses on heterostructures consisting of TI/magnetic multilayers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> Unfortunately, these systems cannot be widely studied due to the
uncommon procedures required to make them. Thus, the design of novel
magnetic topological quantum materials that are widely synthetically
accessible is highly sought. Theorists have scoured the ICSD for previously
reported materials that can display topological electronic properties,
but the design of totally new topological quantum materials remains
rare, especially for cases where the interactions of different quantum
states are expected.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup></p><p>Located at the Zintl border in the periodic table, the element
Sn has moderate electronegativity, thus allowing it to participate
in various types of bonding interactions. This provides flexibility
in tuning the electronic properties of materials in which the electronic
states of tin are dominant.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> Further,
being a 5p-based element, it is expected to display the effects of
spin&#x02013;orbit coupling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> Tin may be
the critical elemental constituent in the topological crystalline
insulator SnTe, for example, and the fabrication of Stanene thin films
has been accomplished with the goal of establishing its topological
electronic properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> Thus, the inclusion of tin in
quantum materials is a good chemical rule when designing quantum materials
with potentially unconventional electronic functionality.</p><p>A
second chemical design rule for finding novel functional materials
is based on symmetry and crystal structure. Experience has shown that
low-dimensional materials are ideal platforms for realizing topological
electronic states due to the weak interlayer interactions and subsequent
partial confinement of the electronic states that is frequently present.
Rhombohedral Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> and Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> and
trigonal Mg<sub>3</sub>Bi<sub>2</sub>, are examples.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> The presence of elements with strong spin&#x02013;orbit
coupling in layers based on triangles is a common structural motif
in topological quantum materials.</p><p>Finally, as a third design
rule, the inclusion of magnetic lanthanide
elements, if well-placed in the crystal structure, can result in the
presence of ordered magnetic states that interact relatively weakly
with the other electronic states present, due to the localized nature
of 4f electrons.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> With appropriately selected
rare earth elements at the appropriate concentration in the appropriate
crystal structure, magnetically ordered states can be found at experimentally
accessible temperatures. In materials with unconventional electronic
structures, this allows for the interactions between magnetic and
topological states to be studied.</p><p>Although nonmagnetic, the
ternary Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub>-type
compound SrSn<sub>2</sub>As<sub>2</sub> has been theoretically predicted
to host three-dimensional Dirac states around the Fermi level.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> Moreover, NaSn<sub>2</sub>As<sub>2</sub>, with the same structure,
is reported to be a superconductor below 1.3 K.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> Consisting of buckled SnAs honeycomb networks separated
by Sr<sup>2+</sup> or Na<sup>+</sup>, consideration of these compounds
and the above materials design criteria inspired us to incorporate
a magnetic rare earth element (Eu<sup>2+</sup>) between Sn-based layers
with a geometry based on triangles to yield both an unconventional
electronic band structure and magnetic properties in a single material.</p><p>Thus, here we report a new material by design, EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. We report its crystallographically and magnetically
ordered structures, determined via single crystal X-ray and neutron
diffraction. We observe a transition to an A-type antiferromagnetic
state (alternating-orientation ferromagnetic layers) near 30 K, and
below that temperature significant magnetoresistance, a type-II nodal-line
semimetal when spin&#x02013;orbit coupling is ignored. Electronic structure
calculations reveal that EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> is an antiferromagnetic
topological insulator when Hubbard (<italic>U</italic>) is included.
The detailed interplay of unconventional electronic states (&#x0201c;band
inversion&#x0201d;), spin&#x02013;orbit coupling, and the surface states
is presented theoretically. The presence of the surface states is
confirmed by angle-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements.
Our new quantum material is easily grown as bulk crystals, displays
magnetic ordering at accessible temperatures, and displays topological
surface states, thus allowing the interactions of ferromagnetism and
topological surface states to be observed in a bulk material with
a simple crystal structure.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Experimental Details</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Single Crystal Growth</title><p>To obtain single crystals of
EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, Eu chunks, red phosphorus, and Sn granules
were placed in an alumina crucible with the molar ratio of 1.1:2:20.
The crucible was sealed into an evacuated quartz tube which was then
heated to 600 &#x000b0;C and held for 24 h followed by a 2 day heat treatment
at 1050 &#x000b0;C. After that, the tube was cooled to 600 &#x000b0;C at
a rate of 3 &#x000b0;C/h. Excess Sn was centrifuged out after reaching
600 &#x000b0;C, and shiny hexagonal single crystals (&#x0223c;1 &#x000d7;
1 &#x000d7; 0.1 mm<sup>3</sup>) were obtained.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Structure Determination</title><p>Multiple EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> crystals (&#x0223c;60 &#x000d7;
60 &#x000d7; 5 &#x003bc;m<sup>3</sup>) were tested by single crystal X-ray
diffraction to determine the
crystal structure of the new material. The structure, consistent among
all crystals, was determined using a Bruker Apex II diffractometer
equipped with Mo radiation (&#x003bb;<sub>K&#x003b1;</sub> = 0.710&#x0202f;73
&#x000c5;) at room temperature. Glycerol was used to protect the samples,
which were mounted on a Kapton loop. The scan width was set to 0.5&#x000b0;
with an exposure time of 10 s. Four different positions of the goniometer
and detector were selected. Data acquisition was made via Bruker SMART
software with the corrections for Lorentz and polarization effects
included.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> The direct method and full-matrix
least-squares on F<sup>2</sup> procedure within the SHELXTL package
were employed to solve the crystal structure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Physical Property Measurement</title><p>DC magnetization data
were measured from 2 to 300 K using a Quantum Design Dynacool Physical
Property Measurement System (PPMS), equipped with a vibrating sample
magnetometer (VSM) option. The magnetic susceptibility was defined
as M/H, where the applied field was 500 Oe. Field-dependent magnetization
data were collected at 2 K with magnetic field up to &#x003bc;<sub>0</sub><italic>H</italic> = 9 T. The electronic transport measurements were
carried out in a PPMS-9 cryostat using the four-terminal method between
1.8 and 300 K under magnetic fields up to &#x003bc;<sub>0</sub><italic>H</italic> = 9 T. Platinum wires were attached to the samples by
silver epoxy to ensure ohmic contact. The normal resistivity, &#x003c1;<sub><italic>xx</italic></sub>, was measured in the basal plane of a single
crystal, simply determined by dividing the observed voltage difference
by the applied current, suitably normalized by the sample dimensions.
The Hall resistance, &#x003c1;<sub><italic>yx</italic></sub>, was similarly
determined by applying the magnetic field perpendicular to a single
crystal basal plane and measuring the voltage within the plane perpendicular
to the direction of the applied current (again suitably normalized
by the sample size).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR)</title><p>A single crystal
of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> was stored in the glovebox before
EPR measurements, and then placed in a closed sample tube. The sample
tube was put into the EPR cavity. The experiment was carried out on
a Bruker ER 300D spectrometer interfaced to a Bruker 1600 computer
for data storage and manipulations. The spectrum was collected by
sweeping the magnetic field from 0 to 5000 G.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Single Crystal Neutron
Diffraction</title><p>Single crystal neutron
diffraction was performed on the Four-Circle Diffractometer (HB-3A)
at the High Flux Isotope Reactor (HFIR) at Oak Ridge National Laboratory
(ORNL). Due to the large neutron absorption coefficient of Eu, a relatively
small single crystal (&#x0223c;0.8 &#x000d7; 0.4 &#x000d7; 0.02 mm<sup>3</sup>) was selected and mounted on an aluminum pin. The measurement was
carried out between 4 and 50 K with an incident neutron wavelength
of 1.550 &#x000c5; from a bent perfect Si-220 monochromator. Absorption
corrections were applied using the PLATON software.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> The nuclear and magnetic structure refinements were carried out
using the FULLPROF refinement suite.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title>Electronic Structure Calculations</title><p>The bulk electronic
structure calculations for EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> were performed
by using the projector augmented wave method as implemented in the
VASP package within the generalized gradient approximation (GGA) scheme.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> The experimental structural parameters were employed. Spin&#x02013;orbit
coupling was included self-consistently in some of the calculations
for comparison to the expected electronic structure with SOC absent.
Spin polarization using GGA+<italic>U</italic> (<italic>U</italic> = 4 eV) was employed for the magnetic models investigated.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> How f electron states are treated in DFT calculations
is of interest because when considered as valence electrons then they
are always found at the Fermi energy for partly filled f orbitals,
which, except in very rare cases such as for heavy fermion materials,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup> is not a realistic picture for their relative position in energy&#x02014;in
our calculations, the energies of the calculated Eu f electron states
are tested to match with the experimental ARPES measurements. A Monkhorst&#x02013;Pack
11 &#x000d7; 11 &#x000d7; 7 <italic>k</italic>-point mesh was used for the <italic>k</italic>-space integrations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup> With
these settings, the calculated total energy converged to less than
0.1 meV per atom. For the surface spectral weight calculations, a
semi-infinite Green&#x02019;s function method, terminated by (001)
surfaces, was employed. Calculations were made for Sn-, P-, and Eu-terminated
(001) surfaces. The median line of the Sn bilayer is selected as the
Sn-terminated surface.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title>Experimental Band Structure Characterization</title><p>Angle-resolved
photoelectron spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements were carried out at
a temperature of 10 K on the (001) surfaces of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> crystals cleaved in a 10<sup>&#x02013;9</sup> Pa vacuum. Linearly
(s and p) polarized light with photon energies in the range 50&#x02013;120
eV was used. Experiments were performed at the Electron Spectro-Microscopy
(ESM) beamline of the National Synchrotron Light Source (NSLS-II).
The photoemitted electrons were collected from a &#x000b1;15&#x000b0; cone
by a Scienta DA30 instrument and analyzed with angular and energy
resolutions of &#x0003c;0.2&#x000b0; and 15 meV, respectively. Core level
spectra using 300 eV photons showed presence of no elements other
than Sn, Eu, and P in the material. Potassium adsorption, commonly
used to fill a material&#x02019;s bands with additional electrons to
increase the Fermi Level at the surface of a sample, resulted in surface
deterioration in the case of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> and no
noticeable Fermi level shift.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><title>Safety Statement</title><p>No unexpected or unusually high safety
hazards were encountered.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Crystal
Structure</title><p>The single crystals of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> are hexagonal plates, as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>A, with the rhombohedral <italic>c</italic>-axis perpendicular to the plates (thus the plates are
(001) or &#x0201c;basal&#x0201d; planes). The results from single crystal
X-ray diffraction reveal that EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> crystallizes
in a rhombohedral lattice with the space group <italic>R</italic>&#x00033;&#x00305;<italic>m</italic>, in analogy to Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub>, which is
a well-known topological insulator. As shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>B, each Eu atom, surrounded by six P atoms,
forms a trigonal prism. The Eu layers are separated by two Sn@P<sub>3</sub> triangular pyramid layers connected by weak Sn&#x02013;Sn
bonds. An inversion center exists in the center of the unit cell.
The layered features of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, and its in-plane
and honeycomb Sn structure viewed along <italic>c</italic>-axis are
presented in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>C,D, respectively. The crystallographic data, including atomic positions,
site occupancies, and equivalent isotropic thermal displacement parameters,
are listed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Tables <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref> and <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref>. The refined anisotropic displacement
parameters are shown in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202/suppl_file/oc9b00202_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Single Crystal Structure Refinement
for EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> at 293 (2) K</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">refined formula</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub></td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">F.W. (g/mol)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">451.28</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">space&#x000a0;group;&#x000a0;<italic>Z</italic></td><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>R</italic>&#x00033;&#x00305;<italic>m</italic>;&#x000a0;3</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic>&#x000a0;(&#x000c5;)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">4.097&#x000a0;(1)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>c</italic>&#x000a0;(&#x000c5;)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">26.162&#x000a0;(5)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>V</italic>&#x000a0;(&#x000c5;<sup>3</sup>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">380.24&#x000a0;(13)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">extinction coefficient</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.0000&#x000a0;(1)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">&#x003b8;&#x000a0;range (deg)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.335&#x02013;33.171</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">no. reflections; <italic>R</italic><sub>int</sub></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2229; 0.0191</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">no.
independent reflections</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">227</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">no. parameters</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub>: <italic>&#x003c9;R</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x000a0;(<italic>I</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;2&#x003b4;(<italic>I</italic>))</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0.0154; 0.0363</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">goodness of
fit</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1.121</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">diffraction peak
and hole (e<sup>&#x02013;</sup>/&#x000c5;<sup>3</sup>)</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">2.481; &#x02212;0.617</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Atomic Coordinates and Equivalent
Isotropic Displacement Parameters for EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> at 293 K<xref rid="tbl2-fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">atom</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">Wyck.</th><th style="border:none;" align="center">occ.</th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><italic>x</italic></th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><italic>y</italic></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="."><italic>z</italic></th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="."><italic>U</italic><sub>eq</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Eu1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">3<italic>a</italic></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.0088&#x000a0;(1)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">Sn2</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">6<italic>c</italic></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.2112&#x000a0;(1)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.0117&#x000a0;(1)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;" align="left">P3</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">6<italic>c</italic></td><td style="border:none;" align="left">1</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td><td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.4053&#x000a0;(1)</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">0.0087&#x000a0;(3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2-fn1"><label>a</label><p><italic>U</italic><sub>eq</sub> is
defined as one-third of the trace of the orthogonalized <italic>U</italic><sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> tensor (&#x000c5;<sup>2</sup>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Crystal structure of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> from different
viewpoints, where the green, gray, and red balls represent Eu, Sn,
and P atoms, respectively. (A) Single crystal picture of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. (B, C) Layered characteristic structure of
EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> (looking perpendicular to the <italic>c</italic>-axis). (D) Emphasizing the honeycomb character of the
double Sn layers in the basal plane and the triangular planes of Eu
(looking parallel to the <italic>c</italic>-axis).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Magnetic Characterization</title><p>To get
insight into the magnetic
properties of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, we performed field-dependent
magnetization measurements at 2 K with applied magnetic fields parallel
and perpendicular to the <italic>c</italic>-axis. The results are
shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>A.
The field-dependent behavior is characteristic of that of a ferromagnetic
material&#x02014;the magnetic moment of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> saturates at &#x0223c;2.8 T for applied fields perpendicular to the <italic>c</italic>-axis and &#x0223c;4.1 T for fields parallel to the <italic>c</italic>-axis. Accordingly, a strong anisotropy of magnetization
is observed, with the easy axis in the basal plane, perpendicular
to the <italic>c</italic>-axis. The saturated magnetizations are &#x0223c;6.0
&#x003bc;<sub>B</sub>/Eu for both orientations.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Field-dependent, direction-dependent,
and temperature-dependent
magnetic properties of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. (A) Field-dependent
magnetization for the two crystal orientations measured at 2 K where
red balls and blue squares represent magnetic field parallel and perpendicular
to the <italic>c</italic>-axis, respectively. (B) Magnetic susceptibility
as a function of temperature measured in an external field of &#x003bc;<sub>0</sub><italic>H</italic> = 500 Oe, both perpendicular (blue) and
parallel (red) to the <italic>c</italic>-axis. The inset shows the
temperature-dependent inverse susceptibility, measured for different
sample orientations. The green line is the Curie&#x02013;Weiss fit
to the high-temperature data.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig><p>The temperature-dependent magnetic susceptibility was measured
under an external field of 500 Oe from 2 to 300 K. A transition to
an antiferromagnetic state (i.e., <italic>T</italic><sub>N</sub>)
is seen at around 30 K. The larger magnetic susceptibility in the
perpendicular field also indicates the anisotropic ordered magnetism
in EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, i.e., that ferromagnetic ordering
is preferred within the <italic>ab</italic>-plane rather than along
the <italic>c</italic>-axis. At temperatures higher than 30 K, classic
Curie&#x02013;Weiss behavior is observed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref></sup> The effective moment and Curie&#x02013;Weiss (CW) temperatures &#x00398;<sub>&#x022a5;</sub> and &#x00398;<sub>//</sub> were fitted from 150 to 300
K by using the Curie&#x02013;Weiss formula &#x003c7; = &#x003c7;<sub>0</sub> + <inline-formula id="d30e1039"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_m001.gif"/></inline-formula> where &#x003c7;<sub>0</sub> is the temperature-independent
part of the magnetic susceptibility, <italic>N</italic><sub>A</sub> is Avogadro&#x02019;s number, <italic>k</italic><sub>B</sub> is the
Boltzmann constant, &#x003bc;<sub>eff</sub> is the effective moment,
and &#x00398;<sub>CW</sub> is the Curie&#x02013;Weiss temperature. The Curie&#x02013;Weiss temperatures in perpendicular and parallel
fields are 31.8(1) and 31.6(1) K, within error of each other, while
the average effective moment is 7.91(3) &#x003bc;<sub>B</sub>/Eu. The
magnetic characteristics above <italic>T</italic><sub>N</sub> are
essentially isotropic.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR)</title><p>The magnetism
observed is consistent with the presence of magnetic Eu<sup>2+</sup> in our material, but to further confirm the electronic state of
Eu in EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, we performed electron paramagnetic
resonance measurements. The obtained data are shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref> as the first derivative of
the absorption data. We observe a sin-function-like strong broad curve
when the applied magnetic field is swept to 2400 G, reaching its maximum
around 3200 G. The intensity subsequently drops to zero at 3530 G,
which indicates the applied field of the strongest absorption, and
continuously becomes more negative, to &#x0223c;&#x02212;6000 (in arbitrary
units) at &#x0223c;3800 Oe, returning to zero intensity beyond 5000
Oe. The asymmetric line shape is as is usually observed in metals
due to the skin effect caused by the small size of the single crystal
used compared with the skin depth. According to the principal EPR
equation, &#x00394;<italic>E</italic> = <italic>h</italic>&#x003bd; = <italic>g</italic>&#x003bc;<sub>B</sub><italic>B</italic><sub>0</sub> where
&#x00394;<italic>E</italic> is the splitting energy, <italic>h</italic> is Planck&#x02019;s constant, &#x003bd; is the frequency of the microwave
used, which is 9481 MHz, <italic>g</italic> is the Land&#x000e9; <italic>g</italic>-factor, &#x003bc;<sub>B</sub> is the Bohr magneton, and <italic>B</italic><sub>0</sub> is the applied magnetic field of the strongest
absorption, we obtain the Land&#x000e9; <italic>g</italic>-factor of
1.9184. Based on &#x003bc;<sub>eff</sub> = <italic>g</italic><inline-formula id="d30e1136"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_m002.gif"/></inline-formula>&#x003bc;<sub>B</sub> and the <italic>g</italic>-factor obtained from the EPR data,
we obtain &#x003bc;<sub>eff</sub> = 7.61 &#x003bc;<sub>B</sub>, which
is within error of the effective
moment obtained from the temperature-dependent magnetic susceptibility
(7.91 &#x003bc;<sub>B</sub>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> Therefore,
we find that, for Eu in EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, <italic>J</italic> = 7/2 and that the Eu ground state is <sup>8</sup>S<sub>7/2</sub>, i.e., that Eu<sup>2+</sup> is the primary valence state for Eu.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Characterization
of the Eu spin state at ambient temperature and
pressure in EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. Room temperature electron
paramagnetic resonance (EPR) measurement with applied magnetic field
from 2300 to 5200 G.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Magnetic Structure</title><p>To better understand the magnetic
properties of our new quantum material, we performed single crystal
neutron diffraction on EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. Antiferromagnetic
order onsets at 30 K, as indicated by observing extra Bragg peaks
with a propagation vector of (0 0 1.5). The ordering parameter was
measured at (0 0 4.5) in reciprocal space (see <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>A) and indicates that <italic>T</italic><sub>N</sub> &#x0223c; 30 K by determination of the intersection of a linear
fitting regime (30&#x02013;50 K) and a two-term power law fit at low
temperatures with <inline-formula id="d30e1209"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_m003.gif"/></inline-formula> where <italic>A</italic>, pl, pu, and <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> are all constants.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> The magnetic
structure is determined by modeling
the magnetic reflections collected at 4.5 K. The lattice parameters
(<italic>a</italic> = 4.069(2) &#x000c5;, <italic>c</italic> = 25.935(9)
&#x000c5;) at 4.5 K are smaller than those determined by single crystal
X-ray diffraction (<italic>a</italic> = 4.097(1) &#x000c5;, <italic>c</italic> = 26.162(5) &#x000c5;) at room temperature due to thermal contraction.
Refining the nuclear reflections collected at 4.5 K yields <italic>R</italic><sub>F</sub> = 9.15% and <italic>R</italic><sub>F</sub><sup>2</sup> = 17.69%. The magnetic structure refinement reaches
the best fit (<italic>R</italic><sub>F</sub> = 6.71% and <italic>R</italic><sub>F</sub><sup>2</sup> = 12.7%) with the magnetic moment of 5.65
(3) &#x003bc;<sub>B</sub>/Eu oriented in the <italic>ab</italic>-plane
at 4.5 K (see <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>B), consistent with the field-dependent magnetization measurements.
As shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>B, the result is ferromagnetic Eu layers antiferromagnetically coupled
with their nearest neighbor layers leading to A-type antiferromagnetism
for EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. The inset of <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>A illustrates the neutron diffraction intensity
maps at both 30 and 4.5 K, showing the magnetic peak at (0 0 4.5).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Magnetic
structure of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. (A) (main
panel) Temperature-dependence of the magnetic scattering. The pixel
number is for the selected region of interest (enclosed in the purple
rectangle insets). The data indicate that <italic>T</italic><sub>N</sub> &#x0223c; 30 K, resulting from the fit of the red curves to the data.
(insets, top right) Magnetic signal intensity map at 30.0 K for the
reciprocal lattice plane (0 0 4.5). (insets, bottom left) Magnetic
signal intensity map at 4.5 K for the reciprocal lattice plane (0
0 4.5). (B) Magnetic unit cell of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. The
red arrows indicate the orientation of magnetic moments for each layer
of Eu atoms.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Charge Transport</title><p>The transport of electrical charge
in materials where interactions between different states may be present
is of interest. The temperature-dependent resistivity for a single
crystal of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, measured in the (001) plane,
is thus shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>A. Decreasing resistivity with decreasing temperature, i.e., metallic
behavior, is observed. The charge transport is sensitive to the magnetic
state of the system: &#x003c1;<sub><italic>xx</italic></sub> (the resistivity
in the <italic>x</italic> direction with the electric field applied
along the <italic>x</italic> direction; <italic>x</italic> and <italic>y</italic> directions are in the plane of the layers, while <italic>z</italic> is perpendicular to the layers) shows a drop below the
Neel temperature (&#x0223c;30 K). The in-plane resistivity &#x003c1;<sub><italic>xx</italic></sub> increases slightly at temperatures above
the magnetic ordering temperature, starting near 58 K. Also, as seen
in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>B, a linear
relation between the Hall resistivity &#x003c1;<sub><italic>yx</italic></sub> (field is applied along <italic>z</italic>, electric field
along <italic>x</italic>, and resistivity measured along <italic>y</italic>) and applied magnetic field <italic>H</italic> is seen at various
temperatures. From this data we are able to calculate the concentration
of the dominant carriers (<italic>n</italic>), which are holes, by
using <italic>n</italic> = 1/(<italic>eR</italic><sub>H</sub>) (where <italic>R</italic><sub>H</sub> is the Hall coefficient, obtained from the
slopes of <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>B,
and <italic>e</italic> is the electron charge).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> We find that, at 2 K, <italic>n</italic> is about 2.9 &#x000d7;
10<sup>20</sup> cm<sup>&#x02013;3</sup>, a relatively large hole concentration.
The slope of the &#x003c1;<sub><italic>yx</italic></sub> (<italic>H</italic>) curve decreases somewhat with increasing temperature, and thus
the carrier concentration is increasing with increasing temperature.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Charge
transport properties of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. (A)
Temperature-dependence of the (001) plane resistivity &#x003c1;<sub><italic>xx</italic></sub> between 1.8 and 300 K in the absence of
an applied magnetic field. (B) Field-dependence of the Hall resistivity
&#x003c1;<sub><italic>yx</italic></sub> at various temperatures (2 K,
10 K, 25 K, 70 K, 100 and 150 K) with applied field from 0 to 9 T.
(C) Field-dependence of &#x003c1;<sub><italic>xx</italic></sub> for
various temperatures (2, 5, 10, 15, 25, 40, and 70 K) on sweeping
applied field from 9 to &#x02212;9 T. (D) Magnetoresistance at the
above temperatures normalized to the values at 0 applied magnetic
field.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig><p>Uncommon behavior for the magnetoresistance
is observed (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>C). At low temperatures,
the material&#x02019;s resistivity &#x003c1;<sub><italic>xx</italic></sub> shows a domelike feature when magnetic field is applied perpendicular
to the basal plane (i.e., along <italic>z</italic>). At 2 K, it decreases
by about 9.4 &#x003bc;&#x003a9; cm when the field increased from 0 to
about 4.1 T, this latter field being where <italic>M</italic> vs <italic>H</italic> saturates at the same temperature (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref>A). This behavior is consistent with the
anomalous magnetoresistance seen in spin flop systems. The field-dependent
resistivity is not quenched until temperatures above 40 K, above the
magnetic ordering temperature&#x02014;the magnetoresistance becomes
more normal for temperatures of 70 K and above. Measurements on a
second sample suggest that the magnetoresistance in a direction perpendicular
to the plane is positive and significantly larger than what is observed
in-plane (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202/suppl_file/oc9b00202_si_001.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>). Further, the
out-of-plane resistivity does not appear to saturate by 9 T and may
continue to rise with larger applied fields. Although the in-plane
magnetoresistance is reminiscent of that observed for WTe<sub>2</sub>, the change of resistivity in field is orders of magnitude lower
than is seen there, and magnetic moments (from the Eu) are actually
present in the current case, while they are absent for WTe<sub>2</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup> Layered ferromagnetic semimetallic (see
below) systems like EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> are relatively rare,
and thus detailed study will be required to fully understand the magnetoresistance
observed in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>D.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title>Calculated Bulk and Surface Electronic Structures</title><p>The
results of first-principles electronic structure calculations for
EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> using the generalized gradient approximation
(GGA), GGA plus correlation parameter <italic>U</italic> (GGA+<italic>U</italic>), and GGA+<italic>U</italic> with spin&#x02013;orbit coupling
(SOC) are compared in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>. The calculations reveal a semimetallic band structure for
this material, with a continuous gap throughout the Brillouin zone,
similar in character to what is observed for WTe<sub>2</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup> The electrons in the 4f orbitals of the Eu atoms are experimentally
observed (see below) as localized in the range 1.0&#x02013;2.0 eV below
the Fermi level (<italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>), and thus the GGA+<italic>U</italic>+SOC calculations appear to be the most representative
of the material.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Calculated electronic structure of bulk EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. (A&#x02013;D) First-principles electronic band structures
for EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> in its A-type antiferromagnetic
ordered state
(both spin up and spin down bands are shown) with and without spin&#x02013;orbit
coupling (SOC) and correlation parameter <italic>U</italic> included.
(E) Deconvolution of the electronic structure to show the energy regimes
of dominance of the Eu, P, and Sn orbitals.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0006" id="gr6" position="float"/></fig><p>The calculations show that P 3p orbitals dominate the energy
bands
just below <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>, while Sn 5p orbitals are
found below &#x02212;5 eV and just above <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub> (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>E). Like
is the case for strong topological insulators, <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>E shows that in the vicinity of the Fermi
energy there are metal states mixed in in significant proportion at
the top of the valence band and P states mixed in in significant proportion
at the bottom of the conducting band; i.e., there is an inversion
of the conventional type of band structure, where this kind of mixing
of states above and below <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub> is negligible.
When the effects of spin polarization are included, the total energies
of the ferromagnetic (FM) and antiferromagnetic (AFM) models are the
lowest (the calculated energy difference between the AFM and FM states
in EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> is about 13 meV per f.u.), and indicate
that the observed antiferromagnetism is energy favored. The magnetic
moments, calculated to be about &#x0223c;6.7 &#x003bc;<sub>B</sub>, are
solely on the Eu atoms, consistent with what is expected in a na&#x000ef;ve
picture for this material, where Eu is the only magnetic atom. The
electronic structure of the material, calculated for the antiferromagnetically
ordered system, shows that the bands near the Fermi level are hybridized
among electrons from the p orbitals on the Sn and P atoms. The GGA
and GGA+<italic>U</italic> calculations result in a semimetallic ground
state, with no band gap, with Fermi surfaces around the &#x00393; and
A points in the Brillouin zone (BZ) (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>A,C).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> When SOC
is included in the calculations, a very small (a few meV) band gap
is present (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref>B,D).</p><p>As was designed, EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> exhibits
interesting
surface states. To understand the surface states of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, surface spectral weight simulations consistent with
the practice used in the topological materials field were employed.
(The first BZ of the rhombohedral lattice is shown in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202/suppl_file/oc9b00202_si_001.pdf">Figure S2</ext-link>.) The (001) surface is our material&#x02019;s
clear cleavage plane. The (001) surface may be terminated by Eu, P,
or Sn atomic layers; surface states are visible for all three possible
(001) terminations in the calculations. Consistent with the full bulk
DFT calculations, the electronic behavior near <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub> in these calculations is predominantly determined by the
dispersion of hybridized bands from Sn and P orbitals. For Sn-terminated
and Eu-terminated surfaces, comparison of the bulk and surface calculations
(<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>) shows that
surface states are located in the bulk energy gap around the &#x00393;
point. The energy dispersion of these states is very similar to the
Dirac surface states of strong Tis (inset of <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>D&#x02013;F). The surface states are more
well-separated in <italic>k</italic> for the P-termination case (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref></xref>E) than they are
for the Sn- and Eu-termination cases. This should make them more observable
experimentally than for the case of WTe<sub>2</sub>, where they are
strongly confined in both energy and wavevector.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of the calculated
bulk and surface band structures for
EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. (A&#x02013;F) Bulk (left) and surface
(right) band spectra of a semi-infinite slab with an (001) surface
terminated at Sn (upper), P (middle), or Eu (lower) layers. The surface
states are the narrow extra states observed in the surface state calculations
(right).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0007" id="gr7" position="float"/></fig><p>It is well-established in materials
physics that time-reversal-based
topological insulators can be described by a &#x0201c;Z<sub>2</sub> invariant&#x0201d;. Generally, Z<sub>2</sub> is undefined in a time-reversal
symmetry (TRS) breaking system such as a ferromagnetic phase. Nonetheless,
recent studies have proposed that the Z<sub>2</sub> invariant can
be expanded to classify topological states in magnetic systems if
the system possesses a specific magnetic configuration, for instance,
an antiferromagnetic state, in which the combined symmetry <italic>S</italic> = &#x00398;<italic>T</italic><sub>1/2</sub> is preserved,
where &#x00398; is the time-reversal operator, and <italic>T</italic><sub>1/2</sub> is the lattice translational symmetry of the crystal
that is broken by the antiferromagnetic order.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref></sup> This is what we have in the current case. Under this definition,
we calculate the Z<sub>2</sub> invariant by the Wilson loop method,
as shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> The Z<sub>2</sub> topological invariant
can be determined by looking at the evolution of the Wannier function
center. In this formalism, the evolution of each Wannier center pair
encloses the representation cylinder an integer number of times, which
can be viewed as the &#x0201c;winding number&#x0201d; of the Wannier
center pair. The Z<sub>2</sub> topological number is related to the
summation of the winding numbers for all the pairs. If it is odd,
then the Z<sub>2</sub> topological number is odd. According to <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>, the entanglement
entropy never becomes zero in the course of any gap- and symmetry-preserving
transformation; this demonstrates the nontriviality of the electronic
structure of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, i.e., its topological
character.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Topological invariant Z<sub>2</sub> of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> (calculated with SOC + <italic>U</italic>). The Wannier charge center
evolution (see ref (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>)) is shown for time-reversal invariant planes between &#x003c0; and
&#x02212;&#x003c0;. The Wannier center crosses any reference line (hypothetical
horizontal line in the figure) the appropriate number of times to
indicate that EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> is a topological insulator.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0008" id="gr8" position="float"/></fig><p>Our calculation shows an open
curve traversing the entire Brillouin
zone in the time-reversal invariant plane <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>z</italic></sub> = 0, indicating a Z<sub>2</sub> invariant equal
to 1, which demonstrates that EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> is indeed
an antiferromagnetic topological insulator (AFM-TI).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> The surface state Fermi contours, calculated by way of
the semi-infinite Green&#x02019;s function,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref></sup> are shown in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref>. The calculated iso-energy band contours at <italic>E</italic> =
0, &#x02212;0.2, and &#x02212;0.3 eV (below the calculated Fermi energy)
are shown for the three possible (001) surface terminations. (The
energies correspond to those of the surface states on the Sn-terminated
surface.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref></sup>) There is a prominent feature
that is seen for the surface band contour in addition to the bulk
states directly around the &#x00393; point in the BZ: a 6-fold symmetry
loop. The loop is small on the Sn-terminated and Eu-terminated surfaces
but is distinctly seen separated from the bulk states in <italic>k</italic> on the P-terminated surfaces.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Calculated surface Fermi surfaces of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. For the (001) surface (the cleavage plane),
terminated by (A&#x02013;C)
an Eu layer, (D&#x02013;F) a P layer, or (G, H) a Sn layer. The calculated
iso-energy band contours are shown for <italic>E</italic> = 0 (the
calculated Fermi Energy), &#x02212;0.2, and &#x02212;0.3 eV for Green&#x02019;s
function surface spectral weight simulation. The depth of the color
indicates the weight of the charge density of each state at the surface
layer. The surface states clearly appear as the extra ringlike Fermi
surfaces in the panels.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0009" id="gr9" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><title>Experimentally Observed Surface Electronic Structures</title><p>The
ARPES spectra, recorded in EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>&#x02019;s
antiferromagnetically ordered state at 10 K, shown in <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Figures <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref></xref> and <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>, reveal the energies of the occupied electronic bands around the
center &#x00393; of the (001) surface projection of the bulk BZ. The
outer (meaning the band with <italic>k</italic> vector furthest from
the center of the surface BZ) band, designated as &#x003c3;, disperses
linearly at about &#x02212;0.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> m/s away from
the Fermi level (<italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>) and appears as a
sharp, intense spectral feature at all incident photon energies. This is in
contrast with all of the other observed electronic bands and reflects
the fact that this is a surface state. Due to the nonconservation
of perpendicular-to-plane momenta of the ARPES method, a range of
perpendicular momenta is observed in the ARPES spectra of the bulk
bands, making them appear as filled-in regions in ARPES maps, distinct
from the surface band where the absence of perpendicular dispersion
results in a sharp feature. The most notable bulk band is the heart-shaped
band, labeled as &#x003b3;, in the center of the surface BZ, which disperses
upward in energy starting from Gamma to about 80 meV below <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub> and turning again down. The broad bright feature
showing little dispersion in the range of energies between &#x02212;1
and &#x02212;2 eV (below <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>) is from the
localized Eu f states.</p><fig id="fig10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Angle-resolved photoemission study of the band
structure of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>. (A, B) Band dispersion
spectra along K&#x02212;&#x00393;&#x02013;K
taken with 76 and 96 eV photons differ mostly in the relative intensities
of the bands due to photoemission selection-rule effects. (C) Incident
photon energy 102 eV, shows a wide energy-range band dispersion spectrum
along M&#x02212;&#x00393;&#x02013;M.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0010" id="gr10" position="float"/></fig><fig id="fig11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>ARPES study continued. (A) Two-dimensional momentum maps at several
energies near the Fermi level obtained with two photon energies to
enhance the visibility of different features in the band structure.
The surface band, designated as &#x003c3;, is clearly observed. (B)
Photon energy-dependent map to follow the band dispersion along the <italic>c</italic> crystal axis. The plot is at the energy of &#x02212;200
meV from <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>. (Vo for the <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>z</italic></sub> calculation was set to &#x02212;10 eV).
Different bands are marked with different Greek letters.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0011" id="gr11" position="float"/></fig><p>As is often the case with surface states, the surface
band &#x003c3;
is found relatively close in <italic>k</italic>-space to one of the
bulk bands, labeled as &#x003b1;. Additional bulk bands below <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>, labeled as &#x003b2; and &#x003b4;, are also
observed. The constant energy maps, <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref></xref>, taken at two different incident photon
energies (hence, at different <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>z</italic></sub> momenta), show the two-dimensional momentum space surface
Fermi surfaces: the hexagonal-loop contour of the surface band &#x003c3;
encloses the contours formed by the bulk bands &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, and
&#x003b3;. These features greatly resemble the &#x02212;300 meV band
contours calculated for the P termination of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>, <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref></xref>B,E,H,
although there is less warping toward the corners of the BZ for the
surface band than is calculated.</p><p>Momentum space mapping that
included a few neighboring surface
BZs revealed no bands in the vicinity of the Fermi level other than
those shown around &#x00393; in <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref></xref>. While three other crystal terminations (Eu, Sn single
and double layer) cannot be excluded in this material without further
theoretical and experimental studies, all our data indicate that the
(001) crystal surfaces are indeed P-terminated: the calculations for
the Eu and Sn terminations show surface states much closer to the
center of the BZ. Moreover, our core level spectra (<xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref></xref>) show that the P 2s levels
occur at two energies, indicative of two starkly different chemical
environments (thus bulk vs surface) for the P atoms. By comparing
the band dispersion observed in the ARPES spectra and the DFT calculations,
we conclude that the cleaved crystals are some 220 meV hole doped.
This is consistent with the large <italic>p</italic>-type carrier
concentration observed in the Hall measurements.</p><fig id="fig12" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Chemistry of the surface
core level spectrum of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> measured using
300 eV incident photons. This shows
that the P has two different environments (there is only one type
of P in the bulk crystal structure) and therefore is present in both
the bulk and the surface.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0012" id="gr12" position="float"/></fig><p>We note that the calculations show the bottom of six elliptical
electron pockets around the M point of the BZ, which are slightly
above the chemical potential (about &#x02212;220 meV compared to the
calculated <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>) observed in the ARPES experiments.
This explains why no trace of those calculated bands is seen in ARPES
(which sees only filled states) and further gives a hint for why the
results of potassium adsorption measurements, expected to electron-dope
the surface, resulted in no noticeable band shifts&#x02014;the flat
bottom of an electron pocket is associated with a high density of
states, and all the states have to be filled for the shifts in other
bands to be observed. We also note that our ARPES measurements at
varying incident photon energies show remarkably little difference
in the band structure of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> at different
perpendicular momenta <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>z</italic></sub>. The bands, most notably the surface state &#x003c3;, <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Figures <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref></xref> and <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>, show little dispersion perpendicular to the layers. The three-dimensional
Fermi surface thus consists of hexagonally warped cylinders formed
by extruding the contours of the bulk bands &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; along
the crystal axis <italic>c</italic> (<xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref></xref>B).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Summary and Conclusions</title><p>The novel quantum material EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> was designed
based on chemical criteria to display both magnetism and electronic
surface states. The hypothesized material was discovered, and crystals
were grown using the Sn-flux method. Its crystal structure and physical
properties were characterized. Its crystal structure consists of hexagonal
Eu, and P layers surrounding a Sn bilayer. It has a positive Curie&#x02013;Weiss
temperature of &#x00398;<sub>CW</sub> = 31(1) K, showing the dominance
of ferromagnetic spin correlations at high temperatures, but it orders
antiferromagnetically near 30 K. Its ordered magnetic structure, refined
from neutron diffraction, shows antiferromagnetically coupled in-plane-ferromagnetic
Eu<sup>2+</sup> layers. The temperature-dependent resistance of EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> is weakly metallic in character, and an anomalous
magnetoresistance is found below the magnetic ordering temperature
and below applied magnetic fields of 4 T, where the magnetization
saturates with applied magnetic field.</p><p>Electronic structure
calculations support magnetic ordering as
the energetically stable state of the system at low temperatures,
and further confirm that the observed magnetic moments solely arise
from the Eu<sup>2+</sup> present. Calculations including both SOC
and correlation parameter <italic>U</italic> best describe the positions
of the Eu f states between 1 and 2 eV below <italic>E</italic><sub>F</sub>, and further show that EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> is an
antiferromagnetic topological insulator (the energies of the valence
band and conduction bands overlap but for electrons of different wave
vectors in the Brillouin zone). The bulk band structure is unconventional
in that metal states contribute significantly just below the Fermi
energy while nonmetal states contribute significantly just above the
Fermi energy. The calculations also predict the presence of Dirac-like
surface states within the bulk energy gap, both above and below the
Fermi energy. The experimental ARPES study shows that surface states
are indeed present in the antiferromagnetically ordered state at 10
K but differ in a minor way from the calculations for a P-terminated
(001) surface. Although we have observed much about the basic properties
of this new quantum material, more detailed work on the properties
from the physics perspective is required to determine whether it is
unique in that it shows both antiferromagnetism and surface states
at low temperatures. The accessible temperatures involved, the simple
crystal structure, the ability to fabricate bulk crystals, and the
combination of properties make the quantum material EuSn<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub> an ideal platform for the detailed study of the interplay
of topological electronic states with magnetism.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="notes1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>The Supporting Information is
available free of charge on the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">ACS Publications website</ext-link> at DOI: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202">10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202</ext-link>.<list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Field-dependence
of &#x003c1;<sub><italic>xx</italic></sub> for various temperatures
for sample 2; magnetoresistance at the
same temperatures for sample 2; first Brillouin zone of the rhombohedral
lattice with the high symmetry momentum points marked (&#x00393;&#x02013;M&#x02013;K)
(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202/suppl_file/oc9b00202_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oc9b00202_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>oc9b00202_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="notes2"><p>The authors
declare no competing financial interest.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The work at Princeton was supported by the ARO MURI
on Topological Insulators, Grant W911NF1210461. W.X. at LSU was supported
by a Beckman Young Investigator award. X.G. at LSU is supported by
the National Science Foundation under NSF-OIA-1832967. H.B.C. acknowledges
support of US DOE BES Early Career Award KC0402010 under Contract
DE-AC05-00OR22725. This research used resources at the High Flux Isotope
Reactor, a DOE Office of Science User Facility operated by the Oak
Ridge National Laboratory. This research also used resources of the
National Synchrotron Light Source II, a U.S. Department of Energy
(DOE) Office of Science User Facility operated for the DOE Office
of Science by Brookhaven National Laboratory under Contract DE-SC0012704.
I.P. thanks J. Jiang, E. Vescovo, and K. Kaznatcheev for their help
with setting up the experiment at the 21-ID-1 (ESM-ARPES) beamline.
T.-R.C. was supported from Young Scholar Fellowship Program by Ministry
of Science and Technology (MOST) in Taiwan, under MOST Grant for the
Columbus Program MOST108-2636-M-006-002 and MOST 107-2627-E-006-001.
W.X. and X.G. thank D. Vineyard for helping with electron paramagnetic
resonance measurement.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Awschalom</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dzurak</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Petta</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum
Spintronics: Engineering and Manipulating Atom-Like Spins in Semiconductors</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>339</volume>, <fpage>1174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1231364</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23471400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Cirac</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Goals and Opportunities in Quantum Simulation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>264</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphys2275</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Ladd</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jelezko</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Laflamme</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum Computers</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>464</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08812</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20203602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Birth
of Topological Insulators</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>464</volume>, <fpage>194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08916</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20220837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Topological Superconductors:
A Review</article-title>. <source>Rep.
Prog. Phys.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>80</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>076501</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1361-6633/aa6ac7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28367833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X.-L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.-C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Dynamical Axion
Field in Topological Magnetic Insulators</article-title>. <source>Nat.
Phys.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphys1534</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.-Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.-C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>M. H. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moodera</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>High-Precision Realization of Robust
Quantum Anomalous
Hall State in a Hard Ferromagnetic Topological Insulator</article-title>. <source>Nat. Mater.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmat4204</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25730394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.-Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.-L.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Experimental Observation of the Quantum Anomalous Hall Effect in
a Magnetic Topological Insulator</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>340</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1234414</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23493424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Katmis</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lauter</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jamer</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Satpati</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Freeland</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eremin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>A High-Temperature
Ferromagnetic Topological Insulating Phase by
Proximity Coupling</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>533</volume>, <fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature17635</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27225124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Mogi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yoshimi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tsukazaki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kozuka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shirakawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tokura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Magnetic Heterostructure
of Topological
Insulators as a Candidate for an Axion Insulator</article-title>. <source>Nat. Mater.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmat4855</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28191899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Slager</surname><given-names>R.-J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mesaros</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Juri&#x0010d;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zaanen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Space
Group Classification of Topological Band-Insulators</article-title>. <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphys2513</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Setyawan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buongiorno Nardelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Curtarolo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Search Model for Topological Insulators with High-Throughput
Robustness Descriptors</article-title>. <source>Nat. Mater.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>614</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>619</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmat3332</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22581314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit13"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Vergniory</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Elcoro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Felser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bernevig</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The (High Quality)
Topological Materials In The World</article-title>. <year>2018</year>, arXiv:1807.10271. arXiv e-Print archive. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.10271">https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.10271</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Po</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vishwanath</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Symmetry-Based Indicators of Band
Topology in the 230 Space Groups</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>50</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00133-2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28667305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Po</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vishwanath</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Towards Ideal Topological
Materials: Comprehensive Database Searches Using Symmetry Indicators</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2019</year>, <volume>566</volume>, <fpage>486</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-0937-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30814709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Bradlyn</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Elcoro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vergniory</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Felser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aroyo</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bernevig</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Topological
Quantum Chemistry</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>547</volume>, <fpage>298</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature23268</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28726818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Nesper</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Zintl-Klemm
Concept &#x02013; A Historical Survey</article-title>. <source>Z. Anorg.
Allg. Chem.</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>640</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/zaac.201400403</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sobczak</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>T.-R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>H.-T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Klimczuk</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Superconducting SrSnP
with Strong Sn&#x02013;P Antibonding Interaction: Is the Sn Atom Single
or Mixed Valent?</article-title>. <source>Chem. Mater.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>6005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemmater.8b02258</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bansil</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Topological
Crystalline Insulators in the SnTe Material Class</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>982</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms1969</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22864575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Epitaxial
Growth of Ultraflat Stanene with Topological Band Inversion</article-title>. <source>Nat. Mater.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1081</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41563-018-0203-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30397308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Checkelsky</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hor</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cava</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Bulk Band Gap and
Surface State Conduction Observed in Voltage-Tuned Crystals of the
Topological Insulator Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>106</volume>, <fpage>196801</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.106.196801</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21668185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.-X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X.-L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.-C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Topological Insulators in Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub>Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> and Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> with
a Single Dirac Cone on the Surface</article-title>. <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
<year>2009</year>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphys1270</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>T.-R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pletikosic</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bian</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Denlinger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kushwaha</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sinkovic</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>H.-T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Valla</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Realization of a Type-II Nodal-Line Semimetal in Mg<sub>3</sub>Bi<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Adv. Sci.</source>
<year>2019</year>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1800897</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/advs.201800897</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="weblink" id="cit24"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Borisenko</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Evtushinsky</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yaresko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buechner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hoesch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cava</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year>, <article-title>Time-Reversal
Symmetry Breaking Type-II Weyl State in YbMnBi<sub>2</sub></article-title>. arXiv:1507.04847. arXiv e-Print archive. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1507.04847">https://arxiv.org/abs/1507.04847</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>L.-Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.-Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>S.-M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z.-P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.-L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B.-B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L.-Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.-Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.-B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>H.-M.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Electronic
Structure of SrSn<sub>2</sub>As<sub>2</sub> near the Topological Critical
Point</article-title>. <source>Sci.
Rep.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6133</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-05386-x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28733663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Heremans</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cava</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Samarth</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Tetradymites
as Thermoelectrics and
Topological Insulators</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Mater.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>2</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>17049</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/natrevmats.2017.49</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Cava</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fuccillo</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>Q. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hor</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Crystal Structure
and Chemistry of Topological Insulators</article-title>. <source>J.
Mater. Chem. C</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>3176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c3tc30186a</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mizuguchi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>SnAs-Based
Layered Superconductor NaSn<sub>2</sub>As<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>123701</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7566/JPSJ.86.123701</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Sheldrick</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Crystal
Structure Refinement with SHELXL</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr.,
Sect. C: Struct. Chem.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>71</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2053229614024218</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25567568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Sheldrick</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Short
History of SHELX</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr., Sect. A:
Found. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2008</year>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0108767307043930</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Spek</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Single-Crystal
Structure Validation with the Program PLATON</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Crystallogr.</source>
<year>2003</year>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0021889802022112</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Spek</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>PLATON
SQUEEZE: A Tool for the Calculation of the Disordered Solvent Contribution
to the Calculated Structure Factors</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr.,
Sect. C: Struct. Chem.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2053229614024929</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25567569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Carvajal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Recent Advances
in Magnetic Structure Determination by Neutron Powder Diffraction</article-title>. <source>Phys. B</source>
<year>1993</year>, <volume>192</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0921-4526(93)90108-I</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Hafner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ab-Initio
Simulations of Materials Using VASP: Density-Functional Theory and
Beyond</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Chem.</source>
<year>2008</year>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>2044</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21057</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18623101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Perdew</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ernzerhof</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Generalized
Gradient Approximation
Made Simple</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<year>1996</year>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>3865</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.77.3865</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10062328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit36"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Local Density Approximations
in Quantum Chemistry and Solid State Physics</source>; <publisher-name>Springer Science &#x00026; Business Media</publisher-name>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>Anisimov</surname><given-names>V. I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aryasetiawan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>A. I.</given-names></name>
<article-title>First-Principles Calculations of
the Electronic Structure and Spectra of Strongly Correlated Systems:
The LDA+U method</article-title>. <source>J. Phys.: Condens. Matter</source>
<year>1997</year>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0953-8984/9/4/002</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Haule</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kotliar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Modeling the
Localized-to-Itinerant
Electronic Transition in the Heavy Fermion System CeIrIn<sub>5</sub></article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>318</volume>, <fpage>1615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1149064</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17975033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>Monkhorst</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Special Points for
Brillouin-Zone Integrations</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
<year>1976</year>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>5188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.13.5188</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit40"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Kittel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Introduction to Solid
State Physics Global ed.</source>; <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>, <year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit41"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mermin</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Solid State Physics</source>; <publisher-name>Saunders College</publisher-name>, <year>1976</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit42"><name><surname>Pletikosi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fedorov</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cava</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Valla</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Electronic
Structure Basis for the Extraordinary Magnetoresistance in WTe<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>113</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>216601</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.113.216601</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25479512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit43"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>Q. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schoop</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Haldolaarachchige</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hirschberger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Large, Non-Saturating
Magnetoresistance in WTe<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>514</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13763</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25219849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit44"><name><surname>Mong</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Essin</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Antiferromagnetic
Topological Insulators</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B: Condens.
Matter Mater. Phys.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>245209</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.81.245209</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit45"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bernevig</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Topological Insulators with Commensurate
Antiferromagnetism</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B: Condens. Matter
Mater. Phys.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>085406</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.88.085406</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit46"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bernevig</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Equivalent
Expression of Z<sub>2</sub> Topological Invariant for Band Insulators
Using the Non-Abelian Berry Connection</article-title>. <source>Phys.
Rev. B: Condens. Matter Mater. Phys.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>075119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.84.075119</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit47"><name><surname>Skriver</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rosengaard</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Self-Consistent Green&#x02019;s-Function
Technique for
Surfaces and Interfaces</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. B: Condens.
Matter Mater. Phys.</source>
<year>1991</year>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>9538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.43.9538</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit48"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>P. D. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hatch</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ovsyannikov</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lupulescu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Landolt</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Slomski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dil</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>; et al. <article-title>Large Tunable Rashba
Spin Splitting of a Two-Dimensional Electron Gas in Bi<sub>2</sub>Se<sub>3</sub></article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<year>2011</year>, <volume>107</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>096802</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.107.096802</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21929260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>