<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison of mixed-carbene and homoleptic NHC complexes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To further contextualize the photoluminescence properties and the CIE coordinates, we can compare complexes 
  <span class="bold">3a–c</span> to homoleptic Ir(C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span>)
  <sub>3</sub> complexes which use the same three NHC ligands. Although Ir(C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span>)
  <sub>3</sub> complexes are available in both 
  <span class="italic">fac</span> and 
  <span class="italic">mer</span> isomers, with the stereochemistry not having a large influence on photoluminescence attributes,
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a>,
  <a rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit14">14</a> we focus here on comparisons to the 
  <span class="italic">mer</span> isomer, since this isomer and 
  <span class="bold">3a–c</span> include a 
  <span class="italic">trans</span> arrangement of two of the NHC ligands. Immobilized in a thin film, compound 
  <span class="bold">3c</span> exhibits nearly identical photoluminescence to that of 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(pmp)
  <sub>3</sub>,
  <a rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit14">14</a> with the same featureless profile and nearly identical maximum wavelengths and CIE coordinates ((CIE
  <span class="italic">x</span>, CIE
  <span class="italic">y</span>) = (0.16, 0.16) for 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(pmp)
  <sub>3</sub>). The photoluminescence attributes of 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span> are also quite similar to their respective 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span>)
  <sub>3</sub> (C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span> = pmi, pmb) analogues. These compounds also emit with maxima near 400 nm, and although precise quantum yield values in polymer film were not reported, they were estimated to be greater than 0.1–0.2.
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a> The photoluminescence quantum yields of 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span> = 0.13) and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span> (
  <span class="italic">Φ</span> = 0.31) are in the same range or greater, suggesting the photoluminescence efficiencies of 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span> are very similar to or better than the homoleptic analogues. In addition, CIE coordinates for electroluminescent devices made from 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(pmb)
  <sub>3</sub> were found to be (0.17, 0.06) and (0.17, 0.08),
  <a rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit12">12</a> very similar to the color profile observed for the photoluminescence of 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span>. One other point of comparison are homoleptic 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span>)
  <sub>3</sub> complexes with CF
  <sub>3</sub>-substituted pmi ligands.
  <a rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit15">15</a> The photoluminescence quantum yields of these compounds were measured in PMMA films, with one isomer having 
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>
  <sub>PL</sub> = 0.14 and another with 
  <span class="italic">Φ</span>
  <sub>PL</sub> = 0.47, similar values to those of 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span>. CIE coordinates for devices made from these CF
  <sub>3</sub>-substituted Ir(pmi)
  <sub>3</sub> analogues are also nearly identical to those observed for 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span>. Taken together, these comparisons indicate that installing cyclometalated ADC ancillary ligands preserves the favorable photoluminescence characteristics of the carbene-based iridium cyclometalates that have been used in some of the top-performing blue devices.
  <a rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit12">12</a>,
  <a rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit14">14</a>,
  <a rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit15">15</a> The subtle influence that the ADC has on the photoluminescence color when compared to homoleptic Ir(C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span>)
  <sub>3</sub> complexes suggests that the ADC-centered orbitals do not contribute substantially to the T
  <sub>1</sub> state, which is born out in the DFT calculations described here.
 </p>
</sec>
