<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electrochemistry</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The redox properties of complexes 
  <span class="bold">3a–c</span> were investigated by cyclic voltammetry, which reveal that substituting NHC ligands with ADCs results in very small perturbations of frontier orbital energies. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3</a> overlays the cyclic voltammograms of 
  <span class="bold">3a–c</span>, recorded in MeCN with 0.1 M NBu
  <sub>4</sub>PF
  <sub>6</sub> electrolyte. All three complexes exhibit reversible one-electron Ir
  <span class="sup">IV</span>/Ir
  <span class="sup">III</span> couples upon sweeping anodically. Sweeping in the negative direction, complexes 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> and 
  <span class="bold">3b</span> do not show any discernible reduction waves within the solvent window, whereas 
  <span class="bold">3c</span> has an irreversible reduction at 
  <span class="italic">ca.</span> –2.60 V 
  <span class="italic">vs.</span> the Fc
  <span class="sup">+</span>/Fc couple. Compared to our previously reported complexes Ir(C^N)
  <sub>2</sub>(C^C:
  <span class="sup">ADC</span>) with nitrogen-containing cyclometalating ligands,
  <a rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit27">27</a> complexes 
  <span class="bold">3a–c</span> are easier to oxidize by at least 160 mV, signifying a destabilized HOMO in these complexes. To contextualize these results further we can compare the potentials to homoleptic 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span>)
  <sub>3</sub> complexes, which likewise place the two NHCs 
  <span class="italic">trans</span> to one another but have another cyclometalated NHC occupying the remaining coordination sites. Replacing one NHC cyclometalating ligand with the ADC in 
  <span class="bold">3a–c</span> has a very small impact on the electrochemical potentials. Complex 
  <span class="bold">3a</span> is oxidized at 0.16 V, which is almost identical to the complex 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(pmi)
  <sub>3</sub> (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>1/2</sub> = 0.14 V).
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a> Similarly, the oxidation potentials for the pairs 
  <span class="bold">3b</span> (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>1/2</sub> = 0.21 V) and 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(pmb)
  <sub>3</sub> (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>1/2</sub> = 0.31 V)
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a> and 
  <span class="bold">3c</span> (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>1/2</sub> = 0.25 V) and 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(pmp)
  <sub>3</sub> (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>1/2</sub> = 0.23 V)
  <a rid="cit14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit14">14</a> are within 100 mV of one another. The homoleptic 
  <span class="italic">mer</span>-Ir(C^C:
  <span class="sup">NHC</span>)
  <sub>3</sub> complexes and new complexes 
  <span class="bold">3a–c</span> are all very difficult to reduce, signifying very high-energy LUMOs that are responsible for the large HOMO–LUMO gaps in these C^C: cyclometalated compounds.
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Overlaid cyclic voltammograms of 
    <span class="bold">3a–c</span>, recorded in acetonitrile with 0.1 M NBu
    <sub>4</sub>PF
    <sub>6</sub> electrolyte. A glassy carbon working electrode, platinum wire counter electrode, and silver wire pseudoreference electrode were used during the measurements, and potentials are referenced to an internal standard of ferrocene. Separate anodic (positive) and cathodic (negative) scans were recorded. Half-wave potentials (
    <span class="italic">E</span>
    <sub>1/2</sub>) are indicated above each oxidation wave, and currents are normalized to bring the plots onto the same scale.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c9sc01386e-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
