<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Chem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Chem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Chem.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Chemistry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2646</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6548831</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fchem.2019.00380</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Temperature Dependence of Rate Processes Beyond Arrhenius and Eyring: Activation and Transitivity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>Valter H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/680982/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>Nayara D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c002"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>Vincenzo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c003"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/642480/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Grupo de Qu&#x000ed;mica Te&#x000f3;rica e Estrutural de An&#x000e1;polis, Campus de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Exatas e Tecnol&#x000f3;gicas, Universidade Estadual de Goi&#x000e1;s</institution>, <addr-line>An&#x000e1;polis</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Dipartimento di Chimica, Biologia e Biotecnologie, Universit&#x000e0; di Perugia</institution>, <addr-line>Perugia</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Istituto di Struttura della Materia, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche</institution>, <addr-line>Rome</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Antonio Aguilar, University of Barcelona, Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Luca Evangelisti, University of Bologna, Italy; Ernesto Garcia, University of the Basque Country, Spain</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Valter H. Carvalho-Silva <email>fatioleg@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Nayara D. Coutinho <email>nayaradcoutinho@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c003">Vincenzo Aquilanti <email>vincenzoaquilanti@yahoo.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Physical Chemistry and Chemical Physics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Chemistry</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>380</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 Carvalho-Silva, Coutinho and Aquilanti.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Carvalho-Silva, Coutinho and Aquilanti</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Advances in the understanding of the dependence of reaction rates from temperature, as motivated from progress in experiments and theoretical tools (e. g., molecular dynamics), are needed for the modeling of extreme environmental conditions (e.g., in astrochemistry and in the chemistry of plasmas). While investigating statistical mechanics perspectives (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), the concept of transitivity was introduced as a measure for the propensity for a reaction to occur. The <italic>Transitivity plot</italic> is here defined as the reciprocal of the apparent activation energy vs. reciprocal absolute temperature. Since the transitivity function regulates transit in physicochemical transformations, not necessarily involving reference to transition-state hypothesis of Eyring, an extended version is here proposed to cope with general types of transformations. The transitivity plot permits a representation where deviations from Arrhenius behavior are given a geometrical meaning and make explicit a positive or negative linear dependence of transitivity for <italic>sub</italic>- and <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius cases, respectively. To first-order in reciprocal temperature, the transitivity function models deviations from linearity in Arrhenius plots as originally proposed by Aquilanti and Mundim: when deviations are increasingly larger, other phenomenological formulas, such as Vogel-Fulcher-Tammann, Nakamura-Takayanagi-Sato, and Aquilanti-Sanches-Coutinho-Carvalho are here rediscussed from the transitivity concept perspective and with in a general context. Emphasized is the interest of introducing into this context modifications to a very successful tool of theoretical kinetics, Eyring's Transition-State Theory: considering the behavior of the transitivity function at low temperatures, in order to describe deviation from Arrhenius behavior under the quantum tunneling regime, a &#x0201c;<italic>d</italic>-TST&#x0201d; formulation was previously introduced (Carvalho-Silva et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In this paper, a special attention is dedicated to a derivation of the temperature dependence of viscosity, making explicit reference to feature of the transitivity function, which in this case generally exhibits a <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius behavior. This is of relevance also for advantages of using the transitivity function for diffusion-controlled phenomena.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>transitivity plot</kwd><kwd>Aquilanti-Mundim (AM) formula</kwd><kwd>Nakamura-Takayanagi-Sato (NTS) formula</kwd><kwd>Volgel-Fulcher-Tammann (VFT) formula</kwd><kwd>viscosity and diffusion</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="39"/><ref-count count="101"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="8720"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>To understand and control the physical chemistry of materials in an ample variety of environments that may be encountered in basic and applied scientific research, information on the kinetics of the involved elementary processes and their role in global mechanisms is needed: of particular interest are the rates, and often in a wide range of conditions&#x02014;specifically of temperature. Theoretical and computational studies are of increasing utility, especially in the cases where experimental results are difficult to obtain, or the measurements are difficult to interpret. Examples span all of chemistry: from the long list that is continuously updated, we refer here to some selected cases from: combustion chemistry (Atkinson, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>); condensed-phase (Limbach et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), atmospheric and astrochemical reactions (Smith, <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Sims, <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>); processes involved in preservation and aging of food and drugs (Darrington and Jiao, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Peleg et al., <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) as well as in basic geochemical (e.g., Giordano and Russell, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) and biochemical environments (e.g., Klinman and Kohen, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Warshel and Bora, <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>A variety of techniques has been applied with remarkable success in several scenarios to investigate the mechanisms to both calculate and interpret the kinetics of reactive processes at a microscopic level (Sikorski et al., <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Pu et al., <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Wang et al., <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Hassanali et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>; Santin et al., <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Roy et al., <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). From the early Arrhenius (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">1889</xref>) and Eyring (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">1935</xref>) formulations, demands emerge for interpretative theoretical tools to study the kinetics of chemical reactions and to phenomenological account of reaction rate data as generated from exact quantum benchmarks or from approximate semi-classical and classical trajectory approaches.</p><p>The seminal phenomenological description of the reaction rate constants, date of birth of theoretical chemical kinetics as a science, can be traced back to 1889 with the empirical formulation of the Arrhenius formula (Arrhenius, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">1889</xref>; Laidler, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>R</italic> is the gas constant and <italic>T</italic> is the absolute temperature. The pre-factor <italic>A</italic> (often found to be temperature independent) has sometimes been given the meaning and the name of a &#x0201c;frequency factor.&#x0201d; The quantity <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> is termed the &#x0201c;energy of activation&#x0201d; of the reaction; according to the Arrhenius interpretation, it represents the energy that the molecule in the initial state of the process must acquire before it can take part in the reaction, whether it be a physical or a chemical process. In the Arrhenius plane prompted by Equation (1) the logarithm of a reaction rate constant, ln <italic>k</italic>(<italic>T</italic>) is plotted against reciprocal temperature, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>: for systems that obey the Arrhenius law, Equation (1), a linear behavior is observed.</p><p>Formulations from first principles of theoretical reaction rates only became realistic after the advent of quantum and statistical mechanics. The Eyring formulation (~1935) proposes a consistent and predictive theory for the kinetic reaction rate constant: the celebrated Transition-State Theory (TST) (Eyring, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">1935</xref>; Glasstone et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1941</xref>) provided the basis for the understanding of many phenomena and triggered most of the subsequent proposals for the understanding of physicochemical rate processes. However, as traditionally implemented, TST is unable to cope with systems with strong deviation from Arrhenius behavior (Masgrau et al., <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The chemical reactions for which quantum tunneling effects play an important role are those where Arrhenius plots show a concave curvature (Limbach et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Silva et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Sanches-Neto et al., <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>): this is the most important case of <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius kinetics for elementary reactions, but in complex processes it may show up, e.g., when concurrent reactions contribute to the mechanism (Hulett, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">1964</xref>; Perlmutter-Hayman, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>; Vyazovkin, <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>Eyring himself amplified the scope of his TST beyond elementary reactions proposing a formulation for including the description of viscosity and diffusion of fluids in physicochemical rate processes (Glasstone et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1941</xref>). However, an ample set of old and more recent data in wide ranges of temperature has been showing again and again a strong convex curvature in Arrhenius plot for both viscosity and diffusion in fluids (Angell, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015b</xref>; Giordano and Russell, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). There are examples of <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius kinetics, rare for elementary processes (Truhlar and Kohen, <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>), but that in complex processes are common, in particular when consecutive reactions contribute to the mechanism (Hulett, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">1964</xref>; Perlmutter-Hayman, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>; Vyazovkin, <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>): these are characteristic cases of <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius kinetics for which the traditional Eyring's transition-state formulation fails. However, the TST connection between the potential energy surface profile with the phenomenological apparent activation energy through Tolman Theorem (Tolman, <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">1920</xref>), serves as a guide toward an interpretation of deviation from Arrhenius behavior.</p><p>In previous work (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) evidence emerged for introducing the phenomenological <italic>Transitivity function</italic> &#x003b3;(<italic>T</italic>) which regulates transit in physicochemical transformations and can be put into a relationship with traditional and recent reaction rate constant formulas available in the literature. With respect to other popular phenomenological approaches, ours arguably offers flexibility for the description of the experimental data over a wide range of temperature alternative to other formulas, that were applied to various sets of problems, ranging from particle diffusion and viscosity in supercooled liquids and glasses (Angell, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Stillinger and Debenedetti, <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) to food and drug preservation and aging processes (Peleg et al., <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>The still popular Kooij formula (Kooij, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">1893</xref>) involving an arbitrary <italic>T</italic><sup><italic>n</italic></sup> parameter multiplying the pre-factor <italic>A</italic> has no justification and is often unable to reproduce observations. Kooij formulation has to be discouraged and is physically unrealistic. It should be abandoned because: (i) at high temperature, the Arrhenius Activation energy is not recovered; (ii) at intermediate temperatures, the non-Arrhenius description is illusory valid only in extremely narrow ranges and is mathematically arbitrary; (iii) at low and ultra-low temperatures, there is consensus that non-Arrhenius behavior is pronounced, and the Kooij formula tends to Arrhenius law in clear disagreement with transitivity concept. Also, the Arrhenius-Break Temperature (ABT) formulation (Kumamoto et al., <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">1971</xref>; Kubo, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>) is often one commonly used: it involves two additional parameters beyond Arrhenius and may turn out misleading from an interpretative viewpoint&#x02014;when possible, it should be avoided in compacting data for modeling.</p><p>The suitability of the transitivity function is being checked against a variety of phenomenological examples with respect to its power to account for deviation from Arrhenius behavior. Here, we will show details on the treatment for amplifying the insight in various directions (section Transitivity Defined). In the subsequent section, specifically regarding the <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius case, we establish the connections with the Vogel-Fulcher-Tammann treatments (VFT) (see Vogel, <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">1921</xref>; Fulcher, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">1925</xref>; Tammann and Hesse, <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">1926</xref>) via the transitivity function. We also generalize the <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius case discussing in a uniform way the trend toward Wigner' limit (Wigner, <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">1948</xref>), yielding Nakamura-Takayanagi-Sato (NTS) formula (Nakamura et al., <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>) and Aquilanti-Sanches-Coutinho-Carvalho (ASCC) (Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>) at low temperature. In section Transition-State Theory Extended to Moderate Tunneling (<italic>d</italic>-TST), the <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius case appropriate for extending the Transition-State Theory of Eyring (the <italic>d</italic>-TST formalism) is accounted for, as introduced and applied recently (Claudino et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Carvalho-Silva et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Sanches-Neto et al., <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). A special attention will be devoted in section Viscosity and Diffusion From the Transitivity Function to a derivation of the temperature dependence of viscosity of fluids from the transitivity function &#x003b3; according for the <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius behavior and establishing the connection with the diffusion coefficient through the Stokes-Einstein equation. The final section is devoted to additional and concluding remarks.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Transitivity Defined</title><sec><title>The Transitivity Plot</title><p>In this section, we will show how the properly defined &#x0201c;Transitivity&#x0201d; function &#x003b3;(<italic>T</italic>) regulates the transit in physicochemical transformations: in other words, it controls the rate of passage with no bias from the transition-state hypothesis. In the 1976 article of Berta Perlmutter-Hayman (Perlmutter-Hayman, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>) the concept of apparent activation energy <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> has been considered in a very deep detail: in her spirit 20 years later, the International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (Laidler, <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>) recommended the now accepted definition:</p><disp-formula id="E2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo class="qopname">ln</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mo class="qopname">ln</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>To be consistent with Equation (1), the assumption of constancy for <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> can be taken as valid for physicochemical processes, at least for the temperature range of interest but deviation occur. According to our classification of <italic>d</italic>-Arrhenius cases (Silva et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2017a</xref>), the deviations are considered as exhibiting <italic>sub</italic>-, <italic>super</italic>-, or <italic>anti</italic>-types of behavior.</p><p>An initial step in order to find out how to account in a simple form for these deviations, we search for a functional dependence of <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> according to a large variety of cases accumulated from experiments and simulations. In her thorough study, a few decades-old, Perlmutter-Hayman (Perlmutter-Hayman, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>) considered a large body of documentation where the dependence were regarded either as</p><disp-formula id="E3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>the latter form clearly inspired by the Arrhenius plot. We have been showing ample phenomenological evidence and deep theoretical motivation (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>) of the insight to be gained by studying</p><disp-formula id="E4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>i.e., to study the behavior of the reciprocal the activation energy studied against reciprocal of absolute temperature. Therefore, from now on, we find convenient to adopt the usual definition in statistical mechanics, of the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> sometime referred to as &#x0201c;the coldness&#x0201d; (e.g., M&#x000fc;ller, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1971</xref>) and often referred as to the Lagrange parameter, because of its ubiquitous role in statistical mechanics where it occurs in optimization procedures involving the Lagrange multipliers.</p><p>From a decade-old work (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), the observation arose that the reciprocal of <italic>E</italic><sub>a</sub> vs. the reciprocal of absolute temperature yielded an approximate linearization by the <italic>d</italic> parameter (italic symbol for the linearization parameter should not be confused with the roman d denoting differentials). Writing as customary the Arrhenius-Eyring energy barrier, &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02021;</sup>, as essentially an energetic obstacle toward reaction, we have</p><disp-formula id="E5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Introducing the &#x0201c;transitivity&#x0201d; function through the identifications</p><disp-formula id="E6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02261;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>and also putting</p><disp-formula id="E7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Equation (5) takes the simple form</p><disp-formula id="E8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>In general, as discussed in preceding work (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>), a linear &#x003b3; dependence from &#x003b2; may be only valid in a specific range around a value &#x003b2;<sub>0</sub>; on a wider range, we can always assume that the function is well-behaved, namely that it has a Laurent power expansion,</p><disp-formula id="E9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where the <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> coefficients are related to <italic>n</italic>-order derivatives of &#x003b3;(&#x003b2;) with respect to &#x003b2;, taken at &#x003b2;<sub>0</sub>.</p><p>The task of a theory of the kinetics of chemical reactions is therefore focused at that of providing a set of such coefficients to connect to experimental or computationally generated <italic>k</italic>(<italic>T</italic>) via Equations (2 and 6). Advantages now are shown for the introduction of the &#x0201c;Transitivity Plot,&#x0201d; defining as the plane &#x003b3; vs. &#x003b2;, which gives insight into the idea of the &#x0201c;canonical&#x0201d; dependence of the &#x003b3; function in regulating transitions in physicochemical processes (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The transitivity plane, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:math></inline-formula>vs. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> serves to give a geometrical meaning to the phenomenological parameters occurring in the study of non-linear Arrhenius plots. The Arrhenius behavior is given as corresponding to a line parallel to the &#x003b2; axis starting at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> and corresponds to a constant apparent activation energy <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>. The well-known double dagger notation was introduced by Eyring (Eyring, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">1935</xref>; Glasstone et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1941</xref>). Deviations from Arrhenius behavior gives to the &#x003b3; function straight line dependence at small &#x003b2; a direction forming the &#x003b4; angle, which it is connected to the <italic>d</italic> parameter of the Aquilanti-Mundim (AM) law. At low temperatures as the &#x0201c;coldness&#x0201d; variable &#x003b2; increases, the transitivity function tends to characteristic ultra-cold limiting values: (i) for <italic>d</italic> &#x0003c; 0 (<italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius) it tends to the Wigner limit and (ii) for <italic>d</italic> &#x0003e; 0 (<italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius), &#x003b3;, namely the propensity for reaction to occur, vanishes in &#x003b2;<sup>&#x02020;</sup>, &#x003b3;(&#x003b2;<sup>&#x02020;</sup>) = 0: the corresponding energy and temperature parameters are denoted by a single dagger, &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02020;</sup>and <italic>T</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup>, respectively, as detailed below.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fchem-07-00380-g0001"/></fig><p>Consistently with the established nomenclature, one gets a positive linear dependence of &#x003b3;(&#x003b2;) for <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius (and negative for <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius, <italic>d</italic> &#x0003e; 0): this according to experimental and theoretical evidence from many sources (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Silva et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Defining in the transitivity plot <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, Equation (7), as a horizontal line (the Arrhenius line), the line of deviations from Arrhenius around &#x003b2;<sub>0</sub> forms &#x003b4; angle which can show <italic>sub</italic>- or <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius-type of behavior, corresponding to anticlock&#x02014;and clockwise direction from the &#x003b2; axis, respectively, yielding an expression corresponding to Equation (8),</p><disp-formula id="E10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo class="qopname">tan</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mo class="qopname">-tan</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>d</italic> &#x0003c; 0 (&#x003b4; &#x0003e; 0) corresponds to the <italic>sub</italic>- case while <italic>d</italic> &#x0003e; 0 (&#x003b4; &#x0003c; 0) corresponds to the <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius case. Rarer cases are found for which <italic>d</italic> &#x0003e; 0 and &#x003b1; &#x0003c; 0, and are referred as corresponding to <italic>anti</italic>-Arrhenius behavior (e.g., Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>).</p><p>The expression for the rate constant can be retrieved, integrating (10) from Equation (2). Introducing an integrating factor, <italic>A</italic> that accounts for a value for &#x003b3; at the reference value, e.g., &#x003b2; = 0: we obtain the Aquilanti-Mundim (AM) or <italic>d</italic>-Arrhenius formula in the form:</p><disp-formula id="E12"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo class="qopname">tan</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo class="qopname">cot</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Through Equations (7, 10) and introducing the Lagrange parameter, we finally obtain the AM formula</p><disp-formula id="E13"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M19"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>in the usual notation (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The Arrhenius law <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo class="qopname">exp</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is obtained in two well-defined cases at &#x003b2; &#x02192; 0 (high temperature limit) and at <italic>d</italic> &#x02192; 0 (the &#x0201c;thermodynamic&#x0201d; limit) (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Limiting Behaviors for the Transitivity Function at Low and High Temperature</title><p>In the AM formulation for <italic>k</italic>, Equation (12), when <italic>d</italic> or tan &#x003b4; tends to zero, one gets the exponential Arrhenius behavior through the Euler limit as detailed in Aquilanti et al. (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In this limit, to first order, the transitivity function deviate linearly from constancy (the Arrhenius behavior) as described by the AM formula. When &#x003b2; increases (low temperature):
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>in the <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius cases, continuing the straight-line behavior one encounters the &#x003b2; axis and gets for &#x003b3; a zero value for a maximum attainable value of &#x003b2;, denoted &#x003b2;<sup>&#x02020;</sup>. Here, one consequently gets a minimum value for the allowed temperature to be denoted <italic>T</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup>. However, in generic <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius behavior, sometimes high-order terms in the transitivity function are to be introduced to describe a sequence of processes, yielding concavities in the transitivity plot and moving the minimum temperature <italic>T</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup> at lower values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>);</p></list-item><list-item><p>in <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius cases, the linear growth of &#x003b3; as &#x003b2; increases may be accelerated at low temperatures: actual experimental information (Limbach et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Tizniti et al., <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Meng et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) is confirmed by computations (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; De Fazio et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Cavalli et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; De Fazio, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>) and is eventually governed by Wigner's limit (Wigner, <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">1948</xref>): before the latter limit is accessed interference effects may superimpose to quantum tunneling effects, which can be studied through microcanonical exact computations (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; De Fazio et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>).</p></list-item></list></p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The transitivity plot is presented for venerable and recent phenomenological reaction rate constant model to account for <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius behavior (Arrhenius, AM, and VFT) and <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius behavior (Arrhenius, AM, ASCC, and NTS). The comparison of the behavior of the transitivity between AM and VFT is exhibited assuming <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> in Equation (26).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fchem-07-00380-g0002"/></fig><p>We are now in the position to look at the <italic>d</italic>-parameter from alternative perspectives. For <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius cases, the &#x003b2; endpoint, &#x003b2;<sup>&#x02020;</sup>, marks the final low-temperature range for the system to be &#x0201c;active&#x0201d;: energetically, the introduction of the corresponding energy &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02020;</sup> = <italic>RT</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup>, permits the identification</p><disp-formula id="E14"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>For <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius, the connection of <italic>d</italic> with features of the potential energy barrier permits to describe quantum tunneling in elementary chemical reactions (see e.g., Silva et al., <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref> and next section).</p><p>Additional insight to the AM formula in Equation (5) for <italic>d</italic> &#x0003c; 0 is obtained when &#x003b2; tends to infinity yielding,</p><disp-formula id="E15"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="M23"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder class="msub"><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="qopname">lim</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Going back to the rate constant, integrating (14) from Equation (2), we obtain</p><disp-formula id="E16"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munder class="msub"><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="qopname">lim</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>formally appearing as the venerable Esson-Harcourt formula (Laidler, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>), and in consonance with the Wigner limit restricted to the case of thermoneutral reactions at ultra-low temperature (Takayanagi, <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Nevertheless, for <italic>d</italic> &#x0003e; 0 a minimum and constant reactivity is obtained for &#x003b2;<sup>&#x02020;</sup>,</p><disp-formula id="E17"><label>(16)</label><mml:math id="M25"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>In Equation (16), when &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02020;</sup> tends to infinity, <italic>k</italic>(&#x003b2;) = <italic>A</italic> respecting the Arrhenius limit (most other formulations do not).</p><p>After the description of the <italic>sub</italic>- and <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius cases in the limit <italic>d</italic> &#x02192; 0 at large &#x003b2;, we turn now to consider the limiting behavior as &#x003b2; &#x02192; 0, namely at high temperature. In most cases, the generic behavior is considered to be the tendency to the Arrhenius as a limit: situations may occur where this assumption has been relaxed [important examples are protein folding (Chan and Dill, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Wallace et al., <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) and reactions in sub- or super-critical solvent (Christensen and Sehested, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>; Lukac, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>; Marin et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>)]. We can take advantage of the following useful expansion (Abe and Okamoto, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Tsallis, <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="E19"><label>(17)</label><mml:math id="M27"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathsize="1.61em"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="-tex-caligraphic">O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathsize="1.61em"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Therefore, Arrhenius behavior is recovered both as &#x003b2; and <italic>d</italic> tend to zero independently:</p><disp-formula id="E20"><label>(18)</label><mml:math id="M28"><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>lim</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>const&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>lim</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>const&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02021;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Phenomenological Models of Temperature Dependence of Reaction Rate Constants through the Transitivity Function</title><p>The previous development opens the way to the next step of our study, the examination and classification through the transitivity concept of previous phenomenological proposals, assessing relationships between them and also attempting at giving a physicochemical meaning to their empirical parameters. As a bonus, more physically motivated formulas can be generated.</p><p>From Equations (2, 6), it is possible to build up the theoretical apparatus to connect experimental or computationally generated reaction rate constants to the transitivity function and <italic>vice</italic>-<italic>versa</italic>. Below traditional and recent phenomenological reaction rate constant formulas and transitivity function are presented to deal with <italic>sub</italic>- and <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius behavior with larger deviations than those not accounted for the AM <italic>d</italic>-Arrhenius formula (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>): VFT, ASCC, and NTS. The basic expression</p><disp-formula id="E21"><label>(19)</label><mml:math id="M29"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo class="qopname">exp</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="qopname">&#x0222b;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Can be employed, where clearly, <italic>A</italic> = <italic>k</italic>(&#x003b2;<sub>0</sub>) represents the initial condition (again, the differential under the integral sign is denoted by the roman letter d to avoid confusion with <italic>d</italic> in italic for the deviation parameters).</p><sec><title>Vogel&#x02013;Fulcher&#x02013;Tammann (VFT) Formula</title><p>It is insightful to obtain the expression for the transitivity function for perhaps the most popular equation for modeling <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius behavior, the Vogel&#x02013;Fulcher&#x02013;Tammann (VFT) formula (Vogel, <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">1921</xref>; Fulcher, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">1925</xref>; Tammann and Hesse, <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">1926</xref>), here written as a rate constant in an Arrhenius-like fashion, but involving one additional parameter:</p><disp-formula id="E22"><label>(20)</label><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo class="qopname">exp</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>A, B, and T</italic><sub>0</sub> are the fitting parameters: they are often designated, respectively being often denoted as the pre-factor, pseudo-activation energy and VFT-temperature, respectively. It is noteworthy, that in the polymer and food science community (Angell, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Peleg et al., <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015b</xref>) Equation (20) is also known as the Williams-Landel-Ferry (WLF) equation: see (Williams et al., <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">1955</xref>; Dudowicz et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) where the equivalence among the respective parameters is demonstrated explicitly.</p><p>The VFT transitivity function is obtained directly from the definition through the analytical logarithmic differentiation of Equation (20) with respect to &#x003b2;: The result is</p><disp-formula id="E23"><label>(21)</label><mml:math id="M31"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>That can be worked out in a more compact representation,</p><disp-formula id="E24"><label>(22)</label><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Here, formula (22) adds insight on the VFT parametrization for &#x003b3; by a summarizing comparison with the Arrhenius and with the AM formulations for the transitivity function: the following general expression,</p><disp-formula id="E25"><label>(23)</label><mml:math id="M33"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>covers three cases for different values of <italic>n</italic>: (i) for <italic>n</italic> = 0 one recovers Arrhenius formula, (ii) for <italic>n</italic> = 1 the AM formula is obtained, and (iii) for <italic>n</italic> = 2 one gets the VFT (and WLF) formula. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, in the transitivity plane, a geometrical interpretation can be given and leads to</p><disp-formula id="E26"><label>(24)</label><mml:math id="M34"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo class="qopname">tan</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>in limiting case of &#x003b2; tending to zero,</p><disp-formula id="E27"><label>(25)</label><mml:math id="M35"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>lim</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathsize="normal"><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>lim</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02021;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02021;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>and the comparison between <italic>n</italic> = 1 (AM) and <italic>n</italic> = 2 (VFT) parametrizations is shown to be</p><disp-formula id="E28"><label>(26)</label><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>See details in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, where the ASCC and NTS formulas, to be discussed next, are also considered.</p></sec><sec><title>Deep Tunneling and the ASCC Formula</title><p>As reported in the earlier literature (Bell, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1980</xref>; Christov, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>), the degree of concavity in the Arrhenius plot can be correlated with the assessment of the role of tunneling in chemical reactions: the definition of a &#x0201c;crossover temperature,&#x0201d;</p><disp-formula id="E29"><label>(27)</label><mml:math id="M37"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="MathClass-ord">&#x0210f;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>permits to conventionally establish (within some arbitrariness) the ranges of tunneling regimes for a specific imaginary frequency at the top of the barrier point, consistently denoted by a double dagger, &#x003bd;<sup>&#x02021;</sup>: classical (<italic>T</italic> &#x0003e; 4<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>), negligible(4<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x0003e; <italic>T</italic> &#x0003e; 2<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>), moderate (2<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x0003e; <italic>T</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>) and deep (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &#x0003e; <italic>T</italic>) regimes. The ranges of tunneling regimes are indicative of the importance of quantum tunneling to affect rate constants in particular cases. From a mathematical viewpoint, the AM formulation has clear limitations in the description of the deep tunneling regime toward the Wigner limit (Wigner, <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">1948</xref>)</p><disp-formula id="E30"><label>(28)</label><mml:math id="M38"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>lim</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0221d;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Details pertinent to the present discussion can be found in a very useful reference (Takayanagi et al., <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>).</p><p>As a counterpart for <italic>sub</italic>-Arrhenius behavior of the <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius VFT formula, it is argued that cases of deep tunneling can be dealt by introducing a modified form of the AM formula (Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>), defined as <italic>Aquilanti-Sanches-Coutinho-Carvalho</italic> (ASCC) expression:</p><disp-formula id="E31"><label>(29)</label><mml:math id="M39"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> as reported in Silva et al. (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and references therein. Here, the formulation introduces the three <italic>A</italic>, &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02021;</sup> and &#x003bd;<sup>&#x02021;</sup> parameters and reproduces the Wigner limit at low temperature, &#x003b2; &#x02192; &#x0221e;. The ASCC transitivity function can be worked out considering the logarithmic differentiation of Equation (29) with respect to &#x003b2; and the result is</p><disp-formula id="E32"><label>(30)</label><mml:math id="M41"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>or in a more compact representation,</p><disp-formula id="E33"><label>(31)</label><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02021;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02021;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02021;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02021;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>For small values of <italic>d&#x003b5;</italic><sup>&#x02021;</sup>, an analogous to VFT formula is recovered, see Equation (22). The ASCC formula was initially applied in Coutinho et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>) for astrochemical reactions in extremely cold environments generated by &#x0201c;exact&#x0201d; benchmark quantum dynamics. More results of applications will be given elsewhere for a variety of processes that involve deep tunneling.</p></sec><sec><title>Nakamura-Takayanagi-Sato (NTS) Formula</title><p>A flexible approach to describe the deep tunneling phenomenology was proposed 30 years ago by Nakamura et al. (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>) and Sato (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>): their formula evolves smoothly behavior down to low temperature and with respect to the tendency toward the Wigner limit (Wigner, <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">1948</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="E34"><label>(32)</label><mml:math id="M43"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo class="qopname">exp</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>A</italic>, &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02021;</sup> and <italic>T</italic><sub>0</sub> are the parameters. Again, &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02021;</sup> is essentially the fitting parameter bearing connection with the barrier height along the minimum energy pathway to reaction.</p><p>Also, in this case, we can work out the Nakamura-Takayanagi-Sato transitivity function</p><disp-formula id="E35"><label>(33)</label><mml:math id="M44"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Beyond Eyring</title><sec><title>Transition-State Theory Extended to Moderate Tunneling (<italic>d</italic>-TST)</title><p>Eyring's Transition-State Theory (TST) and its variants are frequently used to compute rates of chemical reactions typically assuming a well-defined activated complex. The theory has been the object of a number of studies yielding a variety of formulations based on the concept of an equilibrium between the reactants and the activated complex, all assumed with Boltzmann distributions of the internal degrees of freedom. The rate of transformation is, then, obtained by a combining of thermodynamics, kinetics, quantum chemistry, and statistical mechanics arguments. The authoritative textbook is (Glasstone et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1941</xref>). For a general bimolecular reaction, such as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, it is necessary to compute the <italic>Q</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>Q</italic><sub>2</sub>, and <italic>Q</italic><sup>&#x02021;</sup> partition functions of <italic>R</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>R</italic><sub>2</sub> and of the transition state, respectively. However, the conventional TST is not able to account for low temperature curvatures in the Arrhenius plot, particularly when due to quantum tunneling through the reaction barriers (for the viscosity of fluids see next section). To account for the quantum tunneling in chemical reactions, the transitivity function is modeled in analogy with the AM formula, yielding the <italic>deformed-</italic>Transition-State Theory (<italic>d</italic>-TST) (Carvalho-Silva et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="E36"><label>(34)</label><mml:math id="M46"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bd;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>h</italic> is the Planck's constant and &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02021;</sup> is the effective height of the energy barrier, given by the sum of the harmonic zero-point energy correction and the height of the potential energy barrier. This formulation uniformly covers the range from classical to moderate tunneling regimes but is inadequate for deep tunneling. The proposed variant of transition-state theory permits comparison with experiments and tests against alternative formulations (see e.g., Claudino et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Santin et al., <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Sanches-Neto et al., <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Viscosity and Diffusion From the Transitivity Function</title><p>Eyring's proposal of a kinetic rate theory was also amplified toward the description of viscosity and diffusion of fluids in physicochemical processes (Eyring, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">1936</xref>; Glasstone et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1941</xref>). Eventually, it turned out that the theory was unable to describe processes in a wide temperature range, in particular when presenting a convex curvature in the Arrhenius plot. In the present context, this is a manifestation of <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius kinetics (Truhlar and Kohen, <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015b</xref>; Giordano and Russell, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). To describe deviations from Arrhenius of the rates of reaction in fluids, we take into account later developments by Kramers (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">1940</xref>) and Collins and Kimball (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">1949</xref>), involving viscosity and diffusion.</p><p>To account for the temperature dependence of viscosity in cases clearly exhibiting <italic>super</italic>-Arrhenius behavior, we introduce a treatment using the transitivity function concept. From the defining, Equations (2) and (6) we obtain the differential equation,</p><disp-formula id="E37"><label>(35)</label><mml:math id="M47"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>For &#x003b2;<sub>0</sub> = 0 as the lower limit of integration range and the restriction to only two terms of the Taylor&#x02013;McLaurin series of Equation (9), we obtain the AM transitivity function, where &#x003b1; &#x0003c; 0 represents an energetic propensity toward to evolution of the fluid. The <italic>d</italic> is again the deformation parameter, playing an analogous role to that amply discussed previously: the result is an AM-like formula for viscosity (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>),</p><disp-formula id="E38"><label>(36)</label><mml:math id="M48"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>here &#x003b7;<sub><italic>o</italic></sub> is introduced as a counterpart of Arrhenius pre-factor <italic>A</italic> and is the viscosity when the temperature tends to infinity (&#x003b2; &#x02192; 0). At low temperature, in viscous processes the apparent activation energy turns out to increase indefinitely and consequently the propensity to proceed to a kinetic transition approaches zero, &#x003b3; &#x02192; 0: so we establish a direct relationship for the <italic>d</italic> parameter (analogous to the cases dealt in section Limiting Behaviors for the Transitivity Function at Low and High Temperature):</p><disp-formula id="E39"><label>(37)</label><mml:math id="M49"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>and <italic>T</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup> is identified as a phenomenological &#x0201c;freezing&#x0201d; temperature of the process, namely the critical temperature (to be connected with that of glass transition, see Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>), where the kinetic energy of the fluid particles is too low for the process to be turned on. In the early approach by Eyring (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">1936</xref>) and Glasstone et al. (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1941</xref>), it was argued that the &#x003b5;<sup>&#x02021;</sup> parameter be empirically put into relationship with the energy of vaporization of the fluid, &#x00394;<italic>H</italic><sub><italic>vap</italic></sub>, and intuitively connected with the work required to make a hole of molecular size.</p><p>Using the Kauzmann-Eyring pre-factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Kauzmann and Eyring, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">1940</xref>; Glasstone et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">1941</xref>), where <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> is the Avogadro number and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51"><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the molar volume, and Equation (37) for <italic>d</italic>, we finally obtain,</p><disp-formula id="E40"><label>(38)</label><mml:math id="M52"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>when <italic>T</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup> tends to zero, the Arrhenius-Eyring exponential formula for viscosity is recovered, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53"><mml:mi>&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo class="qopname">exp</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02021;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02020;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> through the Euler limit.</p><p>The deviation from Arrhenius behavior in the temperature dependence of diffusion can now be evaluated from Equation (39) through the Stokes-Einstein equation(Einstein, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">1905</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="E41"><label>(39)</label><mml:math id="M54"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x003c0;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b7;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>r</italic> is the hydrodynamic radius (Henriksen and Hansen, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). This treatment of course does not provide further insight into these amply investigated issues, but points at a simple and perhaps useful physical interpretation of a long-standing as well recent intriguing rate phenomena. From a general perspective, the theory encourages considering wide ranges of available data on geochemistry (Giordano and Russell, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), supercooled liquids science (Angell, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>) and biochemistry (Kohen et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) and digging for hidden insights. Preliminary searches, to be published, turned on successful.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Additional and Final Remarks</title><p>This paper applies thoroughly the transitivity concept to a set of topics, completing the presentation of the theory outlined in Aquilanti et al. (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>). A separated paper (Machado et al., submitted) presents the code developed for the implementation to a set of cases of interest in physicochemical kinetics where the need for deviation from Arrhenius behavior is demanded: applications of our formulation can be accessed in the homepage of our computational code&#x02014;Transitivity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vhcsgroup.com/transitivity">www.vhcsgroup.com/transitivity</ext-link>), where manual, installation video, and specific examples are provided. Further remarks follow:</p><sec><title><italic>Ab initio</italic> &#x0201c;Exact&#x0201d; Quantum Dynamics</title><p>In principle, this is the most valuable source of kinetics data but still limited to simple benchmark cases. For full formulations of the reaction kinetics, following the microcanonical path along a quantum chemically or empirically generated potential energy surface, high-level computational effort is demanded. It typically proceeds according to these steps: a) calculation of the intermolecular interactions involved in a reactive process with a high-level of accuracy, b) dynamical evolution in phase-space configurations from the solution of quantum equations of motion, c) identification of reactive trajectories, with consequent calculation of the quantum scattering matrix, cumulative reaction probability and cross sections. Finally, the Boltzmann weight averaging over a large span of kinetics energies yields the canonical expressions of kinetic variables as a function of temperature. These severe prescriptions have been able to provide the exact calculation over a given potential energy surface for reaction rate constants of only a limited number of reactive systems: in fact, the complexity of the programming and the computationally demanding requirements and computational demand strongly limit the study of reactive processes involving only a few atoms. Additional reactions involving isotopic exchange among three hydrogen atoms, exemplary benchmarks to be cited are the three-body reactions: F + H<sub>2</sub> (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), F + HD (De Fazio et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Cavalli et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), H + HeH<sup>+</sup> (De Fazio, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) see also and references therein.</p></sec><sec><title>First-Principles Molecular Dynamics</title><p>Another viable path is becoming possible thanks to improvements in computational facilities, in order to access at kinetic information through first-principles molecular dynamics simulations. However, computationally severe storing and time constraints permitting to obtain myriads of &#x0201c;on-the-fly trajectories&#x0201d; require a great effort toward the aim of generating realistic reactive kinetic data: this in spite of the fact that a wide research activity has been pursued, aiming at developing techniques capable of accurately predicting kinetic reaction rate constants from molecular dynamics simulations. Among examples that have been tackled in recent years, we cite (Pomerantz et al., <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>; D&#x000f6;ntgen et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Fleming et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Wu et al., <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and references therein. However, calculation of reaction rate constants has been limited by the arduous procedures both to accurately characterize reactive activated complexes of many body systems and to overcome the inherent difficulties of producing a number of trajectories with statistical consistency and reasonable completeness in the filling of the dynamically relevant parts of the phase-space. Recently, several works have been yielding values with reliable accuracy: overestimates due to limited sampling of phase-space, when experimental values are available for comparison, may exploit empirical calibration (Coutinho et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2018a</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Phenomenological Considerations and the Role of the Transitivity Concept</title><p>Experimentally and computationally generated kinetic data for polyatomic molecules provide reaction rate constants with the implicit fingerprint of the microscopical variables at work in the reactive process (Angell, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Kohen et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Limbach et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Giordano and Russell, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Capitelli and Pietanza, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, and references therein). Application of the techniques discussed in previous remarks is tremendously laborious for many-body systems: when the Arrhenius law is not obeyed at low temperature transitivity function guides us to an as a fruitful and consistent approach. As discussed in this article the approach turns out to be a powerful tool, capable of establishing a connection between canonical data and microcanonical information, permitting comparisons among apparently uncorrelated formulations: it also allows interpretation of empirical parameters, for example for the AM, ASCC, VFT and NTS formulas considered in this paper. Previous (Tsallis and Bukman, <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Lenzi et al., <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; JiangLin et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Zhou and Du, <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and concomitant (Zhou and Du, <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Guo and Du, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Rosa et al., <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Junior et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) efforts have been dedicated to provide also a connection of anomalous kinetic diffusion effects while surmounting a potential barrier <italic>via</italic> variants of Fokker-Planck equation, tackling a class of phenomenologically physicochemical diffusion process.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion and Perspectives</title><p>In order to extend the validity of the Arrhenius rate law, the introduction of the deformation parameter <italic>d</italic> not only phenomenologically mimics the low temperature dependence of rate constants, but its relevance in producing physical insight is now amply demonstrated. The statistical mechanics aspects are now firmly established (Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) capitalizing on various investigations inspired openly or implicitly on a Maxwellian approach: several examples in the literature have been inspiring the transfer from thermodynamics to the field of kinetics assuming procedures for taking the &#x0201c;thermodynamic limit.&#x0201d; Venerable papers are (Jeans, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">1913</xref>; Condon, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">1938</xref>; Kennard, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">1938</xref>; Landau and Lifshitz, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">1958</xref>), and recent ones (Tsallis, <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Bir&#x000f3; et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Aquilanti et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this manuscript will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation, to any qualified researcher.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors listed have made a substantial, direct and intellectual contribution to the work, and approved it for publication.</p><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>VHC-S thanks Brazilian agency CNPq for the research funding programs [Universal 01/2016&#x02014;Faixa A&#x02212;406063/2016-8] and Organizzazione Internazionale Italo-Latino Americana (IILA) for Biotechnology Sector-2019 scholarship. VA and NDC acknowledge the Italian Ministry for Education, University and Research, MIUR, for financial support: SIR 2014 Scientific Independence for young Researchers (RBSI14U3VF).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Nonextensive Statistical Mechanics and Its Applications. Springer Berlin Heidelberg</source>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.com.br/books?id=caNqCQAAQBAJ">https://books.google.com.br/books?id=caNqCQAAQBAJ</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angell</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Formation of glasses from liquids and biopolymers</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>267</volume>, <fpage>1924</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1935</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.267.5206.1924</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17770101?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17770101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angell</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Why C1 = 16&#x02013;17 in the WLF equation is physical&#x02014;and the fragility of polymers</article-title>. <source>Polymer (Guildf).</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>6261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6266</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0032-3861(97)00201-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angell</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Liquid fragility and the glass transition in water and aqueous solutions</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>2627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2650</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr000689q</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12175262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12175262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coletti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Littlejohn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017a</year>). <source>Combinatorial and Geometrical Origins of Regge Symmetries: Their Manifestations From Spin-Networks to Classical Mechanisms, and Beyond</source> (<publisher-loc>Trieste; Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-62404-4_23</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>From statistical thermodynamics to molecular kinetics: the change, the chance and the choice</article-title>. <source>Rend. Lincei. Sci. Fis. Nat.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12210-018-0749-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Fazio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Volpi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Benchmark rate constants by the hyperquantization algorithm. The F + H<sub>2</sub> reaction for various potential energy surfaces: features of the entrance channel and of the transition state, and low temperature reactivity</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>308</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>253</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemphys.2004.03.027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017b</year>). <article-title>Kinetics of low-temperature transitions and reaction rate theory from non-equilibrium distributions</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. London A</source>
<volume>375</volume>:<fpage>20160204</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsta.2016.0201</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28320904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28320904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elango</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleijn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Temperature dependence of chemical and biophysical rate processes: phenomenological approach to deviations from Arrhenius law</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>498</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cplett.2010.08.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arrhenius</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1889</year>). <article-title>On the reaction rate of the inversion of non-refined sugar upon souring</article-title>. <source>Z. Phys. Chem.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>226</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Kinetics and mechanisms of the gas-phase reactions of the hydroxyl radical with organic compounds under atmospheric conditions</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr00071a004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <source>The Tunnel Effect in Chemistry</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Champman and Hall</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnaf&#x000f6;ldi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000dc;rm&#x000f6;ssy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Statistical power law due to reservoir fluctuations and the universal thermostat independence principle</article-title>. <source>Entropy</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>6497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6514</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/e16126497</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capitelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietanza</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Past and present aspects of Italian plasma chemistry</article-title>. <source>Rend. Lincei. Sci. Fis. Nat.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12210-019-00781-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Deformed transition-state theory: deviation from Arrhenius behavior and application to bimolecular hydrogen transfer reaction rates in the tunneling regime</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Chem.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.24529</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27859380?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27859380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Fazio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Theoretical reaction kinetics astride the transition between moderate and deep tunneling regimes: the F + HD case</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. A</source>
<volume>118</volume>, <fpage>6632</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6641</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp503463w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24893210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24893210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Protein folding in the landscape perspective: Chevron plots and non-Arrhenius kinetics</article-title>. <source>Proteins Struct. Funct. Genet.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0134(19980101)30:1&#x0003c;2::AID-PROT2&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-R</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9443337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9443337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehested</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Reaction of hydroxyl radicals with hydrogen at elevated temperatures. Determination of the activation energy</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem.</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/j100224a027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christov</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The characteristic (crossover) temperature in the theory of thermally activated tunneling processes</article-title>. <source>Mol. Eng.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008274213168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claudino</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gargano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>E Silva</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Cunha</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Investigation of the abstraction and dissociation mechanism in the nitrogen trifluoride channels: combined post-hartree-fock and transition state theory approaches</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. A</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>5464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5473</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpca.6b04947</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27355487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27355487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimball</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1949</year>). <article-title>Diffusion-controlled reaction rates</article-title>. <source>J. Colloid Sci.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0095-8522(49)90023-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Condon</surname><given-names>E. U.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1938</year>). <article-title>A simple derivation of the Maxwell-Boltzmann Law</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>937</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>940</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRev.54.937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>V. H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>H. C. B. de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Stereodirectional origin of anti-Arrhenius kinetics for a tetra-atomic hydrogen exchange reaction: Born-Oppenheimer molecular dynamics for OH + HBr</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem.</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>5408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5417</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpca.6b03958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>H. C. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The HI + OH &#x02192; H<sub>2</sub>O + I reaction by first-principles molecular dynamics: stereodirectional and anti-Arrhenius kinetics</article-title>, in <source>Computational Science and Its Applications&#x02014;ICCSA 2017</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gervasi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murgante</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borruso</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>A. M. A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apduhan</surname><given-names>B. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuzzocrea</surname><given-names>E. S. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Trieste</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>), <fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>313</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-62404-4_22</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanches-Neto</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>H. C. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018a</year>). <article-title>Kinetics of the OH + HCl &#x02192; H<sub>2</sub>O + Cl reaction: rate determining roles of stereodynamics and roaming and of quantum tunneling</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Chem.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>2508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2516</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.25597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30365178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>V. H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Oliveira</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015a</year>). <article-title>Stereodynamical origin of anti-arrhenius kinetics: negative activation energy and roaming for a four-atom reaction</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. Lett.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1558</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpclett.5b00384</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26263312?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26263312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>V. H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>H. C. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015b</year>). <article-title>Description of the effect of temperature on food systems using the deformed Arrhenius rate law: deviations from linearity in logarithmic plots vs. inverse temperature</article-title>. <source>Rend. Lincei</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12210-015-0407-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Cavalli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018b</year>). <article-title>Chemical kinetics under extreme conditions: exact, phenomenological and first-principles computational approaches</article-title>, in <source>Rendiconti Accademia Nazionale delle Scienze detta dei XL</source> (<publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darrington</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Rapid and accurate prediction of degradant formation rates in pharmaceutical formulations using high-performance liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry</article-title>. <source>J. Pharm. Sci.</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>838</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>846</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jps.20006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14999722?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14999722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Fazio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The H + HeH<sup>+</sup> &#x02192; He+ H<sub>2+</sub> reaction from the ultra-cold regime to the three-body breakup: exact quantum mechanical integral cross sections and rate constants</article-title>. <source>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>11662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11672</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c4cp00502c</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24810283?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24810283</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Fazio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Exact quantum calculations of the kinetic isotope effect: cross sections and rate constants for the F + HD reaction and role of tunneling</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>133109</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.2221695</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17029435?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17029435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000f6;ntgen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Przybylski-Freund</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000f6;ger</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonhard</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Automated discovery of reaction pathways, rate constants, and transition states using reactive molecular dynamics simulations</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>2517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2524</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jctc.5b00201</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26575551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26575551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudowicz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The meaning of the &#x0201c;universal&#x0201d; WLF parameters of glass-forming polymer liquids</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>142</volume>:<fpage>014905</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4905216</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25573581?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25573581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Einstein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905</year>). <article-title>&#x000dc;ber die von der molekularkinetischen Theorie der W&#x000e4;rme geforderte Bewegung von in ruhenden Fl&#x000fc;ssigkeiten suspendierten Teilchen</article-title>. <source>Ann. Phys.</source>
<volume>322</volume>, <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>560</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/andp.19053220806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyring</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1935</year>). <article-title>The activated complex in chemical reactions</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1749604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyring</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>). <article-title>Viscosity, plasticity, and diffusion as examples of absolute reaction rates</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>291</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1749836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwary</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaendtner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>New approach for investigating reaction dynamics and rates with <italic>ab initio</italic> calculations</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. A</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpca.5b10667</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26690335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26690335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulcher</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1925</year>). <article-title>Analysis of recent measurements of the viscosity of glasses</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Ceram. Soc.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1151-2916.1925.tb16731.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Towards a structural model for the viscosity of geological melts</article-title>. <source>Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.</source>
<volume>501</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epsl.2018.08.031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasstone</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laidler</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyring</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1941</year>). <source>The Theory of Rate Processes: The Kinetics of Chemical Reactions, Viscosity, Diffusion and Electrochemical Phenomena. McGraw-Hill</source>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.com.br/books?id=7zwGAQAAIAAJ">https://books.google.com.br/books?id=7zwGAQAAIAAJ</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The precise time-dependent solution of the Fokker&#x02013;Planck equation with anomalous diffusion</article-title>. <source>Ann. Phys.</source>
<volume>359</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.AOP.2015.04.019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassanali</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuny</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdolino</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Aqueous solutions: state of the art in ab initio molecular dynamics</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci.</source>
<volume>372</volume>, <fpage>20120482</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20120482</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsta.2012.0482</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24516179?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24516179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>F. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Theories of Molecular Reaction Dynamics: The Microscopic Foundation of Chemical Kinetics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199203864.001.0001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hulett</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>). <article-title>Deviations from the Arrhenius equation</article-title>. <source>Q. Rev. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/qr9641800227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeans</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>). <source>The Dynamical Theory of Gases. Dover Publications Incorporated</source>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.com.br/books?id=UhJfawEACAAJ">https://books.google.com.br/books?id=UhJfawEACAAJ</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>JiangLin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenping</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Kramers escape rate in nonlinear diffusive media</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>024112</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.2150433</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16422576?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16422576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Junior</surname><given-names>A. C. do P. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moret</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <source>Characterization of the non-Arrhenius behavior of supercooled liquids by modeling non-additive stochastic systems</source>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.03156">http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.03156</ext-link> (accessed March 24, 2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kauzmann</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyring</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1940</year>). <article-title>The viscous flow of large molecules</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>3113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennard</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1938</year>). <source>Kinetic Theory of Gases: With an Introduction to Statistical Mechanics. McGraw-Hill</source>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.com.br/books?id=uP4gAAAAMAAJ">https://books.google.com.br/books?id=uP4gAAAAMAAJ</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klinman</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Hydrogen tunneling links protein dynamics to enzyme catalysis</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biochem-051710-133623</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23746260?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23746260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolucci</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klinman</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Enzyme dynamics and hydrogen tunnelling in a thermophilic alcohol dehydrogenase</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>399</volume>, <fpage>496</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>499</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/20981</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10365965?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10365965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kooij</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1893</year>). <article-title>&#x000dc;ber die Zersetzung des gasf&#x000f6;rmigen Phosphorwasserstoffs</article-title>. <source>Zeitschrift f&#x000fc;r Phys. Chemie</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/zpch-1893-1214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramers</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1940</year>). <article-title>Brownian motion in a field of force and the diffusion model of chemical reactions</article-title>. <source>Phys.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-8914(40)90098-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>A view on the break in the Arrhenius plots</article-title>. <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>569</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5193(85)80140-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumamoto</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raison</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>Temperature &#x0201c;breaks&#x0201d; in Arrhenius plots: a thermodynamic consequence of a phase change</article-title>. <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-5193(71)90120-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 5576777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5576777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laidler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Chemical kinetics</article-title>. <source>Harper Row</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>270</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/0-306-48390-4_2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laidler</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>The development of the Arrhenius equation</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Educ.</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ed061p494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laidler</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>A glossary of terms used in chemical kinetics, including reaction dynamics</article-title>. <source>Pure Appl. Chem.</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lifshitz</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>). <source>Statistical Physics. 5th Edn</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anteneodo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borland</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Escape time in anomalous diffusive media</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>51105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.63.051109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11414889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11414889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Limbach</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miguel Lopez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Arrhenius curves of hydrogen transfers: tunnel effects, isotope effects and effects of pre-equilibria</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B. Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>361</volume>, <fpage>1399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1415</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2006.1872</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16873127?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16873127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukac</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Modelling of radiolysis of reactor cooling water&#x02014;a comparative study</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Radiat. Appl. Instrumentation. Part C. Radiat. Phys. Chem.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>230</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/1359-0197(89)90143-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonah</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Reaction of OH<sup>*</sup> radicals with H2 in sub-critical water</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>371</volume>, <fpage>144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-2614(03)00064-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masgrau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Lafont</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lluch</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The curvature of the Arrhenius plots predicted by conventional canonical transition-state theory in the absence of tunneling</article-title>. <source>Theor. Chem. Accounts Theory, Comput. Model.</source>
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>357</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00214-003-0484-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.-R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Direct visualization of concerted proton tunnelling in a water nanocluster</article-title>. <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>239</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphys3225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>The coldness, a universal function in thermoelastic bodies</article-title>. <source>Arch. Ration. Mech. Anal.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>332</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00281870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayanagi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>A modified arrhenius equation</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>160</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0009-2614(89)87599-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peleg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Martinez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corradini</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Non-Arrhenius and non-WLF kinetics in food systems</article-title>. <source>J. Sci. Food Agric.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>1346</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1355</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/Jsfa.1175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peleg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Normand</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corradini</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The Arrhenius equation revisited</article-title>. <source>Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>851</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408398.2012.667460</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22698273?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22698273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perlmutter-Hayman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Progress in inorganic chemistry: on the temperature dependence of Ea</article-title>, in <source>Progress in Inorganic Chemistry</source>, ed. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lippard</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc.</publisher-name>), <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camden</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausfelder</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hase</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Reaction products with internal energy beyond the kinematic limit result from trajectories far from the minimum energy path: an example from H + HBr &#x02192; H <sub>2</sub> + Br</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>16368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16369</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja055440a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16305203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Truhlar</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Multidimensional tunneling, recrossing, and the transmission coefficient for enzymatic reactions</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>3140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3169</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cr050308e</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16895322?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16895322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>A. C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaveliuk</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moret</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A model for diffusive systems: beyond the Arrhenius mechanism</article-title>. <source>Phys. A Stat. Mech. its Appl.</source>
<volume>450</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2015.12.122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schopf</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warshel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Origin of the non-Arrhenius behavior of the rates of enzymatic reactions</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. B</source>
<volume>121</volume>, <fpage>6520</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6526</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpcb.7b03698</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28613876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28613876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanches-Neto</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>A novel assessment of the role of the methyl radical and water formation channel in the CH<sub>3</sub>OH + H reaction</article-title>. <source>Phys. Chem.Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>24467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24477</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7CP03806B</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28890979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28890979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santin</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho-Silva</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gargano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Methanol solvation effect on the proton rearrangement of Curcumin's Enol forms: an <italic>ab initio</italic> molecular dynamics and electronic structure viewpoint</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Chem. C</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>19923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19931</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpcc.6b02393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Tunneling in bimolecular reactions</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>315</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.CHEMPHYS.2005.01.034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sikorski</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkovic</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Tunneling and coupled motion in the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> dihydrofolate reductase catalysis</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>4778</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4779</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja031683w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15080672?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15080672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>V. H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquilanti</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Oliveira</surname><given-names>H. C. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundim</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Uniform description of non-Arrhenius temperature dependence of reaction rates, and a heuristic criterion for quantum tunneling vs classical non-extensive distribution</article-title>. <source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>590</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cplett.2013.10.051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>I. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Low-temperature reactions: tunnelling in space</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>734</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>736</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchem.1736</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23965671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23965671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The temperature-dependence of elementary reaction rates: beyond Arrhenius</article-title>. <source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>812</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>826</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/B704257B</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18362985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18362985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stillinger</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debenedetti</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Glass transition thermodynamics and kinetics</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>285</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-conmatphys-030212-184329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takayanagi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Theory of Atom Tunneling Reactions in the Gas Phase</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin; Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-662-05900-5_2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takayanagi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masaki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>The rate constants for the H + H<sub>2</sub> reaction and its isotopic analogs at low temperatures: Wigner threshold law behavior</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>6133</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.452453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tammann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1926</year>). <article-title>Die Abh&#x000e4;ngigkeit der Viscosit&#x000e4;t von der Temperatur bie unterk&#x000fc;hlten Fl&#x000fc;ssigkeiten</article-title>. <source>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem.</source>
<volume>156</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/zaac.19261560121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tizniti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Picard</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lique</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berteloite</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canosa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The rate of the F + H<sub>2</sub> reaction at very low temperatures</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>145</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchem.1835</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24451590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tolman</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>). <article-title>Statistical mechanics applied to chemical kinetics</article-title>. <source>J. Amer. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>2506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2528</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truhlar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Convex Arrhenius plots and their interpretation</article-title>. <source>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>848</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>851</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.98.3.848</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11158559?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsallis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Nonextensive statistics: theoretical, experimental and computational evidences and connections</article-title>. <source>Braz. J. Phys.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-97331999000100002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsallis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Introduction to Nonextensive Statistical Mechanics: Approaching a Complex World</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsallis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukman</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Anomalous diffusion in the presence of external forces: Exact time-dependent solutions and their thermostatistical basis</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>R2197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>R2200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.54.R2197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9965440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9965440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1921</year>). <article-title>Das temperature-abhangigketsgesetz der viskositat von flussigkeiten</article-title>. <source>Phys. Z.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>646</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vyazovkin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A time to search: finding the meaning of variable activation energy</article-title>. <source>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>18643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18656</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6CP02491B</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27137352?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27137352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klenerman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Non-Arrhenius kinetics for the loop closure of a DNA hairpin</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>5584</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5589</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.101523498</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11320222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11320222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paesani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The water hexamer: cage, prism, or both. Full dimensional quantum simulations say both</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>11116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11119</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja304528m</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22731508?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22731508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warshel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bora</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Perspective: Defining and quantifying the role of dynamics in enzyme catalysis</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>144</volume>:<fpage>180901</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4947037</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27179464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27179464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigner</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>). <article-title>On the behavior of cross sections near thresholds</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>1002</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1009</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRev.73.1002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landel</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1955</year>). <article-title>The temperature dependence of relaxation mechanisms in amorphous polymers and other glass-forming liquids</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>77</volume>, <fpage>3701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3707</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deetz</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Extracting the mechanisms and kinetic models of complex reactions from atomistic simulation data</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Chem.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1592</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.25809</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30802325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30802325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The mean first passage time in an energy-diffusion controlled regime with power-law distributions</article-title>. <source>J. Stat. Mech.</source>
<volume>11005</volume>:<fpage>P11005</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1742-5468/2013/11/P11005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Kramers escape rate in overdamped systems with the power-law distribution</article-title>. <source>Phys. Stat. Mech. Appl.</source>
<volume>402</volume>, <fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2014.01.065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>