<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-nanomaterials-09-00172" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the past two decades, colloidal semiconductor quantum dots (QDs) have attracted a great deal of attention due to their unique quantum-confined optical and electrical properties [
  <a rid="B1-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-nanomaterials-09-00172">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-nanomaterials-09-00172">2</a>]—namely, that the discrete electron energy levels near the Fermi energy level split from the continuum when the particle size is smaller than or comparable to the Bohr exciton radius. The most common quantum dot system contains cadmium-based chalcogenides [
  <a rid="B3-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-nanomaterials-09-00172">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-nanomaterials-09-00172">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-nanomaterials-09-00172">5</a>], which exhibit efficient size-dependent luminescence properties after proper surface passivation (i.e., shelling). However, the demanding synthetic chemistry for the stringent size control, the low tolerance of luminescence properties to defects, and the containment of poisonous heavy metal elements (e.g., cadmium) raise serious concerns for their practical photonic and biophotonic applications. To overcome these problems, new types of quantum dots have been investigated. Among them, much effort has recently been devoted to perovskite quantum dots, including inorgano-organometallic halide perovskites CH
  <sub>3</sub>NH
  <sub>3</sub>PbX
  <sub>3</sub> [
  <a rid="B6-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-nanomaterials-09-00172">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-nanomaterials-09-00172">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-nanomaterials-09-00172">8</a>], and all-inorganic halide perovskites CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> (X = Cl, Br, I). Compared with the organic–inorganic hybrid perovskite quantum dots, all-inorganic CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> (X = Cl, Br or I) perovskite quantum dots (hereafter denoted as CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> PQDs) show better performance, including ultra-high photoluminescence quantum yields, narrow emission bandwidth, large extinction coefficient, high tolerance to crystal defects, and good stability against moisture and oxygen [
  <a rid="B9-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-nanomaterials-09-00172">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-nanomaterials-09-00172">10</a>]. Moreover, the fact that the emission wavelengths of CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> PQDs can be tuned precisely by their composition instead of their size offers a significant advantage over traditional QDs, avoiding the need for complicated and demanding chemistry to produce a narrow band emission. Indeed, CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> PQDs with tunable and bright photoluminescent (PL) properties have been synthesized with different methods such as hot injection [
  <a rid="B11-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nanomaterials-09-00172">11</a>], anion exchange [
  <a rid="B12-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nanomaterials-09-00172">12</a>], ultrasonication [
  <a rid="B13-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-nanomaterials-09-00172">13</a>], solvothermal [
  <a rid="B14-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nanomaterials-09-00172">14</a>], and microwave-assisted [
  <a rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nanomaterials-09-00172">15</a>] methods, and different shapes have been designed [
  <a rid="B14-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nanomaterials-09-00172">14</a>] to obtain better photoelectric performance. Owing to their excellent photoelectric performance, CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> PQDs have great application potential in fields such as solar cells [
  <a rid="B16-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-nanomaterials-09-00172">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-nanomaterials-09-00172">17</a>], light-emitting diodes (LEDs) [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00172">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00172">19</a>], lasers [
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00172">20</a>], and photodetectors [
  <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00172">21</a>]. Although significant progress has been made in the synthesis and application of CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> PQDs, they still need to be explored by providing a comprehensive composition-defined luminescence and by theoretical calculation of structure and properties like band gaps and formation energies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herein, we report the synthesis of double/triple-halide CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> (X = Cl, Br, I) PQDs with precise ratios of Cl/Br or Br/I, using the hot-injection method. A series of light-emitting diodes covering the entire visible spectrum were fabricated and investigated. Furthermore, we applied a comprehensive approach to calculate the band gap and formation energy of the synthesized double/triple-halide CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> (X = Cl, Br, I) PQDs, namely, the projector-augmented plane wave (PAW) method [
  <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00172">22</a>] within the framework of density functional theory (DFT) implemented in the Vienna Ab-initio Simulation Package (VASP) [
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00172">23</a>]. Calculated data are presented and discussed in comparison with the experimental results.
 </p>
</sec>
