<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-nanomaterials-09-00172" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Experimental Section</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Chemicals and Reagents</span>: Cesium carbonate (Cs
  <sub>2</sub>CO
  <sub>3</sub>, 99.9%), 1-octadecene (ODE, ≥90%), oleic acid (OA, AR), oleylamine (OAm, 80–90%), lead chloride (PbCl
  <sub>2</sub>, 99.999%), lead bromide (PbBr
  <sub>2</sub>, 99.999%), and lead iodide (PbI
  <sub>2</sub>, 99.999%) were purchased from Aladdin (Shanghai, China). Hexane (≥95%) was purchased from Tianjin Chemical Works (Tianjin, China). All of the reagents were used without further purification.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Synthesis of Cs-Oleate Precursors</span>: First, Cs
  <sub>2</sub>CO
  <sub>3</sub> (0.816 g, 2.5 mmol), OA (2.5 mL), and ODE (40 mL) were added to a 250 mL three-neck flask and stirred at 125 °C under flowing nitrogen. After a 45-min reaction, the mixture became a clear solution and the Cs-oleate precursors were obtained. The Cs-oleate should be preheated to 100 °C before injection to maintain accuracy because Cs-oleate precipitates out of ODE at room temperature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Synthesis of Single- or Double/Triple-Halide CsPbX3 (X = Cl, Br, or I) PQDs</span>: Colloidal CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> PQDs were synthesized following Protesescu’s procedure [
  <a rid="B6-nanomaterials-09-00172" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-nanomaterials-09-00172">6</a>]. First, 0.6 mmol PbX
  <sub>2</sub> (X = Cl, Br, or I) mixed by a certain molar ratio and 14 mL ODE was added to a 250 mL three-neck flask. Then, the mixture was stirred and heated to 125 °C under flowing nitrogen. After 45 min, OA (2 mL) and OAm (2 mL) were injected into the reaction system to completely solubilize PbX
  <sub>2</sub> and the temperature was raised to 160 °C in the meantime. When a clear solution was obtained, the Cs-oleate precursor (3 mL), preheated to 100 °C, was quickly injected. After 10 s, the reaction system was cooled down by an ice-water bath to terminate the reaction. In order to get pure products, the turbid liquid was centrifuged at 6000 rpm for 5 min. After centrifugation, the supernatant was discarded and the precipitate at the bottom of the centrifuge tube was dispersed in 2 mL hexane. The centrifugation procedure was repeated at 10,000 rpm for 10 min. The final product was redispersed in 2 mL hexane and stored following purification.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">PQDs LED Device Fabrication</span>: The main agent A was mixed with the 10 μL n-hexane solution containing the PQDs and stirred thoroughly before adding the curing agent B. After adding the curing agent, the stirring time usually took 5 min. The PQDs powder and the agent were completely mixed, and the bubbles were removed by low-frequency ultrasound for subsequent use. The agent containing the PQDs was properly stirred and placed in the holder cup of the mold. The mold was put under UV light for 5 min to solidify the agent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Characterization</span>: The size and morphology of CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> PQDs were characterized by transmission electron microscopy (TEM) using a JEOL JEM-2010 microscope (JEOL Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) at an acceleration voltage of 200 kV. The PL spectra were measured by a spectrometer (Ocean Optics FLAME-S-VIS-NIR) under excitation at 365 nm using a UV lamp. X-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns were obtained using a D8 Focus X-ray diffractometer.
 </p>
</sec>
