<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dioxo-Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span>(porphyrin)
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, we want to demonstrate the ability of SNAP to describe chemical reactions. This is another hard challenge for conventional FFs, which generally fail in describing bond breaking. Reactive FFs are currently available (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>), but they typically require a large number of parameters. These FF parameters enter in the definition of the energy in a highly nonlinear form, so the construction of accurate potentials for molecules containing several atomic species is often an insurmountable task (
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>). The system chosen for this task is the Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span>(porphyrin) molecule coordinated with hystidine (Hys) and molecular oxygen. This coordination mimics the active site of the heme group. The impact of the ability to model the O
  <sub>2</sub> binding and dissociation is enormous, since it is the mechanism at play for oxygen exchange in all vertebrates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Upon O
  <sub>2</sub> binding to the Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span>(porphyrin)(Hys) complex, one electron is transferred from the Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span> ion to O
  <sub>2</sub>, and at the same time, a spin crossover transition is observed. This transforms the starting 2
  <span class="italic">S</span> + 1 = 7 spin state into a 2
  <span class="italic">S</span> + 1 = 1 ground state (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>). Predicting this spin crossover phenomenon is already rather challenging at the DFT level (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>), and a precise estimation of the energetics involved is beyond the scope of this work. Here, we restrict our study to the reaction occurring along the singlet Born-Oppenheimer surface, selected as representing ground state for dioxo-Fe
  <span class="sup">+2</span>(porphyrin)(Hys) and correctly showing the charge transfer reversibility along the oxygen dissociation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A set of 150:20:30 configurations (training:validation:test) has been generated by applying random displacements of 0.05 and 0.1 Å to the optimized structure of dioxo-Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span>(porphyrin)(Hys). To include information about the oxygen reactivity, we have also scanned the reaction pathway by performing eight DFT constraint optimizations with Fe-O distances between 1.6 and 3.0 Å. The structures optimized along the reaction path have been used to generate additional 750:120:120 configurations with random displacements of 0.05 and 0.1 Å. Last, the molecular dynamics refinement at 100, 200, and 300 K has been carried out for a total of ∼400 new structures, spanning both the energy minima of the reaction and the transition state. The final model contains 448 parameters and several chemical species, but it has been successfully trained with less than ∼1500 configurations. The overall errors on the training, validation, and test sets are 1.18, 1.38, and 2.42 kcal/mol, respectively. This is an accuracy comparable with DFT.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Figure 5</a> shows that the energetics of the reaction are perfectly reproduced. From a structural point of view, upon dissociation, the O
  <sub>2</sub> bond length goes from 1.27 to 1.20 Å, and at the same time, the Fe
  <span class="sup">+2</span> ion slightly moves out of the porphyrin plane, passing from an octahedral coordination to a square pyramidal one. This is in perfect agreement with DFT results. All these fine structural rearrangements are of many-body nature, and they are well reproduced by the SNAP with great accuracy and without any a priori knowledge of the model.
 </p>
 <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Energy and Fe spin density profile for oxygen bonding reaction with Fe
    <span class="sup">2+</span>(porphyrin).
   </div>
   <p>The lines correspond to the SNAP-predicted total energy (blue line and left-hand side scale) and Fe spin density (red line and right-hand side scale), while the symbols are for the DFT results. Here, energy and spin density are computed along the O
    <sub>2</sub> dissociation path.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aaw2210-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The same methodology applied to predict energy changes upon conformational distortion can be applied to the prediction of any scalar molecular quantity such as the atomic charges and the spin densities. Here, we test this possibility by building a predictive model for the Fe spin density. For any DFT total energy calculation included in the training or validation set, we also perform a Mülliken population analysis to extract the spin density of the Fe ion. Then, using 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E1" href="#E1">Eq. 1</a>, we train a model, which expresses the Fe spin density as a function of the bispectrum components, in total analogy to the method used to predict the energy. The comparison between the DFT and SNAP predictions for the spin density upon O
  <sub>2</sub> dissociation is also reported in 
  <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, showing the local Fe spin crossover process.
 </p>
</sec>
