<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hapticity and coordination: Ferrocene</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the first example of a chemically relevant complex, we choose ferrocene. Ferrocene and its derivatives have no wide-scale applications yet, but they have been intensively investigated as possible catalysts (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>), fuel additives, and in nanomedicine (
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>). In ferrocene, the Fe
  <span class="sup">+2</span> ion is sandwiched between two cyclopentadienyl (Cp) molecules, [C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>]
  <span class="sup">−</span>. The Fe
  <span class="sup">+2</span> ion has a coordination geometry where the π electron cloud of the aromatic rings acts as a single ligand. To make the nature of this bond even more interesting and complex, there is a virtually absent rotational barrier (1.0 kcal/mol from DFT) between two different conformers: one where the two [C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>]
  <span class="sup">−</span> rings are eclipsed and one where they are staggered. This is a typical situation where FFs, to be effective, need to be constructed by making specific assumptions on the bond geometry.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The same recipe described in the previous section has been used here to generate a starting training set for the isolated FeCp molecule for both the staggered and eclipsed conformations for a total of 1600 configurations. The errors on the training, validation, and test sets are 2.94, 4.41, and 3.78 kcal/mol, respectively. Furthermore, 100 configurations from a molecular dynamics run at 300 K and 12 configurations from one at 500 K are included to guarantee the stability of the structure against the high-energy fluctuations encountered in the molecular dynamics. To emphasize the ability of this approach to predict a smooth and accurate PES, we show in 
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a> the energy profile for the reciprocal rotation of the two Cp rings around the metal ion. The rather small energy difference between the staggered and eclipsed configurations is well reproduced with an error of only 0.3 kcal/mol. Note that configurations specifically exploring the rotation were not explicitly included in the training set, so that the knowledge of these fine details of the PES is provided by the configurations generated by molecular dynamics.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Rotational barrier energy profile for the Cp rings of ferrocene.</div>
   <p>The energy profile for the complete reciprocal rotation of the two Cp rings around the Fe
    <span class="sup">+2</span> ion is calculated with both DFT (green line and points) and FF (purple line and points). Note that SNAP describes the energy barrier with an accuracy of about 0.3 kcal/mol.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aaw2210-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
