<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular dynamics for alanine</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amino acid molecule alanine has been chosen as a prototypical organic molecule because of its ubiquitous relevance in biology. The various alanine derivatives are used in the biosynthesis of proteins and occur both in polypeptides in some bacterial cell walls and in peptide antibiotics. In mammals, alanine is key for the glucose-alanine cycle, which links the glucose production in the liver to the energy production in other tissues. Alanine presents a challenge for conventional FFs as it contains chemical species with different local environments and degrees of freedom, whose dynamics spans quite different time scales.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The starting configurations for constructing the FF are 1000 for the training set and 100 for the validation and test sets, respectively. These are constructed by applying random displacements of 0.05 and 0.1 Å to the optimized alanine structure in four different conformers. Additional 691:150:150 (training:validation:test) configurations extracted from molecular dynamics trajectory runs at temperatures between 100 and 400 K are also included in the training set to guarantee a complete sampling of the configurational space of the system. This time, because of the large number of molecular dynamics configurations included at the refinement stage, we have also extended the validation and test sets to some molecular dynamics configurations. This guarantees an unbiased estimation of the FF error. The total energy regression root mean square error (RMSE) is only 2.34 kcal/mol for all the three configuration sets, that is similar to that obtained previously for the simpler benzene and methane molecules.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Machine learning potentials, although successfully applied to organic compounds, are still in their infancy, and they are not widely used for molecular dynamics acquisition runs. Instead, the AMBER family of FFs represents the common choice for the chemistry community involved in molecular dynamics of biological systems, and a comparison with it is crucial. Here, we compare the accuracy of SNAP against that of the general AMBER FF (GAFF) (
  <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
   <span class="italic">34</span>
  </a>). The test is performed by comparing the FF total energy against the DFT one for 450 structures randomly sampled from molecular dynamics at 200, 300, and 400 K. These are all configurations not included in either the training or the validation set. A linear regression analysis, reported in fig. S8, shows that the SNAP is in good agreement with DFT. The RMSE is 1.82 kcal/mol, and the slope of the DFT versus FF energy curve is 1.032. In contrast, the linear regression of GAFF has a slope of 0.812, highlighting a systematic energy overestimation. This is particularly true as the size of the distortions increases, that is, as one considers largely anharmonic displacements. SNAP is able to account for anharmonic contributions to the PES, which are relevant even at relatively low temperatures. This benchmark also offers the chance to compare the computational performance of SNAP with respect to broadly used harmonic potentials. Testing the two potentials on the alanine benchmark, the SNAP potential is only ~100× more expensive than GAFF. Moreover, the time needed for a single SNAP potential energy evaluation scales linearly with the number of central processing units in parallel runs for large systems (
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>), suggesting that the extended size and time scales of common harmonic potentials are still within the reach of this machine learning FF.
 </p>
</sec>
