<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5378044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep03589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep03589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24395054</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>From transistor to trapped-ion computers for quantum chemistry</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mezzacapo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McClean</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lamata</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Center for Quantum Information, Institute for Interdisciplinary Information Sciences, Tsinghua University</institution>, Beijing, 100084, P. R. China</aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Harvard University</institution>, Cambridge MA, 02138, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Physical Chemistry, University of the Basque Country UPV/EHU</institution>, Apartado 644, 48080 Bilbao, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>IKERBASQUE, Basque Foundation for Science</institution>, Alameda Urquijo 36, 48011 Bilbao, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="a5"><label>5</label>These authors contributed equally to this work.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>aspuru@chemistry.harvard.edu</email></corresp><corresp id="c2"><label>b</label><email>enrique.solano@ehu.es</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>3589</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014, Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Over the last few decades, quantum chemistry has progressed through the development of computational methods based on modern digital computers. However, these methods can hardly fulfill the exponentially-growing resource requirements when applied to large quantum systems. As pointed out by Feynman, this restriction is intrinsic to all computational models based on classical physics. Recently, the rapid advancement of trapped-ion technologies has opened new possibilities for quantum control and quantum simulations. Here, we present an efficient toolkit that exploits both the internal and motional degrees of freedom of trapped ions for solving problems in quantum chemistry, including molecular electronic structure, molecular dynamics, and vibronic coupling. We focus on applications that go beyond the capacity of classical computers, but may be realizable on state-of-the-art trapped-ion systems. These results allow us to envision a new paradigm of quantum chemistry that shifts from the current transistor to a near-future trapped-ion-based technology.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Quantum chemistry represents one of the most successful applications of quantum mechanics. It provides an excellent platform for understanding matter from atomic to molecular scales, and involves heavy interplay of experimental and theoretical methods. In 1929, shortly after the completion of the basic structure of the quantum theory, Dirac speculated<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref> that the fundamental laws for chemistry were completely known, but the application of the fundamental laws led to equations that were too complex to be solved. About ninety years later, with the help of transistor-based digital computers, the development of quantum chemistry continues to flourish, and many powerful methods, such as Hartree-Fock, configuration interaction, density functional theory, coupled-cluster, and quantum Monte Carlo, have been developed to tackle the complex equations of quantum chemistry (see e.g. for a historical review<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>). However, as the system size scales up, all of the methods known so far suffer from limitations that make them fail to maintain accuracy with a finite amount of resources<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. In other words, quantum chemistry remains a hard problem to be solved by the current computer technology.</p><p>As envisioned by Feynman<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, one should be able to efficiently solve problems of quantum systems with a quantum computer. Instead of solving the complex equations, this approach, known as <italic>quantum simulation</italic> (see the recent reviews in Refs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>), aims to solve the problems by simulating target systems with another controllable quantum system, or qubits. Indeed, simulating many-body systems beyond classical resources will be a cornerstone of quantum computers. Quantum simulation is a very active field of study and various methods have been developed. Quantum simulation methods have been proposed for preparing specific states such as ground<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> and thermal states<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>, simulating time evolution<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>, and the measurement of physical observables<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>.</p><p>Trapped-ion systems (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>) are currently one of the most sophisticated technologies developed for quantum information processing<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>. These systems offer an unprecedented level of quantum control, which opens new possibilities for obtaining physico-chemical information about quantum chemical problems. The power of trapped ions for quantum simulation is manifested by the high-precision control over both the internal degrees of freedom of the individual ions and the phonon degrees of freedom of the collective motions of the trapped ions, and the high-fidelity initialization and measurement<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>. Up to 100 quantum logic gates have been realized for six qubits with trapped ions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>, and quantum simulators involving 300 ions have been demonstrated<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>.</p><p>In this work, we present an efficient toolkit for solving quantum chemistry problems based on the state-of-the-art in trapped-ion technologies. The toolkit comprises two components <italic>i</italic>) First, we present a hybrid quantum-classical variational optimization method, called quantum-assisted optimization, for approximating both ground-state energies and the ground-state eigenvectors for electronic problems. The optimized eigenvector can then be taken as an input for the phase estimation algorithm to project out the exact eigenstates and hence the potential-energy surfaces (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>). Furthermore, we extend the application of the unitary coupled-cluster method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>. This allows for the application of a method developed for classical numerical computations in the quantum domain. <italic>ii</italic>) The second main component of our toolkit is the optimized use of trapped-ion phonon degrees of freedom not only for quantum-gate construction, but also for simulating molecular vibrations, representing a mixed digital-analog quantum simulation. The phonon degrees of freedom in trapped-ion systems provide a natural platform for addressing spin-boson or fermion-boson-type problems through quantum simulation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>. It is noteworthy to mention that, contrary to the continuous of modes required for full-fledged quantum field theories, quantum simulations of quantum chemistry problems could reach realistic conditions for finite bosonic and fermionic mode numbers. Consequently, trapped ions can be exploited to solve dynamical problems involving linearly or non-linearly coupled oscillators, e.g., spin-boson models<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>, that are difficult to solve either analytically or numerically with a classical computer. Furthermore, we have also developed a novel protocol to measure correlation functions of observables in trapped ions that will be crucial for the quantum simulation of quantum chemistry.</p><sec disp-level="1"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Trapped ions for quantum chemistry</title><p>Quantum chemistry deals with the many-body problem involving electrons and nuclei. Thus, it is very well suited for being simulated with trapped-ion systems, as we will show below. The full quantum chemistry Hamiltonian, <italic>H</italic> = <italic>T<sub>e</sub></italic> + <italic>V<sub>e</sub></italic> + <italic>T<sub>N</sub></italic> + <italic>V<sub>N</sub></italic> + <italic>V<sub>eN</sub></italic>, is a sum of the kinetic energies of the electrons <inline-formula id="m7"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e352" xlink:href="srep03589-m7.jpg"/></inline-formula> and nuclei <inline-formula id="m8"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e355" xlink:href="srep03589-m8.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and the electron-electron <inline-formula id="m83"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e358" xlink:href="srep03589-m83.jpg"/></inline-formula>, nuclei-nuclei <inline-formula id="m84"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e361" xlink:href="srep03589-m84.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and electron-nuclei <inline-formula id="m85"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e364" xlink:href="srep03589-m85.jpg"/></inline-formula> potential energies, where <bold>r</bold> and <bold>R</bold> respectively refer to the electronic and nuclear coordinates.</p><p>In many cases, it is more convenient to work on the second-quantization representation for quantum chemistry. The advantage is that one can choose a good fermionic basis set of molecular orbitals, <inline-formula id="m9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e376" xlink:href="srep03589-m9.jpg"/></inline-formula>, which can compactly capture the low-energy sector of the chemical system. This kind of second quantized fermionic Hamiltonians are efficiently simulatable in trapped ions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. To be more specific, we will choose first <italic>M</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>N</italic> orbitals for an <italic>N</italic>-electron system. Denote <italic>&#x003d5;<sub>p</sub></italic> (<bold>r</bold>) &#x02261; &#x03008;<bold>r</bold>|<italic>p</italic>&#x03009; as the single-particle wavefunction corresponding to mode <italic>p</italic>. The electronic part, <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic>(<bold>R</bold>) &#x02261; <italic>T<sub>e</sub></italic> + <italic>V<sub>eN</sub></italic> (<bold>R</bold>) + <italic>V<sub>e</sub></italic>, of the Hamiltonian <italic>H</italic> can be expressed as follows:<disp-formula id="m1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e439" xlink:href="srep03589-m1.jpg"/></disp-formula>where <italic>h<sub>pq</sub></italic> is obtained from the single-electron integral <inline-formula id="m10"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e447" xlink:href="srep03589-m10.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and <italic>h<sub>pqrs</sub></italic> comes from the electron-electron Coulomb interaction, <inline-formula id="m11"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e455" xlink:href="srep03589-m11.jpg"/></inline-formula>. We note that the total number of terms in <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> is <italic>O</italic>(<italic>M</italic><sup>4</sup>); typically <italic>M</italic> is of the same order as <italic>N</italic>. Therefore, the number of terms in <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> scales polynomially in <italic>N</italic>, and the integrals {<italic>h<sub>pq</sub></italic>, <italic>h<sub>pqrs</sub></italic>} can be numerically calculated by a classical computer with polynomial resources<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>.</p><p>To implement the dynamics associated with the electronic Hamiltonian in Eq. (1) with a trapped-ion quantum simulator, one should take into account the fermionic nature of the operators <italic>c<sub>p</sub></italic> and <inline-formula id="m12"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e506" xlink:href="srep03589-m12.jpg"/></inline-formula>. We invoke the Jordan-Wigner transformation (JWT), which is a method for mapping the occupation representation to the spin (or qubit) representation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>. Specifically, for each fermionic mode <italic>p</italic>, an unoccupied state |0&#x03009;<italic><sub>p</sub></italic> is represented by the spin-down state |&#x02193;&#x03009;<italic><sub>p</sub></italic>, and an occupied state |1&#x03009;<italic><sub>p</sub></italic> is represented by the spin-up state |&#x02191;&#x03009;<italic><sub>p</sub></italic>. The exchange symmetry is enforced by the Jordan-Wigner transformation: <inline-formula id="m13"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e531" xlink:href="srep03589-m13.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="m14"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e534" xlink:href="srep03589-m14.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sup>&#x000b1;</sup> &#x02261; (<italic>&#x003c3;<sup>x</sup></italic> &#x000b1; <italic>i&#x003c3;<sup>y</sup></italic>)/2. Consequently, the electronic Hamiltonian in Eq. (1) becomes highly nonlocal in terms of the Pauli operators {<italic>&#x003c3;<sup>x</sup></italic>, <italic>&#x003c3;<sup>y</sup></italic>, <italic>&#x003c3;<sup>z</sup></italic>}, i.e.,<disp-formula id="m2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e569" xlink:href="srep03589-m2.jpg"/></disp-formula>Nevertheless, the simulation can still be made efficient with trapped ions, as we shall discuss below.</p><p>In trapped-ion physics two metastable internal levels of an ion are typically employed as a qubit. Ions can be confined either in Penning traps or radio frequency Paul traps<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>, and cooled down to form crystals. Through sideband cooling the ions motional degrees of freedom can reach the ground state of the quantum Harmonic oscillator, that can be used as a quantum bus to perform gates among the different ions. Using resonance fluorescence with a cycling transition quantum non demolition measurements of the qubit can be performed. The fidelities of state preparation, single- and two-qubit gates, and detection, are all above 99%<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>.</p><p>The basic interaction of a two-level trapped ion with a single-mode laser is given by<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>, <inline-formula id="m15"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e582" xlink:href="srep03589-m15.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub>&#x000b1;</sub> are the atomic raising and lowering operators, <italic>a</italic> (<italic>a</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup>) is the annihilation (creation) operator of the considered motional mode, and &#x003a9; is the Rabi frequency associated to the laser strength. <italic>&#x003b7;</italic> = <italic>kz</italic><sub>0</sub> is the Lamb-Dicke parameter, with <italic>k</italic> the wave vector of the laser and <inline-formula id="m16"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e610" xlink:href="srep03589-m16.jpg"/></inline-formula> the ground state width of the motional mode. <italic>&#x003d5;</italic> is a controllable laser phase and &#x00394; the laser-atom detuning.</p><p>In the Lamb-Dicke regime where <inline-formula id="m17"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e619" xlink:href="srep03589-m17.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the basic interaction of a two-level trapped ion with a laser can be rewritten as <inline-formula id="m18"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e622" xlink:href="srep03589-m18.jpg"/></inline-formula></p><p>By adjusting the laser detuning &#x00394;, one can generate the three basic ion-phonon interactions, namely: the carrier interaction (&#x00394; = 0) <inline-formula id="m19"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e626" xlink:href="srep03589-m19.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the red sideband interaction (&#x00394; = &#x02212;<italic>&#x003c9;<sub>t</sub></italic>) <inline-formula id="m20"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e634" xlink:href="srep03589-m20.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and the blue sideband interaction (&#x00394; = <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>t</sub></italic>) <inline-formula id="m21"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e642" xlink:href="srep03589-m21.jpg"/></inline-formula>. By combining detuned red and blue sideband interactions, one obtains the M&#x000f8;lmer-S&#x000f8;rensen gate<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref>, which is the basic building block for our methods. With combinations of this kind of gates, one can obtain dynamics as the associated one to <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> in Eq. (2), that will allow one to simulate arbitrary quantum chemistry systems.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Quantum-assisted optimization</title><p>Quantum-assisted optimization<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref> (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>) for obtaining ground-state energies aims to optimize the use of quantum coherence by breaking down the quantum simulation through the use of both quantum and classical processors; the quantum processor is strategically employed for expensive tasks only.</p><p>To be more specific, the first step of quantum-assisted optimization is to prepare a set of quantum states {|<italic>&#x003c8;<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic>&#x03009;} that are characterized by a set of parameters {<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>}. After the state is prepared, the expectation value <italic>E<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic> &#x02261; &#x03008;<italic>&#x003c8;<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic>| <italic>H</italic> |<italic>&#x003c8;<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic>&#x03009; of the Hamiltonian <italic>H</italic> will be measured directly, without any quantum evolution in between. Practically, the quantum resources for the measurements can be significantly reduced when we divide the measurement of the Hamiltonian <inline-formula id="m86"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e695" xlink:href="srep03589-m86.jpg"/></inline-formula> into a polynomial number of small pieces &#x03008;<italic>H<sub>i</sub></italic>&#x03009; (cf Eq. (2)). These measurements can be performed in a parallel fashion, and no quantum coherence is needed to maintain between the measurements (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a and 2b</xref>). Then, once a data point of <italic>E<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic> is obtained, the whole procedure is repeated for a new state <inline-formula id="m22"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e712" xlink:href="srep03589-m22.jpg"/></inline-formula> with another set of parameters {<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>&#x02032;}. The choice of the new parameters is determined by a classical optimization algorithm that aims to minimize <italic>E<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic> (see Methods). The optimization procedure is terminated after the value of <italic>E<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic> converges to some fixed value.</p><p>Finally, for electronic Hamiltonians <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic>(<bold>R</bold>), the optimized state can then be sent to a quantum circuit of phase estimation algorithm to produce a set of data point for some <bold>R</bold> on the potential energy surfaces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2c</xref> shows the 1D case). After locating the local minima of the ground and excited states, vibronic coupling for the electronic structure can be further studied (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Material</xref>).</p><p>The performance of quantum-assisted optimization depends crucially on (a) the choice of the variational states, and (b) efficient measurement methods. We found that the unitary coupled-cluster (UCC) states<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref> are particularly suitable for being the input state for quantum-assisted optimization, where each quantum state |<italic>&#x003c8;<sub>&#x003bb;</sub></italic>&#x03009; can be prepared efficiently with standard techniques in trapped ions. Furthermore, efficient measurement methods for <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> are also available for trapped ion systems. We shall discuss these results in detail in the following sections.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Unitary coupled-cluster (UCC) ansatz</title><p>The unitary coupled-cluster (UCC) ansatz<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref> assumes electronic states |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009; have the following form, <inline-formula id="m23"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e771" xlink:href="srep03589-m23.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where |&#x003a6;&#x03009; is a reference state, which can be, e.g., a Slater determinant constructed from Hartree-Fock molecular orbitals. The particle-hole excitation operator, or cluster operator <italic>T</italic>, creates a linear combination of excited Slater determinants from |&#x003a6;&#x03009;. Usually, <italic>T</italic> is divided into subgroups based on the particle-hole rank. More precisely, <italic>T</italic> = <italic>T</italic><sub>1</sub> + <italic>T</italic><sub>2</sub> + <italic>T</italic><sub>3</sub> + &#x02026; + <italic>T<sub>N</sub></italic> for an <italic>N</italic>-electron system, where <inline-formula id="m24"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e808" xlink:href="srep03589-m24.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="m25"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e811" xlink:href="srep03589-m25.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and so on.</p><p>Here <inline-formula id="m26"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e816" xlink:href="srep03589-m26.jpg"/></inline-formula> creates an electron in the orbital <italic>a</italic>. The indices <italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic> label unoccupied orbitals in the reference state |&#x003a6;&#x03009;, and <italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic> label occupied orbitals. The energy obtained from UCC, namely <inline-formula id="m27"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e835" xlink:href="srep03589-m27.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a variational upper bound of the exact ground-state energy.</p><p>The key challenge for implementing UCC on a classical computer is that the computational resource grows exponentially. It is because, in principle, one has to expand the expression <inline-formula id="m28"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e840" xlink:href="srep03589-m28.jpg"/></inline-formula> into an infinity series, using the Baker-Campbell-Hausdorff expansion. Naturally, one has to rely on approximate methods<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref> to truncate the series and keep track of finite numbers of terms. Therefore, in order to make good approximations by perturbative methods, i.e., assuming <italic>T</italic> is small, one implicitly assumes that the reference state |&#x003a6;&#x03009; is a good solution to the problem. However, in many cases, such an assumption is not valid and the use of approximate UCC breaks down. We explain below how implementing UCC on a trapped-ion quantum computer can overcome this problem.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Implementation of UCC through time evolution</title><p>We can generate the UCC state by simulating a pseudo time evolution through Suzuki-Trotter expansion on the evolution operator <inline-formula id="m29"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e853" xlink:href="srep03589-m29.jpg"/></inline-formula><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. To proceed, we consider an <italic>N</italic>-electron system with <italic>M</italic>, where <italic>M</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>N</italic>, molecular orbitals (including spins). We need totally <italic>M</italic> qubits; the reference state is the Hartree-Fock state where <italic>N</italic> orbitals are filled, and <italic>M</italic> &#x02212; <italic>N</italic> orbitals are empty, i.e, |&#x003a6;&#x03009; = |000&#x02026;0111&#x02026;1&#x03009;. We also define an effective Hamiltonian <italic>K</italic> &#x02261; <italic>i</italic> (<italic>T</italic> &#x02212; <italic>T</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup>), which means that we should prepare the state <italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>iK</italic></sup> |&#x003a6;&#x03009;.</p><p>We decompose <italic>K</italic> into subgroups <italic>K</italic> = <italic>K</italic><sub>1</sub> + <italic>K</italic><sub>2</sub> + <italic>K</italic><sub>3</sub> + &#x02026; + <italic>K<sub>P</sub></italic>, where <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; <italic>N</italic>, and <inline-formula id="m30"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e939" xlink:href="srep03589-m30.jpg"/></inline-formula>. We now write <italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>iK</italic></sup> = (<italic>e</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>iK&#x003b4;</italic></sup>)<sup>1/<italic>&#x003b4;</italic></sup> for some dimensionless constant <italic>&#x003b4;</italic>. For small <italic>&#x003b4;</italic>, we have <inline-formula id="m31"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e969" xlink:href="srep03589-m31.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Since each <italic>K<sub>j</sub></italic> contains <italic>N<sup>j</sup></italic>(<italic>M</italic> &#x02212; <italic>N</italic>)<italic><sup>j</sup></italic> terms of the creation <italic>c</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup> and annihilation <italic>c</italic> operators, we will need to individually simulate each term separately, e.g., <inline-formula id="m32"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1001" xlink:href="srep03589-m32.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="m33"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1004" xlink:href="srep03589-m33.jpg"/></inline-formula>, which can be implemented by transforming into spin operators through Jordan-Wigner transformation. The time evolution for each term can be simulated with a quantum circuit involving many nonlocal controlled gates, which can be efficiently implemented with trapped ions as we shall see below.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Implementation of UCC and simulation of time evolution with trapped-ions</title><p>Our protocol for implementing the UCC ansatz requires the simulation of the small-time <italic>t/n</italic> evolution of non-local product of Pauli matrices of the form: <inline-formula id="m34"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1015" xlink:href="srep03589-m34.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula id="m35"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1018" xlink:href="srep03589-m35.jpg"/></inline-formula> for <italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>, <italic>k</italic> &#x02208; {<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, <italic>z</italic>}. Note that for any <italic>N</italic>-spin interaction, the <inline-formula id="m36"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1043" xlink:href="srep03589-m36.jpg"/></inline-formula> terms are equivalent to <inline-formula id="m37"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1047" xlink:href="srep03589-m37.jpg"/></inline-formula> through local spin rotations, which are simple to implement on trapped ions. Such a non-local operator can be implemented using the multi-particle M&#x000f8;lmer-S&#x000f8;rensen gate<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>: <italic>U</italic><sub>MS</sub>(<italic>&#x003b8;</italic>, <italic>&#x003c6;</italic>) &#x02261; exp [&#x02212;<italic>i&#x003b8;</italic>(cos <italic>&#x003c6;S<sub>x</sub></italic> + sin <italic>&#x003c6;S<sub>y</sub></italic>)<sup>2</sup>/4], where <inline-formula id="m38"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1080" xlink:href="srep03589-m38.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a collective spin operator. Explicitly,<disp-formula id="m3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1083" xlink:href="srep03589-m3.jpg"/></disp-formula>Here <italic>R<sub>N</sub></italic>(<italic>&#x003d5;</italic>) is defined as follows: for any <inline-formula id="m39"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1095" xlink:href="srep03589-m39.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="m40"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1098" xlink:href="srep03589-m40.jpg"/></inline-formula> for <italic>N</italic> = 4<italic>m</italic> &#x000b1; 1, and (ii) <inline-formula id="m41"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1108" xlink:href="srep03589-m41.jpg"/></inline-formula> for <italic>N</italic> = 4<italic>m</italic>, and (iii) <inline-formula id="m42"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1117" xlink:href="srep03589-m42.jpg"/></inline-formula> for <italic>N</italic> = 4<italic>m</italic> &#x02212; 2.</p><p>It is remarkable that the standard quantum-circuit treatment (e.g. see Ref.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>) for implementing each <inline-formula id="m43"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1130" xlink:href="srep03589-m43.jpg"/></inline-formula> involves as many as 2<italic>N</italic> two-qubit gates for simulating <italic>N</italic> fermionic modes; in our protocol one needs only two M&#x000f8;lmer-S&#x000f8;rensen gates, which are straightforwardly implementable with current trapped-ion technology. Furthermore, the local rotation <italic>R<sub>N</sub></italic>(<italic>&#x003d5;</italic>) can also include motional degrees of freedom of the ions for simulating arbitrary fermionic Hamiltonians coupled linearly to bosonic operators <italic>a<sub>k</sub></italic> and <inline-formula id="m44"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1153" xlink:href="srep03589-m44.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Measurement of arbitrarily-nonlocal spin operators</title><p>For any given state |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009;, we show how to encode expectation value of products of Pauli matrices <inline-formula id="m45"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1164" xlink:href="srep03589-m45.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>, <italic>k</italic> &#x02208; {<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, <italic>z</italic>}, onto an expectation value of a single qubit. The idea is to first apply the unitary evolution of the form: <inline-formula id="m46"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1186" xlink:href="srep03589-m46.jpg"/></inline-formula>, which as we have seen (cf Eq. 3) can be generated by trapped ions efficiently, to the state |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009; before the measurement. For example, defining <inline-formula id="m47"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1192" xlink:href="srep03589-m47.jpg"/></inline-formula>, we have the relation<disp-formula id="m4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1196" xlink:href="srep03589-m4.jpg"/></disp-formula>which equals <inline-formula id="m48"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1199" xlink:href="srep03589-m48.jpg"/></inline-formula> for <italic>&#x003b8;</italic> = <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>/4. Note that the application of this method requires the measurement of one qubit only, making this technique especially suited for trapped ion systems where the fidelity of the measurement of one qubit is 99.99%<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref>.</p><p>This method can be further extended to include bosonic operators in the resulting expectation values. For example, re-define <inline-formula id="m49"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1212" xlink:href="srep03589-m49.jpg"/></inline-formula> and consider <italic>&#x003b8;</italic> &#x02192; <italic>&#x003b8;</italic> (<italic>a</italic> + <italic>a</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup>) in Eq. (4). We can obtain the desired correlation through the derivative of the single-qubit measurement: <inline-formula id="m50"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1230" xlink:href="srep03589-m50.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Note that the evolution operator of the form <inline-formula id="m51"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1233" xlink:href="srep03589-m51.jpg"/></inline-formula> can be generated by replacing the local operation <italic>R<sub>N</sub></italic>(<italic>&#x003d5;</italic>) in Eq. 3 with <inline-formula id="m52"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1244" xlink:href="srep03589-m52.jpg"/></inline-formula>. This technique allows us to obtain a diverse range of correlations between bosonic and internal degrees of freedom.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Probing potential energy surfaces</title><p>In the Born-Oppenheimer (BO) picture, the potential energy surface <inline-formula id="m53"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1252" xlink:href="srep03589-m53.jpg"/></inline-formula> associated with each electronic eigenstate |<italic>&#x003d5;<sub>k</sub></italic>&#x03009; is obtained by scanning the eigenvalues <inline-formula id="m54"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1260" xlink:href="srep03589-m54.jpg"/></inline-formula> for each configurations of the nuclear coordinates {<bold>R</bold>}. Of course, we can apply the standard quantum phase estimation algorithm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref> that allows us to extract the eigenvalues. However, this can require many ancilla qubits. In fact, locating these eigenvalues can be achieved by the phase estimation method utilizing one extra ancilla qubit<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref> corresponding, in our case, to one additional ion.</p><p>This method works as follows: suppose we are given a certain quantum state |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009; (which may be obtained from classical solutions with quantum-assisted optimization) and an electronic Hamiltonian <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic>(<bold>R</bold>) (cf. Eq. (1)). Expanding the input state, <inline-formula id="m87"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1284" xlink:href="srep03589-m87.jpg"/></inline-formula>, by the eigenstate vectors |<italic>&#x003d5;<sub>k</sub></italic>&#x03009; of <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic>(<bold>R</bold>), where <inline-formula id="m55"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1301" xlink:href="srep03589-m55.jpg"/></inline-formula>, then for the input state |0&#x03009; |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009;, the quantum circuit of the quantum phase estimation produces the following output state, <inline-formula id="m56"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1307" xlink:href="srep03589-m56.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula id="m57"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1310" xlink:href="srep03589-m57.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The corresponding reduced density matrix,<disp-formula id="m5"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1314" xlink:href="srep03589-m5.jpg"/></disp-formula>of the ancilla qubit contains the information about the weight (amplitude-square) |<italic>&#x003b1;<sub>k</sub></italic>|<sup>2</sup> of the eigenvectors |<italic>&#x003d5;<sub>k</sub></italic>&#x03009; in |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009; and the associated eigenvalues <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>k</sub></italic> in the off-diagonal matrix elements. All |<italic>&#x003b1;<sub>k</sub></italic>|<sup>2</sup>'s and <italic>&#x003c9;<sub>k</sub></italic>'s can be extracted by repeating the quantum circuit for a range of values of <italic>t</italic> and performing a (classical) Fourier transform to the measurement results. The potential energy surface is obtained by repeating the procedure for different values of the nuclear coordinates {<bold>R</bold>}.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Numerical investigation</title><p>In order to show the feasibility of our protocol, we can estimate the trapped-ion resources needed to simulate, e.g., the prototypical electronic Hamiltonian <inline-formula id="m58"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1363" xlink:href="srep03589-m58.jpg"/></inline-formula> as described in Eq. (1), for the specific case of the H<sub>2</sub> molecule in a minimal STO-3G basis. This is a two-electron system represented in a basis of four spin-orbitals. The hydrogen atoms were separated by 0.75 &#x000c5;, near the equilibrium bond distance of the molecule. The Hamiltonian is made up of 12 terms, that include 4 local ion operations and 8 non-local interactions. Each of the non-local terms can be done as a combination of two M&#x000f8;lmer-S&#x000f8;rensen (MS) gates and local rotations, as described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>. Therefore, to implement the dynamics, one needs 16 MS gates per Trotter step and a certain number of local rotations upon the ions. Since <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>/2 MS gates can be done in ~ 50&#x02005;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>s, and local rotations can be performed in negligible times (~ 1&#x02005;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>s)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>, the total simulation time can be assumed of about 800&#x02005;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>s for the <italic>n</italic> = 1 protocol, 1.6&#x02005;ms and 2.4&#x02005;ms for the <italic>n</italic> = 2 and <italic>n</italic> = 3 protocols. Thus total simulation times are within the decoherence times for trapped-ion setups, of about 30&#x02005;ms<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>. In a digital protocol performed on real quantum systems, each gate is affected by an error. Thus, increasing the number of Trotter steps leads to an accumulation of the single gate error. To implement an effective quantum simulation, on one hand one has to increase the number of steps to reduce the error due to the digital approximation, on the other hand one is limited by the accumulation of the single gate error. We plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a, 3b, 3c</xref>, the fidelity loss 1 &#x02212; |&#x03008;&#x003a8;<italic><sub>S</sub></italic>|&#x003a8;<italic><sub>E</sub></italic>&#x03009;|<sup>2</sup> of the simulated state |&#x003a8;<italic><sub>S</sub></italic>&#x03009; versus the exact one |&#x003a8;<italic><sub>E</sub></italic>&#x03009;, for the hydrogen Hamiltonian, starting from the initial state with two electrons in the first two orbitals. We plot, along with the digital error, three horizontal lines representing the accumulated gate error, for <italic>n</italic> = 1, 2, 3 in each plot, considering a protocol with an error per Trotter step of <inline-formula id="m59"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1425" xlink:href="srep03589-m59.jpg"/></inline-formula> (a), <inline-formula id="m60"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1428" xlink:href="srep03589-m60.jpg"/></inline-formula> (b) and <inline-formula id="m61"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1431" xlink:href="srep03589-m61.jpg"/></inline-formula> (c). To achieve a reasonable fidelity, one has to find a number of steps that fits the simulation at a specific time. The vertical lines and arrows in the figure mark the time regions in which the error starts to be dominated by the digital error. Trapped-ion two-qubit gates are predicted to achieve in the near future infidelities of 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>, thus making the use of these protocols feasible<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3d</xref> we plot the behavior of the energy of the system for the initial state |&#x02191;&#x02191;&#x02193;&#x02193;&#x03009; for the exact dynamics, versus the digitized one. Again, one can observe how the energy can be retrieved with a small error within a reduced number of digital steps.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Summarizing, we have proposed a quantum simulation toolkit for quantum chemistry with trapped ions. This paradigm in quantum simulations has several advantages: an efficient electronic simulation, the possibility of interacting electronic and vibrational degrees of freedom, and the increasing scalability provided by trapped-ion systems. This approach for solving quantum chemistry problems aims to combine the best of classical and quantum computation.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><p>To implement the optimization with the UCC wavefunction ansatz on a trapped-ion quantum simulator, our proposal is to first employ classical algorithms to obtain approximate solutions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref>. Then, we can further improve the quality of the solution by searching for the true minima with an ion trap. The idea is as follows: first we create a UCC ansatz by the Suzuki-Trotter method described in the previous section. Denote this choice of the cluster operator as <italic>T</italic><sup>(0)</sup>, and other choices as <italic>T</italic><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup> with <italic>k</italic> = 1, 2, 3, &#x02026;. The corresponding energy <inline-formula id="m62"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1472" xlink:href="srep03589-m62.jpg"/></inline-formula> of the initial state is obtained by a classical computer.</p><p>Next, we choose another set of cluster operator <italic>T</italic><sup>(1)</sup> which is a perturbation around <italic>T</italic><sup>(0)</sup>. Define the new probe state <inline-formula id="m63"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1487" xlink:href="srep03589-m63.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Then, the expectation value of the energy <inline-formula id="m64"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1490" xlink:href="srep03589-m64.jpg"/></inline-formula> can be obtained by measuring components of the second quantized Hamiltonian, <inline-formula id="m65"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1494" xlink:href="srep03589-m65.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Recall that the coefficients <inline-formula id="m66"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1497" xlink:href="srep03589-m66.jpg"/></inline-formula> are all precomputed and known.</p><p>In order to obtain measurement results for the operators <inline-formula id="m67"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1502" xlink:href="srep03589-m67.jpg"/></inline-formula>, we will first convert the fermion operators into spin operators via Jordan-Wigner transformation; the same procedure is applied for creating the state |<italic>&#x003d5;</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x03009;. The quantum measurement for the resulting products of Pauli matrices can be achieved efficiently with trapped ions, using the method we described.</p><p>The following steps are determined through a classical optimization algorithm. There can be many choices for such an algorithm, for example gradient descent method, Nelder-Mead method, or quasi-Newton methods. For completeness, we summarize below the application of gradient descent method to our optimization problem.</p><p>First we define the vector <inline-formula id="m68"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1514" xlink:href="srep03589-m68.jpg"/></inline-formula> to contain all coefficients in the cluster operator <italic>T</italic><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup> at the <italic>k</italic>-th step. We can also write the expectation value <italic>E</italic> (<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>) &#x02261; &#x03008;<italic>&#x003d5;<sub>k</sub></italic>| <italic>H</italic> |<italic>&#x003d5;<sub>k</sub></italic>&#x03009; for each step as a function of <bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>. The main idea of the gradient descent method is that <italic>E</italic> (<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>) decreases fastest along the direction of the negative gradient of <italic>E</italic> (<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>), &#x02212;&#x02207;<italic>E</italic> (<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>). Therefore, the (<italic>k</italic> + 1)-th step is determined by the following relation:<disp-formula id="m6"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1599" xlink:href="srep03589-m6.jpg"/></disp-formula>where <italic>a<sub>k</sub></italic> is an adjustable parameter; it can be different for each step. To obtain values of the gradient &#x02207;<italic>E</italic> (<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>), one may use the finite-difference method to approximate the gradient. However, numerical gradient techniques are often susceptible to numerical instability. Alternatively, we can invoke the Hellman-Feynman theorem and get, e.g., <inline-formula id="m69"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1619" xlink:href="srep03589-m69.jpg"/></inline-formula>, which can be obtained with a method similar to that for obtaining <italic>E</italic>(<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>).</p><p>Finally, as a valid assumption for general cases, we assume our parametrization of UCC gives a smooth function for <italic>E</italic> (<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>). Thus, it follows that <inline-formula id="m70"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1646" xlink:href="srep03589-m70.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and eventually <italic>E</italic> (<bold>T</bold><sup>(<italic>k</italic>)</sup>) converges to a minimum value for large <italic>k</italic>. Finally, we can also obtain the optimized UCC quantum state.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d32e108" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Supplementary Material</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03589-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank J. Whitfield for insightful discussions. The authors acknowledge funding from Basque Government IT472-10 Grant, Spanish MINECO FIS2012-36673-C03-02, Ram&#x000f3;n y Cajal Grant RYC-2012-11391, UPV/EHU UFI 11/55, SOLID, CCQED, PROMISCE and SCALEQIT European projects. M.-H.Y. and A.-A.-G. acknowledge support from the Defense Threat Reduction Agency under grant HDTRA1-10-1-0046-DOD35CAP as well as the National Science Foundation under grant 1037992-CHE, Sponsored by United States Department of Defense. M.-H. Y. also acknowledges the funding from the National Basic Research Program of China Grant 2011CBA00300, 2011CBA00301, and the National Natural Science Foundation of China Grant 61033001, 61061130540. A. A.-G. also acknowledges support from the Air Force Office of Scientific Research under award FA9550-12-1-0046. J.M. is supported by the DOE Computational Science Graduate Fellowship under grant number DE-FG02-97ER25308. The views and conclusions contained in this document are those of the authors and should not be interpreted as representing the official policies, either expressly or implied, of the U.S. Government.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dirac</surname><given-names>P. A. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum Mechanics of Many-Electron Systems</article-title>. <source>Proc. R. Soc. A</source>
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>714</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>733</lpage> (<year>1929</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Back to the Future: A roadmap for quantum simulation from vintage quantum chemistry. eprint arXiv:1208.5524</article-title>. (<year>2012</year>). (To Appear in Advances in Chemical Physics).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Head-Gordon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Artacho</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Chemistry on the computer</article-title>. <source>Phys. Today</source><italic>,</italic>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Feynman</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulating physics with computers</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Theor. Phys.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>488</lpage> (<year>1982</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kassal</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perdomo-Ortiz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulating chemistry using quantum computers</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Phys. Chem.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>185207</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boixo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tempel</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Introduction to Quantum Algorithms for Physics and Chemistry. eprint arXiv</article-title>.,<fpage>1203.1331</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Photonic quantum simulators</article-title>. <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>285291</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum Algorithm Providing Exponential Speed Increase for Finding Eigenvalues and Eigenvectors</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>5162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5165</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dutoi</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Head-Gordon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulated quantum computation of molecular energies</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>309</volume>, <fpage>1704</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16151006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lanyon</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Towards quantum chemistry on a quantum computer</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21124400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wocjan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Preparing Ground States of Quantum Many-Body Systems on a Quantum Computer</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>130503</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19392338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Solving quantum ground-state problems with nuclear magnetic resonance</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22355607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.-S.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Demon-like Algorithmic Quantum Cooling and its Realization with Quantum Optics.eprint arXiv</article-title>.,<fpage>1208.2256</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lidar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Biham</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulating Ising spin glasses on a quantum computer</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>3661</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3681</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wocjan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Sampling from the Thermal Quantum Gibbs State and Evaluating Partition Functions with a Quantum Computer</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>220502</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20366078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagaj</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulation of classical thermal states on a quantum computer: A transfer-matrix approach</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. A</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>060302</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bilgin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Boixo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Preparing Thermal States of Quantum Systems by Dimension Reduction</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>170405</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21231028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Temme</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vollbrecht</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum Metropolis sampling</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>471</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21368829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A quantum-quantum Metropolis algorithm</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22215584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laflamme</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Baugh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Digital quantum simulation of the statistical mechanics of a frustrated magnet</article-title>. <source>Nat. Comm.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>880</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Universal Quantum Simulators</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>273</volume>, <fpage>1073</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1078</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8688088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lanyon</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Universal digital quantum simulation with trapped ions</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>334</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21885735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mezzacapo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamata</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum Simulation of Interacting Fermion Lattice Models in Trapped Ions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>190502</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23003013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zalka</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulating quantum systems on a quantum computer</article-title>. <source>Proc R. Soc. A</source>
<volume>454</volume>, <fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.-A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrd</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Lidar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Polynomial-Time Simulation of Pairing Models on a Quantum Computer</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>89</volume>, <fpage>057904</fpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12144467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kassal</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohseni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Polynomial-time quantum algorithm for the simulation of chemical dynamics</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>18681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulating sparse Hamiltonians with star decompositions</article-title>. <source>Theory of Quantum Computation Communication and Cryptography TQC 2010</source>
<volume>6519</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>, <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lidar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Calculating the thermal rate constant with exponential speedup on a quantum computer</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>2429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2438</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Master</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Efficiency of free-energy calculations of spin lattices by spectral quantum algorithms</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. A</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>032311</fpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kassal</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum algorithm for molecular properties and geometry optimization</article-title>. <source>J. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>224102</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20001019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wocjan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>C.-F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagaj</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Abeyesinghe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum algorithm for approximating partition functions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. A</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>022340</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#x000e4;ffner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Blatt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum computing with trapped ions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rep.</source>
<volume>469</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leibfried</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blatt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wineland</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum dynamics of single trapped ions</article-title>.. <source>Rev. Mod. Phys.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>324</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Engineered two-dimensional Ising interactions in a trapped-ion quantum simulator with hundreds of spins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>484</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22538611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taube</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>New perspectives on unitary coupled-cluster theory</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Quant. Chem.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>3393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3401</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lamata</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;tz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Dirac Equation and Quantum Relativistic Effects in a Single Trapped Ion</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>253005</fpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17678023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gerritsma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Quantum simulation of the Dirac equation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>463</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20054392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Quantum Simulation of Quantum Field Theories in Trapped Ions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>260501</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22243143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hammerer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulating open quantum systems: from many-body interactions to stabilizer pumping</article-title>. <source>New J. Phys.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>085007</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mezzacapo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamata</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Digital Quantum Simulation of the Holstein Model in Trapped Ions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>200501</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23215466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leggett</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Dynamics of the dissipative two-state system</article-title>. <source>Rev. Mod. Phys.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>185</fpage> (<year>1987</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mostame</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Quantum simulator of an open quantum system using superconducting qubits: exciton transport in photosynthetic complexes</article-title>. <source>New J. Phys.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>105013</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gubernatis</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knill</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Laflamme</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum algorithms for fermionic simulations</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. A</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>022319</fpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>M&#x000f8;lmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Multiparticle Entanglement of Hot Trapped Ions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>1835</fpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Peruzzo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>A variational eigenvalue solver on a quantum processor. eprint arXiv</article-title>.,<fpage>1304.3061</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kutzelnigg</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Error analysis and improvements of coupled-cluster theory</article-title>. <source>Theor. Chim. Acta</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage> (<year>1991</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Biamonte</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulation of electronic structure Hamiltonians using quantum computers</article-title>. <source>Mol. Phys.</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>735750</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Myerson</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>High-Fidelity Readout of Trapped-Ion Qubits</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>200502</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18518518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b49"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laflamme</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Mosca</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<source>An introduction to quantum computing.</source> (Oxford University Press, USA, <year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kirchmair</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Deterministic entanglement of ions in thermal states of motion</article-title>. <source>New J. Phys.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>023002</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> M.-H.Y., J.M. and A.A.-G. are responsible for the parts involving quantum chemistry. J.C., A.M., L.L. and E.S. are responsible for the parts involving trapped ions. All authors contributed to the writing of the paper.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Simulating quantum chemistry with trapped ions.</title><p>(a) Scheme of a trapped-ion setup for quantum simulation, which contains a linear chain of trapped ions confined by a harmonic potential, and external lasers that couple the motional and internal degrees of freedom. (b) Transitions between internal and motional degrees of freedom of the ions in the trap. (c) The normal modes of the trapped ions can simulate the vibrational degrees of freedom of molecules. (d) The internal states of two ions can simulate all four possible configurations of a molecular orbital.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03589-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Outline of the quantum-assisted optimization method.</title><p>(a) The key steps for quantum assisted optimization, which starts from classical solutions. For each new set of parameters <italic>&#x003bb;</italic>'s, determined by a classical optimization algorithm, the expectation value &#x03008;<italic>H</italic>&#x03009; is calculated. The potential energy surface is then obtained by quantum phase estimation. (b) Quantum measurements are performed for the individual terms in <italic>H</italic>, and the sum is obtained classically. (c) The same procedure is applied for each nuclear configuration <bold>R</bold> to probe the energy surface.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03589-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Digital error 1 &#x02013; <italic>F</italic> (curves) along with the accumulated gate error (horizontal lines) versus time in <italic>h</italic><sub>11</sub> energy units, for <italic>n</italic> = 1, 2, 3 Trotter steps in each plot, considering a protocol with an error per Trotter step of <inline-formula id="m71"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1710" xlink:href="srep03589-m71.jpg"/></inline-formula> (a), <inline-formula id="m72"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1713" xlink:href="srep03589-m72.jpg"/></inline-formula> (b) and <inline-formula id="m73"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e1717" xlink:href="srep03589-m73.jpg"/></inline-formula> (c). The initial state considered is |&#x02191;&#x02191;&#x02193;&#x02193;&#x03009;, in the qubit representation of the Hartree-Fock state in a molecular orbital basis with one electron on the first and second orbital. Vertical lines and arrows define the time domain in which the dominant part of the error is due to the digital approximation. d) Energy of the system, in <italic>h</italic><sub>11</sub> units, for the initial state | &#x02191;&#x02191;&#x02193;&#x02193;&#x03009; for the exact dynamics, versus the digitized one. For a protocol with three Trotter steps the energy is recovered up to a negligible error.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03589-f3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Using trapped ions to simulate quantum chemistry</title></caption><alternatives><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Simulating Quantum Chemistry</th><th align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Implementation with Trapped Ions</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Hamiltonian transformation:</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">The fermionic (electronic) Hamiltonian <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> is transformed into a spin Hamiltonian through the Jordan-Wigner transformation.</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">The spin degrees of freedom in <italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic> are represented by the internal degrees of freedom of the trapped ions.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Simulation of time evolution:</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">The time evolution operator is split into <italic>n</italic> small-time (<italic>t</italic>/<italic>n</italic>) pieces through the Suzuki-Trotter expansion.</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Each individual term can be simulated with trapped ions through the use of M&#x000f8;lmer-S&#x000f8;rensen gates <italic>U<sub>MS</sub></italic>. Explicitly,</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Obtaining average energy:</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">The average energy &#x03008;<italic>H<sub>e</sub></italic>&#x03009; of the Hamiltonian can be obtained through the sum of the individual terms &#x03008;<italic>H<sub>l</sub></italic>&#x03009;, which reduces to the measurement of products of Pauli matrices.</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50"> For any prepared state |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009;, average values of the products of Pauli matrices can be measured by first applying the pseudo time evolution operator to |<italic>&#x003c8;</italic>&#x03009; and then measuring .</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Measuring eigenvalues:</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">The eigenvalues of the Hamiltonian can be obtained through the phase estimation algorithm. Good trial states can be obtained through classical computing, or the unitary coupled-cluster method.</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50"> The phase estimation algorithm can be implemented through the simulation of controlled time evolutions.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">Molecular vibrations:</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50">The inclusion of vibrational degrees of freedom is necessary for corrections on the Born-Oppenheimer picture in the electronic structure of molecules.</td><td align="justify" valign="top" charoff="50"> The vibrational degrees of freedom are represented by the quantized vibrational motion of the trapped ions.</td></tr></tbody></table><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep03589-t1"/></alternatives></table-wrap></floats-group></article>