<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metalloporphyrins and their derivatives represent a very important group of compounds that play key roles in several natural and artificial systems, due to their peculiar light-absorption and -utilization, coordination, and redox features. Chlorophylls are the main antenna units in green plants for harvesting solar radiation in photosynthesis [
  <a rid="B1-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-molecules-24-01309">1</a>]. Hemoglobin and myoglobin are responsible for oxygen transport in blood [
  <a rid="B2-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-molecules-24-01309">2</a>], while iron-porphyrin-based cytochromes are important electron relays and redox catalysts [
  <a rid="B3-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-molecules-24-01309">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthetic metalloporphyrins have been used, for example, for medical treatments (e.g., photodynamic therapy (PDT) [
  <a rid="B4-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-molecules-24-01309">4</a>]), photocatalytic systems utilizing visible light to generate hydrogen and other fuels [
  <a rid="B5-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-molecules-24-01309">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-molecules-24-01309">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-molecules-24-01309">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-molecules-24-01309">8</a>], and cleavage or release of axially coordinated NO
  <sub>×</sub> ligands [
  <a rid="B9-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-molecules-24-01309">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-molecules-24-01309">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-molecules-24-01309">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In aqueous media, various porphyrins with suitable ionic groups have been applied. Cationic metalloporphyrins (with methylpyridinium substituents) could be successfully utilized for photocatalytic electron transfer with cobalt(III) [
  <a rid="B12-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-molecules-24-01309">12</a>], manganese(III) [
  <a rid="B13-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-molecules-24-01309">13</a>], and nickel(II) [
  <a rid="B14-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-molecules-24-01309">14</a>] centers [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>]. For anionic derivatives, mostly carboxylate and sulfonate substituents have been used. Since the coordination bond between carboxylate and transition metal ions may be sensitive to photoinduced ligand-to-metal (LMCT) processes, in several cases, sulfonation was utilized to transform organic ligands and macrocycles into anionic derivatives for photophysical and -chemical applications in various aqueous systems [
  <a rid="B16-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-molecules-24-01309">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-molecules-24-01309">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-molecules-24-01309">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-molecules-24-01309">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-molecules-24-01309">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-molecules-24-01309">21</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f001" href="#molecules-24-01309-f001">Figure 1</a>a shows the structure of 5,10,15,20-tetrakis(4-sulfonatophenyl)porphyrin (H
  <sub>2</sub>TSPP
  <span class="sup">4−</span>), a typical example of these anionic ligands.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lanthanides (abbreviated as Ln) are a series of elements with atomic numbers 57–71, located in the first row of the 
  <span class="italic">f</span>-block in the periodic table. Lanthanides usually form cations with a +3 oxidation state, and the radius of the Ln
  <span class="sup">3+</span> ions decreases from left to right in the periodic table; this is the well-known lanthanide contraction [
  <a rid="B22-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-molecules-24-01309">22</a>]. The peculiar electronic configuration of lanthanide(III) ions ([Xe]4
  <span class="italic">f
   <span class="sup">n</span>
  </span>, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1–14) results in special photophysical properties [
  <a rid="B23-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-molecules-24-01309">23</a>]. Their absorption spectra are line-like and originate from 
  <span class="italic">f</span>–
  <span class="italic">f</span> transitions [
  <a rid="B24-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-molecules-24-01309">24</a>]. The lanthanide ions, except for Lu
  <span class="sup">3+</span> and Gd
  <span class="sup">3+</span>, show luminescence in the UV and NIR region. Lu
  <span class="sup">3+</span>, being completely filled, and Gd
  <span class="sup">3+</span>, being half-filled, are not luminescent. Although lanthanide(III) ions absorb very weakly in the visible range, their emissions can be sensitized by absorption of organic ligands which transfer energy to the metal center [
  <a rid="B25-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-molecules-24-01309">25</a>,
  <a rid="B26-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-molecules-24-01309">26</a>], providing appropriate compounds for medical diagnostic applications [
  <a rid="B27-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-molecules-24-01309">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-molecules-24-01309">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-molecules-24-01309">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lanthanide(III) ions, being hard Lewis acids, prefer to bind hard bases possessing oxygen-donor groups [
  <a rid="B22-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-molecules-24-01309">22</a>,
  <a rid="B30-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-01309">30</a>]. The coordination number of lanthanides may be even 12, but 8 and 9 are most common, and they are advantageous for the formation of sandwich-type complexes with various macrocycles, producing cubic or square antiprism polyhedra [
  <a rid="B31-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-molecules-24-01309">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-molecules-24-01309">32</a>]. In the absence of a hard basis, Ln
  <span class="sup">3+</span> ions can be coordinated to other types of ligands, such as N-donor porphyrins [
  <a rid="B33-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-molecules-24-01309">33</a>]. This process, however, is very slow due to the high activation energy.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In complexes with porphyrins, also due to their large ionic radii, lanthanide(III) ions are positioned above the ligand plane and form sitting-atop (SAT) or out-of-plane (OOP) metalloporphyrins (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f001" href="#molecules-24-01309-f001">Figure 1</a>b) [
  <a rid="B34-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-molecules-24-01309">34</a>,
  <a rid="B35-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-molecules-24-01309">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-molecules-24-01309">36</a>,
  <a rid="B37-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-molecules-24-01309">37</a>,
  <a rid="B38-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-molecules-24-01309">38</a>]. In sandwich-type complexes of porphyrins, the π–π interactions between the macrocycles can result in interesting electronic, steric, photochemical, and, especially, photophysical features deviating from those of the corresponding monoporphyrin [
  <a rid="B39-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-molecules-24-01309">39</a>,
  <a rid="B40-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-molecules-24-01309">40</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lanthanide porphyrins have proved to very useful and promising in a broad range of application possibilities. Several studies focused on the photophysical properties of Ln(III) porphyrins ([
  <a rid="B41-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-molecules-24-01309">41</a>] and the references therein). Various emission features of Nd, Gd, Er, and Yb complexes were determined in different solvents [
  <a rid="B42-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-molecules-24-01309">42</a>]. The luminescence behavior of Gd(III) and Lu(III) porphyrins indicated their possible application in oxygen sensing [
  <a rid="B43-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-molecules-24-01309">43</a>]. Another significant utilization of the photophysical properties of such complexes is sensitization of NIR emission of the lanthanide(III) center, due to the porphyrin-based, long-lived triplet excited state [
  <a rid="B44-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-molecules-24-01309">44</a>,
  <a rid="B45-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-molecules-24-01309">45</a>]. Since NIR radiation penetrates human tissues considerably deeper than visible photons do, lanthanide porphyrins offer good possibilities in bio-imaging [
  <a rid="B46-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-molecules-24-01309">46</a>,
  <a rid="B47-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-molecules-24-01309">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In water-soluble lanthanide oligoporphyrins, not only sandwich-type (head-to-head) complexes occur, but tail-to-tail connections between the monoporphyrin units are possible through peripheral hard-base substituents (such as carboxylate) and hard-acid Ln(III) ions [
  <a rid="B48-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-molecules-24-01309">48</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SAT or OOP water-soluble porphyrin complexes display a typical photoredox chemistry characterized by an irreversible photodegradation of the porphyrin ligand [
  <a rid="B18-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-molecules-24-01309">18</a>,
  <a rid="B20-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-molecules-24-01309">20</a>]. This special photochemical feature, due to an efficient separation of the reduced metal center and the oxidized macrocycle, following a ligand-to-metal charge transfer, was also observed for water-soluble lanthanide(III) porphyrins [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>,
  <a rid="B30-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-01309">30</a>,
  <a rid="B37-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-molecules-24-01309">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since photophysical and photochemical properties of such complexes are crucial from the viewpoint of their application in aqueous systems (such as in human bodies or various in vitro procedures), the scrutiny of photoinduced properties of lanthanide(III) complexes with water-soluble porphyrins is highly desirable. Hence, continuing our systematic investigation, after studying the coordination compounds of early lanthanides with anionic H
  <sub>2</sub>TSPP
  <span class="sup">4−</span> [
  <a rid="B30-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-01309">30</a>,
  <a rid="B38-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-molecules-24-01309">38</a>], three members in the middle of the series (i.e., Sm(III), Eu(III), and Gd(III)) were examined in this work. Our main goals were to determine the composition, structure, and formation constant of these complexes. Besides photophysical experiments (both absorption and emission spectroscopic measurements, including fluorescence life-time determinations), steady-state photochemical investigations were also carried out for the characterization of the light-induced behavior of these metalloporphyrins.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results clearly demonstrated that the luminescence properties of the bisporphyrins hardly deviated from those of the monomers, indicating a weak interaction between the constituting units. Besides, the photochemistry of these lanthanide(III) porphyrins involved several types of reactions (such as redox degradation, dissociation, and transformations), although the quantum yields of these processes were low. Hence, these photolytic reactions are not expected to considerably limit the applicability of these complexes either for medical, mostly diagnostic, purposes or as sensitizers in photocatalytic systems. Rather, the photoinduced redox reactions may provide opportunities for PDT, too (together with the sensitized production of singlet oxygen) [
  <a rid="B4-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-molecules-24-01309">4</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
