<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot1-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Formation, Composition, and Absorption Spectra</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The efficient light absorption of porphyrins and their metal complexes makes UV–Vis spectroscopy a suitable method to quantitatively investigate the formation, composition, and structure of water-soluble lanthanide(III) porphyrins. Since the insertion of hard-acid lanthanide(III) ions into the cavity of anionic porphyrin is a very slow process, partly due to the strong Ln(III)–H
  <sub>2</sub>O coordinative bond, the formation reaction was carried out at 60 °C. According to our previous observations [
  <a rid="B30-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-01309">30</a>,
  <a rid="B38-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-molecules-24-01309">38</a>], this temperature proved to be enough to overcome the kinetic barrier of the insertion. Depending on the anions in the electrolyte applied to adjust the ionic strength (to I = 0.01 M), the formation of mono- and bisporphyrin complexes occurs. Since in the visible range the absorption of lanthanides(III) is negligible compared with that of porphyrins, metal ion excess was applied in our work to study the formation of these kinetically labile complexes. The behaviors of the three lanthanide(III) ions in this study were very similar; hence, the spectral changes regarding the systems containing Gd(III) are presented to demonstrate the mutual characteristic features, as gadolinium is the most widely investigated and applied member of this triad.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the presence of acetate ions, which strongly coordinate to lanthanides(III) [
  <a rid="B48-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-molecules-24-01309">48</a>], only a monoporphyrin complex could form (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>a), while the noncoordinating perchlorate ions allowed the formation of bisporphyrin, too (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>b).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insertion of a metal ion into the porphyrin cavity, forming an OOP complex, was manifested by the redshift of the main Soret-band, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>a (from 413 to 421 nm), in accordance with the case of other OOP metallo-monoporphyrins (e.g., with Fe(II), Hg(II), Hg(I), Tl(I), and Cd(II) ions [
  <a rid="B19-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-molecules-24-01309">19</a>,
  <a rid="B49-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-molecules-24-01309">49</a>]). Besides the monoporphyrin complex, in the presence of perchlorate, the formation of bisporphyrin (Gd
  <sub>3</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">3−</span>) also took place as the broadening of the Soret-band, along with the decrease of the absorbances, compared with the case of the monoporphyrin (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>b). Similar spectral changes were measured for the corresponding samarium(III) and europium(III) systems, as well as the earlier investigated lanthanum(III), cerium(III), and neodymium(III) porphyrins [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The evaluation of the data regarding the spectrophotometric titrations, described in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309">Section 3.3</a>, provided the stability constants and the individual molar absorption spectra of mono- and bisporphyrin complexes in both the Soret- and Q-range. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f003" href="#molecules-24-01309-f003">Figure 3</a> displays the spectra of the studied gadolinium(III) porphyrins compared with those of the corresponding free base.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t001" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t001">Table 1</a> summarizes the formation constants for the Sm(III), Eu(III), and Gd(III) porphyrins in these systems.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The values determined for the monoporphyrins in acetate solutions (lgβ
  <sub>1:1</sub>(Ac
  <span class="sup">−</span>)) were moderately higher than the corresponding ones obtained in the presence of perchlorate ions. This difference may be interpreted by the trans effect of the acetate ion as a bidentate hard-base (
  <span class="italic">O</span>-donor) ligand bound to the lanthanide(III) ions. It promotes the coordination of the first porphyrin (but hampers the connection of an additional one) [
  <a rid="B33-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-molecules-24-01309">33</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the decrease of the ionic radius in the order of Sm(III) &gt; Eu(III) &gt; Gd(III) was rather moderate, the increase of the corresponding formation constants was similarly monotonous. This tendency can be explained by the shorter coordination bonds due to the better fit of the smaller metal ions into the porphyrin cavity. This interpretation is confirmed by the formation constants obtained earlier for the corresponding La(III), Ce(III), and Nd(III) complexes [
  <a rid="B37-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-molecules-24-01309">37</a>,
  <a rid="B51-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-molecules-24-01309">51</a>]. For example, the values for the formation of cerium(III) monoporphyrin (lgβ
  <sub>1:1</sub>(Ac
  <span class="sup">−</span>) = 4.00; lgβ
  <sub>1:1</sub> = 3.60 [
  <a rid="B51-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-molecules-24-01309">51</a>]) are one order of magnitude lower than those of the europium(III) complex, in accordance with the significantly higher ionic radius of Ce(III) (114.3 pm [
  <a rid="B50-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-molecules-24-01309">50</a>]). The same tendency was valid for the lgβ
  <sub>3:2</sub> values, even if the increase in the order of Sm(III) &lt; Eu(III) &lt; Gd(III) was very slight. However, compared with the value for the Ce
  <sub>3</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> complex (lgβ
  <sub>3:2</sub> = 16.30), the formation constant of the Eu(III) bisporphyrin was more than one order of magnitude higher.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the determination of the individual molar absorption spectra, analyses of the Soret- and Q-bands of the lanthanide(III) porphyrins studied were carried out by fitting Gaussian curves. The most important data obtained are shown in 
  <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t002">Table 2</a> (in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot2-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec2dot2-molecules-24-01309">Section 2.2</a>), compared to the corresponding values regarding the spectrum of the free-base porphyrin.
 </p>
</sec>
