<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Photophysics of Mono- and Bisporphyrins</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To elucidate the structure and the mode of coordination in these lanthanide complexes, particularly in the bisporphyrins, in aqueous systems, their S
  <sub>1</sub>-fluorescence properties were also investigated. Similar to the light-absorption experiments, spectrofluorimetric titrations were also carried out with these systems. The quasi-isosbestic point of the absorption spectra (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f003" href="#molecules-24-01309-f003">Figure 3</a>a) was chosen (at about 417 nm) as the excitation wavelength for the elimination of disturbing absorbance changes during the titration process. From the data of these spectral series, also regarding the systems containing bisporphyrins, the individual emission spectra could be determined. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f004" href="#molecules-24-01309-f004">Figure 4</a> displays the fluorescence spectra of the emitting species in the gadolinium(III)–porphyrin system. Insertion of the lanthanide(III) ion into the porphyrin cavity resulted in a significant blueshift of the fluorescence bands accompanied by a moderate change of their intensity ratio. The characteristic photophysical data of the mono- and bisporphyrins studied, compared to those of the free-base porphyrin, are summarized in 
  <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t002">Table 2</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As previously observed, the insertion of the metal center into the porphyrin cavity (in an out-of-plane position) diminished the fluorescence efficiency of the free base, due mostly to the distortion of the ligand plane and partly to electronic interactions. The fluorescence quantum yields for the Sm(III), Eu(III), and Gd(III) porphyrins investigated were considerably higher than those for the corresponding La(III) and Ce(III) complexes (e.g., 2.74 × 10
  <span class="sup">−2</span> and 1.03 × 10
  <span class="sup">−2</span> for the La(III) mono- and bisporphyrins, respectively) [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>]. This suggests that the significantly larger ionic radius (116 and 114 pm for La
  <span class="sup">3+</span> and Ce
  <span class="sup">3+</span>, respectively), resulting in a higher out-of-plane distance, caused a stronger (dome) distortion of the porphyrin ring. In the case of the corresponding Nd(III) porphyrins, the quantum yield values were similar to those of the Sm(III), Eu(III), and Gd(III) complexes due to the smaller difference between the ionic radii (111 pm for Nd
  <span class="sup">3+</span>) [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>]. Interestingly, however, within the group of the lanthanide(III) ions studied in this work, the quantum yield slightly decreased with the decreasing ionic radius. This phenomenon may be interpreted by an electronic interaction with the unpaired electrons of the metal center, the number of which increased up to the half-filled subshell of Gd
  <span class="sup">3+</span>. The lower ionic radius, due to the shorter bond length, strengthened this effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Excitation of these complexes at the Soret-band led to S
  <sub>1</sub>-fluoresence following an efficient internal conversion from the second singlet excited state to the first one. The ratio of the fluorescence quantum yields obtained by Soret- and Q-band excitations gave the efficiency of the internal conversion (ϕ(IC S
  <sub>2</sub>–S
  <sub>1</sub>) = Ф(S
  <sub>1</sub> − fluo@B)/ϕ(S
  <sub>1</sub> − fluo@Q)).This was a considerably efficient process in the case of these porphyrins (ϕ(IC S
  <sub>2</sub>–S
  <sub>1</sub>) was about 0.7), for both the free base and the lanthanide complexes. Interestingly, while the sandwich-type (head-to-head) OOP metallo-bisporphyrins did not display any appreciable S
  <sub>1</sub>-fluorescence [
  <a rid="B40-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-molecules-24-01309">40</a>], the emission quantum yield of the Ln
  <sub>3</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">3−</span> (tail-to-tail) complexes was about the same order of magnitude as that of the corresponding monoporphyrin. The fluorescence lifetimes were about the same value (1.94 ns) for all lanthanide porphyrins studied. This suggests that there was no significant electronic interaction between the porphyrin rings in the bisporphyrin structure. Basically, the effects of the metal center in the ligand cavity caused the change in the emission properties, compared to those of the free base. The lifetime for the S
  <sub>1</sub>-fluorescence of the free-base porphyrin was 10.0 ns (
  <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t002">Table 2</a>). The coordination of the lanthanide ions into the porphyrin cavity considerably diminished the emission lifetime to less than one-fifth of that of the free-base ligand. This was mainly due to the more complex and distorted structure significantly accelerating the nonradiative decay of the S
  <sub>1</sub> excited state.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The molar absorption spectrum of these lanthanide(III) bisporphyrins were very similar to those of the corresponding monoporphyrins; further, such analogies were also valid for their emission properties. These strong similarities clearly indicate that the electronic interactions between the porphyrin rings in the lanthanide(III) bisporphyrins studied in this work were very weak—almost negligible. Hence, in accordance with our earlier observation regarding the corresponding La(III), Ce(III), and Nd(III) complexes [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>], the monoporphyrin units in the bisporphyrins were connected through a metal bridge between the peripheral sulfonato substituents (i.e., tail-to-tail dimerization, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f005" href="#molecules-24-01309-f005">Figure 5</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
