<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot3-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Photochemistry of Mono- and Bisporphyrins</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The out-of-plane position of the metal center in these porphyrin complexes mostly promoted two types of photochemical reactions: (i) dissociation (to free metal ion and porphyrin ligand) without any redox change and (ii) an LMCT process, which generally led to the irreversible cleavage of the macrocycle, producing an open-chain tetrapyrrole derivative (bilindione) [
  <a rid="B30-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-01309">30</a>,
  <a rid="B52-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-molecules-24-01309">52</a>]. This ring-opening process was accompanied by the disappearance of the characteristic porphyrin bands due to the ceasing of the cyclic conjugated double-bond system [
  <a rid="B20-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-molecules-24-01309">20</a>,
  <a rid="B53-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-molecules-24-01309">53</a>]. Although irradiations at both the Soret- and Q-bands resulted in degradation of these lanthanide(III) porphyrins, different intermediates, depending on the excitation wavelength, were detected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f006" href="#molecules-24-01309-f006">Figure 6</a>a indicates, Soret-band irradiation led to the gradual decrease of the characteristic bands in both wavelength ranges due to the irreversible ring-cleavage. A careful analysis of the spectral change at longer wavelengths (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f006" href="#molecules-24-01309-f006">Figure 6</a>b) revealed the formation of an intermediate, which disappeared in the dark. Such a phenomenon was also observed earlier, in the case of other OOP metalloporphyins (with Bi(III) [
  <a rid="B19-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-molecules-24-01309">19</a>], Hg(II) [
  <a rid="B40-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-molecules-24-01309">40</a>], and Cd(II) [
  <a rid="B18-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-molecules-24-01309">18</a>]). This intermediate, featured by a band at about 450 nm (superimposed on the residual absorbance of the starting porphyrin complexes), may be a radical.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of Q-band irradiations (at about 555 nm) of these lanthanide(III) porphyrins, however, deviating from other OOP metalloporphyrins studied so far, a new type of end-product was observed. As 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f007" href="#molecules-24-01309-f007">Figure 7</a>a shows, this photoproduct gradually accumulated during a 45-min photolysis, and its stability in the dark was well demonstrated by the new absorption band at about 590 nm. This stable product may be a complex formed between a lanthanide(III) ion (in this case, Gd(III)) and the open-chain dioxo-tetrapyrrol photoproduct, due to the favored hard acid-base interaction. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f007" href="#molecules-24-01309-f007">Figure 7</a>b shows the estimated molar absorption spectra in the Gd(III) system. Using the individual molar absorbances, the actual concentration versus time data could be calculated for the absorbing species (as described in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309">Section 3.3</a>). The temporal concentration change of the species in the Gd(III)–porphyrin system during the photolyses, at both the Soret- and the Q-band maxima, are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f008" href="#molecules-24-01309-f008">Figure 8</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the systems containing mono- and bisporphyrins in equilibrium, as well as free-base ligands at very low concentrations, all these species were simultaneously excited in the photolysis. Detailed analyses of the spectral changes indicated that, besides the dissociation and photoredox degradation processes, photoinduced transformations between the mono- and bisporphyrin complexes could take place (leading to a steady-state equilibrium, i.e., a photostationary state [
  <a rid="B37-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-molecules-24-01309">37</a>]). Excitation dramatically accelerated these transformations compared with their rates in the dark [
  <a rid="B38-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-molecules-24-01309">38</a>]. Photoinduced ring-oxidation may also take place on the free-base ligand, although with very low quantum yields [
  <a rid="B49-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-molecules-24-01309">49</a>,
  <a rid="B54-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-molecules-24-01309">54</a>,
  <a rid="B55-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-molecules-24-01309">55</a>]. Besides, excitation may increase the rate of metalation and protonation of the free base. Using the molar absorbances of the photoactive species at the excitation wavelength and their concentration versus time data, the individual quantum yields for their photoinduced reactions could be calculated by the procedure described in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309">Section 3.3</a>. 
  <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t003" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t003">Table 3</a> summarizes the values of these quantum yields for the complexes in the systems studied along with that regarding the photoredox degradation of the free-base porphyrin at Soret-band irradiation. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In accordance with earlier results [
  <a rid="B40-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-molecules-24-01309">40</a>,
  <a rid="B49-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-molecules-24-01309">49</a>,
  <a rid="B53-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-molecules-24-01309">53</a>], the degradation efficiency of the free-base porphyrin at Soret-band irradiation was very small, that is, two orders of magnitude lower than those regarding the corresponding lanthanide(III) complexes. As these results indicate, the predominant part of the overall quantum yields of the complexes originated from the redox degradation due to the out-of-plane-position of the metal center.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As to the tendency regarding the overall quantum yields, they were unambiguously higher for the bisporphyrins than for their corresponding monomers. This was in accordance with the results obtained on the anionic porphyrins of La(III), Ce(III), and Nd(III) [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>]. This phenomenon may be interpreted by the higher probability of utilization of the absorbed photons due to the two metal-porphyrin units, with about the same molar absorbance as that of the corresponding monoporphyrin. The quantum yields for the complexes of the different metal centers did not significantly deviate because their ionic radii and, accordingly, their out-of-plane distances were rather similar. Even so, in the case of the bisporphyrins, a larger ionic radius led to higher overall quantum yield, promoting the demetalation, following the photoinduced electron transfer from the porphyrin ligand to the metal center. These photoinduced features may influence the application of such metalloporphyrins for medical purposes in both therapy and diagnostics.
 </p>
</sec>
