<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec2-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Formation, Composition, and Absorption Spectra</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The efficient light absorption of porphyrins and their metal complexes makes UV–Vis spectroscopy a suitable method to quantitatively investigate the formation, composition, and structure of water-soluble lanthanide(III) porphyrins. Since the insertion of hard-acid lanthanide(III) ions into the cavity of anionic porphyrin is a very slow process, partly due to the strong Ln(III)–H
   <sub>2</sub>O coordinative bond, the formation reaction was carried out at 60 °C. According to our previous observations [
   <a rid="B30-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-01309">30</a>,
   <a rid="B38-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-molecules-24-01309">38</a>], this temperature proved to be enough to overcome the kinetic barrier of the insertion. Depending on the anions in the electrolyte applied to adjust the ionic strength (to I = 0.01 M), the formation of mono- and bisporphyrin complexes occurs. Since in the visible range the absorption of lanthanides(III) is negligible compared with that of porphyrins, metal ion excess was applied in our work to study the formation of these kinetically labile complexes. The behaviors of the three lanthanide(III) ions in this study were very similar; hence, the spectral changes regarding the systems containing Gd(III) are presented to demonstrate the mutual characteristic features, as gadolinium is the most widely investigated and applied member of this triad.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the presence of acetate ions, which strongly coordinate to lanthanides(III) [
   <a rid="B48-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-molecules-24-01309">48</a>], only a monoporphyrin complex could form (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>a), while the noncoordinating perchlorate ions allowed the formation of bisporphyrin, too (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>b).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insertion of a metal ion into the porphyrin cavity, forming an OOP complex, was manifested by the redshift of the main Soret-band, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>a (from 413 to 421 nm), in accordance with the case of other OOP metallo-monoporphyrins (e.g., with Fe(II), Hg(II), Hg(I), Tl(I), and Cd(II) ions [
   <a rid="B19-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-molecules-24-01309">19</a>,
   <a rid="B49-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-molecules-24-01309">49</a>]). Besides the monoporphyrin complex, in the presence of perchlorate, the formation of bisporphyrin (Gd
   <sub>3</sub>P
   <sub>2</sub>
   <span class="sup">3−</span>) also took place as the broadening of the Soret-band, along with the decrease of the absorbances, compared with the case of the monoporphyrin (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f002" href="#molecules-24-01309-f002">Figure 2</a>b). Similar spectral changes were measured for the corresponding samarium(III) and europium(III) systems, as well as the earlier investigated lanthanum(III), cerium(III), and neodymium(III) porphyrins [
   <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The evaluation of the data regarding the spectrophotometric titrations, described in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309">Section 3.3</a>, provided the stability constants and the individual molar absorption spectra of mono- and bisporphyrin complexes in both the Soret- and Q-range. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f003" href="#molecules-24-01309-f003">Figure 3</a> displays the spectra of the studied gadolinium(III) porphyrins compared with those of the corresponding free base.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t001" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t001">Table 1</a> summarizes the formation constants for the Sm(III), Eu(III), and Gd(III) porphyrins in these systems.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The values determined for the monoporphyrins in acetate solutions (lgβ
   <sub>1:1</sub>(Ac
   <span class="sup">−</span>)) were moderately higher than the corresponding ones obtained in the presence of perchlorate ions. This difference may be interpreted by the trans effect of the acetate ion as a bidentate hard-base (
   <span class="italic">O</span>-donor) ligand bound to the lanthanide(III) ions. It promotes the coordination of the first porphyrin (but hampers the connection of an additional one) [
   <a rid="B33-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-molecules-24-01309">33</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the decrease of the ionic radius in the order of Sm(III) &gt; Eu(III) &gt; Gd(III) was rather moderate, the increase of the corresponding formation constants was similarly monotonous. This tendency can be explained by the shorter coordination bonds due to the better fit of the smaller metal ions into the porphyrin cavity. This interpretation is confirmed by the formation constants obtained earlier for the corresponding La(III), Ce(III), and Nd(III) complexes [
   <a rid="B37-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-molecules-24-01309">37</a>,
   <a rid="B51-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-molecules-24-01309">51</a>]. For example, the values for the formation of cerium(III) monoporphyrin (lgβ
   <sub>1:1</sub>(Ac
   <span class="sup">−</span>) = 4.00; lgβ
   <sub>1:1</sub> = 3.60 [
   <a rid="B51-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-molecules-24-01309">51</a>]) are one order of magnitude lower than those of the europium(III) complex, in accordance with the significantly higher ionic radius of Ce(III) (114.3 pm [
   <a rid="B50-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-molecules-24-01309">50</a>]). The same tendency was valid for the lgβ
   <sub>3:2</sub> values, even if the increase in the order of Sm(III) &lt; Eu(III) &lt; Gd(III) was very slight. However, compared with the value for the Ce
   <sub>3</sub>P
   <sub>2</sub> complex (lgβ
   <sub>3:2</sub> = 16.30), the formation constant of the Eu(III) bisporphyrin was more than one order of magnitude higher.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the determination of the individual molar absorption spectra, analyses of the Soret- and Q-bands of the lanthanide(III) porphyrins studied were carried out by fitting Gaussian curves. The most important data obtained are shown in 
   <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t002">Table 2</a> (in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot2-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec2dot2-molecules-24-01309">Section 2.2</a>), compared to the corresponding values regarding the spectrum of the free-base porphyrin.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Photophysics of Mono- and Bisporphyrins</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To elucidate the structure and the mode of coordination in these lanthanide complexes, particularly in the bisporphyrins, in aqueous systems, their S
   <sub>1</sub>-fluorescence properties were also investigated. Similar to the light-absorption experiments, spectrofluorimetric titrations were also carried out with these systems. The quasi-isosbestic point of the absorption spectra (see 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f003" href="#molecules-24-01309-f003">Figure 3</a>a) was chosen (at about 417 nm) as the excitation wavelength for the elimination of disturbing absorbance changes during the titration process. From the data of these spectral series, also regarding the systems containing bisporphyrins, the individual emission spectra could be determined. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f004" href="#molecules-24-01309-f004">Figure 4</a> displays the fluorescence spectra of the emitting species in the gadolinium(III)–porphyrin system. Insertion of the lanthanide(III) ion into the porphyrin cavity resulted in a significant blueshift of the fluorescence bands accompanied by a moderate change of their intensity ratio. The characteristic photophysical data of the mono- and bisporphyrins studied, compared to those of the free-base porphyrin, are summarized in 
   <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t002">Table 2</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As previously observed, the insertion of the metal center into the porphyrin cavity (in an out-of-plane position) diminished the fluorescence efficiency of the free base, due mostly to the distortion of the ligand plane and partly to electronic interactions. The fluorescence quantum yields for the Sm(III), Eu(III), and Gd(III) porphyrins investigated were considerably higher than those for the corresponding La(III) and Ce(III) complexes (e.g., 2.74 × 10
   <span class="sup">−2</span> and 1.03 × 10
   <span class="sup">−2</span> for the La(III) mono- and bisporphyrins, respectively) [
   <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>]. This suggests that the significantly larger ionic radius (116 and 114 pm for La
   <span class="sup">3+</span> and Ce
   <span class="sup">3+</span>, respectively), resulting in a higher out-of-plane distance, caused a stronger (dome) distortion of the porphyrin ring. In the case of the corresponding Nd(III) porphyrins, the quantum yield values were similar to those of the Sm(III), Eu(III), and Gd(III) complexes due to the smaller difference between the ionic radii (111 pm for Nd
   <span class="sup">3+</span>) [
   <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>]. Interestingly, however, within the group of the lanthanide(III) ions studied in this work, the quantum yield slightly decreased with the decreasing ionic radius. This phenomenon may be interpreted by an electronic interaction with the unpaired electrons of the metal center, the number of which increased up to the half-filled subshell of Gd
   <span class="sup">3+</span>. The lower ionic radius, due to the shorter bond length, strengthened this effect.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Excitation of these complexes at the Soret-band led to S
   <sub>1</sub>-fluoresence following an efficient internal conversion from the second singlet excited state to the first one. The ratio of the fluorescence quantum yields obtained by Soret- and Q-band excitations gave the efficiency of the internal conversion (ϕ(IC S
   <sub>2</sub>–S
   <sub>1</sub>) = Ф(S
   <sub>1</sub> − fluo@B)/ϕ(S
   <sub>1</sub> − fluo@Q)).This was a considerably efficient process in the case of these porphyrins (ϕ(IC S
   <sub>2</sub>–S
   <sub>1</sub>) was about 0.7), for both the free base and the lanthanide complexes. Interestingly, while the sandwich-type (head-to-head) OOP metallo-bisporphyrins did not display any appreciable S
   <sub>1</sub>-fluorescence [
   <a rid="B40-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-molecules-24-01309">40</a>], the emission quantum yield of the Ln
   <sub>3</sub>P
   <sub>2</sub>
   <span class="sup">3−</span> (tail-to-tail) complexes was about the same order of magnitude as that of the corresponding monoporphyrin. The fluorescence lifetimes were about the same value (1.94 ns) for all lanthanide porphyrins studied. This suggests that there was no significant electronic interaction between the porphyrin rings in the bisporphyrin structure. Basically, the effects of the metal center in the ligand cavity caused the change in the emission properties, compared to those of the free base. The lifetime for the S
   <sub>1</sub>-fluorescence of the free-base porphyrin was 10.0 ns (
   <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t002">Table 2</a>). The coordination of the lanthanide ions into the porphyrin cavity considerably diminished the emission lifetime to less than one-fifth of that of the free-base ligand. This was mainly due to the more complex and distorted structure significantly accelerating the nonradiative decay of the S
   <sub>1</sub> excited state.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The molar absorption spectrum of these lanthanide(III) bisporphyrins were very similar to those of the corresponding monoporphyrins; further, such analogies were also valid for their emission properties. These strong similarities clearly indicate that the electronic interactions between the porphyrin rings in the lanthanide(III) bisporphyrins studied in this work were very weak—almost negligible. Hence, in accordance with our earlier observation regarding the corresponding La(III), Ce(III), and Nd(III) complexes [
   <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>], the monoporphyrin units in the bisporphyrins were connected through a metal bridge between the peripheral sulfonato substituents (i.e., tail-to-tail dimerization, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f005" href="#molecules-24-01309-f005">Figure 5</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-molecules-24-01309" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Photochemistry of Mono- and Bisporphyrins</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The out-of-plane position of the metal center in these porphyrin complexes mostly promoted two types of photochemical reactions: (i) dissociation (to free metal ion and porphyrin ligand) without any redox change and (ii) an LMCT process, which generally led to the irreversible cleavage of the macrocycle, producing an open-chain tetrapyrrole derivative (bilindione) [
   <a rid="B30-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-01309">30</a>,
   <a rid="B52-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-molecules-24-01309">52</a>]. This ring-opening process was accompanied by the disappearance of the characteristic porphyrin bands due to the ceasing of the cyclic conjugated double-bond system [
   <a rid="B20-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-molecules-24-01309">20</a>,
   <a rid="B53-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-molecules-24-01309">53</a>]. Although irradiations at both the Soret- and Q-bands resulted in degradation of these lanthanide(III) porphyrins, different intermediates, depending on the excitation wavelength, were detected.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f006" href="#molecules-24-01309-f006">Figure 6</a>a indicates, Soret-band irradiation led to the gradual decrease of the characteristic bands in both wavelength ranges due to the irreversible ring-cleavage. A careful analysis of the spectral change at longer wavelengths (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f006" href="#molecules-24-01309-f006">Figure 6</a>b) revealed the formation of an intermediate, which disappeared in the dark. Such a phenomenon was also observed earlier, in the case of other OOP metalloporphyins (with Bi(III) [
   <a rid="B19-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-molecules-24-01309">19</a>], Hg(II) [
   <a rid="B40-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-molecules-24-01309">40</a>], and Cd(II) [
   <a rid="B18-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-molecules-24-01309">18</a>]). This intermediate, featured by a band at about 450 nm (superimposed on the residual absorbance of the starting porphyrin complexes), may be a radical.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of Q-band irradiations (at about 555 nm) of these lanthanide(III) porphyrins, however, deviating from other OOP metalloporphyrins studied so far, a new type of end-product was observed. As 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f007" href="#molecules-24-01309-f007">Figure 7</a>a shows, this photoproduct gradually accumulated during a 45-min photolysis, and its stability in the dark was well demonstrated by the new absorption band at about 590 nm. This stable product may be a complex formed between a lanthanide(III) ion (in this case, Gd(III)) and the open-chain dioxo-tetrapyrrol photoproduct, due to the favored hard acid-base interaction. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f007" href="#molecules-24-01309-f007">Figure 7</a>b shows the estimated molar absorption spectra in the Gd(III) system. Using the individual molar absorbances, the actual concentration versus time data could be calculated for the absorbing species (as described in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309">Section 3.3</a>). The temporal concentration change of the species in the Gd(III)–porphyrin system during the photolyses, at both the Soret- and the Q-band maxima, are shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01309-f008" href="#molecules-24-01309-f008">Figure 8</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the systems containing mono- and bisporphyrins in equilibrium, as well as free-base ligands at very low concentrations, all these species were simultaneously excited in the photolysis. Detailed analyses of the spectral changes indicated that, besides the dissociation and photoredox degradation processes, photoinduced transformations between the mono- and bisporphyrin complexes could take place (leading to a steady-state equilibrium, i.e., a photostationary state [
   <a rid="B37-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-molecules-24-01309">37</a>]). Excitation dramatically accelerated these transformations compared with their rates in the dark [
   <a rid="B38-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-molecules-24-01309">38</a>]. Photoinduced ring-oxidation may also take place on the free-base ligand, although with very low quantum yields [
   <a rid="B49-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-molecules-24-01309">49</a>,
   <a rid="B54-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-molecules-24-01309">54</a>,
   <a rid="B55-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-molecules-24-01309">55</a>]. Besides, excitation may increase the rate of metalation and protonation of the free base. Using the molar absorbances of the photoactive species at the excitation wavelength and their concentration versus time data, the individual quantum yields for their photoinduced reactions could be calculated by the procedure described in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309" href="#sec3dot3-molecules-24-01309">Section 3.3</a>. 
   <a rid="molecules-24-01309-t003" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-01309-t003">Table 3</a> summarizes the values of these quantum yields for the complexes in the systems studied along with that regarding the photoredox degradation of the free-base porphyrin at Soret-band irradiation. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In accordance with earlier results [
   <a rid="B40-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-molecules-24-01309">40</a>,
   <a rid="B49-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-molecules-24-01309">49</a>,
   <a rid="B53-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-molecules-24-01309">53</a>], the degradation efficiency of the free-base porphyrin at Soret-band irradiation was very small, that is, two orders of magnitude lower than those regarding the corresponding lanthanide(III) complexes. As these results indicate, the predominant part of the overall quantum yields of the complexes originated from the redox degradation due to the out-of-plane-position of the metal center.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As to the tendency regarding the overall quantum yields, they were unambiguously higher for the bisporphyrins than for their corresponding monomers. This was in accordance with the results obtained on the anionic porphyrins of La(III), Ce(III), and Nd(III) [
   <a rid="B15-molecules-24-01309" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-01309">15</a>]. This phenomenon may be interpreted by the higher probability of utilization of the absorbed photons due to the two metal-porphyrin units, with about the same molar absorbance as that of the corresponding monoporphyrin. The quantum yields for the complexes of the different metal centers did not significantly deviate because their ionic radii and, accordingly, their out-of-plane distances were rather similar. Even so, in the case of the bisporphyrins, a larger ionic radius led to higher overall quantum yield, promoting the demetalation, following the photoinduced electron transfer from the porphyrin ligand to the metal center. These photoinduced features may influence the application of such metalloporphyrins for medical purposes in both therapy and diagnostics.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
