<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is well known that silver ions have a bactericidal action. The bactericidal mechanism of silver ions is related to the strong interaction of ionic silver with the sulfhydryl group of enzymes, which results in enzyme inactivation [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02518">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02518">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02518">3</a>], enhanced caspase-3 activity, and DNA ladder formation in mammalian cells [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-02518">4</a>]. Small electron-dense granules formed by silver and sulfur cause changes in cell membrane structure and production of free radical [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02518">5</a>]. In the research of food packaging material, materials containing silver nanoparticles (AgNPs) for food packaging are classified into non-degradable polymer matrices [
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02518">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-02518">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-02518">8</a>] and biodegradable coating films made of a polymer or a stabilizer [
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-16-02518">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-02518">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-02518">11</a>]. The addition of AgNPs as an antimicrobial agent in food packaging material is a mature technology, but there is still a risk of safety accidents caused by the migration of silver ions (Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span>) from the package to food. Numerous studies have shown that AgNPs have a toxic effect on the skin, liver, lung, brain, and vascular cells of mammals [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-02518">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-02518">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-02518">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-16-02518">15</a>]. It has been reported that AgNPs may induce cytotoxicity in phagocytic cells (such as mouse peritoneal macrophages) and human monocytes. It has been suggested that cytotoxicity can be induced by reactive oxygen species (ROS) at low concentrations and for short incubation times, resulting in cellular apoptosis [
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-16-02518">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-16-02518">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-02518">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-16-02518">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-16-02518">20</a>]. Silver is highly toxic to various microorganisms [
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-16-02518">21</a>]. Studies have shown that DNA loses its ability to replicate, and the structure of the cell membrane changes after treatment with silver ions [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02518">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conventional methods widely used to detect silver ions include atomic absorption spectrometry (AAS) [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-02518">22</a>] and inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP–MS) [
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-16-02518">23</a>]. However, complex instrumentation and sample preparation processes limit the application of AAS and ICP–MS for silver ion detection. As a common metal element analysis method, flame atomic absorption spectrometry (FAAS) has a wide range of applications due to its simple analytical operation and fast analysis. However, this method is limited by the low atomization efficiency and short residence time of the atomic vapor in the optical path [
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-16-02518">24</a>]. Electrothermal atomic absorption spectrometry (ETAAS) is a method with the advantages of high sensitivity and low cost [
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-16-02518">25</a>]. However, it is limited by the lack of certification references for trace metals in different materials. Fluorescent sensors are applied in various biological and environmental matrices for the detection of metal ions at ng or sub-ng levels due to their high simplicity and sensitivity [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-16-02518">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-16-02518">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-02518">28</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent years, carbon-based fluorescent nanomaterials have attracted great attention for the development of molecular diagnostic tools [
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-02518">29</a>]. Carbon quantum dots (CQDs) have been widely used in photovoltaic devices [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02518">30</a>,
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-16-02518">31</a>] and photocatalysis [
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-02518">32</a>] because of their superior luminescence, good biocompatibility [
  <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-02518">33</a>], and strong resistance to photodegradation [
  <a rid="B34-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-16-02518">34</a>,
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-16-02518">35</a>]. Element doping increases quantum yield greatly. Nitrogen-doped carbon quantum dots (N-CQDs) exhibit outstanding performance in bioimaging and catalysis [
  <a rid="B36-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-16-02518">36</a>,
  <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-02518">37</a>]. It has been reported that N-CQDs have high quantum yields and a large number of semiconductor quantum dots, and the emission intensity of N-CQDs depends on their nitrogen content [
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-02518">38</a>,
  <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-02518">39</a>,
  <a rid="B40-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-16-02518">40</a>,
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-16-02518">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, N-CQDs with yellow-green fluorescence were prepared by surface functionalization of carbon quantum dots through a solvent-thermal reaction. N-CQDs were used for the detection of trace Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span>, demonstrating that they provide a new way for the detection of trace Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span> in food packaging materials.
 </p>
</sec>
