<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot6-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6. Detection of Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span> in Food Packaging Materials
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of the quantitative detection of silver ions in a food packaging sample by the N-CQDs detection method and the Chinese standard method are shown in 
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02518-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02518-t001">Table 1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02518-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02518-t001">Table 1</a>, the concentration of Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span> in the sample was determined to be 1.352 mg/L by the Chinese standard method GB11907-89, corresponding to 22.10 mg/kg. The content of harmful heavy metal ions in packaging materials should not exceed 100 mg/kg according to Chinese food safety regulations, so the Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span> content in this sample did not exceed the standard limit.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The concentration of Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span> in the sample was 1.442 mg/L according to the N-CQDs detection method. As shown in 
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02518-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02518-t001">Table 1</a>, the comparison between the results of the N-CQDs detection method and the Chinese standard method GB 11907-89 indicates that the relative error was 6.24%, and the test result was reliable. Food contact materials tend to be contaminated by heavy metals such as lead [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-16-02518">47</a>] and cadmium [
  <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-02518">48</a>] during processing, and the presence of these heavy metal ions causes a certain degree of fluorescence quenching of N-CQDs. Compared with the national standard method (GB 11907-89), the N-CQDs method may have a tendency to produce false positive results. In the experiment shown, the reason may be that the tested food packaging material contained heavy metals such as lead and cadmium.
 </p>
</sec>
