<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mechanism of silver ions detection by N-CQDs is shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f001" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f001">Figure 1</a>. When N-CQDs react with Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span>, the fluorescence of N-CQDs is quenched. Fluorescence quenching of N-CQDs can be attributed to the interaction of Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span> and N-CQDs, which promotes a transfer of charge from the excited state of N-CQDs to Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span>.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Characterization of Structure and Composition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, the prepared N-CQDs were tested with high-resolution TEM. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f002">Figure 2</a>a, there was no significant lattice stripe of N-CQDs, which indicated that the prepared N-CQDs were amorphous structures. As can be seen from the FT-IR spectra (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f002">Figure 2</a>b), the functional groups of N-CQDs were mainly amine (3421 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), methylene (2895, 2965 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), and amide carbonyl (1716 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), and the chemical bonds were C=C (1458, 1507 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), C–N (1410 cm
   <span class="sup">-1</span>), aromatic C–NH (1271 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), and C–O (1097 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>). XPS measurements were carried out to probe the N atoms in the N-CQDs. XPS full-scan spectra showed three peaks around 284.8, 399.3, and 532 eV that were ascribed to carbon, nitrogen, and oxygen, respectively (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f002">Figure 2</a>c). As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f002">Figure 2</a>c,d, there was no significant difference in the concentrations of N1s at depths of 10, 20, and 30 nm from the N-CQDs surface. This indicates that the internal structure of the prepared N-CQDs was uniform. The content of N was about 16% (N/C atomic ratio is about 20.0%), which is much higher than that of various N-doped graphene-based materials (0.3–8.3%) [
   <a rid="B43-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-16-02518">43</a>,
   <a rid="B44-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-16-02518">44</a>,
   <a rid="B45-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-16-02518">45</a>,
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-02518">46</a>]. Elemental analysis indicated that the prepared N-CQDs contained about 19% of nitrogen element.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Characterization of Fluorescence Quantum Yield and Fluorescence Lifetime</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f003" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f003">Figure 3</a>a, the fluorescence quantum yield of the prepared N-CQDs was 5.11%, as determined by the calculation formula (1) in 4.4.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fluorescence lifetime of N-CQDs was measured by time-correlated single-photon counting (TCSPC). After processing and fitting the measurement data, the fluorescence lifetime was obtained, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f003" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f003">Figure 3</a>b. According to the exponential fitting curve in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f003" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f003">Figure 3</a>b and the data (τ
   <sub>1</sub> = 2.1605 ns, τ
   <sub>2</sub> = 6.4231 ns, B1 = 96.774 %, B2 = 184.864 %, χ
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 1.068) from fitting the parameters of the fluorescence decay curve, the average weighted lifetime of fluorescence attenuation of the N-CQDs under the excitation of 400 nm was 5.79 ns, as determined by using formula (2) in 4.5, where χ
   <span class="sup">2</span> was 1.068.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Fluorescence Intensity of N-CQDs at Different Dilutions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f004" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f004">Figure 4</a>a, we found an excitation peak around 400 nm. When excited at 400 nm, the N-CQDs exhibited strong photoluminescence (PL) emission centered at 546 nm. The fluorescence intensities of N-CQDs at different dilutions were measured by fluorescence spectrometry (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f004" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f004">Figure 4</a>b). The fluorescence intensity of N-CQDs diluted 50 times in water was the strongest. Therefore, N-CQDs diluted 50 times in ultrapure water was finally applied for the detection of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot4-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Determination of the Concentration of Silver Ions by N-CQDs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various concentrations of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> (0–30 μM) were added to the N-CQDs (pH = 7) to explore the performance of N-CQDs in the detection of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> in aqueous solution. It can be seen in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f005" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f005">Figure 5</a>a that the enhancement of the fluorescence quenching effect of N-CQDs can be attributed to the increase of silver ion concentration. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f005" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f005">Figure 5</a>b, as the Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> increased from 0 to 30 μM, the fluorescence quenching efficiency gradually increased. With the increase of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> concentration, the quenching efficiency of N-CQDs became increasingly higher, and the maximum efficiency was as high as 40%. The calibration curve of the quenching efficiency depending on Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> concentrations of 0–10 μM and 10–30 μM can be expressed as y = 0.00614x + 0.02296, with correlation coefficient (R
   <span class="sup">2</span>) = 0.99, and I = 0.01789C − 0.09467. The experimental data showed that the fluorescence quenching efficiency of N-CQDs in the presence of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> showed a linear relationship with silver ion concentrations of 0–10 μM and 10–30 μM.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot5-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Selective Detection of Silver Ions by N-CQDs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f006" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f006">Figure 6</a>a, there was no significant effect on the fluorescence intensity of N-CQD after adding Hg
   <span class="sup">2+</span>, Cu
   <span class="sup">2+</span>, Cd
   <span class="sup">2+</span>, Cd
   <span class="sup">2+</span>, Co
   <span class="sup">2+</span>, Zn
   <span class="sup">2+</span>, or Mn
   <span class="sup">2+</span>. Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> exerted a significant fluorescence quenching effect on N-CQDs, indicating that N-CQDs had a good selectivity for Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span>. This phenomenon may be due to the coordination reaction between Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> and N–H. The types of bonds between Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> and N-CQDs may be coordination interactions between Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> and C–N groups. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02518-f006" href="#ijerph-16-02518-f006">Figure 6</a>b shows that CdSe quantum dots had higher selectivity for copper ions than silver ions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot6-ijerph-16-02518" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6. Detection of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> in Food Packaging Materials
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of the quantitative detection of silver ions in a food packaging sample by the N-CQDs detection method and the Chinese standard method are shown in 
   <a rid="ijerph-16-02518-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02518-t001">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a rid="ijerph-16-02518-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02518-t001">Table 1</a>, the concentration of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> in the sample was determined to be 1.352 mg/L by the Chinese standard method GB11907-89, corresponding to 22.10 mg/kg. The content of harmful heavy metal ions in packaging materials should not exceed 100 mg/kg according to Chinese food safety regulations, so the Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> content in this sample did not exceed the standard limit.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The concentration of Ag
   <span class="sup">+</span> in the sample was 1.442 mg/L according to the N-CQDs detection method. As shown in 
   <a rid="ijerph-16-02518-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02518-t001">Table 1</a>, the comparison between the results of the N-CQDs detection method and the Chinese standard method GB 11907-89 indicates that the relative error was 6.24%, and the test result was reliable. Food contact materials tend to be contaminated by heavy metals such as lead [
   <a rid="B47-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-16-02518">47</a>] and cadmium [
   <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-02518" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-02518">48</a>] during processing, and the presence of these heavy metal ions causes a certain degree of fluorescence quenching of N-CQDs. Compared with the national standard method (GB 11907-89), the N-CQDs method may have a tendency to produce false positive results. In the experiment shown, the reason may be that the tested food packaging material contained heavy metals such as lead and cadmium.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
