<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this article we have presented quantum non-adiabatic DCT results of the He
  <span class="sup">+</span>+H
  <sub>2</sub> collision, employing an electronic diabatic representation, previously computed by Aguado et al. (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">1993</a>), a WP time dependent formalism, and a flux analysis. Specifically, we have taken into account the non-adiabatic CI coupling between the first two excited diabatic PESs of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M66" class="math">
    <div class="msubsup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mtext">HeH</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">+</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>. Dynamical calculations are performed for the ground and first excited vibrational states of H
  <sub>2</sub>, for investigating vibrational effects on the DCT dynamics, and collision energies up to 3 eV are considered. Reaction probabilities and ICSs present strong and narrow resonance features up to 0.5 eV, due to quasi-bound molecular states embedded in the continuum and trapped in the ion-induced dipole minimum of the reactant channel, near the CI. These features are very hard to converge and affect all the DCT dynamics. These intense resonance features have a determinant role in the radiative charge-transfer formation (Mrugala et al., 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">2013</a>) of stable 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M67" class="math">
    <div class="msubsup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mtext">HeH</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">+</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, probably present in the interstellar medium (Tennyson and Miller, 
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">1987</a>). At higher collision energies the computational load reduces drastically owing to a near conservation of the helicity quantum number. Our results are in reasonable agreement with previous experimental and theoretical studies of this reaction, confirming the strong vibrational enhancement previously founded. In fact, rate constants increase of about two orders of magnitude just adding one vibrational quantum to the H
  <sub>2</sub> reactants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the best of our knowledge, these are the first rigorous quantum DCT calculations presented for a chemical system, made possible by the joint implementation of time-dependent WP, time-to-energy Fourier transform, and flux methods. On the other hand, a more rigorous approach, as time independent close coupling calculations, cannot be attempted at the present state-of-the-art of the reaction dynamics theories, because of the difficulty of these methods to treat the three-bodies breakup (see e.g., (Pack et al., 
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">1998</a>), and references therein). The results achieved could have relevant consequences in astrophysics and in particular in the early Universe evolution models (Bovino et al., 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">2011</a>). Although the reaction is probably negligible when the molecular hydrogen is relaxed in its ground vibrational state, the strong increase with the vibrational energy suggests that it could have a role during the early stages of the adiabatic expansion at high redshift, destroying the molecular hydrogen formed and slowing down further cooling of the primordial gas. Of course, to determinate its role, evolution Universe models with at least a vibrational resolution of the chemical network (Coppola et al., 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">2011</a>, 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">2012</a>) are required. Moreover, this reaction could be also relevant in other different astrophysical environments, as for example in the study of the Sun atmosphere where the temperature is very high and hydrogen and helium are very abundant species.
 </p>
</sec>
