<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cellular uptake experiments with lipodots</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, we focused on the potential of lipodots for cellular uptake into salivary gland duct cells. In incubation experiments similar to that performed with free QD655, small salivary gland lobes were treated for 120 min with physiological saline containing 10 nM lipodots. Prior lipodots addition, only the autofluorescence signal could be detected, as mentioned above. However, in the presence of lipodots the acquired luminescence intensity images and the corresponding 2P-FLIM images suggested a successful uptake of QD655 from the DOPC:DOPE-lipodots (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>). Since, no visible changes of the cellular morphology between lipodots-treated cells and the control untreated cells were observed, we assumed no significant cytotoxicity of QD655 in the used cells. Approximately 5 min after incubation, we observed inhomogeneously distributed bright luminescent spots within the cytosol, but excluded from the nucleus. The luminescence intensity in the cells slightly increased with acquisition time up to a saturation point at approx. 30 min. A similar uptake pattern has been reported for QD610-loaded liposomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> as well as for QD655 (PEG)-loaded liposomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. The intracellular luminescent spots could be attributed to aggregates of quantum dots formed intracellularly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>
  </span>. Surprisingly, this luminescence signal was more pronounced in the green detection channel than in the red detection channel, although the QD655 emission maximum was observed at 652 nm (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). This in turn could by partly explained by luminescence quenching of intact quantum dots due to the changed intracellular microenvironment, especially concerning the ionic strength and possible interactions of quantum dots with cellular molecules
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>
  </span>. In addition, the enhanced signal in the green detection channel indicated a blue shift in the quantum dot luminescence. This could be in fact the result of degradation processes after release of QD655 from lipodots for instance by endosomal and lysosomal activity. Moreover, we observed also an increasing clustering of luminescent particles in the extracellular surrounding medium without any changes in the red luminescence (bright red spots only in the red detection channel). This clustering behaviour of lipodots in physiological saline is different to that observed in the case of free QD655 without any liposomal carrier (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). The assumed effect of quenching and degradation of quantum dot luminescence in the cells was confirmed by the luminescence decay curves obtained from the regions of interest in the green detection channel, which were fitted to a biexponential decay function yielding reasonable residuals and reduced 
  <div id="IEq6" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M23" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\chi }_{R}^{2}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M24" class="math">
     <div class="msubsup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">χ</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Article_IEq6.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> values (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>). Thus, the resulted average decay times were one order of magnitude shorter than those of free QD655 and lipodots in PBS microenvironment (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). After a saturation point, reached approximately after 30 min incubation, the intensity-weighted average decay time 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> continued to decrease from 2.70 ± 0.29 ns at 30 min up to 2.57 ± 0.38 ns at 120 min (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 18) measured in the green detection channel. Thus, the observation of strong blue-shifted luminescence emission combined with shorter luminescence decay times most probably indicates the intracellular release of free QD655 rather than accumulation of intact lipodots.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Analysis of the cellular uptake of neutral lipodots into living duct cells. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Representative 2P-luminescence intensity images and corresponding 2P-FLIM images of duct cells recorded in the green (BP 514/44) and red (BP 700/75) detection channels at distinct time points. The cells were treated for 120 min with physiological saline containing 10 nM DOPC:DOPE-lipodots. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Luminescence decay curves extracted from intracellular regions of interest from 2P-FLIM images recorded in the green detection channel. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Autocorrelation curves obtained from 2P-FCS line-scan measurements performed in duct cells recorded in the green detection channel.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2028" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, we examined the diffusion behaviour of quantum dots in cells by performing line-scan FCS in the cellular regions. The cytoplasm is a heterogeneous environment consisting of internal membrane structures, cytoskeletal meshwork and other macrobiomolecules, so that the diffusive transport of molecules deviates from ideal behaviour and strongly depends on the position within the cell
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>
  </span>. It has been already reported, that while most of quantum dot aggregates in living cells are immobile, some of them move, often in a fairly straight paths in a rapidly fashion
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>
  </span>. However, Ruan 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. postulated a random diffusion of released quantum dots in crowded cytoplasm. They estimated that the time to diffuse through a 20 µm-diameter cell for a single quantum dot of a hydrodynamic radius of 10 nm would be ~30 s, whereas it would be ≥5 h for a vesicle of a hydrodynamic size of 80 nm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. However, in most cases, we could measure reasonable autocorrelation curves, that showed in general a shift to slightly longer diffusion times compared to the autocorrelation curves obtained for the intrinsic autofluorescence alone (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a>). While for some autocorrelation curves the diffusion times increased up to 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D</sub> = 1.3 ± 0.2 s (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 12), in several cases we determined two different diffusion times with 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> = 800 ± 113 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 61%) and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D2</sub> = 1.17 ± 0.52 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 39%) (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 26). We compared these results with the diffusion times of freely diffusing QD655 in PBS and we attributed the slow diffusion component to possible intracellular quantum dots aggregates, as mentioned before. The appearance of the faster diffusion time component could be the result from single diffusing free quantum dots, even though this value is smaller than that obtained from free QD655 in PBS (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). The discrepancy is probably based on the fitting procedure of the quite different time components (800 ms 
  <span class="italic">vs</span>. 1.17 ms) leading to an underestimation of the fast time component. This fact would support a successful release of quantum dots from the lipodots. Previous studies suggest that especially endocytosis and lipid-mediated fusion with the cell membranes are the major pathways for liposomal internalisation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>
  </span>. Dudu 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. revealed a consistent difference in the mechanism of quantum dot internalisation in two different cancer cell lines using the same cationic liposomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Since it is known, that the liposome-binding with the cell plasma membrane is non-specific and mostly driven by electrostatic interactions between the liposome carriers and proteoglycans present at the cell surface, the fusion probability of the liposomes strongly depends on their surface charge and lipid composition
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>
  </span>. It has been proposed that the use of cationic lipids is essential for increased cellular uptake of liposomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>
  </span>. Recently, it has been shown that in addition to neutral and cationic lipids the presence of an aromatic molecule significantly improves the fusion efficiency of liposomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>
  </span>. However, in this study the presence of neutral DOPE in the lipodots was sufficient and could be reasonable for their membrane association. DOPE facilitates the internalisation by fusion with the membrane, which can be attributed to their minimally hydrated head group and the resulting high affinity toward cell membrane
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>
  </span>. This is called the transbilayer internalisation pathway
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>
  </span>. Nevertheless, further studies have to be performed in future to investigate the mechanisms of cellular uptake as well as intracellular trafficking mechanism for lipodots, especially in different complex cell types.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, we tested the interactions of DOPC:DOPS-lipodots with salivary gland duct cells. Since DOPC:DOPS-lipodots showed a more negative zeta potential compared to DOPC:DOPE-lipodots, they could exhibit a different interaction behaviour. The 2P-FLIM images of the duct cells exposed to the negatively charged lipodots showed in addition to cytoplasmic luminescence also a strong luminescence signal at the membrane, indicating an accumulation of lipodots at the cell surface (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6a</a>). This was especially true for the red detection channel, monitoring the spectroscopic unchanged quantum dots. As soon as QD655 was accumulated intracellularly, the luminescence decay time decreased and the emission was blue-shifted (green detection channel). Thus, the intracellular quantum dot stability seems to be insufficient and further quantum dot surface modifications are required. Nevertheless, no considerable differences in the intracellular labelling pattern, luminescence decay time and diffusion behaviour could be observed between both types of lipodots. Indeed, also in the case of DOPC:DOPS-lipodots a decrease in the intensity-weighted average decay time from 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> = 2.58 ± 0.37 ns at 30 min up to 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> = 2.20 ± 0.24 ns at 120 min (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 13) has been observed (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6b</a>). A shift of the autocorrelation curves to longer diffusion times (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6c</a>) resulted either in a single diffusion time of 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D</sub> = 792 ± 175 ms (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 18) or two different diffusion time components with 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> = 523 ± 107 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 55%) and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D2</sub> = 1.85 ± 0.96 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 45%) (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 10).
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Analysis of the cellular uptake of negatively charged lipodots into living duct cells. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Representative 2P-luminescence intensity images and corresponding 2P-FLIM images of duct cells recorded in the green (BP 514/44) and red (BP 700/75) detection channels at distinct time points. The cells were treated for 120 min with physiological saline containing 10 nM DOPC:DOPS-lipodots. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Luminescence decay curves extracted from intracellular regions of interest from the 2P-FLIM images recorded in the green detection channel. 
     <span class="bold">(c)</span> Autocorrelation curves obtained from 2P-FCS line-scan measurements performed in duct cells recorded in the green detection channel.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2205" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a> shows the time-dependent changes in the intracellular luminescence intensity measured in the green detection channel for the two differently composed lipodots compared with free QD655. The application of free QD655 did not result in significant changes compared to the intracellular autofluorescene, indicating their ineffective cellular uptake. On the other hand, the application of encapsulated quantum dots resulted in their sufficient intracellular uptake, however, accompanied with altered luminescence properties. An increase in the luminescence intensity was observed after the initial 5 min bath application of lipodots to the cells, but this change was surprisingly reversible. After approx. 30 min incubation period, the intracellular luminescence intensity slowly decreased, probably due to intracellular degradation. This cellular uptake behaviour was consistent with the findings for two different cell lines, HeLa and GPC
  <span class="sup">PDGF</span>, which showed a rapid uptake of cationic lipodots, although the intracellular luminescence intensity increased continuously, even after 60 min incubation period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Internalisation of cationic liposomes labelled with quantum dots into human lung epithelial carcinoma A549 cells has been already observed after 5 min post-injection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, whereas in the case of anionic lipodots a luminescence signal in melanoma cells could be only observed after 2 h incubation period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. That study pointed out, that the internalisation efficiency of quantum dot-loaded liposomes strongly depends on the liposomal cargo and composition as well as the cell types, so it is often difficult to compare the results among each other. However, more systematic work needs to be carried out to reveal and interpret the exact intracellular trafficking mechanism for lipodots. Furthermore, to improve the biological application of quantum dots, novel forms of 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> tracking, including multi-colour and three-dimensional quantum dot tracking tools are essential
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>
  </span>. In recent years, a new class of nanocrystal quantum dots, the so called non-blinking giant quantum dots, has been introduced
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>
  </span>. The stable emission from these quantum dots allows an extended tracking duration compared to conventional core/shell blinking quantum dots, leading to observations of heterogeneous receptor diffusion occurring over time scales of minutes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Time-dependent relative luminescence intensity changes in duct cells. Intracellular luminescence intensity changes of regions of interest were recorded during a period of 2 h for cells in physiological saline alone (grey line) and separately for cells incubated in physiological saline with 5 nM QD655 (black line) or 10 nM lipodots using one of the two different lipid compositions (red &amp; blue lines). Intensity changes relative to the starting point (
     <span class="italic">t</span> = 0) were analysed from 2P-FLIM images recorded in the green detection channel; means ± SEM of 
     <span class="italic">N</span> = 3–18.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e2256" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
