<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cellular uptake experiments with free QD655</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the benefit of lipodots for cellular uptake experiments, we started with incubation experiments using only free QD655. Thus, small salivary gland lobes were treated for 120 min with physiological saline containing 5 nM QD655 and the described results are representative for 
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 6 independent experiments. Since the cellular autofluorescence mainly resulted from NADH and FAD as discussed above and according to their luminescence emission maxima
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, the luminescence intensity within the duct cells was more pronounced in the green than in the red detection channel at 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 0 min (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). The bath incubation with free QD655 for 120 min did not significantly change the intracellular luminescence intensity in both detection channels. In addition, the weak intracellular luminescence decayed in the range of the measured autofluorescence (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>). However, no FCS data could be analysed due to the low luminescence signals. On the other hand, considerable QD655 luminescence could be recognised in the extracellular surrounding physiological saline, but only in the red detection channel as expected from their emission spectrum (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The luminescence in this channel decayed triexponentially with intensity-weighted average decay times of 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> = 5.8–6.3 ns at the different time points (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a>). These luminescence decay times were shorter than that of free QD655 in pure PBS (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). This could be probably due to the unspecific interaction with extracellular components as well as the limited time resolution of the 2P-FLIM imaging setup compared to the 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> spectroscopic setup. Thus, the applied free QD655 could be not sufficiently incorporated into the duct cells and were mainly accumulated in the cellular surrounding due to sedimentation at the coverslip bottom of the recording chamber. Similar reports on low cellular uptake efficiencies of free, non-functionalised quantum dots have been published previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Analysis of the cellular uptake of free QD655 into living duct cells. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Representative 2P-luminescence intensity images and corresponding 2P-FLIM images of duct cells recorded in the green (BP 514/44) and red (BP 700/75) detection channels at distinct time points. The cells were treated for 120 min with physiological saline containing 5 nm QD655. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Luminescence decay curves extracted from intracellular regions of interest from 2P-FLIM images recorded in the green detection channel. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Luminescence decay curves extracted from extracellular regions of interest from 2P-FLIM images recorded in the red detection channel.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1934" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
