<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characterisation of liposomes and lipodots</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum dots with the emission maximum at 655 nm are ellipsoid shaped, with a Cd/Se core and ZnS shell with a 6 nm (minor axis) and 12 nm (major axis) diameter. QD655 with carboxylic acid surface (negative charged) have a hydrodynamic size of 18 nm in borate solution
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Since it is known that the encapsulation of such quantum dots in cationic, fusogenic liposomes is problematic due to the electrostatic interactions between the negatively charged quantum dots and the positively charged lipids of the liposomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>, we decided to encapsulate the quantum dots in negatively charged liposomes. Moreover, the use of such lipodots should favour their bioimaging applications due to lower cell damage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. For empty DOPC:DOPE-liposomes, DLS measurements resulted in an average hydrodynamic size of 111 ± 1.42 nm (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) with a polydispersity index of 0.08 ± 0.01. This did not significantly change after loading with QD655, leading to a size of 103 ± 2.99 nm (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) with the same polydispersity index of 0.08 ± 0.01. In the case of DOPC:DOPS lipid composition, empty liposomes had a size of 96 ± 0.53 nm (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) with a polydispersity index of 0.07 ± 0.01. DOPC-DOPS-lipodots exhibited a similar size of 97 ± 0.82 nm (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) with a polydispersity index of 0.10 ± 0.02. The zeta potential is an indicator of the stability of nanocarriers. Since it is known, that at pH near 7.0 the phospholipid anchor DOPE introduces a negative charge to the liposomal surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>, both liposome compositions used in this study should possess a negative charge. Zeta potential measurements revealed that the surface potential of empty liposomes was at −5.49 ± 0.12 mV (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) for DOPC:DOPE-liposomes and −17.77 ± 2.05 mV (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) for DOPC:DOPS-liposomes. After loading with quantum dots, the zeta potential strongly decreased to values of −13.20 ± 2.10 mV (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) and −23.53 ± 1.62 mV (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) for DOPC:DOPE-lipodots and DOPC:DOPS-lipodots, respectively. These changes indicated the effective interaction of quantum dots with the liposomes. The obtained values were similar to data reported in the literature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span> and indicated that the used lipodot systems were sufficiently stable
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The absorption and emission spectra are exemplarily shown for DOPC:DOPS-liposomes in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Since empty liposomes scatter light, their absorption spectrum was just a measure of scattered light with higher intensities at shorter wavelengths as known from literature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. Free QD655 displayed the attractive property of a broad absorption that gradually increased toward shorter wavelengths, a very common feature for free quantum dots in aqueous solution
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. In contrast, the absorption spectrum of lipodots was the sum of scatted light from the liposomes and the absorption property of QD655 so that this resulted in a slightly changed absorption spectrum compared to that of free QD655. The luminescence spectrum of lipodots exhibited a symmetric, sharp band with a maximum at 652 nm, very similar to the luminescence spectrum of free QD655. These results suggested that the liposome-encapsulated quantum dots still exhibit a strong luminescence signal without significant quantum dot self-quenching or spectral changes. Moreover, this was a good evidence for the stability of quantum dots within the liposome microenvironment, since blue-shifted emission spectra could indicate quantum dot aggregation or even degradation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spectroscopic properties. Absorption spectrum of empty liposomes (DOPC:DOPS) (dotted line) as well as absorption and normalised luminescence spectra (λ
     <sub>ex</sub> = 480 nm) of free QD655 (dashed line) and DOPC:DOPS-lipodots (100 nm) (solid line) in phosphate buffered saline (pH 7.0).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1436" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
