<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">In vitro</span> measurements of lipodots luminescence decay times and diffusion times
 </div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the luminescence intensity of a fluorophore, its luminescence decay time and translational diffusion time can provide additional information about the fluorophores microenvironment. Compared to organic fluorophores and fluorescent proteins, colloidal quantum dots exhibit in general longer luminescence decay times. Their multiexponential decay behaviour is a common feature of quantum dots, although the origin of such complex behaviour is still not well understood. In the present study, we compared the luminescence decay behaviour of free QD655 and lipodots, both dissolved in PBS (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). As expected, for free QD655 a triexponential fit model provided the best fitting results with an intensity-weighted average decay time of 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> = 29.7 ± 2.31 ns (
  <div id="IEq3" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M17" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\chi }_{R}^{2}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M18" class="math">
     <div class="msubsup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">χ</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Article_IEq3.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> = 2.351). In the case of QD655 encapsulated into DOPC:DOPS-liposomes, the intensity-weighted average decay time of the triexponential fit analysis increased to 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> = 41.4 ± 2.09 ns (
  <div id="IEq4" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M19" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\chi }_{R}^{2}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M20" class="math">
     <div class="msubsup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">χ</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Article_IEq4.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> = 1.512), probably indicating a better stabilisation of the quantum dots within the liposomes. A very similar scenario was observed for QD655 encapsulated into DOPC:DOPE-liposomes yielding 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> = 39.9 ± 2.71 ns (
  <div id="IEq5" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M21" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\chi }_{R}^{2}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M22" class="math">
     <div class="msubsup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">χ</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Article_IEq5.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> = 1.495). Generalov 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. observed a decrease of the QD655 average luminescence decay time upon encapsulation in phospholipid vesicles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, but this was not the case in the present study. This confirmed that the luminescence decay behaviour of quantum dots is strongly dependent on their microenvironment. Nevertheless, their long luminescence decay times allow for straightforward signal separation from background signals such as cellular autofluorescence or scattered light, in comparison to the analysis of quantum dot luminescence intensities.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparative 
     <span class="italic">in vitro</span> characterisation of free QD655 and lipodots in phosphate buffer saline (PBS). (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Representative luminescence decay curves of free QD655 (black lines) and lipodots (red &amp; blue lines) recorded at λ
     <sub>ex</sub> = 371 nm. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Left: normalised luminescence autocorrelation curves of free QD655 (black lines) and lipodots (red &amp; blue lines) together with fits (dashed lines) based on a two-component diffusion model according to Eq. (
     <a rid="Equ4" ref-type="" href="#Equ4">4</a>). Right: corresponding luminescence intensity traces for free QD655 and DOPC:DOPS-lipodots.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46732_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1548" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By using the FCS technique, we analysed intensity fluctuations arising from luminescent particles diffusing through the detection volume yielding their translational diffusion times. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a> shows the normalised autocorrelation curves with their corresponding fitting curves according to Eq. (
  <a rid="Equ4" ref-type="" href="#Equ4">4</a>) as well as selected luminescence intensity traces for free QD655 and lipodots. For freely diffusing QD655, the diffusion times of 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> = 2.34 ± 0.14 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 73%) and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D2</sub> = 0.04 ± 0.01 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 27%) were determined. The diffusion time 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> corresponded to the unhindered diffusion of QD655 and fits very well with data from a previous study reporting 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D</sub> = 2.78 ms for quantum dots in PBS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. In comparison with freely diffusing organic dyes such as fluorescein, rhodamine 6G or Atto655-carboxylic acid with sizes in the range of ~0.5 nm, this diffusion is 55 times slower, because of the larger particle size of quantum dots
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. Based on the obtained diffusion coefficient 
  <span class="italic">D</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 4.5 ± 0.67 µm
  <span class="sup">2</span>/s, the hydrodynamic particle size of QD655 was estimated to 35 nm by using the Stokes-Einstein relation (Eq. (
  <a rid="Equ5" ref-type="" href="#Equ5">5</a>)). The presence of a second diffusion component with the diffusion time 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D2</sub> was not entirely clear. A possible explanation could be the unstable blinking of quantum dots due to the surface charge density, induced by a pH change from pH 9 in borate buffer to pH 7 in PBS as well as the used excitation light intensities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When QD655 was encapsulated into a liposomes, the observed diffusion behaviour corresponded to the lipodot entity and was significantly slower than in the case of freely diffusing QD655 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). Thus, the autocorrelation curve of the DOPC:DOPS-lipodots shifted to longer diffusion times yielding 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> = 11.0 ± 0.99 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 88%) and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D2</sub> = 0.27 ± 0.05 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 12%). Again, a very similar scenario was observed for DOPC:DOPE-lipodots yielding 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> = 11.4 ± 1.71 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 86%) and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D2</sub> = 0.21 ± 0.11 ms (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 14%). The dominant time 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> could be attributed to the diffusion of lipodots and the minor time 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D2</sub> to the diffusion of an unknown component. Using the calculated diffusion coefficient 
  <span class="italic">D</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 1.42 ± 0.22 µm
  <span class="sup">2</span>/s, we found for the lipodots a hydrodynamic particle size of 120 nm, which fits very well with the size determined by DLS recordings (see above). Finally, the comparison of the average count rates obtained from luminescence intensity traces clearly indicated the higher luminescence intensity bursts of lipodots compared to that of free QD655. Camblin 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. have reported similar diffusion time changes for freely diffusing quantum dots and polymersomes-encapsulated quantum dots being 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D</sub> = 4 ms and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D</sub> = 15–17 ms, respectively
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the encapsulation efficiency was not analysed in detail, the complementary luminescence decay time and translational diffusion time recordings allowed for proofing an effective and stable loading of QD655 into both types of liposomes under the applied experimental conditions. First, after the extrusion process during the lipodots preparation procedure quantum dot luminescence could be detected on the membrane filters under UV light. Thus, the quantum dot sticking at the polycarbonate membrane allowed for separation of free QD655 from liposome-encapsulated QD655 as previously reported
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>. Second, the QD655 luminescence decay time increased uniformly in the presence of both types of liposomes (
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>av(int)</sub> ~30 ns 
  <span class="italic">vs</span>. ~40–41 ns) indicating the changed quantum dot microenvironment after encapsulation. Third, the increase in the diffusion time after lipodots preparation (
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>D1</sub> ~2 ms 
  <span class="italic">vs</span>. ~11 ms) indicated the recording of lipodots rather than free QD655. In addition, the very dominant relative fraction of this slow diffusion time (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>1</sub> ~86–88%) also supported the sufficient lipodots separation from free QD655. Thus, both types of lipodots preparations seemed to be feasible for cellular imaging studies.
 </p>
</sec>
