<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material and sample preparation</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The neutral lipids 1,2-dioleoyl-
  <span class="italic">sn</span>-glycero-3-phosphocholine (DOPC), 1,2-dioleoyl-
  <span class="italic">sn</span>-glycero-3-phosphoethanolamine (DOPE) and the anionic lipid 1,2-dioleoyl-
  <span class="italic">sn-</span>glycero-3-phospho-L-serine (DOPS) were purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids (Alabaster, USA). Qdot 655 ITK Carboxyl Quantum Dots (QD655) were obtained from Thermo Fisher Scientific (Darmstadt, Germany). Phosphate buffered saline (PBS) was from Sigma-Aldrich (Steinheim, Germany), chloroform and other chemicals were from Carl Roth (Karlsruhe, Germany).
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lipodots were prepared using a thin film hydration method. DOPC:DOPE and DOPC:DOPS (3:1 molar ratio) were dissolved in chloroform and dried in a glass vial under nitrogen stream followed by removal of residual solvent under vacuum for ~3 h. The final concentration of lipids was 1 mM. Multilamellar vesicles were obtained by hydrating the lipid films using PBS (pH 7.0) supplemented with 10 nM QD655. After 60 min incubation at 25 °C, the suspensions were subjected to 15 freeze-thaw cycles in liquid nitrogen with vortexing after each cycle.</p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To form large unilamellar vesicles, the suspensions were passed 35 times through a mini-extruder (Avanti Polar Lipids, Alabaster, USA) using two-stacked polycarbonate membrane filters with a pore size of 100 nm. The final lipodot preparations were stored in the dark at 4 °C and used for experiments up to 7 days. All 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> experiments were performed in PBS. For the cellular uptake experiments, 100 µL of lipodots in PBS were added to a recording chamber containing the salivary gland tissue in 400 µL physiological saline.
 </p>
</sec>
