<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bravyi–Kitaev Mapping</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Bravyi–Kitaev
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18" href="#ref18">18</a>−
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20" href="#ref20">20</a>
  </span> mapping is an attempt to improve upon the linear scaling of the occupation and parity bases. In essence, it is a middle ground between these approaches. For a molecular orbital basis of size 
  <span class="italic">N</span>, there are again 
  <span class="italic">N</span> qubits used.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30" href="#ref30">30</a>
  </span> However, the information stored within each qubit now varies dependent on the index 
  <span class="italic">i</span>. Note that we begin indexing at 
  <span class="italic">i</span> = 0. Where 
  <span class="italic">i</span> is even, qubit 
  <span class="italic">i</span> stores the occupation number of orbital 
  <span class="italic">i</span>, as in the Jordan–Wigner mapping. Where 
  <span class="italic">i</span> is odd, the qubit stores the parity of a particular set of occupation numbers. When log
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <span class="italic">i</span>+1) is an integer, the qubit stores the parity of the occupation numbers of all orbitals with indices less than or equal to 
  <span class="italic">i</span>. For other cases, the qubit stores the parity of the occupation numbers of orbitals in subdividing binary sets. This complex mapping is best understood through consideration of the matrix which transforms a vector of orbital occupations to qubit states. For example, in the eight orbital/qubit case, this is given by
  <div id="eq6" class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="ct-2018-00450n_0001" id="GRAPHIC-d7e979-autogenerated" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <span class="label">6</span>
  </div>Here, each 
  <span class="italic">o</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> value corresponds to the occupation number of the orbital with index 
  <span class="italic">i</span>, and the 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> values correspond to the state of the qubit with index 
  <span class="italic">i</span>. Where 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> is 0, qubit 
  <span class="italic">i</span> is in the |0⟩ state and similarly where 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> is 1, qubit 
  <span class="italic">i</span> is in the |1⟩ state. All sums are performed in modulo 2. The matrix on the left is thus the matrix which transforms orbital occupation numbers to qubit states.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both occupation and parity information is now stored nonlocally. Inspection of 
  <a rid="eq6" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#eq6">eq 
   <a rid="eq6" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#eq6">6</a>
  </a> shows that this information is stored in a number of qubits which grows logarithmically. Thus, any electronic creation or annihilation operation can be simulated in 
  <div id="d30e586" class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="ct-2018-00450n_m008.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> qubit operations. We omit a detailed proof of this here for reasons of brevity. Further details can be found in refs (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18" href="#ref18">18</a>−
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20" href="#ref20">20</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the superior asymptotic scaling of the Bravyi–Kitaev mapping, it is important to consider the increased overhead of its use. Initial implementations noted that the Bravyi–Kitaev mapping is more efficient than the Jordan–Wigner mapping in the simulation of molecular hydrogen in a minimal basis, the smallest possible nontrivial example.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19" href="#ref19">19</a>
  </span> It was thus argued that the overhead was not a significant factor, and the superior scaling effectively dominated in all cases. However, further investigation on methane in a minimal basis revealed that this is not the case.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20" href="#ref20">20</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One purpose of this paper is to find the point at which this asymptotically superior scaling dominates. Examination of the Bravyi–Kitaev creation and annihilation operators permits a rough estimate of this. Note that the qubit creation and annihilation operator equivalents using the Bravyi–Kitaev transformation are given by
  <div id="eq7" class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="ct-2018-00450n_m009" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <span class="label">7</span>
  </div>
  <div id="eq8" class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="ct-2018-00450n_m010" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <span class="label">8</span>
  </div>where 
  <span class="italic">U</span>(
  <span class="italic">i</span>) is the “update set” of qubit 
  <span class="italic">i</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">P</span>(
  <span class="italic">i</span>) is the “parity set” of qubit 
  <span class="italic">i</span>. For brevity we do not discuss these sets here; however, their size is of maximum order 
  <div id="d30e632" class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="ct-2018-00450n_m011.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>. These expressions are valid only in the case of even 
  <span class="italic">i</span>. However, this does not affect our rough estimate. Examining these equations, it is evident that at most 4log
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="italic">i</span> + 2 gates are required for the simulation of one Fermionic operation. This quantity is smaller than the simple 
  <span class="italic">i</span> gates of the Jordan–Wigner mapping when 
  <span class="italic">i</span> ≥ 19. Thus, noting that the Bravyi–Kitaev mapping is most efficient when 
  <span class="italic">N</span> approaches a power of 2 (as it can take increased advantage of its binary tree structure), we conservatively estimate that this point should be at 
  <span class="italic">N</span> ≈ 32. We thus would expect quantum computational cost to be reduced when using the Bravyi–Kitaev transformation for systems with more than 
  <span class="italic">N</span> ≈ 32 spin–orbitals.
 </p>
</sec>
