<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-nanomaterials-09-00929" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The understanding of light-matter interaction at a nanoscale has been developed rapidly in recent years. Various models [
  <a rid="B1-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-nanomaterials-09-00929">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-nanomaterials-09-00929">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-nanomaterials-09-00929">3</a>] have been proposed to understand and optimize several applications such as Surface Enhanced Raman Scattering (SERS) [
  <a rid="B4-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-nanomaterials-09-00929">4</a>], photo-emission [
  <a rid="B5-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-nanomaterials-09-00929">5</a>], fluorescence [
  <a rid="B6-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-nanomaterials-09-00929">6</a>], Nanoparticle Enhanced Laser Induced Breakdown Spectroscopy (NELIBS) [
  <a rid="B7-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-nanomaterials-09-00929">7</a>], and more. It is well known that, when an incident radiation illuminates a metal nanoparticle (NP), it induces polarization of the NPs conduction electrons and, if the radiation frequency is in resonance with the plasmonic frequency of the particle itself, a strong electromagnetic field is induced on the border of the NPs [
  <a rid="B8-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-nanomaterials-09-00929">8</a>]. If the radiation with adequate frequency interacts with a set of NPs placed at a distance, which is smaller than the diameter of the NP, a strong field enhancement is generated in the gap between the NPs, i.e., the so-called “hot spot” [
  <a rid="B9-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-nanomaterials-09-00929">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-nanomaterials-09-00929">10</a>]. In this case, an effective variation of the Coulomb restoring force that exists between the positive metallic lattice of the NPs and the oscillating electrons occurs because of the interaction of adjacent NPs dipoles. This results in a notable change of the system’s resonance energy. Several experiments and models have been performed in order to quantify this phenomenon and, thus, determine the resonance wavelength of the NPs system [
  <a rid="B11-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nanomaterials-09-00929">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nanomaterials-09-00929">12</a>]. Although various compositions of multi-NPs have been investigated [
  <a rid="B13-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-nanomaterials-09-00929">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nanomaterials-09-00929">14</a>], due to the mathematical approach complexity and the difficult experimental realization of the controlled structure at the nanoscale level, most studies have focused on the dimeric system of NPs. In this frame, the nature and the dependence on the particle size, as well as on interparticle distances, in the dimeric system, has been largely investigated and numerous articles have been published [
  <a rid="B11-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nanomaterials-09-00929">11</a>,
  <a rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nanomaterials-09-00929">15</a>] outlining a full description of NPs dimer both from theoretical and experimental point of views. The classical approach for studying plasmon effects is based on the determination of the permittivity function. This is done by modeling the optical properties of the metals using different multi-parameter methods. Even though this classical approach is very useful, it becomes less sufficiently accurate and extremely time consuming when applied in investigating a complex system of NPs. On the other hand, NP interactions can be studied in analogy with atom interactions during the formation of molecules [
  <a rid="B16-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-nanomaterials-09-00929">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-nanomaterials-09-00929">17</a>]. In this frame, an individual NP can be described with a wavefunction and their interaction can be studied in the same way as the interaction of atomic orbitals in the Hückel theory. Good examples are the case of π-bonding in the dienic system and the molecular orbital interactions between ligands and metal in coordination chemistry. This second approach enables us to apply the methodologies used to determine molecular bonding and the energy changes during the atomic orbitals interaction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we propose a quantum mechanics approach, called the Hückel’s Variational Method (VM) [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00929">18</a>], inspired by the analogy between NP systems and the molecular orbital theory, which was initially proposed by Nordlander at al. in the hybridization model [
  <a rid="B16-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-nanomaterials-09-00929">16</a>,
  <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00929">19</a>], for a rapid and simple estimation of energy and the resonance wavelength in the NPs chain and cluster systems. This approach requires input data that has been already reported in literature i.e., the energy shift of simple systems such as dimers or single NPs on the surface [
  <a rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nanomaterials-09-00929">15</a>,
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00929">20</a>]. They enable us to obtain information on more complex NPs systems without having to resort to time consuming calculations. Apart from self-consistent methodologies [
  <a rid="B11-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nanomaterials-09-00929">11</a>] for multiple metal NPs where the random phase approximation in the secular determinants is also used to estimate the surface plasmon resonant energies that, in turn, depend on the nanoparticle spacing, this approach requires the energy shift of simple systems as initial input data, such as dimers and single NPs on the surface that has already been reported in literature [
  <a rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nanomaterials-09-00929">15</a>,
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00929">20</a>]. These input data of the energy, which contains the dependence on the nanoparticle distance and surrounding medium, enable us to obtain information on more complex NPs systems without having to resort to time-consuming calculations. Beyond the practical result, i.e., the determination of the resonance energy shift, the investigation of NPs system with the VM provides an insight of the analogies and differences between NPs plasmon and the π-molecular orbital.
 </p>
</sec>
