<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-nanomaterials-09-00929" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. NPs Chain Systems</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Let us consider the case of a chain of AuNPs and one of AgNPs, where the plasmon energy ω
  <sub>0</sub> and the dimer shift Δω
  <sub>dim</sub> are ω
  <sub>0</sub> = 2.375 eV, β = −0.28 eV and ω
  <sub>0</sub> = 3.10 eV and β = −0.52 eV, respectively, for AuNPs of 40 nm and AgNPs of 50 nm [
  <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00929">22</a>]. Results of the VM are reported in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f002" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f002">Figure 2</a>, which shows an increase of the wavelength as a function of the number of NPs in the chain, which, in turn, results in the red-shift of the resonance wavelength of the lowest energy mode, obtained with the solution of the secular determinant of Equation (5).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As expected, the wavelength of the longitudinal modes shifts to higher values as the number of NPs in the system increases. This moves toward a plateau for n → ∞. Although, with the present model, we are not investigating the behavior of the Hot Spot [
  <a rid="B31-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-nanomaterials-09-00929">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-nanomaterials-09-00929">32</a>] generated in the NPs system. However, it is possible to estimate just the number of Hot Spots assuming they are equal to the number of coherent interactions between adjacent NPs. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each mode, the number of available coherent dipole interactions, i.e., potential hot spots, is m = n–k, where n is the number of NPs constituting the system and k is the mode number, assuming k = 1 for the lowest energy mode. This observation makes it clear that the maximum number of available coherent dipole interactions is obtained for the mode with the lowest energy. This mode represents the dipole configuration, which allows the maximum electromagnetic field enhancement. On the contrary, the number of sites where the dipole assumes the opposite orientation corresponds to the number N of nodes of the wavefunction representing the specific mode, so that N = n − 1 − m = k − 1. Consequently, in order to polarize a given mode, it is necessary that the number of constructive interactions between the dipoles is greater than the number of dipoles with a destructive interaction. This means that the number of coherent dipole interactions has to be greater than the number of nodes, m &gt; N (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f001">Figure 1</a>). This observation suggests that, in a bright mode m &gt; N, consequently, ω &lt; ω
  <sub>0,</sub> and the corresponding wavefunction represents a system with a net total dipole. On the contrary, when m &lt; N, then ω &gt; ω
  <sub>0</sub>, and the wavefunction describes a system where no effective dipole exists, which is a dark mode [
  <a rid="B33-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-nanomaterials-09-00929">33</a>]. In the case of the dark mode, the total wavefunction presents more nodes than coherent interactions and, therefore, in agreement with the general knowledge, they cannot be excited.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering the broadening of each state due to the quantum limit of the investigated system [
  <a rid="B34-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-nanomaterials-09-00929">34</a>], it should be expected that all these states merge together in a wide band. Consequently, the system of NPs can be suitably polarized along a broad range of incident electromagnetic field frequencies generating a band of resonance including all the bright modes within the limits of possible configurations, which the dipoles in the chain can assume. Since the VM does not allow taking into account the broadening of the energy levels resulting from the quantum limits and a detailed investigation on the broadening would be required [
  <a rid="B35-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-nanomaterials-09-00929">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-nanomaterials-09-00929">36</a>], with the only aim to show how the broadening of the states may form a band of resonance, in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f003" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f003">Figure 3</a>, we also report the convolution of the modes, assuming a Gaussian shape with a broadening (FWHM, Full Width at Half Maximum) of 80 nm in agreement with the broadening of the SPR (Surface Plasmon Resonance) of the single AuNPs of 40 nm [
  <a rid="B34-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-nanomaterials-09-00929">34</a>]. Even though, this is an arbitrary condition for a chain system and it underestimates the real broadening, it gives an idea of the correlation between the states of the system and the peculiarities of the band of resonance generally observed in the experimental applications.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This phenomenon underlines the most important feature of the NPs systems: the possibility to adapt the configuration of their dipoles to the incident electromagnetic radiation, which allows a sort of cooperation in reaching resonance with the incoming perturbation. Clearly, this effect is not achievable with more rigid systems, e.g., the atomic ones, where resonance occurs only at a specific frequency. This flexibility of the NPs systems in reaching resonance with the perturbation occurs as an effect of a system that borders strongly quantized systems such as atoms and macroscopic (i.e., not quantized) systems such as particles.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is interesting to compare the results of the VM with other results based on different approaches reported in literature, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f004" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f004">Figure 4</a>. In this case, we compare the lowest energy mode obtained with VM with different properties reported in literature and related to the resonance energy of the plasmonic system. Observation of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f004" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f004">Figure 4</a> indicates an impressively high level of agreement of the results of VM with those obtained with Electrodynamic Simulation, S, [
  <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00929">22</a>] and Finit Integration Technique, FIT, [
  <a rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-nanomaterials-09-00929">26</a>], as well as with experimental results, E, [
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00929">24</a>]. The values of ω
  <sub>0</sub> and β used for comparisons of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f004" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f004">Figure 4</a> are ω
  <sub>0</sub> = 2.34 eV, β = −0.57 eV for the comparison with experimental results (EM), ω
  <sub>0</sub> = 2.36 eV, β = −0.33 eV for the comparison with Electrodynamics simulation (MS) and ω
  <sub>0</sub> = 2.37 eV, β = −0.27 eV for the comparison with the Finit Integration Technique (MFIT). The agreement of the proposed method with literature data shows the similarity of the plasmonic characteristics of NPs system with a conjugated dienic system, where this theoretical approach is considered one of the most accurate ways to determine the energy of π-bonding. 
 </p>
</sec>
