<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-nanomaterials-09-00929" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. NPs Cluster Systems</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the most attracting results that can be obtained with the VM is the determination of resonance energy of a more complex system than a dimmer and, as mentioned in the introduction, the VM allows us to study the interaction between NPs in a different geometrical configuration. As an example, let us consider the heptamer in three geometries: linear chain, ring chain, and cluster. The energy diagram obtained for these systems is reported in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f005" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f005">Figure 5</a>. Same as in the previous section, we considered a system of Au-NPs with ω
  <sub>0</sub> = 2.375 eV and β = −0.28 eV. We can note that the linear chain and ring chain had a similar energy shift, 1.86 eV and 1.88 eV, respectively. However, while in the linear chain, there was no degeneracy of the modes, the ring chain presented a degeneracy equal to 2 of all the modes except the one with the higher energy with k = 7. This effect was due to the geometrical symmetry of the ring system. When comparing the chain systems with the heptamer cluster, a further redshift was observed as a result of the strong coupling with the NP placed in the center in the heptamer cluster. It interacts with all the surrounding NPs, which increases the number of coherent interactions. The latter observation introduces a general feature of 2D systems, which is an increase of the number of bright modes with respect to the dark modes. In this frame, the heptamer shows a general condition where the NPs packing (i.e., the ratio between NP diameter and interparticle mean distances) is optimized, which allows the central NP to have a full interaction with several other units, since it will be discussed below in the section about the 2D lattice of NPs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a second case, we investigated the effect of ordered 2D NPs clusters. It was necessary to take into account that there were different types of interaction between adjacent NPs and particles placed on the diagonal direction. Therefore, for the latter ones, we used a different value of the interaction integral, which is β′ = β/√2, according to geometric considerations (see supporting information). As a result of the dipole’s interaction, a new energy diagram was obtained and is reported in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f006" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f006">Figure 6</a>A. The figure shows that the energy of bright modes decreases with the increasing of NPs in the reticular cluster and that the number of bright modes is always greater than the one of dark modes. As mentioned above, this is due to the increasing number of coherent dipole interactions. For this reason, and because the total energy of the levels must be conserved, the dark modes notably increase their energy. Once again, for ω &lt; ω
  <sub>0</sub>, the energy stabilization and, in turn, the wavelength increasing is dependent on the number of interactions that every NP is able to perform.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ordered reticular system of NPs does not represent the best situation since the packing factor can be improved by decreasing the average distances between the NPs. This effect is demonstrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f006" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f006">Figure 6</a>B where the energy diagram of the 2D lattice is reported. The figure clearly shows a further decrease of the energy of about 0.1 eV corresponding in a wavelength red-shift of about 40 nm when the chain composing the 2D-lattice is shifted with respect to the adjacent chains in order to optimize the packing of the NPs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <a rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-t002" ref-type="table" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-t002">Table 2</a>, for a fast comparison of resonance energy of different cluster geometries, the energy and the corresponding wavelength of the lowest energy mode (k = 1), that, as mentioned above, corresponds to the main peak of the resonance band, is reported at ω
  <sub>0</sub> = 2.375 eV, β = −0.28 eV.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lastly, in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00929-f007" href="#nanomaterials-09-00929-f007">Figure 7</a>, we compared the case of triangular, square, and heptamer cluster with some results published in Reference [
  <a rid="B37-nanomaterials-09-00929" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-nanomaterials-09-00929">37</a>]. For all the examined structures, there is good agreement of the resonance wavelength obtained with Generalized Mie Theory (GMT) and the wavelength corresponding to the lowest energy mode, as calculated applying the VM.
 </p>
</sec>
