<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec6-nanomaterials-09-00929" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the most important advantage of the proposed method is the rapid response and ease of application to all kinds of chain and cluster NPs systems, if the basic interactions of the elements of the system are known. This means that this approach is unable to determine the dependence of the energy shift due to the interparticle distance and particle size. However, it enables us to estimate how a given interaction changes as a result of an increasing number of conjugated NPs. This is possible without having to resort to a time-consuming calculation routine. As a consequence of a higher number of dipoles involved constructively in the state with lower energy, the corresponding wavelength represents the wavelength of the peak of the system’s resonance band. On the contrary, the whole band, with this quantum chemistry approach, is the result of the convolution of all the set of modes that are obtained by solving the secular determinant. The latter observation suggests that the incident electromagnetic radiation can polarize the NPs dipoles in a wide range of wavelengths.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lastly, the aim of the application of this methodology is to support, by means of a rapid overview of the resonance wavelength characteristics of the system, the realization of more complex models as well as of experiments at nanoscale. Moreover, the present approach allows us to investigate the effect of the geometrical distribution of the NPs system, as well as the effect of substrates in an immediate way and this can be useful for selecting the laser source in laser-based analytical techniques as well as for selecting optimal substrates for the analysis. Although, in the present study, we focused our efforts on introducing a new model for interpreting the plasmon resonance in complex NPs system. In a future work, the use of the obtained wavefunctions will be investigated for estimating other properties of the plasmonic resonance from a more applicative point of view.</p>
</sec>
