<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An obvious metric for evaluating the performance of any simulation algorithm can be simply described as some accuracy measure vs. some cost measure. While the accuracy measure in a simulation is often easy to define, the cost measure is more nuanced. For variational quantum simulations, there are two factors which largely determine the overall cost: circuit depth and number of measurements (or shot count). Shot count is important as it determines the time to solution. It is possible that due to the sheer number of measurements, a particular quantum simulation becomes intractable. However, for NISQ devices in which coherence times (and thus number of gates) are limited, circuit depth is usually the most critical cost metric, as it determines whether or not a simulation can occur at all. By taking circuit depth as the most important cost metric to address, the original VQE has been successful by minimizing circuit depth at the cost of increased number of measurements. Similar to the original VQE, our new ADAPT-VQE algorithm seeks to further minimize the circuit depth with an increased number of measurements.</p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this direction, the data clearly demonstrates that ADAPT-VQE succeeds in creating a more compact and accurate wavefunction ansatz than UCCSD. The algorithm achieves this by systematically identifying the optimal set and ordering of operators to use in the wavefunction ansatz for a given problem. The efficiency of ADAPT-VQE makes it very promising for quantum chemistry simulations on NISQ devices, where circuit depth limitations remain a significant challenge.</p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of shot-count, ADAPT-VQE will likely have an increased number of measurements compared to UCCSD-based VQE due to the necessary gradient measurements. However, this is perhaps an easier problem to address (compared to circuit depth) as the individual runs can in principle occur simultaneously if several devices exist. Further, the shot count also depends on the number of iterations required for the classical optimization of the ansatz parameters. For strongly correlated systems where perturbation theory fails, the existing approach of using classical MP2 amplitudes to initialize the UCCSD parameters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> is not likely to provide much improvement in the UCCSD-based VQE. Alternatively, each iteration of ADAPT-VQE only adds a single new parameter, with the previously optimized parameters already being initialized to rather sensible values. This might ultimately decrease the number of iterations needed for the VQE subroutine in ADAPT-VQE, thus decreasing the shot count (although this is not likely to fully compensate for the large number of measurements for the gradient). As hardware capabilities continue to increase, in terms of both the size and number of quantum processors available, ADAPT-VQE will offer an ideal quantum-parallel approach to performing nontrivial quantum chemistry simulations. We therefore expect this algorithm to have a strong impact on these efforts in the near term.
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the name suggests, ADAPT-VQE could be classified as one member of a family of adaptive-basis strategies that has seen success in constructing compact many-electron wavefunctions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> and single-electron wavefunctions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>, or as a relative of methods using sequential transformations which have been explored in the context of multireference coupled-cluster theory
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. Of these, the ADAPT ansatz is perhaps most closely related to the @-CC method of Lyakh and Bartlett
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>, in which a compact set of cluster operators is iteratively determined to describe the state of interest on a classical computer. Our approach is distinct in that it is not only designed for a quantum computer implementation, but also defined for a different wavefunction form (product of unitary operators vs. coupled cluster) and a different importance metric (operator gradient of the many-electron state vs. a single electron-defined importance function, see ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>) for determining new parameters.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important aspect of ADAPT-VQE is that several steps of the algorithm can be implemented in multiple ways, lending it still greater versatility across a wide landscape of problems and suggesting that it should perhaps be thought of as a class of algorithms rather than a specific one. In the “Results” section, we already discussed a few algorithmic options, including different ways to perform the gradient-based parameter update and to determine convergence. We also mentioned the possibility of freezing early parameters at later stages of the algorithm in order to speed up the re-optimization steps. Below, we discuss a few more modifications to explore.</p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the ADAPT-VQE algorithm is notably not a perturbative approach, it still has a perturbative flavor in that the suitability of the next iteration’s best operator only involves the interaction of that operator with the Hamiltonian. As such, the algorithm may not be able to recognize the best quadruple excitation (for example) during one update. That being said, the physics described by quadruple excitations is ultimately captured after multiple iterations through the product of at least two two-body interactions. The consequence of this is that convergence will likely not be as fast for strongly correlated systems because the algorithm can only “see” two body operators at a time. Because only local knowledge of the FCI energy landscape is used to update the ADAPT-VQE ansatz construction, the “true optimally compact ansatz” is not guaranteed. As a result, flat energy landscapes (associated with “false gradient troughs”) are possible. Further classical simulations and device implementations are needed to provide better insight into the numerical behavior.</p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fortunately, however, multiple strategies can be pursued to address any possible slow convergence issues. One possible approach would be to add a selection of three- or four-body interactions into the operator pool, such that these could be inserted when needed. Alternatively, one might imagine trying to update the ansatz with two (or more) operators in each iteration, such that the best set of operators is added. The operator pool would still consist of only one- and two-body interactions, but higher-body interactions could be incorporated through products of operators. Even further, one might imagine computing the second derivative and using Hessian matrix elements to identify cooperative effects between operators in the pool. We will explore each of these approaches in future work, with the aim of determining the fastest converging algorithm in different chemical scenarios.</p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we presented ADAPT-VQE, a novel variational hybrid quantum-classical algorithm designed to achieve exact results at convergence. Unlike typical ansätze, which tends to be ad hoc, our approach is based on an ansatz that is determined by the system being simulated, and it features a well-defined, built-in convergence criterion. Moreover, the parameter count, and thus the gate depth, is kept to a minimum. A detailed description of the algorithm is given, and numerical examples are provided to demonstrate the performance of the ADAPT method with both weakly and strongly correlated systems. Based on these results, we find the ADAPT-VQE algorithm to be an operator- and parameter-efficient method capable of high accuracy, with controllable errors, that routinely outperforms UCCSD. Its compatibility with classical routines for compiling state preparation circuits and quantum-parallelism should make ADAPT-VQE extremely useful for simulations of molecules on both currently available and future quantum computers.</p>
</sec>
