<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jcc25364-sec-0014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis and molecular property</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RAQET can perform several analyses and evaluations of molecular properties such as the populations, electric, and magnetic properties in the WFT framework. The Mulliken population analyses are available to obtain charges at the NR and SF levels. In addition, atomic spin vectors can be evaluated in GHF based on the Mulliken‐type atomic division at the NR, SF, and SD levels. For the electric properties, first‐ and second‐order analytical derivatives of the electronic energy with respect to the electric field were implemented to evaluate the electric dipole moment and static polarizability, which are formulated based on both the NR and IODKH/NR Hamiltonians at the SF and SD levels. For the magnetic properties, the first‐ and second‐order analytical derivatives with respect to the external magnetic field and/or the nuclear magnetic moment were implemented to evaluate the magnetic dipole moment and the nuclear magnetic shielding constant. These schemes are constructed in the IODKH/NR schemes at the SD level as well as the NR one. To perform gauge‐origin independent calculations in the NR framework, RAQET employs the gauge‐including/independent atomic orbital (GIAO).
  <a rid="jcc25364-bib-0154" ref-type="ref" href="#jcc25364-bib-0154">154</a>, 
  <a rid="jcc25364-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#jcc25364-bib-0155">155</a> In the 2c relativistic framework, RAQET employs the gauge factorization before unitary transformation (GF‐UT) formulation, which has been derived for gauge‐origin independent calculations by introducing the gauge factor and 2c unitary transformation into the molecular orbitals.
  <a rid="jcc25364-bib-0156" ref-type="ref" href="#jcc25364-bib-0156">156</a> The SD relativistic effect, which can include the spin‐dipolar and the Fermi‐contact contributions, is essential for molecules containing heavy elements,
  <a rid="jcc25364-bib-0157" ref-type="ref" href="#jcc25364-bib-0157">157</a> particularly for calculation of the nuclear magnetic shielding constant. The second‐order properties with respect to both the electric and magnetic fields require analytical derivatives of the density matrices. RAQET utilizes the coupled perturbed HF framework based on RHF, UHF, and GHF, which is solved by an iterative procedure.
  <a rid="jcc25364-bib-0158" ref-type="ref" href="#jcc25364-bib-0158">158</a>, 
  <a rid="jcc25364-bib-0159" ref-type="ref" href="#jcc25364-bib-0159">159</a>
 </p>
</sec>
