<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jcc25364-sec-0022" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary and Future Development</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The RAQET program has been developed for QC calculations of systems containing heavy elements based on the 2c relativistic framework. In this article, we have introduced the main features of RAQET in terms of the 2c relativistic Hamiltonian, WFT, DFT, core potential method, two‐electron integral techniques, molecular properties, initial guesses, SCF convergence techniques, GUI, and hybrid parallelization. Several techniques were customized to allow efficient calculations for heavy elements and the relativistic formulations including the SF and SD Hamiltonians. Higher‐order electron correlation calculations provided from the tensor contraction engine with the DC technique are also available in the relativistic framework. RAQET has been registered in MateriApps,
  <a rid="jcc25364-bib-0172" ref-type="ref" href="#jcc25364-bib-0172">172</a> which is Japanese portal site of materials science simulation for computational materials science researchers, theoreticians, experimentalists, and computer scientists. Furthermore, RAQET is partially open to the public. We hope that RAQET will become a useful tool to push the frontiers of the element strategy.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We hope to make RAQET a more sophisticated package by adding extensions designed in the 2c relativistic framework. For the full SD treatment of energy and higher‐order electron correlation calculations, the SD formulation of two‐electron interactions will be implemented. In addition to the grand state calculation, excited state calculation schemes in both WFT and DFT are under development. For analyses of thermodynamics and reactions, we can use frequency calculations, transition‐state optimizations, and reaction path searches. The solvent effect will be also required for accurate analysis and prediction. For the further high‐performance computation, especially on supercomputer systems, massive‐parallelization will be adopted.</p>
</sec>
