<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6704071</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">48380</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-48380-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Width dependence of the 0.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;(2e<sup>2</sup>/h) conductance plateau in InAs quantum point contacts in presence of lateral spin-orbit coupling</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Partha Pratim</given-names></name><address><email>daspm@nitk.edu.in</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cahay</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name><address><email>marc.cahay@uc.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalita</surname><given-names>Shashikala</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2520-4371</contrib-id><name><surname>Mal</surname><given-names>Sib Sankar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5827-6016</contrib-id><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>Alok Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9398 3798</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444525.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Physics, </institution><institution>National Institute of Technology Karnataka, </institution></institution-wrap>Surathkal, 575025 India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2179 9593</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.24827.3b</institution-id><institution>Spintronics and Vacuum Nanoelectronics Laboratory, </institution><institution>University of Cincinnati, </institution></institution-wrap>Cincinnati, Ohio 45040 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9058 9832</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.45982.32</institution-id><institution>Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering, </institution><institution>Tezpur University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tezpur, Assam 784028 India </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9398 3798</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444525.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry, </institution><institution>National Institute of Technology Karnataka, </institution></institution-wrap>Surathkal, 575025 India </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2110 1386</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.258806.1</institution-id><institution>Department of Materials Science and Engineering, </institution><institution>Kyushu Institute of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Tobata-ku, Kitakyushu 804-8550 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>12172</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The evolution of the 0.5G<sub>o</sub> (G<sub>o</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2e<sup>2</sup>/h) conductance plateau and the accompanying hysteresis loop in a series of asymmetrically biased InAs based quantum point contacts (QPCs) in the presence of lateral spin-orbit coupling (LSOC) is studied using a number of QPCs with varying lithographic channel width but fixed channel length. It is found that the size of the hysteresis loops is larger for QPCs of smaller aspect ratio (QPC channel width/length) and gradually disappears as their aspect ratio increases. The physical mechanisms responsible for a decrease in size of the hysteresis loops for QPCs with increasing aspect ratio are: (1) multimode transport in QPCs with larger channel width leading to spin-flip scattering events due to both remote impurities in the doping layer of the heterostructure and surface roughness and impurity (dangling bond) scattering on the sidewalls of the narrow portion of the QPC, and (2) an increase in carrier density resulting in a screening of the electron-electron interactions in the QPC channel. Both effects lead to a progressive disappearance of the net spin polarization in the QPC channel and an accompanying reduction in the size of the hysteresis loops as the lithographic width of the QPC channel increases.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Engineering</kwd><kwd>Nanoscience and technology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Science and Engineering Research Board, Department of Science and Technology, Government of India, grant award EMR/2016/000808</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Exploring viable route and device architecture to create, manipulate and detect spin-polarized current through <italic>all-electric means</italic> has received considerable attention over the last decade<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Spin-orbit coupling (SOC) offers numerous interesting ways in this direction in variety of device architectures made from two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Among others quantum point contacts (QPCs) have shown promising applications for spin based devices<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">For more than two decades, conductance anomalies have been observed experimentally in QPCs at non-integer multiples of <italic>G</italic><sub>0</sub> (=<italic>2e</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>/h</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Thomas <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> suggested that the 0.7<italic>G</italic><sub>0</sub> conductance anomaly may be due to a spontaneous ferromagnetic spin polarization in the QPC constriction. Theoretical explanations for the conductance anomalies include the onset of spontaneous spin polarization in the narrow portion of the QPC as a result of the exchange-correlation interaction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>, the presence of quasi-bound states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> being formed in the QPC constriction, and the Kondo effect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, among others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Crook <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> observed a 0.5G<sub>o</sub> conductance plateau in a symmetric GaAs QPC with symmetrically biased top split-gates, which they also attributed to the onset of spontaneous spin-polarization. The plateau was found to be more pronounced when the QPC potential energy landscape was made <italic>symmetric</italic> with the proximity of a low-temperature scanning probe. Over the last few years, spin polarization in a QPC channel and the accompanying 0.5G<sub>o</sub> conductance plateau have been reported by several groups when an <italic>asymmetric bias</italic> is applied between the top or in-plane side-gates (SGs) of a QPC. The 0.5G<sub>o</sub> conductance plateau has been found in QPCs made of different materials (GaAs and InAs) with 2DEG of different electron mobility, and with a wide variety of heterostructure design (including suspended QPCs) and QPC dimensions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Specifically, over the last decade, we have experimentally observed (in both InAs and GaAs 2DEG based QPCs) conductance plateaus around 0.5G<sub>0</sub> by tuning the electrostatic confining potential of the QPC constriction using an asymmetric bias on its side-gates (SGs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. We argued that onset of such a conductance anomaly constitutes indirect evidence of the creation of spontaneous spin-polarized current in the narrow portion of the QPCs. It was shown that lateral spin-orbit coupling (LSOC), due to the lateral in-plane electric field of the confining potential of the QPCs with in-plane SGs, is an efficient way to generate a strongly spin-polarized current by <italic>purely electrical means</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Furthermore, we used Non-Equilibrium Green&#x02019;s Function (NEGF) analysis to model both InAs and GaAs QPCs with SGs in the presence of LSOC. Assuming a parabolic dispersion relation for the conduction band in the InAs QPC channel, the following three conditions were found to be <italic>sufficient</italic> to create a strong spin polarization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>: (1) an asymmetric lateral confinement in the narrow portion of the QPC, (2) a LSOC due to the lateral confining potential of the QPC and (3) a strong electron-electron (e-e) interaction. More importantly, NEGF simulations suggest that a very strong SOC is not paramount for achieving a strong spin polarization. In fact, we have observed 0.5G<sub>0</sub> conductance plateaus in both GaAs and InAs QPCs with very different LSOC strength<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">The effects of LSOC in a one-dimensional asymmetrically biased quantum wire were studied by Karlsson <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> using a Hartree&#x02013;Fock method. They showed that spin polarization can be generated by LSOC in the presence of a non-zero source-to-drain bias. The latter was shown to be due to either numerical noise mimicking the effects of a random magnetic field generated by the metallic contacts to the device or due to a random background magnetic field such as the earth magnetic field. Karlsson <italic>et al</italic>. showed that electrons spontaneously form spin texture in the quantum wire with an associated finite spin polarization as a result of e-e interaction. They also found that the spin polarization direction is random at zero source-drain bias and that LSOC influences the spin rows orientation only when a non-zero source-to-drain bias is applied across the quantum wire.</p><p id="Par7">Recently, Chuang <italic>et al</italic>. achieved near 100% spin injection and detection in an all-electric AlGaAs/GaAs spin valve made of asymmetrically biased QPCs with top gates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Chuang <italic>et al</italic>. argued that the asymmetry in LSOC in their devices is ultimately responsible for the efficient spin injection and detection. Very recently, Zhdanov <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> and Pokabov <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> performed conductance measurements on unsuspended and suspended GaAs QPCs with in-plane SGs and the 0.5G<sub>o</sub> conductance plateau was only observed for the latter. They argued that in their suspended QPCs spin transport mechanism was also governed by LSOC and that the onset of 0.5G<sub>o</sub> plateau in asymmetrically biased QPCs is due to enhanced e-e interaction, when the QPCs were suspended. These observations further support the argument that it is the strong e-e interaction which is instrumental for the appearance of 0.5G<sub>o</sub> plateau. These reports further suggest that the onset of half-integer conductance plateau can be treated as indirect evidence of spin-polarization in QPC constrictions.</p><p id="Par8">To date, only a few groups have reported theoretical and experimental investigations of the presence of hysteresis in electrical characteristics of QPCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Shailos <italic>et al</italic>. studied conventional QPC devices with an additional gate whose purpose was to modify the electron density on one side of the device and break the QPC symmetry in a controlled manner<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. As the bias on this additional finger gate was varied, reproducible conductance anomalies below the normal conductance plateau G<sub>o</sub> were found. In addition, alterations to the normal conductance plateaus were also observed. Furthermore, hysteresis was observed in the conductance characteristics while varying the split-gate voltage in opposite directions. Starting with a density functional theory, Ihnatenska and Zozoulenko calculated the conductance of a typical QPC in the presence of a symmetric potential applied to its split-gates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The latter is responsible for lifting the spin degeneracy of the conductance channels and a broad conductance plateau near 0.5G<sub>0</sub>. Their calculations also predict the onset of hysteresis in the conductance curves when forward and reverse sweeps are applied to the QPC split-gates &#x02013; a feature attributed to the presence of quasi bound states in the narrow portion of the QPC. Finally, hysteresis in the conductance characteristics of QPCs can be generated by surface acoustic wave, as recently shown by Song <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. The surface acoustic wave is responsible for a modification of surface state distribution on the QPC sidewalls which is ultimately responsible for the observed hysteresis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">In the past, we observed hysteresis when sweeping the common mode bias, V<sub>G</sub>, applied to the two in-plane SGs of asymmetrically biased GaAs QPC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> in both directions. The hysteresis loops were found to be larger when the amount of bias asymmetry &#x00394;<italic>V</italic><sub>G</sub> between the SGs was increased and to be dependent on the &#x00394;<italic>V</italic><sub>G</sub> polarity. These results are in agreement with NEGF simulations which show that the conductance plots versus common gate voltage applied to a QPC SGs reveal the presence of single or multiple hysteresis loops when varying the QPC dimensions and biasing conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. The following features were predicted by NEGF simulations: (a) hysteresis in the conductance plots is present only for sufficiently long QPCs and the e-e interaction in the channel must be strong enough; (b) The size of the hysteresis loops depends both on the polarity and magnitude of the asymmetric bias between the side gates, &#x00394;<italic>V</italic><sub>G</sub>, and also on the magnitude of the e-e interaction; (c) The hysteresis loops are sensitive to the presence of dangling bonds on the QPC sidewalls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. We also used NEGF simulations to illustrate how to fine tune the location of the 0.5 G<sub>0</sub> and the onset of hysteresis loops in four-gate QPCs when LSOC is present in the channel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. The rich plethora and sensitivity of the hysteresis loops is a fingerprint of the wide variety of metastable spin textures accompanying the onset of a net spin polarization and the appearance of conductance anomalies in the QPC constriction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. The observation of hysteresis loops is yet another indirect evidence for the onset of spontaneous spin polarization in the QPC constriction. Previously, we have shown that the observed hysteresis loops depend on the sweep rate of the common mode potential applied to the QPC SGs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">In a recent study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> using InAs QPCs with identical lithographic width but longer channel length, we found that there is approximately a fourfold increase in the range of common sweep voltage over which the 0.5G<sub>0</sub> conductance plateau is observed when the QPC aspect ratio (ratio of lithographic length over lithographic width of the narrow portion of the structure) increases by a factor of 3. NEGF simulations indicate that the observation of 0.5G<sub>0</sub> conductance plateau over a larger range of common sweep voltage is due to an increased importance of the effects of e-e interactions in QPC devices with larger aspect ratio (longer length for fixed width)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par11">In this work, we perform a systematic study on how the size of the hysteresis loops observed in the conductance measurements during forward and reverse sweeps evolves in a number of asymmetrically biased side-gated InAs QPCs (with different lithographic channel widths while keeping their lithographic channel length fixed). QPC devices were fabricated using a high-electron-mobility InAs/InAlAs quantum well based 2DEG. The details of the quantum well structure and QPC fabrication process are described elsewhere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Shubnikov-de Haas and quantum Hall measurements at 4.2&#x02009;K were used to determine the carrier concentration and electron mobility of the 2DEG which were found to be equal to 2.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>16</sup>/m<sup>2</sup> and 3.67&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>/Vs, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, electron beam lithography and a wet etching technique were used to define deep trenches in the 2DEG to form narrow QPC constrictions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic representation and (<bold>b</bold>) scanning electron micrograph (SEM) of an InAs based QPC with two in-plane SGs (G1 and G2). Dark areas are the deep-etched isolation trenches defining the two SGs. The current flows in the x-direction. Application of an asymmetric bias potential between the SGs leads to a lateral electric field along y-direction. The latter is responsible for LSOC in the QPC narrow portion. The 2DEG lies on the xy-plane. The z axis is the direction of growth of the heterostructure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e671"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">We fabricated seven QPCs with different aspect ratios (i.e., ratio of lithographic width over lithographic length). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a,b</xref> represent a schematic and a scanning electron micrograph of one of our fabricated QPC structures with in-plane SGs (G1 and G2), respectively. In QPC 1 through 7, the narrow portion had the same lithographic length (L ~ 890&#x02009;nm) but different lithographic widths (W) varying from 220&#x02009;nm, 260&#x02009;nm, 330&#x02009;nm, 410&#x02009;nm, 520&#x02009;nm, 640&#x02009;nm, and 780&#x02009;nm, respectively. This corresponds to a QPC aspect ratio (W/L) ranging from 0.247, 0.292, 0.371, 0.461, 0.584, 0.719 to 0.876 for QPC 1 through 7, respectively. The reason the maximum lithographic length of the channel for all QPC devices was maintained around 890&#x02009;nm is because InAs has a measured electron spin coherence length less than a micron at 4.2 K<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. In fact, one of our earlier reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> has shown the existence of the broadest 0.5G<sub>o</sub> plateau for an InAs QPC having lithographic channel length around 930&#x02009;nm. We varied the electrostatic width of the QPC channel by applying a bias to the ohmic in-plane SGs. This leads to a depletion of the channel in the narrow portion of the QPC. DC bias was applied to maintain fixed negative voltages <italic>V</italic><sub>G1</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>G2</sub> on the two SGs, as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>. The QPC devices were first cooled down to liquid nitrogen (77&#x02009;K) and then to liquid helium (4.2&#x02009;K). Further details of our conductance measurements are provided elsewhere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The QPC conductance was measured as a function of a common sweep voltage, <italic>V</italic><sub>G</sub>, applied to the two SGs. A four-probe lock-in technique with a drive frequency of 17&#x02009;Hz was used to measure the linear conductance <italic>G</italic> (=<italic>I</italic>/<italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ds</italic></sub>) of the QPC channel for different bias asymmetry &#x00394;<italic>V</italic><sub>G</sub> while varying the common sweep voltage <italic>V</italic><sub>G</sub> applied to the two SGs. In all conductance measurements performed at 4.2&#x02009;K, a small source-to-drain voltage of <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>ds</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100 &#x003bc;V was applied across the QPC. For all QPCs, the negative voltages <italic>V</italic><sub>G1</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>G2</sub> applied to the two SGs were varied until a robust 0.5G<sub>o</sub> plateau was observed as the common gate voltage <italic>V</italic><sub>G</sub> was continuously swept<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par13">Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> show the common gate voltage (V<sub>G</sub>) dependence of the conductance for the forward (blue arrows) and reverse sweeps (green arrows) for QPCs 1 through 3 and QPCs 4 through 7, respectively. For ease of comparison of the conductance plots, the range of V<sub>G</sub> was kept same for all QPCs. Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> show that the threshold voltage in the forward sweep, i.e., the value V<sub>G</sub> at which the conductance plot rises depends on the QPC dimensions.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forward (blue arrows) and reverse sweeps (green arrows) in conductance G (in units of <italic>2e</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>/h</italic>) plots for QPCs 1 through 3. Although the individual pinch-off voltage for each QPC channel is different from one another, the range of common gate signal (V<sub>G</sub>) is kept the same for all devices for clarity. All conductance measurements were taken at T&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.2&#x02009;K. V<sub>G</sub> is the common mode voltage superimposed on initial side gate potentials V<sub>G1</sub> and V<sub>G2</sub> applied to generate the asymmetric potential energy profile in the narrow portion of the QPC.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e819"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Forward (blue arrows) and reverse sweeps (green arrows) in conductance G (in units of <italic>2e</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>/h</italic>) plots for QPCs 4 through 7, as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e838"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">Focusing on the conductance behavior near the 0.5G<sub>0</sub> conductance plateau, it can be seen that the latter is more pronounced for QPC1 with the smallest channel width and gradually disappears as the QPC width increased. For QPC7, the conductance plot is close to linear and there is no remnant of the original conductance plateau as&#x000a0;observed for QPC1. The conductance plot for QPC7 is indicative of a near ohmic behavior for the QPC with the largest width. Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> show that the hysteresis loop size in the conductance plots also diminishes as the QPC width increases. QPCs 1 and 2 also have an anomalous conductance plateau around 1.5G<sub>0</sub> and QPCs 3 and 4 have another conductance plateau slightly above the normal conductance plateau G<sub>0</sub>, typically observed in symmetrically biased QPCs with top split-gates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par15">Some of the features described above can be explained based on our earlier systematic study of the number and locations of anomalous conductance plateaus in InAs/In<sub>0.52</sub>Al<sub>0.48</sub>As QPCs as a function of the polarity of the common gate voltage between its SGs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Some anomalous conductance plateaus were shown to occur over a range of the common sweep voltage as large as 1&#x02009;V. A similar trend is observed in the size of the 0.5 G<sub>0</sub> plateau for QPCs 1 and 2 reported here.</p><p id="Par16">The sensitivity of the conductance measurements to the constant negative voltages <italic>V</italic><sub>G1</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>G2</sub> applied to the two SGs prior to the application of the common sweep voltage V<sub>G</sub> stems from the importance of surface scattering present on the rugged QPC side walls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Since the 7 QPCs are fabricated with different channel widths, the amount of surface scattering on their side walls will be different leading to both a difference in the threshold voltage in the forward sweep conductance plots and the need for an adjustment in the voltages <italic>V</italic><sub>G1</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>G2</sub> to observe an anomalous conductance plateau around 0.5 G<sub>0</sub>, is listed in column 4 of Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Details of the QPC geometrical dimensions (lithographic width and length), aspect ratios (W/L) and the value of the asymmetric bias potential applied on the SGs to achieve the most pronounced anomalous plateaus at conductance value 0.5G<sub>o</sub> during the forward sweep of the common gate voltage <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>G</italic></sub>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>QPC#</th><th>W, L (nm)</th><th>Aspect Ratio W/L</th><th>(<italic>V</italic><sub>G1</sub>,<italic>V</italic><sub>G2</sub>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>QPC 1</td><td>220,890</td><td>0.247</td><td>&#x02212;2&#x02009;V, &#x02212;0.3&#x02009;V</td></tr><tr><td>QPC 2</td><td>260,890</td><td>0.292</td><td>&#x02212;1&#x02009;V, &#x02212;3&#x02009;V</td></tr><tr><td>QPC 3</td><td>330,890</td><td>0.371</td><td>&#x02212;2.5&#x02009;V, &#x02212;5&#x02009;V</td></tr><tr><td>QPC 4</td><td>410,890</td><td>0.461</td><td>&#x02212;3.2&#x02009;V, &#x02212;6.4&#x02009;V</td></tr><tr><td>QPC 5</td><td>520,890</td><td>0.584</td><td>&#x02212;4.5&#x02009;V, &#x02212;7.9&#x02009;V</td></tr><tr><td>QPC 6</td><td>640,890</td><td>0.719</td><td>&#x02212;3.5&#x02009;V, &#x02212;7.8&#x02009;V</td></tr><tr><td>QPC 7</td><td>780,890</td><td>0.876</td><td>&#x02212;5&#x02009;V, &#x02212;9.8&#x02009;V</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The last column gives the applied potential <bold>(</bold><italic>V</italic><sub>G1</sub>, <italic>V</italic><sub>G2</sub>) applied to the two SGs before applying the common gate signal <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>G</italic></sub>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par17">Next, we investigate the physical mechanisms responsible for the progressive disappearance of the 0.5 G<sub>0</sub> plateau and decrease in size of the hysteresis loops as the width of the QPC channel increases. Since the QPC is fabricated using a nominally symmetric InAs quantum well surrounded by two similar InAlAs barriers of equal height (See Fig. 2 of ref.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>), the spatial inversion asymmetry is negligible along the heterostructure growth axis and the associated Rashba spin-orbit coupling can be neglected in our QPC structures. Furthermore, the Dresselhaus spin-orbit interaction due to the bulk inversion asymmetry in the direction of current flow is also neglected for simplicity. The major spin-orbit interaction in our QPCs is LSOC due to a lateral confinement provided by the wet etching of the channel to form the QPC and applied potential from the contact gates (See Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In the QPC narrow portion, the single-particle Hamiltonian is given by<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{array}{rcl}H &#x00026; = &#x00026; {H}_{0}+{H}_{SO}\\ {H}_{SO} &#x00026; = &#x00026; \beta \overrightarrow{\sigma }\cdot (\overrightarrow{k}\times \overrightarrow{\nabla }U)=\overrightarrow{\sigma }\cdot {\overrightarrow{B}}_{SO}\end{array},$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="center"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mo>&#x02207;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${H}_{0}=\frac{1}{2{m}^{\ast }}({p}_{x}^{2}+{p}_{y}^{2})+U(x,y)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0204e;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\beta $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the intrinsic SOC parameter, <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overrightarrow{\sigma }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the vector of Pauli spin matrices and <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\overrightarrow{B}}_{SO}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the effective magnetic field induced by the LSOC.</p><p id="Par18">We assume that the 2DEG is located in the (<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>) plane, where <italic>x</italic> is the direction of current flow from source contact to drain contact and <italic>y</italic> the direction of lateral confinement in the QPC channel; <italic>U</italic>(x, y) is the confinement potential due to both the electrostatic potential on the SGs and the conduction band discontinuity <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\Delta {E}_{c}(y)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mi>&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> at the InAs/vacuum interface. The details of the conductance band energy profile in the vicinity of the QPC constriction, the strength of the LSOC, and the strength of the e-e interaction were analyzed in refs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">A schematic representation of the confining potential U(0,y) along the y direction in the QPC constriction is illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, where a symmetric (full line) or asymmetric bias (dashed line) is applied on its SGs. The application of the same potential to the two SGs results in effective magnetic field <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\overrightarrow{B}}_{SO}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> which has the same magnitude but opposite directions along the two sidewalls that define the narrowest part of the QPC constriction. Electrons flowing through the QPC constriction with opposite spins experience opposite LSOC forces leading to an accumulation of spins with opposite polarity on the QPC sidewalls (thick green arrows in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The spin-up (spin-down) electrons are the majority spin species on edge I (edge II) and the minority species on edge II (edge I) of the QPC. Since the difference of spin density is anti-symmetric with respect to the middle of the narrow portion of the QPC (<italic>y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>w</italic>/2), there is no net polarization in the QPC channel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The application of asymmetric bias voltage between the QPC SGs leads to a population of spin-up electrons on the sidewall I, which is larger than the population of spin-down electrons on the sidewall II. This leads to an imbalance in the spin density profiles and results in a net spin-up polarization in the narrow portion of the QPC. The presence of a strong repulsive Coulomb e-e interaction enhances this spin imbalance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. In the regime of single-mode transport though the QPC, a 0.5 conductance plateau appears as the spontaneous spin polarization can reach near 100% in this regime<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Illustration of the onset of spin polarization in the narrow portion of a QPC in the presence of LSOC when a finite bias is applied between the two SGs. The full and dashed lines represent the potential energy profile U(0,y) in the middle portion of the QPC in the presence of a symmetric and asymmetric bias between the two SGs, respectively. The thick green arrows indicate the amount of spin polarization on either sides of the QPC. Also show are the y-component of the electrical field (<inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${E}_{I}\,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${E}_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) near the QPC sidewalls and the associated effective magnetic field <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\overrightarrow{B}}_{SO,I}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\overrightarrow{B}}_{SO,II}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> on both sides of the QPC channel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1493"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">In QPCs with symmetrically biased top split-gates, it has been shown that backscattering events destroy the quantized normal conductance plateaus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. For instance, Laughton <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> have shown that remote impurity scattering from the doped layers in the heterostructures used to build the QPCs is responsible for an indirect mechanism for electron backscattering. This leads to scattering via quasi-localized sates which can occur for any propagating mode and is more pronounced with higher mode occupancy.</p><p id="Par21">In the presence of LSOC in a narrow channel, non-magnetic impurity scattering can lead to coupling between eigen spinors of spin-up and spin-down electrons (at the same energy) on the same or opposite sides of the QPC channel because these eigenspinors are not orthogonal, a phenomenon similar to what has been reported in the transport properties of spin field effect transistors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. As a result, impurity scattering can cause both elastic intra-subband and inter-subband transitions that relax spin and reduce the overall spin polarization in the QPC channel. In our QPCs, we have shown in the past that in addition to remote impurity scattering, surface roughness and impurity (dangling bond) scattering on the sidewalls of the QPC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> trigger additional backscattering events. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> illustrates the different scattering mechanisms leading to a reduction of the spin polarization in the narrow portion of the QPC including: back-scattering spin-flip events on left and right sidewalls of the QPC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a,b</xref>), forward scattering from the left (I) to the right side (II) of the QPC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>), and forward scattering from the right (II) to the left side (I) of the QPC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>). In the presence of multimode transport, the wave vector of the scattered electron <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overrightarrow{{k}^{\text{'}}}\,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>can either be equal or different in magnitude compared to the wave vector <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overrightarrow{k}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> of the electron prior to scattering. In all panels in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, the top and bottom circles next to each arrow showing the direction of the incident and scattered electron indicate the directions of the effective magnetic field <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\overrightarrow{B}}_{SO}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> as well as the directions of alignment of the electron spin along the z axis. The influence of remote impurity scattering increases with the QPC&#x000a0;channel width. For a fixed of value of (V<sub>G</sub> - V<sub>T</sub>),where V<sub>T</sub> is the specific pinch-off voltage for conduction in a QPC, the electron density in the QPC channel increases with the width of the QPC channel. As a result, there is an increased screening of the electron-electron interaction leading to a less favorable condition for the existence of a spin polarized state in the QPC channel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Illustration of various scattering mechanisms leading to a reduction of the amount of spin polarization in the narrow portion of a QPC and accompanying reduction in the hysteresis loops in the conductance plots: back-scattering spin-flip events on (<bold>a</bold>) the left (I) and (<bold>b</bold>) right sidewall (II) of the QPC, (<bold>c</bold>) forward scattering from the left (I) to the right side (II) of the QPC, and (<bold>d</bold>) forward scattering from the right (II) to the left side (I) of the QPC. In the presence of multimode transport, the wave vector of the scattered electron <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overrightarrow{{k}^{\text{'}}}\,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>can either be equal or different in magnitude compared to the wave vector <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overrightarrow{k\,}\,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>of the electron prior to scattering. In all cases, next to each arrow indicating the direction of the incident and scattered electron, the top and bottom circles illustrate the direction of the effective magnetic field <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\overrightarrow{B}}_{SO}\,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>and the direction of alignment of the electron spin along the z axis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1682"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par22">The physical mechanisms responsible for the disappearance of the 0.5G<sub>o</sub> conductance plateau and the decrease in size of the hysteresis loops in a series of asymmetrically biased InAs based QPCs with varying channel width but identical channel length (as their aspect ratio (width/length) increases) were identified as: (1) multimode transport in the QPC with larger channel leading to spin-flip backscattering events due to both remote impurities in the doping layer of the heterostructure and surface roughness and impurity (dangling bond) scattering on the sidewalls of the QPC constriction, and (2) an increased in carrier density leading to the screening of the e-e interaction in the QPC channel.</p><p id="Par23">In the QPC devices studied here, as their aspect ratio increases, more channels participate in conduction through the narrow portion of the QPC and screening effects are more important in the QPC channel reducing the importance of e-e interaction. As a result, the 0.5G<sub>0</sub> conductance plateau gradually disappears as the QPC channel width increases, a trend supported by NEGF simulations we reported in the past<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par24">The progressive disappearance of the net spin polarization in the QPC channel and the accompanying reduction in the size of the hysteresis loops as the QPC channel width increases is an another indirect proof of the onset of spin polarization in InAs based QPCs in the presence of LSOC and an asymmetric bias between the QPC SGs.</p><p id="Par25">Asymmetrically biased QPCs with in-plane SGs can act as efficient spin injectors and detectors which could lead to the fabrication of all-electric spin valves. It is anticipated that the asymmetrically biased QPCs studied here could be used as spin-based sensors, filters, and interferometers for future spintronic applications. Furthermore, the onset of hysteresis in the current-voltage characteristics of spin based devices could lead to their potential applications in multilevel logic and data storage circuits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par26">Towards that goal, it is imperative to explore means to increase the temperature at which QPC spin polarizer can be used for any practical application. InAs has a high intrinsic SOC but a short spin coherence length of around a micron at 4.2&#x02009;K<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. The latter is only around tens of nanometers at ambient temperatures. Hence, InAs or any other semiconductor with a large intrinsic SOC, is not suitable for practical applications at room temperature. Our NEGF simulations have shown that even a very weak SOC can cause significant spin polarization provided the electron-electron interaction is very strong<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Our past finding shows that QPC devices made of GaAs (that possesses a weak intrinsic SOC) can also be useful in generating fully spin polarized current by purely electrical means<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Some advantages of using GaAs based QPCs include: its long spin coherence length of tens of microns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> at ambient temperatures; GaAs samples can be grown with very low electron concentration leading to a strong e-e interaction; The existence of a large Schottky barrier at GaAs/metal interfaces which is beneficial for the deposition of surface gates.</p><p id="Par27">However, one disadvantage of GaAs is that it has a large surface depletion due to the Fermi level pining by surface states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. In fact, in our previous experiments with GaAs QPC devices, we had to apply a large positive bias (more than&#x02009;+&#x02009;10 volts) on both the SGs to first open the QPC constriction at 4.2K. This is a drawback for GaAs based QPC devices if they are to be used in future generations of low power circuits. In contrast, for InAs QPCs, the Fermi level is pinned into the conduction band bottom, making it easier to form Ohmic contacts to the device which facilitates already-open QPC channel at T&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.2&#x02009;K and below. There is therefore a need to look into alternative semiconductors and their compounds for asymmetrically biased QPC devices to become operational at temperature much higher than liquid helium.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>P.P.D. acknowledges financial support from Science and Engineering Research Board, Department of Science and Technology, Government of India through grant award EMR/2016/000808.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>P.P.D. conceived the experiments and fabricated the devices. M.C. and P.P.D. analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. S.K., S.S.M. and A.K.J. assisted with sample preparation, conductance measurements and provided feedback on the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par28">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awschalom</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Challenges for semiconductor spintronics</article-title><source>Nature physics</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphys551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flatt&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solid-state physics: Silicon spintronics warms up</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>462</volume><issue>7272</issue><fpage>419</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/462419a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19940906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19940906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awschalom</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Samarth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trend: Spintronics without magnetism</article-title><source>Physics</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>50</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/Physics.2.50</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin-orbit coupling effects in two dimensional electron and hole systems</article-title><source>Book Series: Springer Tracts in Modern Physics</source><year>2003</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin accumulation in the electron transport with Rashba interaction</article-title><source>Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials</source><year>2007</year><volume>310</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>702</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmmm.2006.10.1029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetic magnetoelectric effect in a two-dimensional semiconductor strip due to boundary-confinement-induced spin-orbit coupling</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2006</year><volume>74</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>075302</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.74.075302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q-feng</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulation of opposite spins on the transverse edges of a two-dimensional electron gas in a longitudinal electric field</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2006</year><volume>74</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>155313</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.74.155313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ihnatsenka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zozoulenko</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin polarization of edge states and the magnetosubband structure in quantum wires</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2006</year><volume>73</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>075331</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.73.075331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ihnatsenka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zozoulenko</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conductance of a quantum point contact based on spin-density-functional theory</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2007</year><volume>76</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>045338</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.76.045338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlagheck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of short-range interactions on transport through quantum point contacts: A numerical approach</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2007</year><volume>75</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>045346</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.75.045346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of polarization in a spin-orbit coupling quantum wire with a constriction</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2007</year><volume>76</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>195304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.76.195304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>T-M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moment formation in quantum point contacts due to spin-orbit interaction</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2010</year><volume>82</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>115309</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.82.115309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Szafran</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin current source based on a quantum point contact with local spin-orbit interaction</article-title><source>Applied Physics Letters</source><year>2013</year><volume>103</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>202404</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4830372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chuburin. Spin polarization and conductance of the laterally asymmetric quantum point contact</article-title><source>Physics Letters A</source><year>2014</year><volume>378</volume><issue>30&#x02013;31</issue><fpage>2211</fpage><lpage>2216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physleta.2014.05.052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuburin</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin polarization of the asymmetric quantum point contact and conductance anomalies in the case of resonances</article-title><source>Physica E: Low-dimensional Systems and Nanostructures</source><year>2015</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physe.2015.05.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin polarization in the vicinity of quantum point contact with spin-orbit interaction</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>125307</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.94.125307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alomar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Isabel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interplay between resonant tunneling and spin precession oscillations in all-electric all-semiconductor spin transistors</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>075402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.94.075402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farghadan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of Rashba spin&#x02013;orbit coupling by electron&#x02013;electron interaction</article-title><source>RSC Advances</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>82</issue><fpage>78714</fpage><lpage>78719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6RA16289D</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khrapai</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaev</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin-orbit coupling and resonances in the conductance of quantum wires</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2018</year><volume>98</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>121401</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.98.121401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>All-electric quantum point contact spin-polarizer</article-title><source>Nature Nanotechnology</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>759</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nnano.2009.240</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19893512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19893512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Juang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Umansky</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of impurity scattering on the linear and nonlinear conductances of quasi-one-dimensional disordered quantum wires by asymmetrically lateral confinement</article-title><source>Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>39</issue><fpage>395303</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21403225?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21403225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anomalous conductance quantization observed in a quantum point contact with an asymmetric confinement potential</article-title><source>Journal of the Korean Physical Society</source><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1907</fpage><lpage>1910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3938/jkps.60.1907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iye</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsumoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence of Spin-Filtering in Quantum Constrictions with Spin&#x02013;Orbit Interaction</article-title><source>Journal of the Physical Society of Japan</source><year>2012</year><volume>81</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>054706</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1143/JPSJ.81.054706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>M. Kohda, S. Nakamura, Y. Nishihara, K. Kobayashi, T. Ono, J.-i. Ohe, Y. Tokura, T. Mineno, and J. Nitta, Nat. Commun. 3, 1082 (2012)</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1082</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2080</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23011136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23011136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spin&#x02013;orbit induced electronic spin separation in semiconductor nanostructures</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1082</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms2080</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23011136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23011136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>All-electrical injection and detection of a spin-polarized current using 1D conductors</article-title><source>Physical review letters</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>177202</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.109.177202</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23215217?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23215217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Understanding the anomalous conductance plateau in asymmetrically biased InAs/In0. 52Al0. 48As quantum point contacts&#x02014;A step towards a tunable all electric spin valve</article-title><source>Applied Physics Letters</source><year>2011</year><volume>99</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>122105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.3636413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Newrock</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observation of a 0.5 conductance plateau in asymmetrically biased GaAs quantum point contact</article-title><source>Applied Physics Letters</source><year>2012</year><volume>101</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>102401</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4749817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Herbert. Influence of surface scattering on the anomalous conductance plateaus in an asymmetrically biased InAs/In0.52Al0.48As quantum point contact</article-title><source>Nanotechnology</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>215201</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0957-4484/23/21/215201</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22551945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22551945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dependence of the 0.5&#x000d7;(2e<sup>2</sup>/h) conductance plateau on the aspect ratio of InAs quantum point contacts with in-plane side gates</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Physics</source><year>2017</year><volume>121</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>083901</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4977110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhandari</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>T. Herbert. Steps toward an all-electric spin valve using side-gated quantum point contacts with lateral spin&#x02013;orbit coupling. <italic>Advances in Natural</italic></article-title><source>Sciences: Nanoscience and Nanotechnology</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>013002</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cahay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin transistors: Closer to an all-electric device</article-title><source>Nature nanotechnology</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nnano.2014.305</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25531087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>All-electric all-semiconductor spin field-effect transistors</article-title><source>Nature nanotechnology</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nnano.2014.296</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25531088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunawan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De Poortere</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shayegan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantized conductance in an AlAs two-dimensional electron system quantum point contact</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2006</year><volume>74</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>155436</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.74.155436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de. Jong</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieck</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Wal</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Split-gate quantum point contacts with tunable channel length</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Physics</source><year>2013</year><volume>113</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>024507</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4774281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>S-T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Controlled spatial separation of spins and coherent dynamics in spin-orbit-coupled nanostructures</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>15997</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms15997</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28691707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28691707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shojaei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Demonstration of gate control of spin splitting in a high-mobility InAs/AlSb two-dimensional electron gas</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2016</year><volume>93</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>075302</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.93.075302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shchamkhalova</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin current induced by a charged tip in a quantum point contact</article-title><source>Physica B: Condensed Matter</source><year>2017</year><volume>509</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physb.2016.12.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhdanov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ballistic magnetotransport in a suspended two-dimensional electron gas with periodic antidot lattices</article-title><source>Semiconductors</source><year>2017</year><volume>51</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/S1063782617010250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pokhabov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lateral-electric-field-induced spin polarization in a suspended GaAs quantum point contact</article-title><source>Applied Physics Letters</source><year>2018</year><volume>112</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>082102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.5019906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conductance quantization at a half-integer plateau in a symmetric GaAs quantum wire</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>312</volume><issue>5778</issue><fpage>1359</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1126445</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16741116?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16741116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Possible spin polarization in a one-dimensional electron gas</article-title><source>Physical Review Letters</source><year>1996</year><volume>77</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.77.135</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10061790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10061790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pepper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bird.</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 0.7 feature and interactions in one-dimensional systems</article-title><source>Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>160301</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Micolich</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What lurks below the last plateau: experimental studies of the 0.7&#x000d7; 2e<sup>2</sup>/h conductance anomaly in one-dimensional systems</article-title><source>Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><issue>44</issue><fpage>443201</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21997403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21997403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berggren</surname><given-names>K-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrons in one dimension</article-title><source>Philos.Trans.R.Soc.London, Sect.A</source><year>2010</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsta.2009.0226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starikov</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Irina</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name><surname>Berggren</surname><given-names>K-F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scenario for the 0.7-conductance anomaly in quantum point contacts</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2003</year><volume>67</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>235319</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.67.235319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaksch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Irina</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>and Karl-Fredrik Berggren. From quantum point contacts to quantum wires: Density-functional calculations with exchange and correlation effects</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2006</year><volume>74</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>235320</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.74.235320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Havu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martti</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieminen</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ville</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron transport through quantum wires and point contacts</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>233308</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.70.233308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shelykh</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Galkin</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagraev</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantum point contact with a large localized spin: Fractional quantization of the ballistic conductance</article-title><source>Physical Review</source><year>2006</year><volume>B74</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>085322</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.74.085322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Meir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phys. Rev. Lett. 90, 026804 (2003)</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2003</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>026804</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.90.026804</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12570569?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12570569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Debray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Newrock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Possible origin of the 0.5 plateau in the ballistic conductance of quantum point contacts</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2009</year><volume>80</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>155440</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.80.155440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakimenko</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name><surname>Berggren</surname><given-names>K-F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nature of magnetization and lateral spin&#x02013;orbit interaction in gated semiconductor nanowires</article-title><source>Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter</source><year>2018</year><volume>30</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>215302</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29623898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29623898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tscheuschner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreas</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantum ballistic transport in in-plane-gate transistors showing onset of a novel ferromagnetic phase transition</article-title><source>Superlattices and Microstructures</source><year>1996</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/spmi.1996.0123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shailos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Linear conductance of quantum point contacts with deliberately broken symmetry</article-title><source>Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1715</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hysteresis in the quantized current characteristics of single-electron-transport device</article-title><source>Physics Letters A</source><year>2010</year><volume>374</volume><issue>11&#x02013;12</issue><fpage>1389</fpage><lpage>1392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physleta.2010.01.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Gate Hysteresis in Single Electron Transport Driven by Surface Acoustic Wave (SAW/SET) Devices</article-title><source>Journal of Low Temperature Physics</source><year>2017</year><volume>189</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10909-017-1799-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra Dutta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahay</surname></name><name><surname>Newrock</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hysteresis in the conductance of asymmetrically biased GaAs quantum point contacts with in-plane side gates</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Physics</source><year>2013</year><volume>114</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>033702</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4813506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhandari, N. <italic>et al.</italic> Potential Applications of All Electric Spin Valves Made of Asymmetrically Biased Quantum Point Contacts. <italic>Nanomagnetic and Spintronic Devices for Energy&#x02010;Efficient Memory and Computing</italic>, 9&#x02013;64 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Newrock</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic bistability in quantum point contacts with in-plane side gates</article-title><source>Applied Physics Letters</source><year>2013</year><volume>102</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>112413</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4798524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jones A., Cahay, M., Yakimenko, I. &#x00026; Berggren, K. F. Indirect Evidence of Net Spin Polarization in Quantum Point Contacts With Four In-Plane Side-Gates, pp.123&#x02013;158 in Contemporary topics in spintronics, World Scientific, S. Bandyopadhyay, M. Cahay, and J. P. Leburton, Eds (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spin separation and spin Hall effect in quantum wires due to lateral-confinement-induced spin-orbit-coupling</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2006</year><volume>74</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>155321</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.74.155321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;ttiker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantized transmission of a saddle-point constriction</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>1990</year><volume>41</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>7906</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.41.7906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laughton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modal analysis of transport through quantum point contacts using realistic potentials</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>1991</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1150</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.44.1150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Harold</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breakdown of quantized conductance in point contacts calculated using realistic potentials</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>1991</year><volume>43</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>12638</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.43.12638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cahay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phase-coherent quantum mechanical spin transport in a weakly disordered quasi-one-dimensional channel</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2004</year><volume>69</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>045303</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.69.045303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhandari, N. <italic>et al</italic>. Potential Applications of All Electric Spin Valves Made of Asymmetrically Biased Quantum Point Contacts. <italic>Nanomagnetic and Spintronic Devices for Energy Efficient Memory and Computing</italic>, 9&#x02013;64 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davies, J. H. <italic>The physics of low-dimensional semiconductors: an introduction</italic>. (Cambridge university press, 1998).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>