<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical system and experimental conditions</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> shows the structure of the investigated model chemical compass, a molecular triad consisting of covalently linked carotenoid (
   <span class="bold">C</span>), porphyrin (
   <span class="bold">P</span>) and fullerene (
   <span class="bold">F</span>) moieties. Its photophysical behaviour and response to high fields, in the absence and presence of resonant radiofrequency fields, have been studied previously
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span>. As depicted in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>, photo-excitation of the porphyrin at 532 nm is followed by rapid intramolecular electron transfer, first generating a primary radical pair 
   <span class="bold">C</span>-
   <span class="bold">P</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span>-
   <span class="bold">F</span>
   <span class="sup">•−</span> of picosecond lifetime, before subsequent electron transfer leads to the formation of the secondary radical pair 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span>-
   <span class="bold">P</span>-
   <span class="bold">F</span>
   <span class="sup">•−</span>, which lives for up to roughly a microsecond . Previous work, in similar solvent and temperature conditions to those employed here, demonstrated that this secondary radical pair is formed predominantly in the singlet state, 
   <span class="sup">S</span>[
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span>-
   <span class="bold">P</span>-
   <span class="bold">F</span>
   <span class="sup">•−</span>], with just 7% of radical pairs being created in the triplet state
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. While each radical pair is born in a spin-correlated state (either singlet or triplet), the magnetic field characteristics of the radical pair ensemble are complex, as will be shown below.
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Chemical structure, photocycle, and time dependence of the magnetic field effect (MFE) of 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span>. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Structure of the molecular 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span> triad. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Simplified photoscheme including all processes of relevance for this study. For simplicity, the secondary radical pair 
      <span class="bold">C</span>
      <span class="sup">•+</span>-
      <span class="bold">P</span>-
      <span class="bold">F</span>
      <span class="sup">•−</span> is shown as created in a pure singlet state. For more detailed photochemical information, refer to refs. 
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
      </span>. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> Transient absorption subtraction signal ΔΔ
      <span class="italic">A</span> of the radical pair, probed at 980 nm, obtained upon application of a magnetic field of 
      <span class="italic">B</span>
      <sub>0</sub> = 100 μT. The dotted lines in red, green, and blue indicate delay times of 0.08, 0.28, and 0.71 μs after laser excitation, respectively. 
      <span class="bold">d</span> Magnetic field dependence of the MFE averaged for a time window of 20 ns centred around the indicated delay times. The dotted black line indicates the field position of 100 μT and the field region approximately corresponding to the low field region is highlighted in grey
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11655_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e599" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measurements were carried out at 120 K, where the solvent, 2-methyltetrahydrofuran (MTHF), forms an optically transparent glass. Recombination of 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span>-
   <span class="bold">P</span>-
   <span class="bold">F</span>
   <span class="sup">•−</span> is possible from either the singlet or triplet states and occurs with rate constants 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>S</sub> and 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>T</sub>, respectively. The rates are strongly dependent on the solvent properties, notably its dielectric constant. Under similar conditions, 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>S</sub> has been shown to be some three orders of magnitude faster than 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>T</sub>, and consequently, a significant change in the recombination kinetics is observed upon application of a magnetic field
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. Further details on the sample preparation and experimental set-up are given in the Methods section.
  </p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most experimental investigations of MFEs have relied on optical methods in which either the concentration of the radicals themselves or of one of their recombination products is determined as a function of field. Here we use nanosecond TA spectroscopy to obtain the concentration profile of the carotenoid radical cation 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span> via its absorbance in the near infrared, following radical pair creation by a 532 nm laser pulse. Application of a magnetic field, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub>, is expected to change the rate of singlet–triplet interconversion and consequently the overall radical pair kinetics, concentration and absorbance. The effect of the field is typically quantified via ΔΔ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub>) = Δ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub>) − Δ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub> = 0), where Δ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub>) and Δ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub> = 0) refer to the absorbance of the transient species at 980 nm (predominantly 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <span class="bold">•</span>
    <span class="bold">+</span>
   </span>), in the presence and absence of the field, respectively. 
   <span class="italic">t</span> defines the time after the 532 nm pump laser pulse. It can also be instructive to calculate the so-called percentage field effect, defined as MFE(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub>) = ΔΔ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub>)/Δ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub> = 0) × 100%.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time and field strength dependence</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a> demonstrates that a 100 μT field confers a pronounced effect on the recombination kinetics of the radical pair. In the presence of the magnetic field, the concentration of radicals immediately following the laser pulse is enhanced, ΔΔ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span> &lt; 220 ns, 100 μT) &gt; 0, but fewer radicals survive to microsecond timescales, ΔΔ
   <span class="italic">A</span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span> &gt; 220 ns, 100 μT) &lt; 0. This biphasic behaviour has been noted before and seems to be characteristic of singlet-born radical pairs with 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>S</sub> &gt; 
   <span class="italic">k</span>
   <sub>T</sub> undergoing spin–lattice relaxation at a rate comparable to recombination
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span>. The mixed initial spin state (93% singlet: 7% triplet) in 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span>-
   <span class="bold">P</span>-
   <span class="bold">F</span>
   <span class="sup">•−</span> further enhances this effect. Moreover, semiclassical spin dynamics simulations have recently reproduced some of the complex field- and time-dependent TA characteristics of 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <span class="bold">•</span>
    <span class="bold">+</span>
   </span>-
   <span class="bold">P</span>-
   <span class="bold">F</span>
   <span class="sup">•−</span> without implicit consideration of relaxation processes or mixed initial spin states
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage field effects MFE(
   <span class="italic">t</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>0</sub>), obtained at different times 
   <span class="italic">t</span> after laser excitation, are shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>. Our initial discussion will concentrate on the data obtained at early and late times, i.e., 
   <span class="italic">t</span> = 0.08 μs and 
   <span class="italic">t</span> = 0.71 μs. Both MFE traces follow the expected behaviour, with application of both low and high fields effecting changes in radical concentration of opposite sign. Following the discussion in reference
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>, weak magnetic fields mainly enhance the 
   <span class="italic">S</span>–
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>0</sub> interconversion efficiency, which results in an increase in radical concentration at early times after laser excitation (the initially predominantly singlet population is driven more effectively into less reactive triplet) and in a decrease in radical concentration at late times (when formed triplet radical pairs can return more efficiently to singlet radical pairs, which might subsequently recombine).
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, higher fields affect the radical recombination via the Zeeman effect, energetically isolating the 
   <span class="italic">S</span>/
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>0</sub> manifold from the 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>+</sub>/
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>−</sub> levels, therefore impeding efficient singlet–triplet mixing. Following the arguments above, this results in a decrease in radical concentration at early times after the laser pulse and a corresponding increase on longer timescales.
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is, at first sight, perhaps surprising that the MFE data obtained at intermediate times, namely, 0.28 μs after the laser pulse, do not exhibit a sign inversion of the MFE. This finding is, however, in agreement with the results in ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span> in which it was demonstrated that the field effects on the populations of 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>0</sub> and 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>+</sub>/
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>−</sub> are not only in opposite directions but evolve at different timescales. While the initially positive LFE has, at 0.28 μs, already changed sign, the high-field effect lags about 0.2 μs behind in its evolution (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Complementary experiments were also performed on a partially deuterated analogue of the 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span> triad, from now on referred to as 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="bold">D</span>
   </sub>, the chemical structure of which is shown in Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>. Significantly different MFE traces were recorded, while the kinetics of both triad molecules in the absence of any applied field were identical within experimental error (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). The observed dependencies of the position and amplitude of the low- and high-field effects are in agreement with the reduced effective hyperfine coupling in the carotenoid radical (the gyromagnetic ratio of the deuteron is approximately a factor of 6.5 smaller than that of the proton). A reduction in this effective coupling is expected to result in a reduction of the size of the LFE and a shift of the maximum of the LFE to smaller fields
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span>, in agreement with Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>. A detailed interpretation of the difference in the time evolution of the field effects is more complex since the probabilities of finding the radical pair in the triplet and singlet states are determined by an intricate interplay of hyperfine couplings, applied magnetic field strengths and kinetics
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>. For reference, the measured time-evolution of the MFE is compared for both triads in Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> and a visualisation of the calculated proton hyperfine coupling tensors in the carotenoid radical is shown in Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>.
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Orientation dependence of the magnetic field effect (MFE) of 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span>. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Illustration of the experimental geometry. 
      <span class="italic">x</span>, 
      <span class="italic">y</span> and 
      <span class="italic">z</span> indicate the three laboratory axes, 
      <span class="italic">θ</span> defines the angle between the −
      <span class="italic">z</span> axis and the applied magnetic field. The polarisation axes of the pump and probe beams are parallel and are indicated in the figure. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> MFE for 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span> (red) and 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="bold">D</span>
      </sub> (orange) as a function of applied field. The field positions where the anisotropy curves were recorded are indicated by vertical dashed lines. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> MFE of 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span>, recorded at 100 μT as a function of 
      <span class="italic">θ</span>. 
      <span class="bold">d</span> MFE data for 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="bold">D</span>
      </sub>, recorded at 200 μT as a function of 
      <span class="italic">θ</span>. 
      <span class="bold">e</span> MFE recorded for 
      <span class="bold">CPF</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="bold">D</span>
      </sub> and same parameters as 
      <span class="bold">d</span> but recorded with the polarisation directions of both pump and probe beam rotated by 45° in the 
      <span class="italic">xz</span> plane. The data shown in all panels were averaged over a time window from 0.07 to 0.09 μs after laser excitation. The grey bars in panels 
      <span class="bold">c</span>–
      <span class="bold">e</span> indicate the (average) standard deviation of the mean. The black solid lines represent best sinusoidal fits to the data
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11655_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1031" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The compass response</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have so far characterised the triad’s response to magnetic fields as a function of time and field strength. Crucial for chemical compass behaviour, we now investigate the dependence of the MFE on the orientation of the triad molecule with respect to the external field. The optically transparent glass formed by MTHF at 120 K immobilises the triad molecules on the timescale of the experiment. This allows the use of photo-selection to pump and probe only a subset of triad molecules with transition dipole moments predominantly parallel to the laser polarisation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. Previous calculations have shown that the transition dipole moments of the 532 nm porphyrin excitation and the 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span> absorption at 980 nm are almost parallel to the long axis of 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span>, so that molecules aligned with the polarisation axis are preferentially excited and detected
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Orientation-dependent field effects are obtained as illustrated in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>: (i) Parallel, linearly polarised pump (532 nm, green) and probe (980 nm, red) beams along the laboratory 
   <span class="italic">y</span> direction excite the sample and detect the field-dependent absorption of 
   <span class="bold">C</span>
   <span class="sup">•+</span>, respectively. (ii) The applied magnetic field, at constant magnitude but varying orientation, is generated by three mutually perpendicular pairs of Helmholtz coils; the field strength along the laser beam path is 0 mT, and the field orientation in the 
   <span class="italic">xz</span> plane, perpendicular to the propagation direction of the laser beams, can be varied at will. Crucially, the magnetic field strength was calibrated to within an accuracy of &lt;±10 μT at all orientations. (iii) The MFE was recorded as a function of the angle 
   <span class="italic">θ</span> (in random order) between the field and the −
   <span class="italic">z</span> axis of the laboratory frame.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of such measurements on the protonated triad (red graph) and deuterated triad (orange graph) are shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c–e</a>. All curves are shown for early times (0.08 μs after laser excitation). Unless otherwise stated, the data have been recorded with the pump and probe beams polarised along the 
   <span class="italic">x</span> axis of the laboratory frame, corresponding to a horizontal polarisation (
   <span class="italic">h</span>/
   <span class="italic">h</span> in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For reference, the graphs in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a> indicate the field responses of the triads in the low-field region recorded 0.08 μs after the laser pulse. These data illustrate that the LFE is shifted towards smaller fields in the deuterated triad, as expected given its reduced hyperfine couplings.
  </p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The magnetic field responses of triads 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span> and 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="bold">D</span>
   </sub> with respect to angle 
   <span class="italic">θ</span> are shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c and d</a>, respectively. The data were recorded using field strengths of only 100 μT for 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span> and 200 μT for 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="bold">D</span>
   </sub>. The respective data recorded at 50 μT are shown in Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It can clearly be seen from the data that both triads act as sensitive weak-field chemical compasses: The MFE is expected
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span> to be proportional to sin
   <span class="sup">2</span>
   <span class="italic">θ</span>, with 
   <span class="italic">θ</span> being defined in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. This can be expressed as a simple sinusoidal variation of the MFE, sin
   <span class="sup">2</span>
   <span class="italic">θ</span> = 0.5 − 0.5 sin(2
   <span class="italic">θ</span> + 
   <span class="italic">π</span>/2), justifying the sinusoidal fit to the experimental data shown in black in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. The MFE response of both triad systems shows a pronounced dependence on the angle 
   <span class="italic">θ</span>. Both chemical compasses are invariant to inversion of the field direction so that MFE(
   <span class="italic">θ</span>) = MFE(
   <span class="italic">θ</span> + 
   <span class="italic">π</span>), a characteristic shared by the avian magnetic compass
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2e</a> illustrates, on the example of 
   <span class="bold">CPF</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="bold">D</span>
   </sub>, that the observed angular dependence of the MFE response is driven by anisotropic hyperfine couplings. The data were recorded after a 45 degree (clockwise) rotation of the polarisation direction of the light within the 
   <span class="italic">xz</span> laboratory plane (with respect to 
   <span class="italic">h</span>/
   <span class="italic">h</span> polarisation). All other experimental parameters (including the orientation of the field coils) were kept the same. The corresponding 45 degree shift in the resulting compass response confirms the robustness of our calibration and affirms the chemical compass properties of the triad system.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
