<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental set-up</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The samples were excited at 532 nm using a Nd:YAG laser operated at a repetition rate of 10 Hz (7 ns pulse duration), employing pump energies of &lt;1 mJ. The radical pair kinetics were monitored via the absorption of the carotenoid radical cation at 980 nm using a modulated cw laser diode with a duty cycle of only 4% (to avoid excessive sample heating), corresponding to peak energies of ~3 mW at the sample during the measurement. The transmitted light was detected using an infrared-sensitive photodiode.</p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The magnetic field was generated using three sets of orthogonal Helmholtz coils. A small pair created a static field in the propagation direction of the pump and probe laser beams (
  <span class="italic">y</span> direction) to cancel out the component of the Earth’s magnetic field in this direction. Two larger sets were used to precisely control the magnetic field strength and direction applied in the experiment in the plane perpendicular to the laser propagation direction (
  <span class="italic">xz</span> plane). A field angle 
  <span class="italic">θ</span> of 0° corresponds to a field in −
  <span class="italic">z</span> direction, whereas a field angle of 90° indicates a field applied in the 
  <span class="italic">x</span> direction. Details on the field calibration procedure are given in Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The laser polarisations were controlled by making use of 
  <span class="italic">λ</span>/2 waveplates. The pump and probe beam paths were collinear at the sample cell and decoupled after the sample prior to signal detection using dielectric mirrors (HR 532 nm). The used beam geometry maximised the pump–probe overlap at the sample. The polarisations of pump and probe beams were chosen to be parallel to simplify the analysis of the anisotropic data. A detailed scheme and description of the experimental set-up can be found in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a> and Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
