<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The compass response</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have so far characterised the triad’s response to magnetic fields as a function of time and field strength. Crucial for chemical compass behaviour, we now investigate the dependence of the MFE on the orientation of the triad molecule with respect to the external field. The optically transparent glass formed by MTHF at 120 K immobilises the triad molecules on the timescale of the experiment. This allows the use of photo-selection to pump and probe only a subset of triad molecules with transition dipole moments predominantly parallel to the laser polarisation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Previous calculations have shown that the transition dipole moments of the 532 nm porphyrin excitation and the 
  <span class="bold">C</span>
  <span class="sup">•+</span> absorption at 980 nm are almost parallel to the long axis of 
  <span class="bold">CPF</span>, so that molecules aligned with the polarisation axis are preferentially excited and detected
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Orientation-dependent field effects are obtained as illustrated in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>: (i) Parallel, linearly polarised pump (532 nm, green) and probe (980 nm, red) beams along the laboratory 
  <span class="italic">y</span> direction excite the sample and detect the field-dependent absorption of 
  <span class="bold">C</span>
  <span class="sup">•+</span>, respectively. (ii) The applied magnetic field, at constant magnitude but varying orientation, is generated by three mutually perpendicular pairs of Helmholtz coils; the field strength along the laser beam path is 0 mT, and the field orientation in the 
  <span class="italic">xz</span> plane, perpendicular to the propagation direction of the laser beams, can be varied at will. Crucially, the magnetic field strength was calibrated to within an accuracy of &lt;±10 μT at all orientations. (iii) The MFE was recorded as a function of the angle 
  <span class="italic">θ</span> (in random order) between the field and the −
  <span class="italic">z</span> axis of the laboratory frame.
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of such measurements on the protonated triad (red graph) and deuterated triad (orange graph) are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c–e</a>. All curves are shown for early times (0.08 μs after laser excitation). Unless otherwise stated, the data have been recorded with the pump and probe beams polarised along the 
  <span class="italic">x</span> axis of the laboratory frame, corresponding to a horizontal polarisation (
  <span class="italic">h</span>/
  <span class="italic">h</span> in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For reference, the graphs in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a> indicate the field responses of the triads in the low-field region recorded 0.08 μs after the laser pulse. These data illustrate that the LFE is shifted towards smaller fields in the deuterated triad, as expected given its reduced hyperfine couplings.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The magnetic field responses of triads 
  <span class="bold">CPF</span> and 
  <span class="bold">CPF</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="bold">D</span>
  </sub> with respect to angle 
  <span class="italic">θ</span> are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c and d</a>, respectively. The data were recorded using field strengths of only 100 μT for 
  <span class="bold">CPF</span> and 200 μT for 
  <span class="bold">CPF</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="bold">D</span>
  </sub>. The respective data recorded at 50 μT are shown in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It can clearly be seen from the data that both triads act as sensitive weak-field chemical compasses: The MFE is expected
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> to be proportional to sin
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="italic">θ</span>, with 
  <span class="italic">θ</span> being defined in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. This can be expressed as a simple sinusoidal variation of the MFE, sin
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="italic">θ</span> = 0.5 − 0.5 sin(2
  <span class="italic">θ</span> + 
  <span class="italic">π</span>/2), justifying the sinusoidal fit to the experimental data shown in black in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. The MFE response of both triad systems shows a pronounced dependence on the angle 
  <span class="italic">θ</span>. Both chemical compasses are invariant to inversion of the field direction so that MFE(
  <span class="italic">θ</span>) = MFE(
  <span class="italic">θ</span> + 
  <span class="italic">π</span>), a characteristic shared by the avian magnetic compass
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2e</a> illustrates, on the example of 
  <span class="bold">CPF</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="bold">D</span>
  </sub>, that the observed angular dependence of the MFE response is driven by anisotropic hyperfine couplings. The data were recorded after a 45 degree (clockwise) rotation of the polarisation direction of the light within the 
  <span class="italic">xz</span> laboratory plane (with respect to 
  <span class="italic">h</span>/
  <span class="italic">h</span> polarisation). All other experimental parameters (including the orientation of the field coils) were kept the same. The corresponding 45 degree shift in the resulting compass response confirms the robustness of our calibration and affirms the chemical compass properties of the triad system.
 </p>
</sec>
