<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We were able to record a high-resolution molecular movie of the ultrafast coherent rotational motion of impulsively aligned OCS molecules. State-selection and an optimised two-pulse sequence yielded an unprecedented degree of field-free alignment of 〈cos
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>2D</sub> = 0.96〉, with a very narrow angular confinement of 13.4° FWHM, shown in Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>. Limiting the analysis to a determination of 〈cos
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>2D</sub>〉, as it is common in experiments on time-dependent alignment, did not allow to capture the rich rotational dynamics, while the use of a polynomial expansion up to an appropriate order did. We completely unravelled the rotational wavepacket, from which the complex coefficients and, hence, the full information about the rotational wavepacket under study was extracted. The 2D projection of the obtained rotational wavepacket allowed a direct comparison with the experimentally measured data.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the extension toward the investigation of chemical dynamics, we point out that strong-field-ionisation-induced Coulomb-explosion imaging can be used, for instance, to image the configuration of chiral molecules
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> or internal torsional dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Following the dynamics of such processes with the detail and quality presented here would directly yield a molecular movie of the chemical and, possibly, chirality dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, the very high degree of field-free alignment achieved here would be extremely useful for stereochemistry studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> as well as for molecular-frame imaging experiments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
