<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental movie</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, snapshots of the experimentally recorded molecular movie, that is 2D ion-momentum distributions, are shown for several probe times covering a whole rotational period. The phase of 0 and 2
  <span class="italic">π</span> correspond to 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 38.57 and 120.78 ps after the peak of the first alignment-laser pulse at 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 0, respectively. The simplest snapshot-images, reflecting an unprecedented degree of field-free alignment 〈cos
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>2D</sub>〉 = 0.96, were obtained for the alignment revivals at phases of 0 and 2
  <span class="italic">π</span>, which correspond to the prompt alignment and its revival regarding the second laser pulse. Here, the molecular axes are preferentially aligned along the alignment-laser polarisation. For the antialignment at a phase of 
  <span class="italic">π</span> the molecules are preferentially aligned in a plane perpendicular to the alignment-laser polarisation direction. Simple quadrupolar structures are observed at 
  <span class="italic">π</span>/2 and 3
  <span class="italic">π</span>/2. At intermediate times, at 
  <span class="italic">π</span>/3 or 7
  <span class="italic">π</span>/12, the images display rich angular structures, which could be observed due to the high angular experimental resolution of the recorded movie, which is 4° as derived in the Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>. This rich structure directly reflects the strongly quantum-state selected initial sample exploited in these measurements, whereas the structure would be largely lost in the summation of wavepackets from even a few initially populated states.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Rotational clock depicting the molecular movie of the observed quantum dynamics. Individual experimental VMI images of O
     <span class="sup">+</span> ion-momentum distributions depicting snapshots of the rotational wavepacket over one full period. The displayed data were recorded from the first (prompt) revival at 38.57 ps (0) to the first full revival at 120.78 ps (2
     <span class="italic">π</span>); the phase-evolution of 
     <span class="italic">π</span>/12 between images corresponds to ~3.43 ps and the exact delay times of the individual images are specified. Full movies are available as Supplementary Movies 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> and 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11122_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e583" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
