<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Populations and phases in the wavepacket</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>, the extracted rotational-state populations are shown for the wavepacket created from the rotational ground state after the first and the second alignment-laser pulse. It clearly shows that the rotational-state distribution is broader after the second pulse, reaching up to 
  <span class="italic">J</span> ≥ 16. This also matches the convergence of the Legendre-polynomial series, with eight even terms, derived from the fit to the data above. In Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a> the corresponding phase differences for all populated states relative to the state with the largest population in the wavepacket are shown, where 
  <span class="italic">ϕ</span>(
  <span class="italic">J</span>) is the phase of the complex coefficient 
  <span class="italic">a</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">J</span>
  </sub> in (
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>). Combining these populations and phases it became clear that the very high degree of alignment after the second alignment pulse arises from the combination of the broad distribution of rotational states, reaching large angular momenta, and the very strong and flat rephasing of all significantly populated states at the revival at 120.78 ps, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a> (red). Similarly, the antialignment at 79.58 ps occurs due to alternating phase differences of 
  <span class="italic">π</span> between adjacent populated rotational states, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a> (black).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Populations and phase differences in the rotational wavepacket at alignment and antialignment times. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Rotational-state populations and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> phase differences to the phase of the state with largest population, 
     <span class="italic">J</span> = 2, 
     <span class="italic">J</span> = 6, respectively, at the alignment revival following a single-pulse excitation, 2.78 ps (blue dots), and the two-pulse excitation, 120.78 ps (red dots) as well as for the antialignment at 79.58 ps (black dots, populations coincide with the red dots). Only states with even angular momentum are populated due to the Raman-transition selection rules Δ
     <span class="italic">J</span> = ±2
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11122_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e895" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
