<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study shows that oxidative stability of Li-ion battery electrolytes is governed by non trivial coupling between anion and solvent, and requires their coupling to be simulated explicitly. We find that only one molecule, either the solvent or the anion, loses an electron upon oxidation, but the value of the ionization potential (IP) depends on the chemistry of the components. The overall oxidative stability of the combined solvent-anion system is often significantly lower than the stability of each individual species, and increasing the IP of one of them does not necessarily increase the stability of the resulting electrolyte. By computationally examining a wide range of anion and solvent combinations we find a universal coupling behavior which is explained by the formation of a charge transfer complex upon oxidation, depending on the IP of anions and solvents and their electrostatic interaction. We construct a simple model based on this understanding that is able to quantitatively capture the counterintuitive trends observed in ΔSCF ionization potentials and predicts trends that are consistent with experimental observations. We emphasize that common semi-local density functionals suffer from charge delocalization errors when describing oxidation of representative molecular clusters and are likely to miss the qualitative features and the magnitude of the charge transfer effect that is determined by the electrostatic interaction between local charges resulting from ionization. Using this model, we show how the IP of the pair can be approximated in a simple way. We find that the resulting final state of the electron removal may impact the decomposition process, however, more investigation is needed to understand the coupled effects of solvent reorganization, molecular relaxation and how much the charge transfer may impact the subsequent decomposition reaction. In vacuum, we show how the dipole formation may facilitate Hydrogen abstraction as a subsequent step in solvent decomposition. Results presented here provide direct implications and quantitative rules for designing stable battery electrolytes, emphasizing that both solvent and salt anions must be optimized as a whole.</p>
</sec>
