<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Charge Transport</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The transport of electrical charge in materials where interactions between different states may be present is of interest. The temperature-dependent resistivity for a single crystal of EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>, measured in the (001) plane, is thus shown in 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Figure 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">5</a>
  </a>A. Decreasing resistivity with decreasing temperature, i.e., metallic behavior, is observed. The charge transport is sensitive to the magnetic state of the system: ρ
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">xx</span>
  </sub> (the resistivity in the 
  <span class="italic">x</span> direction with the electric field applied along the 
  <span class="italic">x</span> direction; 
  <span class="italic">x</span> and 
  <span class="italic">y</span> directions are in the plane of the layers, while 
  <span class="italic">z</span> is perpendicular to the layers) shows a drop below the Neel temperature (∼30 K). The in-plane resistivity ρ
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">xx</span>
  </sub> increases slightly at temperatures above the magnetic ordering temperature, starting near 58 K. Also, as seen in 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Figure 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">5</a>
  </a>B, a linear relation between the Hall resistivity ρ
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">yx</span>
  </sub> (field is applied along 
  <span class="italic">z</span>, electric field along 
  <span class="italic">x</span>, and resistivity measured along 
  <span class="italic">y</span>) and applied magnetic field 
  <span class="italic">H</span> is seen at various temperatures. From this data we are able to calculate the concentration of the dominant carriers (
  <span class="italic">n</span>), which are holes, by using 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1/(
  <span class="italic">eR</span>
  <sub>H</sub>) (where 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>H</sub> is the Hall coefficient, obtained from the slopes of 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Figure 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">5</a>
  </a>B, and 
  <span class="italic">e</span> is the electron charge).
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41" href="#ref41">41</a>
  </span> We find that, at 2 K, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> is about 2.9 × 10
  <span class="sup">20</span> cm
  <span class="sup">–3</span>, a relatively large hole concentration. The slope of the ρ
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">yx</span>
  </sub> (
  <span class="italic">H</span>) curve decreases somewhat with increasing temperature, and thus the carrier concentration is increasing with increasing temperature.
 </p>
 <div id="fig5" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Charge transport properties of EuSn
    <sub>2</sub>P
    <sub>2</sub>. (A) Temperature-dependence of the (001) plane resistivity ρ
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">xx</span>
    </sub> between 1.8 and 300 K in the absence of an applied magnetic field. (B) Field-dependence of the Hall resistivity ρ
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">yx</span>
    </sub> at various temperatures (2 K, 10 K, 25 K, 70 K, 100 and 150 K) with applied field from 0 to 9 T. (C) Field-dependence of ρ
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">xx</span>
    </sub> for various temperatures (2, 5, 10, 15, 25, 40, and 70 K) on sweeping applied field from 9 to −9 T. (D) Magnetoresistance at the above temperatures normalized to the values at 0 applied magnetic field.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0005" id="gr5" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncommon behavior for the magnetoresistance is observed (
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Figure 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">5</a>
  </a>C). At low temperatures, the material’s resistivity ρ
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">xx</span>
  </sub> shows a domelike feature when magnetic field is applied perpendicular to the basal plane (i.e., along 
  <span class="italic">z</span>). At 2 K, it decreases by about 9.4 μΩ cm when the field increased from 0 to about 4.1 T, this latter field being where 
  <span class="italic">M</span> vs 
  <span class="italic">H</span> saturates at the same temperature (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Figure 
   <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">2</a>
  </a>A). This behavior is consistent with the anomalous magnetoresistance seen in spin flop systems. The field-dependent resistivity is not quenched until temperatures above 40 K, above the magnetic ordering temperature—the magnetoresistance becomes more normal for temperatures of 70 K and above. Measurements on a second sample suggest that the magnetoresistance in a direction perpendicular to the plane is positive and significantly larger than what is observed in-plane (see 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acscentsci.9b00202/suppl_file/oc9b00202_si_001.pdf" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Figure S1</span>). Further, the out-of-plane resistivity does not appear to saturate by 9 T and may continue to rise with larger applied fields. Although the in-plane magnetoresistance is reminiscent of that observed for WTe
  <sub>2</sub>, the change of resistivity in field is orders of magnitude lower than is seen there, and magnetic moments (from the Eu) are actually present in the current case, while they are absent for WTe
  <sub>2</sub>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42" href="#ref42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43" href="#ref43">43</a>
  </span> Layered ferromagnetic semimetallic (see below) systems like EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> are relatively rare, and thus detailed study will be required to fully understand the magnetoresistance observed in 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Figure 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">5</a>
  </a>D.
 </p>
</sec>
