<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The magnetism observed is consistent with the presence of magnetic Eu
  <span class="sup">2+</span> in our material, but to further confirm the electronic state of Eu in EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>, we performed electron paramagnetic resonance measurements. The obtained data are shown in 
  <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">Figure 
   <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">3</a>
  </a> as the first derivative of the absorption data. We observe a sin-function-like strong broad curve when the applied magnetic field is swept to 2400 G, reaching its maximum around 3200 G. The intensity subsequently drops to zero at 3530 G, which indicates the applied field of the strongest absorption, and continuously becomes more negative, to ∼−6000 (in arbitrary units) at ∼3800 Oe, returning to zero intensity beyond 5000 Oe. The asymmetric line shape is as is usually observed in metals due to the skin effect caused by the small size of the single crystal used compared with the skin depth. According to the principal EPR equation, Δ
  <span class="italic">E</span> = 
  <span class="italic">h</span>ν = 
  <span class="italic">g</span>μ
  <sub>B</sub>
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <sub>0</sub> where Δ
  <span class="italic">E</span> is the splitting energy, 
  <span class="italic">h</span> is Planck’s constant, ν is the frequency of the microwave used, which is 9481 MHz, 
  <span class="italic">g</span> is the Landé 
  <span class="italic">g</span>-factor, μ
  <sub>B</sub> is the Bohr magneton, and 
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <sub>0</sub> is the applied magnetic field of the strongest absorption, we obtain the Landé 
  <span class="italic">g</span>-factor of 1.9184. Based on μ
  <sub>eff</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">g</span>
  <div id="d30e1136" class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_m002.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>μ
  <sub>B</sub> and the 
  <span class="italic">g</span>-factor obtained from the EPR data, we obtain μ
  <sub>eff</sub> = 7.61 μ
  <sub>B</sub>, which is within error of the effective moment obtained from the temperature-dependent magnetic susceptibility (7.91 μ
  <sub>B</sub>).
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41" href="#ref41">41</a>
  </span> Therefore, we find that, for Eu in EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">J</span> = 7/2 and that the Eu ground state is 
  <span class="sup">8</span>S
  <sub>7/2</sub>, i.e., that Eu
  <span class="sup">2+</span> is the primary valence state for Eu.
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Characterization of the Eu spin state at ambient temperature and pressure in EuSn
    <sub>2</sub>P
    <sub>2</sub>. Room temperature electron paramagnetic resonance (EPR) measurement with applied magnetic field from 2300 to 5200 G.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0003" id="gr3" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
