<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimentally Observed Surface Electronic Structures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ARPES spectra, recorded in EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>’s antiferromagnetically ordered state at 10 K, shown in 
  <a rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#fig10">Figures 
   <a rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#fig10">10</a>
  </a> and 
  <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">11</a>, reveal the energies of the occupied electronic bands around the center Γ of the (001) surface projection of the bulk BZ. The outer (meaning the band with 
  <span class="italic">k</span> vector furthest from the center of the surface BZ) band, designated as σ, disperses linearly at about −0.5 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m/s away from the Fermi level (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>F</sub>) and appears as a sharp, intense spectral feature at all incident photon energies. This is in contrast with all of the other observed electronic bands and reflects the fact that this is a surface state. Due to the nonconservation of perpendicular-to-plane momenta of the ARPES method, a range of perpendicular momenta is observed in the ARPES spectra of the bulk bands, making them appear as filled-in regions in ARPES maps, distinct from the surface band where the absence of perpendicular dispersion results in a sharp feature. The most notable bulk band is the heart-shaped band, labeled as γ, in the center of the surface BZ, which disperses upward in energy starting from Gamma to about 80 meV below 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>F</sub> and turning again down. The broad bright feature showing little dispersion in the range of energies between −1 and −2 eV (below 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>F</sub>) is from the localized Eu f states.
 </p>
 <div id="fig10" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 10</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Angle-resolved photoemission study of the band structure of EuSn
    <sub>2</sub>P
    <sub>2</sub>. (A, B) Band dispersion spectra along K−Γ–K taken with 76 and 96 eV photons differ mostly in the relative intensities of the bands due to photoemission selection-rule effects. (C) Incident photon energy 102 eV, shows a wide energy-range band dispersion spectrum along M−Γ–M.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0010" id="gr10" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="fig11" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 11</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>ARPES study continued. (A) Two-dimensional momentum maps at several energies near the Fermi level obtained with two photon energies to enhance the visibility of different features in the band structure. The surface band, designated as σ, is clearly observed. (B) Photon energy-dependent map to follow the band dispersion along the 
    <span class="italic">c</span> crystal axis. The plot is at the energy of −200 meV from 
    <span class="italic">E</span>
    <sub>F</sub>. (Vo for the 
    <span class="italic">k</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">z</span>
    </sub> calculation was set to −10 eV). Different bands are marked with different Greek letters.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0011" id="gr11" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As is often the case with surface states, the surface band σ is found relatively close in 
  <span class="italic">k</span>-space to one of the bulk bands, labeled as α. Additional bulk bands below 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>F</sub>, labeled as β and δ, are also observed. The constant energy maps, 
  <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">Figure 
   <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">11</a>
  </a>, taken at two different incident photon energies (hence, at different 
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> momenta), show the two-dimensional momentum space surface Fermi surfaces: the hexagonal-loop contour of the surface band σ encloses the contours formed by the bulk bands α, β, and γ. These features greatly resemble the −300 meV band contours calculated for the P termination of EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>, 
  <a rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#fig9">Figure 
   <a rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#fig9">9</a>
  </a>B,E,H, although there is less warping toward the corners of the BZ for the surface band than is calculated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Momentum space mapping that included a few neighboring surface BZs revealed no bands in the vicinity of the Fermi level other than those shown around Γ in 
  <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">Figure 
   <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">11</a>
  </a>. While three other crystal terminations (Eu, Sn single and double layer) cannot be excluded in this material without further theoretical and experimental studies, all our data indicate that the (001) crystal surfaces are indeed P-terminated: the calculations for the Eu and Sn terminations show surface states much closer to the center of the BZ. Moreover, our core level spectra (
  <a rid="fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#fig12">Figure 
   <a rid="fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#fig12">12</a>
  </a>) show that the P 2s levels occur at two energies, indicative of two starkly different chemical environments (thus bulk vs surface) for the P atoms. By comparing the band dispersion observed in the ARPES spectra and the DFT calculations, we conclude that the cleaved crystals are some 220 meV hole doped. This is consistent with the large 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-type carrier concentration observed in the Hall measurements.
 </p>
 <div id="fig12" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 12</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Chemistry of the surface core level spectrum of EuSn
    <sub>2</sub>P
    <sub>2</sub> measured using 300 eV incident photons. This shows that the P has two different environments (there is only one type of P in the bulk crystal structure) and therefore is present in both the bulk and the surface.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0012" id="gr12" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We note that the calculations show the bottom of six elliptical electron pockets around the M point of the BZ, which are slightly above the chemical potential (about −220 meV compared to the calculated 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>F</sub>) observed in the ARPES experiments. This explains why no trace of those calculated bands is seen in ARPES (which sees only filled states) and further gives a hint for why the results of potassium adsorption measurements, expected to electron-dope the surface, resulted in no noticeable band shifts—the flat bottom of an electron pocket is associated with a high density of states, and all the states have to be filled for the shifts in other bands to be observed. We also note that our ARPES measurements at varying incident photon energies show remarkably little difference in the band structure of EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> at different perpendicular momenta 
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub>. The bands, most notably the surface state σ, 
  <a rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#fig10">Figures 
   <a rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#fig10">10</a>
  </a> and 
  <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">11</a>, show little dispersion perpendicular to the layers. The three-dimensional Fermi surface thus consists of hexagonally warped cylinders formed by extruding the contours of the bulk bands α and β along the crystal axis 
  <span class="italic">c</span> (
  <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">Figure 
   <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">11</a>
  </a>B).
 </p>
</sec>
