<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The design and discovery of new quantum materials with desired electronic and magnetic functionality, especially materials where quantum effects result in topological electronic properties, is a new challenge and one of the frontiers of research in materials chemistry and materials physics.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1" href="#ref1">1</a>
  </span> There is a crucial need for the discovery of new materials that in particular harness the topological quantum states of matter, to increase our understanding of these newly recognized electronic states and to realize their potential in devices.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2" href="#ref2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3" href="#ref3">3</a>
  </span> In this context, topological insulators (TIs), which support fundamentally different surface (i.e., “topologically protected”) and bulk electronic states, are of particular interest.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4" href="#ref4">4</a>
  </span> When additional quantum phases such as superconductivity, magnetism, or charge density waves are also present, new electronic properties can arise due to their interactions with the surface states.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5" href="#ref5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6" href="#ref6">6</a>
  </span> Currently, the study of such systems in materials physics frequently focuses on heterostructures consisting of TI/magnetic multilayers.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7" href="#ref7">7</a>−
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10" href="#ref10">10</a>
  </span> Unfortunately, these systems cannot be widely studied due to the uncommon procedures required to make them. Thus, the design of novel magnetic topological quantum materials that are widely synthetically accessible is highly sought. Theorists have scoured the ICSD for previously reported materials that can display topological electronic properties, but the design of totally new topological quantum materials remains rare, especially for cases where the interactions of different quantum states are expected.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11" href="#ref11">11</a>−
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16" href="#ref16">16</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Located at the Zintl border in the periodic table, the element Sn has moderate electronegativity, thus allowing it to participate in various types of bonding interactions. This provides flexibility in tuning the electronic properties of materials in which the electronic states of tin are dominant.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17" href="#ref17">17</a>
  </span> Further, being a 5p-based element, it is expected to display the effects of spin–orbit coupling.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18" href="#ref18">18</a>
  </span> Tin may be the critical elemental constituent in the topological crystalline insulator SnTe, for example, and the fabrication of Stanene thin films has been accomplished with the goal of establishing its topological electronic properties.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19" href="#ref19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20" href="#ref20">20</a>
  </span> Thus, the inclusion of tin in quantum materials is a good chemical rule when designing quantum materials with potentially unconventional electronic functionality.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A second chemical design rule for finding novel functional materials is based on symmetry and crystal structure. Experience has shown that low-dimensional materials are ideal platforms for realizing topological electronic states due to the weak interlayer interactions and subsequent partial confinement of the electronic states that is frequently present. Rhombohedral Bi
  <sub>2</sub>Se
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21" href="#ref21">21</a>
  </span> and Bi
  <sub>2</sub>Te
  <sub>3</sub>,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22" href="#ref22">22</a>
  </span> and trigonal Mg
  <sub>3</sub>Bi
  <sub>2</sub>, are examples.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23" href="#ref23">23</a>
  </span> The presence of elements with strong spin–orbit coupling in layers based on triangles is a common structural motif in topological quantum materials.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, as a third design rule, the inclusion of magnetic lanthanide elements, if well-placed in the crystal structure, can result in the presence of ordered magnetic states that interact relatively weakly with the other electronic states present, due to the localized nature of 4f electrons.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24" href="#ref24">24</a>
  </span> With appropriately selected rare earth elements at the appropriate concentration in the appropriate crystal structure, magnetically ordered states can be found at experimentally accessible temperatures. In materials with unconventional electronic structures, this allows for the interactions between magnetic and topological states to be studied.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although nonmagnetic, the ternary Bi
  <sub>2</sub>Te
  <sub>3</sub>-type compound SrSn
  <sub>2</sub>As
  <sub>2</sub> has been theoretically predicted to host three-dimensional Dirac states around the Fermi level.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25" href="#ref25">25</a>−
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27" href="#ref27">27</a>
  </span> Moreover, NaSn
  <sub>2</sub>As
  <sub>2</sub>, with the same structure, is reported to be a superconductor below 1.3 K.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28" href="#ref28">28</a>
  </span> Consisting of buckled SnAs honeycomb networks separated by Sr
  <span class="sup">2+</span> or Na
  <span class="sup">+</span>, consideration of these compounds and the above materials design criteria inspired us to incorporate a magnetic rare earth element (Eu
  <span class="sup">2+</span>) between Sn-based layers with a geometry based on triangles to yield both an unconventional electronic band structure and magnetic properties in a single material.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, here we report a new material by design, EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>. We report its crystallographically and magnetically ordered structures, determined via single crystal X-ray and neutron diffraction. We observe a transition to an A-type antiferromagnetic state (alternating-orientation ferromagnetic layers) near 30 K, and below that temperature significant magnetoresistance, a type-II nodal-line semimetal when spin–orbit coupling is ignored. Electronic structure calculations reveal that EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> is an antiferromagnetic topological insulator when Hubbard (
  <span class="italic">U</span>) is included. The detailed interplay of unconventional electronic states (“band inversion”), spin–orbit coupling, and the surface states is presented theoretically. The presence of the surface states is confirmed by angle-resolved photoelectron spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements. Our new quantum material is easily grown as bulk crystals, displays magnetic ordering at accessible temperatures, and displays topological surface states, thus allowing the interactions of ferromagnetism and topological surface states to be observed in a bulk material with a simple crystal structure.
 </p>
</sec>
