<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Magnetic Characterization</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To get insight into the magnetic properties of EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>, we performed field-dependent magnetization measurements at 2 K with applied magnetic fields parallel and perpendicular to the 
  <span class="italic">c</span>-axis. The results are shown in 
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Figure 
   <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">2</a>
  </a>A. The field-dependent behavior is characteristic of that of a ferromagnetic material—the magnetic moment of EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> saturates at ∼2.8 T for applied fields perpendicular to the 
  <span class="italic">c</span>-axis and ∼4.1 T for fields parallel to the 
  <span class="italic">c</span>-axis. Accordingly, a strong anisotropy of magnetization is observed, with the easy axis in the basal plane, perpendicular to the 
  <span class="italic">c</span>-axis. The saturated magnetizations are ∼6.0 μ
  <sub>B</sub>/Eu for both orientations.
 </p>
 <div id="fig2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Field-dependent, direction-dependent, and temperature-dependent magnetic properties of EuSn
    <sub>2</sub>P
    <sub>2</sub>. (A) Field-dependent magnetization for the two crystal orientations measured at 2 K where red balls and blue squares represent magnetic field parallel and perpendicular to the 
    <span class="italic">c</span>-axis, respectively. (B) Magnetic susceptibility as a function of temperature measured in an external field of μ
    <sub>0</sub>
    <span class="italic">H</span> = 500 Oe, both perpendicular (blue) and parallel (red) to the 
    <span class="italic">c</span>-axis. The inset shows the temperature-dependent inverse susceptibility, measured for different sample orientations. The green line is the Curie–Weiss fit to the high-temperature data.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0002" id="gr2" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The temperature-dependent magnetic susceptibility was measured under an external field of 500 Oe from 2 to 300 K. A transition to an antiferromagnetic state (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>N</sub>) is seen at around 30 K. The larger magnetic susceptibility in the perpendicular field also indicates the anisotropic ordered magnetism in EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>, i.e., that ferromagnetic ordering is preferred within the 
  <span class="italic">ab</span>-plane rather than along the 
  <span class="italic">c</span>-axis. At temperatures higher than 30 K, classic Curie–Weiss behavior is observed.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40" href="#ref40">40</a>
  </span> The effective moment and Curie–Weiss (CW) temperatures Θ
  <sub>⊥</sub> and Θ
  <sub>//</sub> were fitted from 150 to 300 K by using the Curie–Weiss formula χ = χ
  <sub>0</sub> + 
  <div id="d30e1039" class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_m001.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> where χ
  <sub>0</sub> is the temperature-independent part of the magnetic susceptibility, 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>A</sub> is Avogadro’s number, 
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>B</sub> is the Boltzmann constant, μ
  <sub>eff</sub> is the effective moment, and Θ
  <sub>CW</sub> is the Curie–Weiss temperature. The Curie–Weiss temperatures in perpendicular and parallel fields are 31.8(1) and 31.6(1) K, within error of each other, while the average effective moment is 7.91(3) μ
  <sub>B</sub>/Eu. The magnetic characteristics above 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>N</sub> are essentially isotropic.
 </p>
</sec>
