<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Magnetic Structure</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To better understand the magnetic properties of our new quantum material, we performed single crystal neutron diffraction on EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>. Antiferromagnetic order onsets at 30 K, as indicated by observing extra Bragg peaks with a propagation vector of (0 0 1.5). The ordering parameter was measured at (0 0 4.5) in reciprocal space (see 
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Figure 
   <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">4</a>
  </a>A) and indicates that 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>N</sub> ∼ 30 K by determination of the intersection of a linear fitting regime (30–50 K) and a two-term power law fit at low temperatures with 
  <div id="d30e1209" class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_m003.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> where 
  <span class="italic">A</span>, pl, pu, and 
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">c</span>
  </sub> are all constants.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33" href="#ref33">33</a>
  </span> The magnetic structure is determined by modeling the magnetic reflections collected at 4.5 K. The lattice parameters (
  <span class="italic">a</span> = 4.069(2) Å, 
  <span class="italic">c</span> = 25.935(9) Å) at 4.5 K are smaller than those determined by single crystal X-ray diffraction (
  <span class="italic">a</span> = 4.097(1) Å, 
  <span class="italic">c</span> = 26.162(5) Å) at room temperature due to thermal contraction. Refining the nuclear reflections collected at 4.5 K yields 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>F</sub> = 9.15% and 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>F</sub>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 17.69%. The magnetic structure refinement reaches the best fit (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>F</sub> = 6.71% and 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>F</sub>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 12.7%) with the magnetic moment of 5.65 (3) μ
  <sub>B</sub>/Eu oriented in the 
  <span class="italic">ab</span>-plane at 4.5 K (see 
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Figure 
   <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">4</a>
  </a>B), consistent with the field-dependent magnetization measurements. As shown in 
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Figure 
   <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">4</a>
  </a>B, the result is ferromagnetic Eu layers antiferromagnetically coupled with their nearest neighbor layers leading to A-type antiferromagnetism for EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub>. The inset of 
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Figure 
   <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">4</a>
  </a>A illustrates the neutron diffraction intensity maps at both 30 and 4.5 K, showing the magnetic peak at (0 0 4.5).
 </p>
 <div id="fig4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Magnetic structure of EuSn
    <sub>2</sub>P
    <sub>2</sub>. (A) (main panel) Temperature-dependence of the magnetic scattering. The pixel number is for the selected region of interest (enclosed in the purple rectangle insets). The data indicate that 
    <span class="italic">T</span>
    <sub>N</sub> ∼ 30 K, resulting from the fit of the red curves to the data. (insets, top right) Magnetic signal intensity map at 30.0 K for the reciprocal lattice plane (0 0 4.5). (insets, bottom left) Magnetic signal intensity map at 4.5 K for the reciprocal lattice plane (0 0 4.5). (B) Magnetic unit cell of EuSn
    <sub>2</sub>P
    <sub>2</sub>. The red arrows indicate the orientation of magnetic moments for each layer of Eu atoms.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="oc-2019-00202n_0004" id="gr4" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
