<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary and Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The novel quantum material EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> was designed based on chemical criteria to display both magnetism and electronic surface states. The hypothesized material was discovered, and crystals were grown using the Sn-flux method. Its crystal structure and physical properties were characterized. Its crystal structure consists of hexagonal Eu, and P layers surrounding a Sn bilayer. It has a positive Curie–Weiss temperature of Θ
  <sub>CW</sub> = 31(1) K, showing the dominance of ferromagnetic spin correlations at high temperatures, but it orders antiferromagnetically near 30 K. Its ordered magnetic structure, refined from neutron diffraction, shows antiferromagnetically coupled in-plane-ferromagnetic Eu
  <span class="sup">2+</span> layers. The temperature-dependent resistance of EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> is weakly metallic in character, and an anomalous magnetoresistance is found below the magnetic ordering temperature and below applied magnetic fields of 4 T, where the magnetization saturates with applied magnetic field.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electronic structure calculations support magnetic ordering as the energetically stable state of the system at low temperatures, and further confirm that the observed magnetic moments solely arise from the Eu
  <span class="sup">2+</span> present. Calculations including both SOC and correlation parameter 
  <span class="italic">U</span> best describe the positions of the Eu f states between 1 and 2 eV below 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>F</sub>, and further show that EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> is an antiferromagnetic topological insulator (the energies of the valence band and conduction bands overlap but for electrons of different wave vectors in the Brillouin zone). The bulk band structure is unconventional in that metal states contribute significantly just below the Fermi energy while nonmetal states contribute significantly just above the Fermi energy. The calculations also predict the presence of Dirac-like surface states within the bulk energy gap, both above and below the Fermi energy. The experimental ARPES study shows that surface states are indeed present in the antiferromagnetically ordered state at 10 K but differ in a minor way from the calculations for a P-terminated (001) surface. Although we have observed much about the basic properties of this new quantum material, more detailed work on the properties from the physics perspective is required to determine whether it is unique in that it shows both antiferromagnetism and surface states at low temperatures. The accessible temperatures involved, the simple crystal structure, the ability to fabricate bulk crystals, and the combination of properties make the quantum material EuSn
  <sub>2</sub>P
  <sub>2</sub> an ideal platform for the detailed study of the interplay of topological electronic states with magnetism.
 </p>
</sec>
