<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First-Principles Molecular Dynamics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another viable path is becoming possible thanks to improvements in computational facilities, in order to access at kinetic information through first-principles molecular dynamics simulations. However, computationally severe storing and time constraints permitting to obtain myriads of “on-the-fly trajectories” require a great effort toward the aim of generating realistic reactive kinetic data: this in spite of the fact that a wide research activity has been pursued, aiming at developing techniques capable of accurately predicting kinetic reaction rate constants from molecular dynamics simulations. Among examples that have been tackled in recent years, we cite (Pomerantz et al., 
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">2005</a>; Coutinho et al., 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">2015a</a>; Döntgen et al., 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">2015</a>; Fleming et al., 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2016</a>; Wu et al., 
  <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">2019</a>) and references therein. However, calculation of reaction rate constants has been limited by the arduous procedures both to accurately characterize reactive activated complexes of many body systems and to overcome the inherent difficulties of producing a number of trajectories with statistical consistency and reasonable completeness in the filling of the dynamically relevant parts of the phase-space. Recently, several works have been yielding values with reliable accuracy: overestimates due to limited sampling of phase-space, when experimental values are available for comparison, may exploit empirical calibration (Coutinho et al., 
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">2016</a>, 
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">2017</a>, 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">2018a</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
