<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenomenological Considerations and the Role of the Transitivity Concept</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimentally and computationally generated kinetic data for polyatomic molecules provide reaction rate constants with the implicit fingerprint of the microscopical variables at work in the reactive process (Angell, 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">1995</a>; Kohen et al., 
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">1999</a>; Limbach et al., 
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">2006</a>; Giordano and Russell, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">2018</a>; Capitelli and Pietanza, 
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">2019</a>, and references therein). Application of the techniques discussed in previous remarks is tremendously laborious for many-body systems: when the Arrhenius law is not obeyed at low temperature transitivity function guides us to an as a fruitful and consistent approach. As discussed in this article the approach turns out to be a powerful tool, capable of establishing a connection between canonical data and microcanonical information, permitting comparisons among apparently uncorrelated formulations: it also allows interpretation of empirical parameters, for example for the AM, ASCC, VFT and NTS formulas considered in this paper. Previous (Tsallis and Bukman, 
  <a rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" href="#B91">1996</a>; Lenzi et al., 
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">2001</a>; JiangLin et al., 
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">2006</a>; Zhou and Du, 
  <a rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100">2013</a>) and concomitant (Zhou and Du, 
  <a rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" href="#B101">2014</a>; Guo and Du, 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">2015</a>; Rosa et al., 
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">2016</a>; Junior et al., 
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">2019</a>) efforts have been dedicated to provide also a connection of anomalous kinetic diffusion effects while surmounting a potential barrier 
  <span class="italic">via</span> variants of Fokker-Planck equation, tackling a class of phenomenologically physicochemical diffusion process.
 </p>
</sec>
