<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study a powerful and advanced combination of experimental (TRLFS and CW-spectroscopy) and theoretical (PARAFAC and TD-DFT) methods was proposed for the speciation of luminescent metals. It has been demonstrated to be successful for uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) hydrolysis without contradictions to the literature. A consistent spectroscopic detection as well as identification of species distribution of major hydrolysis species (uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) aquo ion, 1 : 1, 3 : 5, 3 : 7, 1 : 3) within one experimental setup (fixed uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) concentration [U] = 10
  <span class="sup">–5</span> M, pH 2 to 11) was achieved for the first time. Spectra shape and lifetimes were found to be well comparable with those in the literature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Deconvolution of strong overlapping excitation spectra is not straightforward. As before, PARAFAC has demonstrated its validity and robustness. Therefore the deconvolution of heavy metal luminescence data, based on differences in excitation, can be applied at room temperature. Individual excitation spectra of detected uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) hydrolysis species were extracted for a UV range from 180 nm to 370 nm. This impressively demonstrates for the first time that excitation in this region is highly sensitive and specific. According to the TD-DFT calculations, excitation in this spectral range is due to ligand-to-metal charge transfer (LMCT) and the spectra features are ligand specific (water, hydroxo, oxo). Therefore even the shape of the uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) excitation spectra is indicative of complex stoichiometry.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Luminescence decay is an excellent parameter to discriminate between several uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) complexes. However, a correlation with structure is difficult and reported lifetimes are often inconsistent.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="cit60" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit60">60</a>
  </span> Moreover the choice of the laser wavelength for TRLFS measurements can directly influence the results. A better discrimination of several uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) compounds with accessible structural information might be achieved by the ‘site sensitive excitation’ here proposed. Therefore further elucidation of the thermodynamics of uranyl(
  <span class="sc">vi</span>) polynuclear species becomes possible.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This combination of experimental and theoretical methods can be applied for better understanding the speciation of luminescent metals in general. In addition to actinides (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span> Np, U, Am, Cm) an application area is coordination chemistry of rare earth elements (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span> Ce, Nd, Eu, Tb) which are of strategic importance for high-technology products world-wide.
 </p>
</sec>
