<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material and experimental</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample preparation was carried out in an inert gas glove box (nitrogen) to avoid carbonate complexation. Uranyl(
   <span class="sc">vi</span>) solutions (10
   <span class="sup">–5</span> M U(
   <span class="sc">vi</span>) in 10
   <span class="sup">–2</span> M NaClO
   <sub>4</sub> (Merck), unless stated otherwise) were prepared directly before the experiment. Same solutions without uranyl(
   <span class="sc">vi</span>) were used as blank. No precipitation was visually observed during the measurements. Pure water was degassed with nitrogen and stored in a glove box. Uranyl(
   <span class="sc">vi</span>) stock solution (10
   <span class="sup">–1</span> M in 0.1 M HClO
   <sub>4</sub>) was prepared from solid UO
   <sub>2</sub>(NO
   <sub>3</sub>)
   <sub>2</sub>·6H
   <sub>2</sub>O (Chemapol) as previously described.
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="cit46" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit46">46</a>
   </span> NaClO
   <sub>4</sub> solution was prepared before each experimental series. The sample pH ranged from 2 to 11 and was adjusted by adding suitable amounts of NaOH and HClO
   <sub>4</sub> (Merck). The pH was measured directly after the luminescence measurements, to avoid quenching by chloride from the electrode. The pH measurements were carried out with a glass electrode (SenTix Mic, WTW), which was calibrated with 3 buffer solutions (NIST/PTB standard buffers).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time-resolved laser-induced fluorescence spectroscopy (TRLFS)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A quadrupled (266 nm) Nd:YAG laser (minilite, Continuum) with 0.3 mJ per 4 ns pulse was used for excitation of the sample in a quartz glass cuvette. A light guide was used for transmission of emitted light to the spectrometer (Horiba, slit width 200 μm). A 100 lines per mm grate produced monochromatic light (resolution circa 0.5 nm) that was detected by a cooled (–20 °C) ICCD camera (Horiba). The initial delay was set to 0.1 μs and an aperture of 4 μs was used. An average of 75 accumulations was collected and the baseline correction was performed with the software LabSpec 5 (Horiba). A 150 ns step size for 148 spectra (setup 25 °C) and a 70 ns step size for 101 spectra (setup 1 °C) were used, respectively. Sample temperature was fixed with a controlled Peltier element (TC125 Temperature Control, Quantum Northwest).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Continuous wave (CW) spectroscopy</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photoluminescence measurements were performed on a fluorescence spectrofluorometer (QuantaMaster 40) equipped with a 75 W xenon arc lamp. Wavelengths were chosen by motorized excitation and emission monochromators with a bandwidth of 10 nm and 2 nm, respectively. Spectra were recorded by scanning emission with 1 nm resolution at each excitation wavelength. This procedure was iterated for the entire excitation range with 5 nm resolution. An integration time of 1 s was chosen. Sample temperature was fixed with a controlled Peltier element (identical to the previous). Data from CW spectroscopy were baseline corrected with the recorded blanks.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
