<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Networking and Networked Software Applications</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Networking and assembling networked software applications for the Molecular science community begun within COST (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cost.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.cost.eu/</span>) Action D23 (METACHEM) and D37 (Grid Computing in Chemistry: GRIDCHEM). In METACHEM the activities of various Molecular Science research laboratories were networked on a shared computing platform made of a geographically distributed cluster of heterogeneous computers operating as a single virtual parallel machine (Foster and Kesselman, 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">1999</a>). In the following Action GRIDCHEM Grid solutions and paradigms for molecular science research developed by D23 were consolidated on the grid. GRIDCHEM leveraged the creation and the use of distributed computing infrastructures (the “Grid”) to drive collaborative computer modeling and simulation in chemistry toward “new frontiers in complexity and a new regime of time-to-solution” (GRIDCHEM, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">2006–2010</a>). At more infrastructural level, the European projects EGEE (Enabling Grids for E-sciencE, 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cordis.europa.eu/project/rcn/87264_en.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://cordis.europa.eu/project/rcn/87264_en.html</span>), first, and the EGI (European Grid Infrastructure, 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European-Grid-Infrastructure" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European-Grid-Infrastructure</span>), next, provided various disciplines, including Molecular Science, with a world class level platform for computational collaborations. In particular, during EGEE-III, the first pilot computational application called GEMS (Laganà et al., 
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">2010</a>)—designed to enable the distributed calculation of cross sections and rate coefficients starting from the ab initio computation of the electronic structure of the molecular system followed by the fitting of the computed ab initio points using a combination of analytic formulae into a proper functional representation of the interaction in short, intermediate and long-range regions—was implemented. This allows at present routine computation of reactive and nonreactive properties of elementary systems based on the desired number of molecular geometries (Storchi et al., 
  <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">2006</a>) and collisional paths (Gervasi and Laganà, 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2004</a>) by distributing them on the grid. The scheme of the most recent evolution of GEMS toward the atomistic simulation of the kinetics of more complex systems, together with the related “data analysis and validation” and “open archive and reuse” in a cloud service perspective, is sketched in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F10" href="#F10">Figure 10</a>.
 </p>
 <div id="F10" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 10</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Block diagram of the present evolution of GEMS.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fchem-07-00309-g0010" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The molecular science community has been accordingly organized into the COMPCHEM (Laganà et al., 
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">2010</a>) VO first and in the CMMST (Chemistry, Molecular and Materials Science a Technologies) VRC (Virtual Research Community) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wiki.egi.eu/wiki/Towards_a_CMMST_VRC" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://wiki.egi.eu/wiki/Towards_a_CMMST_VRC</span>) later. On a national basis, then, the different disciplinary communities were gathered in Joint Research Units (JRU), for example in Italy with IGI (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.italiangrid.it" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.italiangrid.it</span>), in order to give a higher local momentum to networked applications. In this spirit, the following activities were pursued in networked Molecular Sciences: 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>orchestrate the initiatives of the e-infrastructure experts and of the disciplinary researchers so as to enable an effective intra- and trans-community networked implementation and coordination of a collaborative/competitive (synergistic) research environment by allowing a selection of compute resources based on quality parameters;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>compose higher level of complexity chained applications through the coordinated usage of distributed hardware and software, the creation of specialized web portals and workflows facilitating the production of data and innovative know how, the direct re-use of the produced data and knowledge in education, training and further research, the rewarding of the work done on behalf of the community by proactive members;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>produce and provide computational services useful to enhancing multi-scale treatments necessary to reproduce the observables of realistic systems in the areas of energy, environment, materials, pharmacology, biology, biotechnologies, medicine, etc., by means of state-of-the-art first principle electronic structure and nuclei dynamics computations, high level of accuracy multiscale design of complex molecular systems, knowledge management for training and education in sciences and technologies;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>turn (in collaboration with partner SMEs), the versatility of the adopted e-infrastructure tools, the richness of the developed CMMST knowledge and the credit mechanism supporting the synergistic operating into a business model, enabling an efficient transfer of the activities to the market, thereby ensuring business sustainability by leveraging synergistic models.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
