<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. Assembling Cloud Computing Infrastructures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cloud-oriented computing infrastructure developed for our calculations is an embryonic platform of the Beowulf type running under the OpenStack platform sketched in the lower side of Figure 3 of Vitillaro and Laganà (
  <a rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" href="#B88">2018</a>) named HERLA (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beowulf_cluster" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beowulf_cluster</span>). HERLA has been established at the Dipartimento di Chimica, Biologia e Biotecnologia (DCBB) of the University of Perugia. The platform consists of a couple of HPC clusters, (CG/training) and (FE/research) running Scientific Linux 6.x with two distinct access nodes. The clusters are connected using NIS in a single-image system and are used first for students' training (CG) and second for scientists' research (FE). The management of Herla is presently carried out by the CMS
  <span class="sup">2</span> Consortium (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cms-2.org/index.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cms-2.org/index.php</span>) of the University of Perugia, CNR-ISTM - Perugia unit and the two companies Master-UP s.r.l. and Molecular Horizon s.r.l. Recently, cloud images of HERLA (VHERLA) have been created and deployed in a storage system (CEPH located at DCBB). This effort was meant to support as well the activities of the School on Open Science Cloud (SOSC17) held in Perugia on June 2017 in collaboration with the Department of Physics and Geology (DFG) and INFN Perugia (running under the INFN OpenStack platform sketched in the lhs upper side of Figure 3 of Vitillaro and Laganà, 
  <a rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" href="#B88">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Later, as sketched in the rhs side of Figure 4 of Vitillaro and Laganà (
  <a rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" href="#B88">2018</a>), the images of VHERLA were allocated to the OpenStack GARR Cloud platform in Palermo within the project “cnr-istm” and were used to install the version VHERLA(GARR-CLOUD) hscw (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hscw.herla.unipg.it/ganglia/?p=2&amp;c=FrontEnd" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hscw.herla.unipg.it/ganglia/?p=2&amp;c=FrontEnd</span>) bearing the following features: Access node hscw (2 core, 4Gb RAM, 200Gb storage) and Cluster (7 nodes, 96 cores, 360Gb RAM, 700Gb storage). The Access node hscw, can be reached at the IP address [90.147.189.20] via SSH and the following 7 nodes, 96core, 380Gb, 512Gb scratch are defined at Torque(PBS)/MAUI as [Intel Xeon E3-12xx v2(Ivy Bridge)/2.6Ghz]. This allowed the generation of a virtual cluster for Molecular Sciences that has also been used for the training of the Students of the XIII EM TCCM (European Master in Theoretical Chemistry and Computational Modeling) Intensive Course (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-old.chm.unipg.it/chimgen/mb/theo2/TCCM2018/EM-TCCM2018/EM-TCCM/Welcome.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www-old.chm.unipg.it/chimgen/mb/theo2/TCCM2018/EM- TCCM2018/EM-TCCM/Welcome.html</span>) with details at the following reference web page: 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hscw.herla.unipg.it" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hscw.herla.unipg.it</span> URL.
 </p>
</sec>
