<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Developing a Sustainable Operational Model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As to the operational model we have already developed a sustainable open collaborative user/producer (Prosumer), whose prototype has been first implemented for running the ECTN (European Chemistry Thematic Network (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ectn.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ectn.eu/</span>)) EChemTest 
  <span class="italic">e</span>-tests based on the use of the educational LibreEOL (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://echemtest.libreeol.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://echemtest.libreeol.org</span>) and GLOREP (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://glorep.unipg.it/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://glorep.unipg.it/</span>) services Laganà et al., 
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">2018a</a>. An important feature of the Prosumer model adopted for EChemTest was the containment of costs by leveraging the fact that the ECTN member HEIs running 
  <span class="italic">e</span>-test Self Evaluation Sessions (SES)s for the assessment of the Chemistry competences of their own students already act at the same time as consumers of EChemTest services and as producers of Question and Answers (Q&amp;A)s, assessors of students' competences, designers and developers of e-learning materials (a typical cluster of the horizontal type) for the harmonization at the European level of the assessment of Molecular Science competences. This behavior is quite usual in education and research activities in which knowledge is a common good to be at the same time produced and consumed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The only additional action needed to the end of making the prosumer model sustainable was to assign to a company the role of market spinner. For EChemTest this role was taken by Master-Up s.r.l. thanks to its nature as a former spinoff of the University of Perugia (started in the year 2004 out of the aggregation of some members of the Chemistry Department and the Mathematics and Informatics Department who were experts in molecular dynamics simulations and computer science) devoted to design, production and marketing services for technological innovation as its main goal. As a matter of fact, the mission of Master-Up has been since the very beginning the design and development of cloud services for molecular sciences and technologies. In the particular case of EChemTest, the Prosumer model has led to the production in the year 2018 of 2622 SESs, with an increase of 5 percent over the previous year. Further efforts have also been spent in the period up to January 2019 for the implementation of the already mentioned MOlecular Simulator Enabled Cloud Services (MOSEX), a European Open Science Cloud Pilot designed as a follow-up of the EGI COMPCHEM VO activities for the following applications: 
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Molecular electronic structure and dynamical properties programs of GEMS (including the QC ones reported reported in this paper)</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Drug design programs (QSPR and 3D QSPR models)</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Distributed repository of molecular science data (including the IOCHEM (
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iochem-bd.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.iochem-bd.org/</span>) software for the organization, publication and storage of molecular information on materials)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Dissemination and evaluation of molecular knowledge through GLOREP (Distributed repository of shared Learning Objects and educational tools) for the assemblage of Molecular Science multimedia Learning Objects.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
