<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BN-polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (BN-PAHs) have received increasing interest over the past few years [
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">1</a>–
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">5</a>], particularly in the field of materials science [
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">6</a>]. The presence of a polarized B–N bond induces significant changes in the photophysical properties of these compounds when compared to their PAH analogues containing only non-polar C=C bonds. This fact opens up new opportunities for creating improved optoelectronic devices [
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">7</a>–
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The introduction of substituents is known to have a substantial influence on the photophysical properties of PAHs. However, although some particular examples of the impact of substituents on the behaviour of BN-PAHs have been reported [
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">16</a>–
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">21</a>], systematic studies are not usually performed, probably due to the difficulties associated with their synthesis and the lack of general methods for their functionalization [
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have recently designed an efficient synthesis for one of the simplest BN-PAHs, namely BN-phenanthrene 
  <span class="bold">1a</span> [
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">23</a>]. We are interested in evaluating the reactivity [
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">24</a>] and properties of 
  <span class="bold">1a</span> in greater detail as this could provide valuable information that leads to a better understanding of the behaviour of BN-aromatics. Interestingly, 
  <span class="bold">1a</span> turned out to be weakly fluorescent [
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">23</a>], in contrast to other BN-phenanthrene isomers described previously [
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">25</a>–
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">26</a>]. The presence of aryl or amino substituents at C1, which can be introduced via bromination and subsequent palladium-catalyzed cross coupling, does not have a significant impact on the fluorescence of these compounds (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>) [
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">23</a>]. In order to gain a deeper understanding of the photophysical properties of the BN-phenanthrene core, we decided to evaluate the influence of substituents located in other positions. We were particularly interested in the effect of alkynyl substituents, as their presence in PAHs is known to alter the fluorescence properties thereof markedly [
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">27</a>–
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">29</a>]. In this regard, we have recently described a methodology for the synthesis of a chloro-substituted BN-benzo[
  <span class="italic">c</span>]phenanthrene and its subsequent derivatization via palladium-catalyzed cross-coupling reactions [
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">30</a>], and we envisioned that this reaction could be used to prepare C7 substituted BN-phenanthrenes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>BN-phenanthrene 
    <span class="bold">1a</span> and synthesis of substituted derivatives proposed in this work.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="Beilstein_J_Org_Chem-15-1257-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herein we report the synthesis of chloro-substituted BN-phenanthrene 
  <span class="bold">1b</span>, its derivatization via palladium-catalyzed cross-coupling reactions and the significant effect of the substituents on the fluorescence properties of the compounds prepared.
 </p>
</sec>
