<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-micromachines-10-00439" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ternary I-III-VI
  <sub>2</sub> nanocrystals (NCs), including AgInS
  <sub>2</sub> (AIS) and CuInS
  <sub>2</sub> (CIS), have been developed recently to replace the toxic Cd- and Pb-contained NCs as fluorescence label and probes for biomedical and biological investigations [
  <a rid="B1-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-micromachines-10-00439">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-micromachines-10-00439">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-micromachines-10-00439">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-micromachines-10-00439">4</a>]. These semiconductor nanomaterials have many advantages, such as high absorption coefficient, low toxicity, high energy conversion efficiency, and stability to solar radiation [
  <a rid="B5-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-micromachines-10-00439">5</a>]. Therefore, they have great potential applications in photoelectric conversion and photocatalysis. These NCs have also been used in light-emitting diodes [
  <a rid="B6-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-micromachines-10-00439">6</a>] and solar cells [
  <a rid="B7-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-micromachines-10-00439">7</a>]. I-III-VI
  <sub>2</sub>-based ternary and quaternary semiconductors, such as CuInSe
  <sub>2</sub> [
  <a rid="B8-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-micromachines-10-00439">8</a>], CuGaSe
  <sub>2</sub> [
  <a rid="B9-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-micromachines-10-00439">9</a>], CuGa
  <sub>x</sub>In
  <sub>2-x</sub>S
  <sub>3.5</sub> [
  <a rid="B10-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-micromachines-10-00439">10</a>], and CuGa
  <sub>1-x</sub>In
  <sub>x</sub>Se
  <sub>2</sub> [
  <a rid="B11-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-micromachines-10-00439">11</a>], have been synthesized. In recent years, ternary AIS has become one of the research focuses in quantum dot synthesis and application investigation. The AIS nanoparticles possess a tunable band gap from 1.87 to 2.03 eV, which matches the solar spectrum very well and does not contain elemental Se. It can be used as a photoelectric conversion material to fabricate high-efficiency solar cells [
  <a rid="B12-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-micromachines-10-00439">12</a>]. In addition, the fluorescence emission peak of AIS is also adjustable from visible to near infrared, and it possesses good photostability and large absorption coefficient, making it suitable for lighting and bio-imaging in vivo and in vitro [
  <a rid="B13-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-micromachines-10-00439">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-micromachines-10-00439">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AIS nanocrystals have been synthesized by several methods, such as thermal decomposition of sulfur-containing complexes of different metals or direct reaction of sulfur with metal ions in the presence of coating agents [
  <a rid="B15-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-micromachines-10-00439">15</a>]. In the synthetic reaction, metal ions usually form metal complexprecursors with amines or dodecyl mercaptan to ensure controlled growth during the synthesis process. Sulfur powder, mercaptan, dithiocarbamate, or carbon disulfide was used as sulfur sources. Metal mercaptan and dithiocarbamate were the single precursors to provide both metal ions and sulfur elements. The optical properties of bulk AgInS
  <sub>2</sub> were studied in 1976 [
  <a rid="B16-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-micromachines-10-00439">16</a>]. Redjai et al. [
  <a rid="B17-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-micromachines-10-00439">17</a>] investigated the donor–acceptor pair transition in bulk AgInS
  <sub>2</sub> by time-resolved spectroscopy, and obtained the thermal quenching curve of its emission. The effect of defects in bulk and AgInS
  <sub>2</sub> film, such as vacancies and interstitial atoms, has also been carefully tested [
  <a rid="B18-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-micromachines-10-00439">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-micromachines-10-00439">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-micromachines-10-00439">20</a>]. Recently, it has been observed that AgInS
  <sub>2</sub> nanocrystals have wide fluorescence emission peaks and relatively large Stokes shifts. It has been suggested that its fluorescence emission was caused by carrier recombination captured by energy levels in the band gap formed by structural defects. It was the characteristic of donor–acceptor pair transition [
  <a rid="B21-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-micromachines-10-00439">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, the AIS core has relatively lower photoluminescence (PL) quantum yields (QYs) [
  <a rid="B22-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-micromachines-10-00439">22</a>]. Over the last decade, the quantum yields of AIS have been enhanced by two approaches. The first method is the synthesis of core–shell structure coated with a ZnS shell [
  <a rid="B23-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-micromachines-10-00439">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-micromachines-10-00439">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-micromachines-10-00439">25</a>]. More reports demonstrated the improvement of QYs for core–shell AIS NCs with smaller cores synthesized at lower reaction temperatures. However, smaller cores decreased the crystallinity and increased surface defects, leading to a cumbersome experimental procedure [
  <a rid="B26-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-micromachines-10-00439">26</a>]. The second strategy for increasing QYs and tuning photoluminescence (PL) of AIS NCs involved alloyed AIS with ZnS to form Zn-Ag-In-S solid solutions at a higher temperature [
  <a rid="B26-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-micromachines-10-00439">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-micromachines-10-00439">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-micromachines-10-00439">28</a>]. A series of (AgIn)
  <sub>x</sub>Zn
  <sub>2(1-x)</sub>S
  <sub>2</sub> solid solution materials with different compositions have also been reported. Unlike the AgInS
  <sub>2</sub>/ZnS core–shell structure, in solid solution nanocrystals, Zn was doped into the crystal structure and participated in the formation of conduction bands. The density functional theory (DFT) results showed that the 4d orbital of Ag and the 3p orbital of S formed valence bands of (AgIn)
  <sub>x</sub>Zn
  <sub>2(1-x)</sub>S
  <sub>2</sub> [
  <a rid="B29-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-micromachines-10-00439">29</a>]. The 5s5p orbital of In and 4s4p orbital of Zn participated in the formation of conduction bands. The highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) and the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO) orbits of solid solution crystals are located between ZnS and AgInS
  <sub>2</sub>. By changing the ratio of AgInS
  <sub>2</sub> to ZnS in solid solution, the valence band and conduction band can be changed continuously. Increasing the amount of Zn in AIS directly resulted in a large blue shift of the PL emissions [
  <a rid="B30-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-micromachines-10-00439">30</a>], which is ascribed to the increase of the band gap caused by the zinc being incorporated into the AIS core. The alloyed layer abated the lattice mismatch between AIS and ZnS, reduced surface defects, and improved PL properties. Therefore, the band gap and PL emission of AIS-based NCs can be conveniently adjusted by changing their composition and size.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So far, a large number of reports have focused on the preparation and the application of Zn-Ag-In-S NCs. Most of the synthetic methods concentrated on the thermolysis of (AgIn)
  <sub>x</sub>Zn
  <sub>2(1-x)</sub>(S
  <sub>2</sub>CN(C
  <sub>2</sub>H
  <sub>5</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>)
  <sub>4</sub> precursors to form (AgIn)
  <sub>x</sub>Zn
  <sub>2(1−x)</sub>S
  <sub>2</sub> NCs [
  <a rid="B31-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-micromachines-10-00439">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-micromachines-10-00439">32</a>,
  <a rid="B33-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-micromachines-10-00439">33</a>,
  <a rid="B34-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-micromachines-10-00439">34</a>]. In these reports, the molar ratio of (Zn + Ag) to In was varied to achieve the different PL emissions, in which the relative dose of Zn and Ag remained constant. In our previous work [
  <a rid="B35-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-micromachines-10-00439">35</a>], high-quality non-stoichiometric Zn
  <sub>x</sub>Cu
  <sub>y</sub>InS
  <sub>1.5+x+0.5y</sub> NCs were synthesized using a one-pot strategy, which exhibited excellent PL QYs and tunable PL in 450–640 nm by holding Zn (mole% = 20–35%), In, and S constant and changing the mole percentage of Cu in the precursor. For the prepared (ZnCu)
  <sub>x</sub>InS
  <sub>2</sub> nanoparticles in the same reaction condition, the PL emissions were in the range of 560–640 nm and the PL intensities were lower than those of the Zn constant (25%) samples. Here, we extend this one-pot strategy to fabricate the non-stoichiometric Zn
  <sub>x</sub>Ag
  <sub>y</sub>InS
  <sub>1.5+x+0.5y</sub> nanocrystals (ZAIS NCs). This is the first exploration of the synthesis of ZAIS NCs with Zn constant (25%) and a different molar ratio of Ag to In, which exhibits composition-dependent photoluminescence properties with high PL QYs and tunable PL wavelength.
 </p>
</sec>
