<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-micromachines-10-00439" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In(Ac)
  <sub>3</sub> (99.99%), sulfur powder (S, 99.99%), Zn(Ac)
  <sub>2</sub> (99.99%), Ag(Ac) (99.99%), oleic acid (OA, 90%), octadecene (ODE, 90%), and 1-dodecanthiol (DDT, 99.9%) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). Nitric acid (70%), methanol (AR), and chloroform (AR) were purchased from Beijing Chemical Reagent Ltd., Beijing, China. All chemicals were used without further purification.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zn
  <sub>x</sub>Ag
  <sub>y</sub>InS
  <sub>1.5+x+0.5y</sub> (ZAIS) NCs were prepared using our previous methods [
  <a rid="B35-micromachines-10-00439" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-micromachines-10-00439">35</a>] with a slight modification. For a typical synthetic reaction, 0.01 mmol Ag(Ac), 0.025 mmol Zn(Ac)
  <sub>2</sub>, 0.1 mmol In(Ac)
  <sub>3</sub>, 1 mmol DDT, 0.4 mmol OA, and 4 g of ODE were loaded in a round bottom flask. The mixture was heated at 180 °C for 30 min to form a clear solution and then kept at 260 °C for 10 min. A sulfur solution of ODE (0.3 mmol)was injected into the three-neck flask and heated for 10 min at 260 °C, followed by cooling to room temperature. The precipitation was obtained by centrifugation at 13,000 rpm for 15 min after adding 8-fold volume of methanol to the reaction solution and then the precipitation was redispersed in chloroform. The purification approach ofthe ZAIS NCs was carried out by repeating the above process several times. Changing the Ag dosage in the precursor, a series of ZAIS NCs with different Ag content (including 0.015, 0.01, 0.005, 0.0025, 0.00125, 0.000625, and 0 mmol, and denoted ZAIS-1 to ZAIS-7, respectively) was obtained. The chemical compositions of ZAIS-1 to ZAIS-7 were carried by inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometry/mass spectrometry (ICP-OES/MS, Thermo Jarrell-Ash Corporation, Franklin, MA, USA). The purified ZAIS NCs were first digested by nitric acid. The concentrations of In
  <span class="sup">3+</span>, Ag
  <span class="sup">+</span>, and Zn
  <span class="sup">2+</span> ions in the clear digestion solutions were determined directly by ICP-OES/MS after being diluted with distilled water. The relative PL quantum yield of the ZAIS NCs was determined by comparing the integrated emission of the samples to that of Rhodamine 6G (Rhodamine 6G in ethanol, QY = 95%) solutions with the same optical density at the excitation wavelength and similar fluorescence wavelength.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transmission electron microscope (TEM, Hillsboro, OR, USA) and high-resolution transmission electron microscope (HRTEM, Hillsboro, OR, USA) images were examined on an FEI Tecnai G2 F20 using 200 kV acceleration voltage. ZAIS NCs were dispersed in chloroform and then dropped on carbon-coated copper grids. X-ray powder diffraction (XRD) patterns were obtained from a Rigaku D/max-2500 X-ray diffractometer (Rigaku Corporation, Tokyo, Japan) with Cu Kα radiation (λ = 1.5418 Å). UV-vis absorption spectra were performed on a Cary 50 spectrophotometer (Varian, Salt Lake City, UT, USA). Fluorescence spectra were recorded on a LS55 luminescence spectrometer (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA). A Lecroy Wave Runner 6100 digital oscilloscope (Teledyne LeCroy, Chestnut Ridge, NY, USA) was employed to obtain the fluorescence decay curve. A Continuum Sunlite optical parametric oscillator (Teledyne LeCroy, Chestnut Ridge, NY, USA) was the excitation source with tunable laser (pulse width = 4 ns, gate = 50 ns).</p>
</sec>
