<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec4-micromachines-10-00439" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A facile one-pot hot injection approach to successfully synthesize high-quality non-stoichiometric ZAIS NCs in the size range of 2.8–3.1 nm was presented. XRD, HRTEM, and fluorescence spectra showed that Zn, Ag, In, and S formed the alloyed non-stoichiometric solid solution. The fluorescence spectra had single band gap features, and indicated the formation of alloy states rather than simple composite structures. The effects of different reaction conditions on the composition and PL emission properties of the solid solution were investigated. It was found that the appropriate ratio of DDT was beneficial to the formation of alloy state ZAISNCs, which was the key factor in the synthesis of the ZAIS solid solution. The appropriate proportion of DDT can prevent the precipitation in the reaction system, increase the fluorescence quantum yield, reduce their half-peak width, and improve their luminescence properties. The photoluminescence wastunable from blue to red in the range of 450–700 nm since the Zn and Ag contents in the precursor changed. The PL and absorption spectra of the ZAIS NCs showed a significant blue shift with the decrease of Ag content in the precursor. As there were no obvious differences in the average particle sizes of the ZAIS NCs amples, these results fully revealed the composition-dependent photoluminescence properties of the ZAIS NCs. The relative quantum yield reached 35%. The fluorescence lifetimes (τ
  <sub>1</sub> = 115–148 ns and τ
  <sub>2</sub> = 455–483 ns) were analogous to those of AIS and (AgIn)
  <sub>x</sub>Zn
  <sub>2(1−x)</sub>S
  <sub>2</sub>. The components of 115–148 ns can be assigned to donor–acceptor pairrecombination related to surface defects and vacancies. The components of 455–483 ns can be allocated to transitions of intrinsic donor–acceptor pair recombination.
 </p>
</sec>
