<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sesquiterpene synthases</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant sesquiterpene synthases, a subset of the terpene synthase superfamily, are a mechanistically diverse family of enzymes capable of synthesizing hundreds of complex compounds with high regio- and stereospecificity and are of biological importance due to their role in plant defense mechanisms. Several excellent reviews on the larger terpene synthase family are available covering the essential enzymatic transformations, structural biology and phylogenetics [
  <a rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0082">82</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0085">85</a>]. Sesquiterpene synthases bind farnesyl diphosphate and three divalent Mg
  <span class="sup">2+</span> ions. Sesquiterpene biosynthesis is initiated by ionization of the C1-OPP bond generating a reactive carbocation (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0002" href="#F0002">Figure 2</a> for a depiction of the unfolded form) and the first major important branching of a mechanistic network. At this point, the diphosphate moiety can then bind to C3, isomerize about the C2-C3 bond, and then ionize the C3-OPP bond to form the reactive nerolidyl carbocation. Carbocations can be quenched by proton transfer from the intermediate to the enzyme or by addition of water molecules at any point along the mechanistic decision network. Otherwise, the synthesis can proceed through an intermolecular electrophilic attack on one of the two double bonds of the substrate to form a cyclic species. Possible subsequent reactions include hydride shifts, proton transfers, methyl or methylene shifts, and further intermolecular electrophilic additions. Sesquiterpene synthases span a large range of specificity. Increasingly, similar catalytic versatility is being discovered in several protein families and may be an inherent property of enzymes [
  <a rid="CIT0086" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0086">86</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0087" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0087">87</a>]. Such secondary catalytic activities can become the primary activity through gene duplication and subsequent divergence as well as the starting points for directed evolution in protein engineering applications [
  <a rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0015">15</a>]. Understanding these secondary activities may help lower attrition rates in drug discovery programs and identify drug interaction surfaces less susceptible to escape mutations [
  <a rid="CIT0088" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0088">88</a>].
 </p>
 <div id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Chemical reactions progressing from the shared eudesmane carbocation intermediate to premnaspirodiene (methylene transfer followed by proton abstraction from C6), 4-epi-eremophilene and 5-epi-aristolocholene (methyl transfer followed by proton abstraction from C6 or C8 respectively).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="CSBJ-2-e201209018-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a recent study of sesquiterpene synthases (that encompasses all the hallmarks of the classical molecular evolution studies previously noted) in which a 5-epi-aristolocholene synthase (5EAS) was transformed to a premnaspirodiene synthase (PSDS) through mutational swaps of nine residues (none of which make specific contacts with the substrate) as well as experimental classification of all 512 proteins with different combinations of these nine residues, a functional landscape underlying the evolution of sesquiterpene chemical diversity was revealed (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0002" href="#F0002">Figures 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0003" href="#F0003">3</a>) [
  <a rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0089">89</a>]. The catalytic cycle of both synthases passes through several common intermediate states and only diverges in the last few chemical steps with some mutants along this putative evolutionary swath producing 4-epi-eremophilene, a product with hybrid activity; possibly ancestral to both enzymes. Also of significance, the mutants exhibited functional epistasis by the fact that 1) no single amino acid correlated with the product distribution and 2) the effect of a mutation depended on the state of the other eight residues. While these studies on sesquiterpene synthases are highly innovative and relevant to the task of seeking fundamental enzyme design principles, a decisive physicochemical explanation for the evolution of novel sesquiterpene synthase function is lacking. Therefore, our lab began investigating these details by first performing an extensive molecular phylogenetic analysis and then leveraging this information to support mechanistic conclusions obtained from atomic MD simulations [
  <a rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0002">2</a>]. Uncovering the biophysical principles governing a functional landscape can assist in narrowing the many possible evolutionary pathways to novel functions [
  <a rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0009">9</a>]; information that deepens our knowledge of structure-function relationships.
 </p>
 <div id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The nine residues and their substitutions located outside the active site designated here by the farnesylhydroxyphosphonate (FHP) surface and other highly conserved residues that functionally convert a 5-epi-aristolocholene synthase to a premnaspirodiene synthase.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="CSBJ-2-e201209018-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our recently published molecular phylogenetic analysis of the plant sesquiterpene synthase family has been, and can in the future, be utilized to support conclusions from the simulations and to leverage experimental results on sesquiterpene synthases from other branches of the phylogenetic tree [
  <a rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0002">2</a>]. The number and complexity of sesquiterpene products had in the past inhibited the use of phylogenetic analysis for constructing sequence-function relationships because of uncertainties in the statistical relevance of the resulting inferences. However, through a carefully-crafted multiple sequence alignment of ∼200 plant sesquiterpene synthases using the procedures described in the Molecular Phylogenetics section, we observed that all sequences that cluster together on the phylogenetic tree into well-defined groups share at least the first reaction in the catalytic mechanism subsequent to the initial ionization step and many share steps beyond this, down to proton transfers between the enzyme and substrate. The multiple sequence alignment showed 15 highly conserved residues (95% and above) in the C-terminal catalytic domain, five of which are outside the active site. Most significant was the previously unreported high conservation of a Tyr520-Asp444-Asp525 triad (numbering according to the Nicotiana tobacum sequence for which there is a structure, see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0004" href="#F0004">Figure 4</a>). Given the high conservation of the Asp444-Tyr-520-Asp-525 triad, its position relative to a folded substrate analogue [
  <a rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0090">90</a>], the demonstration of its importance in generating (+)-germacrene A either as an intermediate or product [
  <a rid="CIT0091" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0091">91</a>], and our own atomistic MD simulations of the eudesmane carbocation in 5EAS, and finally the absence of likely proton donors/acceptors in other parts of many plant sTS active sites, we proposed that this triad is an important functional element responsible for many proton transfers to and from the substrate and intermediates along the plant sesquiterpene synthase catalytic cycle. Though this triad is obviously not the key to understanding all of plant sTS enzymatic chemistry, we nevertheless proposed that the triad can be tuned in a variety of ways to generate a diversity of products. These include 1) substituting residues on the opposite side of the active site forcing the farnesyl diphosphate to fold in different ways so that through both mechanisms the triad will donate/abstract protons to and from different carbons and 2) substituting residues surrounding the triad to shift their position relative to the substrate and/or intermediates. Finally, these results highlight what insights can be gained and a wealth of hypotheses that can arise from a phylogenetic analysis coupled to molecular modeling of the substrate/intermediate-enzyme complex. Developing these hypotheses was critical to our efforts to dissect the 5EAS mechanism further by hybrid QC/MM methods.
 </p>
 <div id="F0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Highly conserved (&lt;95%) residues highlighted on the 5-epi-aristolocholene synthase active site structure (PDB entry: 5eat). Also shown are the co-crystallized Mg
    <span class="sup">2+</span> ions (green) and farnesylhydroxyphosphanate substrate mimic (middle). Helices are in purple.
   </p>
   <p>Reprinted from Reference 2 with permission.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="CSBJ-2-e201209018-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first structural models of a plant sesquiterpene synthase [
  <a rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0090">90</a>] based on x-ray crystallography presented enough information to propose a full mechanism for the many chemical steps in transforming farnesyl pyrophosphate to its product, 5-epi-aristolocholene (5EA). Part of this mechanism has gained experimental support [
  <a rid="CIT0091" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0091">91</a>], though the latter steps that form the basis of functional divergence remain to be fully explained. Furthermore, much is still unknown about the atomic details of many sesquiterpene synthase mechanisms, even though the intrinsic reactivity of the substrate has in several cases been elucidated through quantum chemical calculations [
  <a rid="CIT0092" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0092">92</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0093" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0093">93</a>]. A QC/MM simulation study on a fungal aristolocholene synthase discovered an energetically feasible intramolecular proton transfer reaction leading to formation of the eudesmane carbocation as well as determining the functional roles of active site residues [
  <a rid="CIT0094" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0094">94</a>]. Another QC/MM study on a closely related bornyl diphosphate synthase revealed how the electrostatic environment of the enzyme's active site steered the substrate to its’ final product [
  <a rid="CIT0095" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0095">95</a>]. Due to the transient nature of so many intermediate states along terpene synthase catalytic cycles, it is extremely difficult to experimentally determine reaction rates or thermodynamic data for the individual reactions. In addition, simulation studies on terpene synthases are quite challenging due to the fact that the enzymes’ contribution to catalysis may be relatively subtle with residues appearing to act in concert and ones outside the active site affecting product distributions [
  <a rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0089">89</a>]. Past QC calculations on the methyl and methylene transfer reactions emanating from the eudesmane carbocation in 5EAS [
  <a rid="CIT0096" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0096">96</a>] have primarily served to amplify the mystery behind the physicochemical properties that control sesquiterpene synthase product distributions. These reactions could be under thermodynamic or kinetic control. The enzyme may preferentially stabilize the non-classical carbocation (carbonium ions) structures that occur along both of these reaction paths. Yet, our latest simulation results (manuscript in preparation) employing QC/MM methods and representation of the fully solvated 5EAS-eudesmane carbocation intermediate reveals the basis for 5EAS specificity is the preferential stabilization of the 4-epi-eremophilenyl intermediate (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0002" href="#F0002">Figure 2</a>) over the premnaspirodienyl intermediate. The calculated free energy barrier for both reactions is very low, around 5-6 kcal/mol. The free energy differences, on the other hand, are exergonic for the methyl transfer reaction and endergonic for the methylene transfer. The methyl transfer reaction from the eudesmane carbocation is favored in 5EAS in part because the active site forms a “cage” around the substrate's isoprenyl group which is not “disturbed” by the methyl transfer reaction. In contrast, the methylene transfer reaction results in a more substantial change in the shape of the intermediate and several steric clashes occur between the isoprenyl group of the substrate and surrounding residues. Furthermore, the catalytic triad of Asp444-Tyr520-Asp525 is favorably positioned to abstract the proton from C8 of the 4-epi-eremophilenyl carbocation resulting in 5EA product formation. Thus, there are multiple structural and functional requirements for specificity to arise in 5EAS. Further examination of this functional landscape [
  <a rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0089">89</a>] through hybrid QC/MM simulations could provide direction on how to engineer these enzymes to be less promiscuous and biosynthesize completely new natural products.
 </p>
</sec>
