<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary and Outlook</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mechanistic details of enzymatic reactions obtained from hybrid QC/MM simulations combined with identification of amino acid residues critical for the maintenance and diversity of function within a enzyme (super)family is a powerful approach for elucidating enzyme design principles. This information can then be leveraged to design enzymes for environmental remediation, energy production, the prediction of antibiotic resistance and the production of therapeutic compounds. The use of QC/MM methods to investigate enzymatic reactions still requires some expertise. The resulting free energy profiles or surfaces can be very sensitive to the initial coordinates, protonation states of surrounding residues, the QC method, and the length of umbrella sampling simulations [
  <a rid="CIT0104" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0104">104</a>]. Nevertheless, there have been significant improvements in software employing QC/MM methods over the last ten years since the authors began using them. We can expect to see further improvement in semiempirical molecular orbital parameterizations and methods which will enable faster exploration of possible reactive configurations as well as the generation of initial reaction paths that can be refined with higher level QC methods. But possibly more importantly is that in the future we will increasingly see the atomic and subatomic level details of enzyme reaction mechanisms interpreted within the context of its evolutionary history using molecular phylogenetics. One of the main limitations in this endeavor today is the fact that so many sequences are uncharacterized or even mischaracterized [
  <a rid="CIT0105" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0105">105</a>]. Assignment of function by homology may only be successful at relatively high sequence identities. Beyond this, the enzyme may carry out essentially the same catalytic chemistry but on very different substrates. Until this problem is remedied, the value of the sequence data will not reach its full potential benefit for use in enzyme design. For example, if a much larger percentage of plant sesquiterpene synthase sequences had experimentally determined functions, then analyses could be performed on the MSA to determine what residues are most responsible for traversing the nerolidyl pathway versus the trans pathway. Nevertheless, these are exciting times for computational biochemists who have an amazing opportunity to utilize both atomic-scale MD simulations, using both MM and QC/MM potential energy functions, and molecular phylogenetics in their research that will provide results and subsequent stories (publications), one could argue, that can stand aside some of the past classical studies of adaptation and begin to provide robust answers to the challenging questions posed in this review.
 </p>
</sec>
