<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ferulic acid (FA), one of the best-known natural phenolic acids, widely distributes in grains, vegetables, fruits, alcoholic beverages, and herbs (e.g., rice, wheat, barley, onion, orange, tomato, corn, pineapple, beer, 
  <span class="italic">Ferula asafoetida</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Ligusticum chuanxiong</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Lycopodium selago</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Equisetum hiemale</span>) [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>]. FA exhibits numerous biological activities, such as antioxidant, anticancer, antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, and antidiabetic effects [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. Moreover, FA has been proved effective in protecting skin from the onset of erythema from UVB rays [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. It is therefore necessary to quantify FA [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>]. For the sensitive determination of FA, several methods have been developed including high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>], electrochemical techniques [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>, 
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>], Raman spectroscopy [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>], chemiluminescence [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>], and fluorescence [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. However, some of these methods need professional operators and/or sophisticated instruments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum dots (QDs) exhibited unique optical and chemical features, such as facile preparation procedures, size- and composition-tunable photoluminescence-emission modifiable surfaces, high quantum yield, good chemical and photo stability, and superior aqueous dispersibility [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>, 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>], which then attracted a lot of attention and were widely exploited in sensing, bioimaging, and diagnostic. To improve the selectivity, highly-specific groups or materials were always designed to modify the surface of QDs. Molecularly imprinted polymers (MIPs) contained recognition sites with memory function of shape, size, and functional groups to template for high selectivity, which have attracted excellent attention in solid-phase extraction [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>–
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>]. When MIPs were coated on QDs (QDs@MIPs), a promising sensor is provided with high selectivity and sensitivity and facile operation [
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>–
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>]. Among different polymerization methods for MIPs [
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>–
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>], sol-gel polymerization, using 3-(aminopropyl) triethoxysilane (APTES) as the functional monomer and tetraethyl orthosilicate (TEOS) as the crosslinker, is the widely selected strategy because of the simple synthesis process and water-compatible capability [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. The Stöber method and reverse microemulsion method were the two main methods for sol-gel polymerization, and the reverse microemulsion method could control the thickness of MIPs layer better for accessible recognition sites [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>, 
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. Up to date, some excellent reports about QDs@MIPs by the reverse microemulsion method have been fabricated. Ensafi et al. prepared QDs@MIPs with average diameter at approximate 40 nm, which were then utilized to sensitively detect thioridazine hydrochloride in plasma within 2 min [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>]. Yang et al. fabricated QDs@MIPs with a diameter at about 75 nm and then used them for sensitive and selective determination of tetracycline in fish within 5 min [
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>]. Wu et al. grafted MIPs onto QDs, and the resultant QDs@MIPs with diameter at about 49 nm could successfully determine malachite green in fish samples within 5 min [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. Although FA-imprinted polymers have been reported, almost all of them were prepared by copolymerization of allylic functional monomer and crosslinker in the presence of FA under the auxiliary of nitrogen [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>–
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>]. Up to date, QDs@MIPs for sensitive determination of FA have not been reported.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the current work, a fluorescence sensor based on CdTe-QDs@MIPs was fabricated via the reverse microemulsion method for highly selective and sensitive determination of FA. Preparation and determination conditions were optimized. The resultant CdTe-QDs@MIPs with MIPs layer at about 15 nm were applied to detected FA in fruits based on the charge transfer principle with equilibrium time within 3 min and LOD at 0.85 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g·L
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. Therefore, a rapid, selective, and sensitive method for determination of FA was developed.
 </p>
</sec>
