<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Synthesis of CdTe-QDs@MIPs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fabrication of CdTe-QDs@MIPs included the preparation of TGA-capped CdTe-QDs and surface MIPs. Firstly, TGA-capped CdTe-QDs were synthesized with some modifications according to previous report [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>]. Typically, 30.7 mg of CdCl
  <sub>2</sub>·2H
  <sub>2</sub>O and 70.0 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l of TGA were dissolved in 100.0 ml of water, and then, 0.5 mol/l of NaOH solution was added dropwise to adjust pH at 9.0. At the same time, under nitrogen atmosphere, 25.5 mg of tellurium powder and 30.3 mg of NaBH
  <sub>4</sub> were mixed in 2.0 ml of water, and the mixture was stirred for about 3 h to obtain NaHTe solution. After that, two above-prepared solutions were mixed and refluxed at 90°C for 13 h to obtain TGA-capped CdTe-QDs solution. Subsequently, CdTe-QDs@MIPs were prepared via the reverse microemulsion method. Triton-X (1.8 ml) and cyclohexane (7.5 ml) were mixed in a three-necked flask and stirred for 30 min. Then, TGA-capped CdTe-QDs solution (1.0 ml) and TEOS (50 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l) were added and continuously stirred for 30 min. At this time, FA (34.0 mg) and APTES (22.8 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l) were separately dissolved in anhydrous methanol, and the resultant solutions were slowly dropped into the three-necked flask. Mixtures were kept stirring for 12 h at room temperature. After that, acetone (40.0 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l) was injected to break the microemulsion and mixtures were centrifuged at 9000 rpm for 1 min. The resultant precipitate was extracted with ethanol to remove FA. As a control, CdTe-QDs@nonimprinted polymers (CdTe-QDs@NIPs) were prepared in the absence of template, FA. CdTe-QDs@MIPs and CdTe-QDs@NIPs were both dried under vacuum and stored at 4°C for further use.
 </p>
</sec>
