<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. CdTe-QDs@MIPs Synthesis and Characterization</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reverse microemulsion method was used to prepare CdTe-QDs@MIPs, in which Triton-X and cyclohexane were served as the surfactant and continuous phase, respectively. APTES reacted with FA through hydrogen bonds and electrostatic interaction and hydrolyzed and condensated with TEOS to form FA-imprinted polymers on CdTe-QDs. The fluorescence intensity of CdTe-QDs@MIPs was quenched after binding with FA, which was then recovered after removal of FA. It was obvious that the molar ratio of template-functional monomer-crosslinker was crucial to the recognition ability of MIPs [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. CdTe-QDs@MIPs with different molar ratios of FA : APTES : TEOS (1 : 3 : 13–1 : 9 : 13) were prepared. Fluorescence intensities of CdTe-QDs@MIPs decreased with the increase of FA content; however, maximum fluorescence quenching efficiency of CdTe-QDs@MIPs was obtained when the molar ratio of FA : APTES : TEOS was 1 : 6 : 13 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>). Furthermore, polymerization time was optimized (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(b)</a>). Obviously, fluorescence intensities decreased when polymerization time was over 12 h because of the thicker MIPs shell and more-embedded recognition sites. At the same time, quenching efficiency decreased when the polymerization time was less than 12 min, which was probably because of the less recognition sites in thinner MIPs shell. CdTe-QDs@MIPs with polymerization time at 12 h showed the highest quenching efficiency. Fluorescence intensities of resultant CdTe-QDs@MIPs before and after FA removal were measured. As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>, the maximum emission was about 600 nm when excited at 380 nm and the fluorescence intensities of CdTe-QDs@MIPs after FA removal was 89.7% that of CdTe-QDs@NIPs, which indicated that CdTe-QDs@MIPs were successfully fabricated and could selectively detect FA.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a> presented the morphology and particle size of CdTe-QDs@MIPs, which indicated that CdTe-QDs@MIPs particles showed a clear core-shell structure with an average diameter of 350 nm and the thickness of MIPs layer at about 15 nm. The reverse microemulsion method can be used in MIPs synthesis with better controlling of particle size than the Stöber method and another sol-gel polymerization method [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>, 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>–
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. FT-IR spectra were also employed to characterize CdTe-QDs@MIPs (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>). The bands at 1211 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and 1403 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for O−H stretching and C=O stretching and the band at 1581 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for deformation vibration of the carboxylic group ascribed to the modification of TGA on CdTe-QDs (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(a)</a>). Furthermore, the typical peaks at 1172 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and 772 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> were associated with the asymmetric stretching of Si−O−Si and the bending vibration of Si−O (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(b)</a>), which confirmed the successful preparation of CdTe-QDs@MIPs.
 </p>
</sec>
