<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Optimization of Determination Conditions for FA</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During fluorescence detection, several factors, such as the CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentration, pH, and adsorption time, can affect the linear rang and sensitivity, and then, they were optimized.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentration was very important for fluorescence intensity and quenching efficiency. It has been reported that a narrow linear range came from too low CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentrations and low sensitivity happened by using too high CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentrations [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>]. As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">Figure 6(a)</a>, the fluorescence intensities increased when the CdTe-QDs@MIPs increased from 30 to 100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml and decreased from 100 to 200 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml. In higher concentrations, slight agglomeration of CdTe-QDs@MIPs would happen. Highest quenching efficiency was achieved with a CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentration at 80 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The solution pH values presented a great effect on the fluorescence intensities of CdTe-QDs@MIPs and the recognition of FA (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">Figure 6(b)</a>). Among noncovalent interactions, binding energy of electrostatic interaction is higher than that of hydrogen bonding and 
  <span class="italic">π</span>-
  <span class="italic">π</span> stacking. Therefore, by electrostatic interaction, template-functional monomer complex is more stable and recognition ability is stronger [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. Here, surface MIPs were synthesized at pH 8.0 because of the electrostatic interaction and hydrogen bonding between FA and APTES. However, imprinting silica layer was ionized at higher alkaline conditions, which resulted in the poor recognition for FA. Therefore, fluorescence intensity and quenching efficiency of CdTe-QDs@MIPs decreased at pH ≥ 8. Finally, Tris buffer (10 mM, pH 8.0) was chosen as the optimum pH value for high fluorescence intensity and quenching efficiency.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of incubation time of CdTe-QDs@MIPs with FA was important for the complete binding. As presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">Figure 6(c)</a>, quenching efficiency of CdTe-QDs@MIPs increased sharply from 0 to 3 min and after that tended to be stable. Therefore, incubation time was set at 3 min. The fast mass transfer rate was assigned to surface thin MIPs layers.
 </p>
</sec>
