<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. CdTe-QDs@MIPs Synthesis and Characterization</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reverse microemulsion method was used to prepare CdTe-QDs@MIPs, in which Triton-X and cyclohexane were served as the surfactant and continuous phase, respectively. APTES reacted with FA through hydrogen bonds and electrostatic interaction and hydrolyzed and condensated with TEOS to form FA-imprinted polymers on CdTe-QDs. The fluorescence intensity of CdTe-QDs@MIPs was quenched after binding with FA, which was then recovered after removal of FA. It was obvious that the molar ratio of template-functional monomer-crosslinker was crucial to the recognition ability of MIPs [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. CdTe-QDs@MIPs with different molar ratios of FA : APTES : TEOS (1 : 3 : 13–1 : 9 : 13) were prepared. Fluorescence intensities of CdTe-QDs@MIPs decreased with the increase of FA content; however, maximum fluorescence quenching efficiency of CdTe-QDs@MIPs was obtained when the molar ratio of FA : APTES : TEOS was 1 : 6 : 13 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>). Furthermore, polymerization time was optimized (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(b)</a>). Obviously, fluorescence intensities decreased when polymerization time was over 12 h because of the thicker MIPs shell and more-embedded recognition sites. At the same time, quenching efficiency decreased when the polymerization time was less than 12 min, which was probably because of the less recognition sites in thinner MIPs shell. CdTe-QDs@MIPs with polymerization time at 12 h showed the highest quenching efficiency. Fluorescence intensities of resultant CdTe-QDs@MIPs before and after FA removal were measured. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>, the maximum emission was about 600 nm when excited at 380 nm and the fluorescence intensities of CdTe-QDs@MIPs after FA removal was 89.7% that of CdTe-QDs@NIPs, which indicated that CdTe-QDs@MIPs were successfully fabricated and could selectively detect FA.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a> presented the morphology and particle size of CdTe-QDs@MIPs, which indicated that CdTe-QDs@MIPs particles showed a clear core-shell structure with an average diameter of 350 nm and the thickness of MIPs layer at about 15 nm. The reverse microemulsion method can be used in MIPs synthesis with better controlling of particle size than the Stöber method and another sol-gel polymerization method [
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>, 
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>–
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. FT-IR spectra were also employed to characterize CdTe-QDs@MIPs (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>). The bands at 1211 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 1403 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> for O−H stretching and C=O stretching and the band at 1581 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> for deformation vibration of the carboxylic group ascribed to the modification of TGA on CdTe-QDs (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(a)</a>). Furthermore, the typical peaks at 1172 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 772 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span> were associated with the asymmetric stretching of Si−O−Si and the bending vibration of Si−O (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(b)</a>), which confirmed the successful preparation of CdTe-QDs@MIPs.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Imprinting Mechanism of CdTe-QDs@MIPs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Figure 5(a)</a>, the fluorescence lifetimes of CdTe-QDs@MIPs in the absence and presence of FA were 7.98 and 8.35 ns, respectively. The variable fluorescence lifetimes suggested that there existed energy or charge transfer between CdTe-QDs and FA [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>]. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5"> Figure 5(b)</a> revealed that FA had adsorption bands at 300 and 322 nm, which were close to the band gap of CdTe-QDs [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>], and far away from the emission spectrum (600 nm) of CdTe-QDs@MIPs. Therefore, charges in the conduction band of CdTe-QDs could transfer to the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital of FA, and energy resonance transfer was not the possible quenching mechanism. Furthermore, hydroxyl and carboxyl groups in FA could interact with the amino group in APTES through electrostatic interaction and hydrogen bond; therefore, it could be concluded that the observed fluorescence quenching was attributed to the charge transfer between FA and CdTe-QDs.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Optimization of Determination Conditions for FA</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During fluorescence detection, several factors, such as the CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentration, pH, and adsorption time, can affect the linear rang and sensitivity, and then, they were optimized.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentration was very important for fluorescence intensity and quenching efficiency. It has been reported that a narrow linear range came from too low CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentrations and low sensitivity happened by using too high CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentrations [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>]. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">Figure 6(a)</a>, the fluorescence intensities increased when the CdTe-QDs@MIPs increased from 30 to 100 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml and decreased from 100 to 200 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml. In higher concentrations, slight agglomeration of CdTe-QDs@MIPs would happen. Highest quenching efficiency was achieved with a CdTe-QDs@MIPs concentration at 80 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The solution pH values presented a great effect on the fluorescence intensities of CdTe-QDs@MIPs and the recognition of FA (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">Figure 6(b)</a>). Among noncovalent interactions, binding energy of electrostatic interaction is higher than that of hydrogen bonding and 
   <span class="italic">π</span>-
   <span class="italic">π</span> stacking. Therefore, by electrostatic interaction, template-functional monomer complex is more stable and recognition ability is stronger [
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. Here, surface MIPs were synthesized at pH 8.0 because of the electrostatic interaction and hydrogen bonding between FA and APTES. However, imprinting silica layer was ionized at higher alkaline conditions, which resulted in the poor recognition for FA. Therefore, fluorescence intensity and quenching efficiency of CdTe-QDs@MIPs decreased at pH ≥ 8. Finally, Tris buffer (10 mM, pH 8.0) was chosen as the optimum pH value for high fluorescence intensity and quenching efficiency.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of incubation time of CdTe-QDs@MIPs with FA was important for the complete binding. As presented in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">Figure 6(c)</a>, quenching efficiency of CdTe-QDs@MIPs increased sharply from 0 to 3 min and after that tended to be stable. Therefore, incubation time was set at 3 min. The fast mass transfer rate was assigned to surface thin MIPs layers.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Specificity Study</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selectivity was one of the most important issues in fabrication of optical sensors. It was reported that phenylpropanoid acids (e.g., CA, pCA, and FA) could simultaneously quench the fluorescence of CdTe-QDs [
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>, 
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>]. Bare CdTe-QDs could not selectively detect phenylpropanoid acid; therefore, surface modification should be fabricated. Six structural analogues, chlorogenic acid (CGA), 4-hydroxybenzoic acid (4-HBA), caffeic acid (CA), 
   <span class="italic">p</span>-coumaric acid (pCA), vanillic acid (VA), and protocatechuic aldehyde (PA) with a concentration at 10 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/l were selected and investigated to estimate the selectivity of CdTe-QDs@MIPs and CdTe-QDs@NIPs. As illustrated in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">Figure 7</a>, the quenching efficiency of FA was obviously different between CdTe-QDs@MIPs (
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>0</sub>/
   <span class="italic">F</span>, 1.27) and CdTe-QDs@NIPs (
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>0</sub>/
   <span class="italic">F</span>, 1.04), which verified that CdTe-QDs@MIPs had specific recognition ability to FA. However, CGA, 4-HBA, CA, pCA, VA, and PA quenching efficiencies all close to 1.00 were not easy to identify. Results further demonstrated that the recognition ability of CdTe-QDs@MIPs was based on the recognition sites.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Method Validation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linearity, limit of detection (LOD), limit of quantification (LOQ), precision, and specificity were determined to investigate the method validation. The fluorescence intensities of CdTe-QDs@MIPs decreased with the increase of FA concentrations (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8(a)</a>). The fluorescence quenching efficiencies followed Stern–Volmer equation: 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>0</sub>/
   <span class="italic">F</span> = 1 + 
   <span class="italic">K</span>
   <sub>sv</sub>[
   <span class="italic">C</span>], where 
   <span class="italic">K</span>
   <sub>sv</sub> and [
   <span class="italic">C</span>] were the quenching constant and FA concentrations. Furthermore, a good linearity (
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>0</sub>/
   <span class="italic">F</span> = 1.0688 + 0.0198 C) was observed at the concentration range from 2 to 100 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/l with coefficient (
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>) at 0.9996 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8(b)</a>). LOD (0.85 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/l) and LOQ (2.81 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/l) were achieved for FA. Intraday RSD and interday RSD values over a five-day span were 0.62% and 1.61%, respectively, indicating the high reproducibility. Accordingly, the developed method was sufficiently practical for selective quantification of FA. To further investigate the developed performance, the results with other methods were compared [
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>–
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>, 
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>–
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>, 
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>]. As shown in 
   <a rid="tab1" ref-type="table" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>, different methods have different superiorities and disadvantages. It can be seen the developed method was one of the most sensitive for FA quantification.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> 3.6. Real Sample Measurement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The practicability of the developed CdTe-QDs@MIPs-based sensor was further evaluated for quantitative analysis of FA in pineapple juice and apple juice. In addition to dilution, no sample pretreatment procedures were required. Recoveries of FA ranged from 91.8% to 110.3% with excellent RSD values less than 6.6% (
   <a rid="tab2" ref-type="table" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>). Finally, FA was estimated in pineapple juice at a concentration of 724.6 ± 29.5 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/l, and no FA was detected in apple juice.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Pharmacopoeia of the People's Republic of China, FA was always quantified by HPLC-UV. Quantitative analysis of FA in pineapple juice and apple juice has been developed in our group by HPLC after MIPs extraction [
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>]. Results indicated the concentrations of FA in pineapple juice and apple juice were 683.3 ± 33.1 and 0 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/l, which were consistent with those determined by our developed CdTe-QDs@MIPs-based method.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
