<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Reagents and Chemicals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tellurium powder, thioglycolic acid (TGA), CdCl
   <sub>2</sub>·2H
   <sub>2</sub>O, and sodium borohydride (NaBH
   <sub>4</sub>) were supported by Aladdin Reagent Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). TEOS, APTES, NaOH, anhydrous methanol, acetone, Triton X-100, Tris (hydroxymethyl) aminomethane, and anhydrous methanol were acquired from Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). Standards, ferulic acid (FA), chlorogenic acid (CGA), 4-hydroxybenzoic acid (4-HBA), caffeic acid (CA), 
   <span class="italic">p</span>-coumaric acid (pCA), vanillic acid (VA), and protocatechuic aldehyde (PA) were ordered from Xiya Reagent Co., Ltd. (Chengdu, China). All stock solutions were prepared with ultrapure water (18.2 MΩ) from a Milli-Q water purification system (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Apparatus</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fluorescence spectroscopy was investigated on a LS-55 fluorescence spectrometer (PerkinElmer Ltd., Washington, USA) and a Fluo Time 100 fluorescence spectrometer (PicoQuant, Germany). UV-vis absorption spectra were recorded using an UV-2600 spectrometer (Shimadzu, Tokyo, Japan). Functional groups were measured on a Nicolet-Avatar 360 Fourier transform infrared (FT-IR) spectrometer within the wavenumber from 400 to 4,000 cm
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. Structure and morphology of CdTe-QDs@MIPs were determined on a Tecnai G2 20S-Twin transmission electron microscope (TEM, FEI, Prague, Czech Republic). The average value of the particle size was determined by a particle size analysis (PSA) (Malvern Instruments Ltd., Malvern, UK).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">HPLC analysis was carried out on an Agilent 1260 HPLC system with a UV detector at 322 nm (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA). A Waters SunFire-C
   <sub>18</sub> chromatographic column (250 nm × 4.6 mm i.d., 5 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m, Waters, Milford, MA) was selected for separation at 25°C, and 0.3% acetic acid in ultrapure water/acetonitrile (20/80, v/v) was used as mobile phase for isocratic elution with a flow rate of 0.8 ml/min. Sample (20 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l) was injected directly into HPLC after passing through a 0.22 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m polytetrafluoroethylene syringe filter.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Synthesis of CdTe-QDs@MIPs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fabrication of CdTe-QDs@MIPs included the preparation of TGA-capped CdTe-QDs and surface MIPs. Firstly, TGA-capped CdTe-QDs were synthesized with some modifications according to previous report [
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>]. Typically, 30.7 mg of CdCl
   <sub>2</sub>·2H
   <sub>2</sub>O and 70.0 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l of TGA were dissolved in 100.0 ml of water, and then, 0.5 mol/l of NaOH solution was added dropwise to adjust pH at 9.0. At the same time, under nitrogen atmosphere, 25.5 mg of tellurium powder and 30.3 mg of NaBH
   <sub>4</sub> were mixed in 2.0 ml of water, and the mixture was stirred for about 3 h to obtain NaHTe solution. After that, two above-prepared solutions were mixed and refluxed at 90°C for 13 h to obtain TGA-capped CdTe-QDs solution. Subsequently, CdTe-QDs@MIPs were prepared via the reverse microemulsion method. Triton-X (1.8 ml) and cyclohexane (7.5 ml) were mixed in a three-necked flask and stirred for 30 min. Then, TGA-capped CdTe-QDs solution (1.0 ml) and TEOS (50 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l) were added and continuously stirred for 30 min. At this time, FA (34.0 mg) and APTES (22.8 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l) were separately dissolved in anhydrous methanol, and the resultant solutions were slowly dropped into the three-necked flask. Mixtures were kept stirring for 12 h at room temperature. After that, acetone (40.0 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l) was injected to break the microemulsion and mixtures were centrifuged at 9000 rpm for 1 min. The resultant precipitate was extracted with ethanol to remove FA. As a control, CdTe-QDs@nonimprinted polymers (CdTe-QDs@NIPs) were prepared in the absence of template, FA. CdTe-QDs@MIPs and CdTe-QDs@NIPs were both dried under vacuum and stored at 4°C for further use.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Fluorescence Measurement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For fluorescence quenching analysis of FA towards CdTe-QDs@MIPs and CdTe-QDs@NIPs, 0.3 ml of CdTe-QDs@MIPs or CdTe-QDs@NIPs solution (0.8 mg/ml) was dispersed in 2.7 ml of Tris-HCL buffer (10.0 mM and pH 8.0) and then 30.0 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l of FA standard solution with different concentrations was added. After 3 min stirring process, the fluorescence spectra were recorded. In fluorescence detection, the excitation wavelength was set at 380 nm with an emission range of 550−650 nm, the excitation and emission slit width were both at 10 nm, and the photomultiplier tube voltage was tuned to 900 V.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Determination of FA in Fruit Juices</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The real sample applicability of the developed method was to analyze FA in pineapple juice and apple juice (Beijing Huiyuan Beverage and Food Co., Ltd., China) from local supermarket in Changsha. Fruit juices were filtered through a 0.22 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m filter and further used without any sample pretreatment. Briefly, 30.0 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l of fruit juices, 0.3 ml of CdTe-QDs@MIPs solution (0.8 mg/ml), and 2.7 ml of Tris-HCL buffer (10 mM, pH 8.0) were mixed and vortexed for 3 min, and then, the fluorescence intensities were recorded with excitation wavelength at 380 nm.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
