<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemicals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cs
   <sub>2</sub>CO
   <sub>3</sub> (Aldrich, 99.9%), PbBr
   <sub>3</sub> (ABCR, 98%), Cadmium (II) oxide (Sigma Aldrich, 99.5%), Oleic Acid (OA, Sigma Aldrich, 90%), 1-octadecene (ODE, Sigma Aldrich, tech. 90%), Sulfur (Sigma Aldrich, 99.98%), Oleylamine (OME, Sigma Aldrich, tech. 70%), Toluene (Sigma Aldrich, 99.8%), CBP (Xi'an Polymer Light Technology Co., Ltd.), Molybdenum Oxide (MoO
   <sub>3</sub>, from Aladdin-reagent), ZnO:Mg (Xingshuo Nano Technology Co., Ltd.).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cd-oleate Solution Synthesis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the synthesis of Cd-oleate solution a protocol by Li et al. (
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">2011</a>) was adopted. A 0.38 M Cd-oleate solution was made by dissolving 383 mg CdO in 3.9 ml oleic acid and 3.9 ml ODE at 280°C under N
   <sub>2</sub> flow. After 1 h the CdO was dissolved and the clear solution was degassed for 30 min at 110°C.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CsPbBr
   <sub>3</sub>/CdS Core/Shell QDs Synthesis
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the synthesis of CsPbBr
   <sub>3</sub> core QDs a protocol by Protesescu et al. (
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2015</a>) was adopted. One hundred milligram Cs
   <sub>2</sub>CO
   <sub>3</sub> was loaded into a 100 ml 3-neck flask along with 4 ml 1-octadecene, and 0.5 ml OA (oleic acid), then heated under N
   <sub>2</sub> to 120°C until the powder was completely dissolved. Five milliliter ODE and 69 mg PbBr
   <sub>2</sub> were loaded into a 100 ml 3-neck flask and heated under N
   <sub>2</sub> to 120°C 1 h. 0.5 ml OME and 0.5 ml OA was injected at 120°C under N
   <sub>2</sub>. After the PbBr
   <sub>2</sub> salt was completely dissolved, the temperature was raised to 150°C and the Cs-oleate solution (0.4 ml, 0.125 M in ODE, prepared as described above) was quickly injected and, 5 s later, the reaction finished. Four milliliter ODE, 1 ml Cd-oleate solution, and 0.4 ml 1 M sulfur in OME solution, was mixed when the reaction for CsPbBr
   <sub>3</sub> QDs finished and added dropwise over 20 min to the CsPbBr
   <sub>3</sub> solution at 150°C under N
   <sub>2</sub> flow. After the addition was complete, the mixture was allowed to react for 20 min at 150°C and was subsequently cooled by an ice-water bath, washed with toluene several times, and dispersed in toluene.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation of QLED</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cleaned ITO/glass was treated under UV–ozone for 30 min. The ZnO:Mg nanoparticles were spin-coated onto ITO/glass at 3,000 rpm for 40 s, and annealed at 100°C for 10 min. The perovskite QDs were deposited by spin-coating at 2,000 rpm for 60 s. CBP (40 nm), MoO
   <sub>3</sub> (10 nm), and Al (100 nm) electrodes were deposited using a thermal evaporation system through a shadow mask under a high vacuum of ≈1 × 10
   <span class="sup">−4</span> Pa. All device operations were performed in a nitrogen-filled glove box.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optical Characterization</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photoluminescence spectra were measured by Agilent Cary Eclipse spectrograph FLS920P. XRD characterization was done by Shimadzu/6100 X-ray diffractometer, using a Cu Kα radiation source (wavelength at 1.5405 Å). TEM images were recorded on a Zeiss/Libra 200 FE. The PLQY measurements were carried out in solutions with an Edinburgh Instruments fluorescence spectrometer (FLS920), which included a xenon lamp with monochromator for steady-state PL excitation. A calibrated integrating sphere was used for PLQY measurements. The EL spectra and luminance (
   <span class="italic">L</span>)—current density (
   <span class="italic">J</span>)—voltages (
   <span class="italic">V</span>) characteristics were collected using a Keithley 2400 source and a PR-670 Spectra Scan spectrophotometer (Photo Research) at room temperature.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
