<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the past two decades, huge efforts have been devoted to various QDs as the light-emitting layer of QLEDs (Coe et al., 
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">2002</a>; Sun et al., 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2007</a>; Kwak et al., 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">2012</a>; Seth and Samanta, 
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">2016</a>; Chen et al., 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2017</a>). Recently, perovskite QDs have attracted great attention due to their excellent optoelectronic performance, due to their tunable bandgap, high absorbance coefficient, and high photoluminescence quantum yield (PLQY) (Protesescu et al., 
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2015</a>; Song et al., 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">2015</a>; Tang et al., 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">2016</a>; Heejae et al., 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">2017</a>). However, the electroluminescence (EL) EQE of halide perovskite QLEDs is relatively lower to that of CdSe based QLEDs, which seriously limits further commercial application (Shirasaki et al., 
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">2013</a>; Dai et al., 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">2014</a>; Wang et al., 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">2018</a>). It is known that the photoluminescence (PL) performance of the QDs emitting layer plays a crucial role in QLED. Therefore, how to synthesize QDs with high quality is one critical step for preparing high performance QLEDs. It was recognized that the formation of core/shell structure between semiconductors is one effective approach to improve the performance of nanocrystals and QLEDs devices (Hines and Guyot-Sionnest, 
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">1996</a>; Li et al., 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">2011</a>). Many research groups have reported that the non-radiative Auger recombination of CdSe QDs could be efficiently suppressed by being coated with larger bandgap materials such as CdS and ZnS, where better optical properties have been achieved (Chen et al., 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">2008</a>; Bae et al., 
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">2013</a>; Efros and Nesbitt, 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">2016</a>). However, few studies on the core/shell structure for perovskite materials have been reported. Therefore, it is still a challenge to investigate a perovskite-based core/shell structure and the corresponding QLEDs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herein, we synthesized novel colloidal perovskite core/shell QDs by covering CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> QDs with a CdS shell. Moreover, the inverted QLEDs (ITO/ZnO:Mg/QDs/CBP(4,4′-Bis(N-carbazolyl)-1,1′-biphenyl)/MoO
  <sub>3</sub>/Al) based on CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub>/CdS core/shell QDs and pure CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> QDs were fabricated, respectively. The CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub>/CdS QDs based QLED exhibited the maximum luminance of 354 cd/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> with a CE of 0.3 cd/A and the best EQE of 0.4% was 5.4 times of the pure CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> QDs based QLEDs.
 </p>
</sec>
