<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation of electronic Hamiltonians</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The electronic structure is a quantum chemistry many-body problem that is usually difficult to solve due to the exponential growth of the Hilbert space with the size of the system. Typically, the aim is to compute ground-state energies and their associated eigenvectors of these interacting electron systems in a fixed nuclear potential.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the variety of methods for simulating fermionic models with quantum technologies, one of the most studied approaches considers quantum algorithms using the second quantized formalism of electronic systems
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">17</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">18</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">22</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>. The associated Hamiltonian may be represented in different bases, leading to different methods of encoding and scaling improvements in the number of qubits and gates required
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>. Furthermore, other approaches related to the Configuration Interaction (CI) matrix have been recently studied
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The generic Hamiltonian describing a molecular electronic structure consists of the electron kinetic energy term, two-electron Coulomb interactions, and the electron-nuclei potential energy representing the electronic environment
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">1</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" href="#b2">2</a>. This Hamiltonian in second quantization may be written as
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq1" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e283" xlink:href="srep27836-m1.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where the operators 
  <div id="d33e286" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e287" xlink:href="srep27836-m2.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> and 
  <span class="italic">c</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> stand for the electrons and obey the fermionic anticommutation relations. Coefficients 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ij</span>
  </sub> come from the single-electron integrals of the electron kinetic terms and electron-nuclei interactions, and 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ijkl</span>
  </sub> correspond to the two-electron integrals associated with the electron-electron Coulomb interaction. That is, it is expressed in atomic units as
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq3" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e309" xlink:href="srep27836-m3.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq4" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e312" xlink:href="srep27836-m4.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">k</span>
  </sub> are nuclear coordinates, 
  <span class="italic">r</span> electronic coordinates, and 
  <span class="italic">Z</span> the atomic number representing the nuclear charge. Here, {
  <span class="italic">φ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="bold">r</span>)} defines a set of spin orbitals, and 
  <span class="bold">r</span> = (
  <span class="italic">r</span>, 
  <span class="italic">σ</span>) denotes the pair of spatial and spin parameters.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optimal strategies of computation for quantum chemistry merge quantum simulation and classical numerical techniques. These methods, that we name as algorithmic quantum simulation
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">45</a>, allow us to employ quantum simulators for the computationally hard tasks, such as time evolution, on top of the classical algorithm, which provides flexibility for computing relevant observables. In the context of quantum chemistry, we have the example of ground state finding via a variational eigensolver
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">11</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">14</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" href="#b46">46</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">47</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">48</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulation of the dynamics associated with the electronic Hamiltonian in 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" href="#eq1">equation (1)</a> involves fermionic operators. Computations with fermionic degrees of freedom in superconducting circuits require the encoding of fermionic operators and their anticommutative algebra in the natural variables of this quantum platform. The Jordan-Wigner transformation
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">49</a> maps the fermionic operators into spin-1/2 operators, which gives us the qubit representation of the Hamiltonian. In the case of a hydrogen molecule, considering four electronic orbitals, the relations can be written as
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq5" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e362" xlink:href="srep27836-m5.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After this mapping, the Hamiltonian of 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" href="#eq1">equation (1)</a> for the H
  <sub>2</sub> molecule is rewritten in terms of spin-1/2 operators considering only the nonzero coefficients 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ij</span>
  </sub> and 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ijkl</span>
  </sub>, which are computed classically with polynomial resources
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">18</a>,
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq6" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e388" xlink:href="srep27836-m6.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq7" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e393" xlink:href="srep27836-m7.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, an analog quantum simulation of an arbitrary Hamiltonian evolution is a difficult problem
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" href="#b50">50</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">51</a>, since one cannot Straightforwardly map the dynamics of a given simulated system onto a given quantum platform. The flexibility and universality of digital quantum simulations allows us to reproduce models that do not appear naturally in a quantum platform. This is done via an expansion of the quantum evolution into discrete steps of quantum gates
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">52</a>. An additional advantage of such digital quantum simulations, in the spirit of gate-based quantum algorithms, is their possible improvement with quantum error correction techniques
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" href="#b53">53</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">54</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We consider the digital quantum simulation of the 
  <div id="d33e404" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e405" xlink:href="srep27836-m8.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> molecule via the Trotter expansion, which consists in dividing the evolution time 
  <span class="italic">t</span> into 
  <span class="italic">l</span> time intervals of length 
  <span class="italic">t</span>/
  <span class="italic">l</span>, and applying sequentially the evolution operator of each term of the Hamiltonian for each time interval
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">8</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">52</a>. The expression of this expansion for a Hamiltonian of the form 
  <div id="d33e422" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e423" xlink:href="srep27836-m9.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> reads
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq10" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e427" xlink:href="srep27836-m10.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">for large 
  <span class="italic">l</span>, where the dominating error component is 
  <div id="d33e433" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e434" xlink:href="srep27836-m11.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, which depends on the value of the commutators and scales with 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>/
  <span class="italic">l</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our case, we consider the evolution operators associated with the different summands of the Hamiltonian in 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10" href="#eq10">equation (5)</a>, which corresponds to the sequence of gates in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>. We propose an algorithm based on the optimised tunable CZ
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ϕ</span>
  </sub> gate, which allows one to perform efficiently ZZ interactions, or XX interactions in our basis
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>. In this sense, we arrange the gates and the simulated interactions such that it allows us to simplify the algorithm by eliminating some entangling gates and their inverses, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>. The single Trotter step depicted in this figure represents the approximated evolution for a time 
  <span class="italic">t</span>/
  <span class="italic">l</span> of the complete Hamiltonian. Note that the third and fourth logical qubits correspond to the fourth and third physical qubits, respectively. We choose this notation due to the reduction of SWAP gates needed for the performance of the protocol. The optimized Trotter step contains 24 XX two-qubit gates between nearest-neighbour qubits, 24 SWAP gates and 20 single-qubit rotations. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>, we show the efficiency of the digital protocol for different number of Trotter steps. Here, we analyze the loss of the state fidelity and the expected value of some operators performed in the simulation, considering simulated phases up to 
  <span class="italic">θ</span> = 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>11</sub>
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 2. We break down the Hamiltonian terms and plot the energies of each of them to observe separately the Trotter error associated with the different kinds of interactions appearing in the algorithm. We observe that, for a single Trotter step, the energies related to single-qubit gates are similar to the exact evolution, while in the case of the four body terms the deviation is higher.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Symmetric Trotter expansions provide the improvement of the digital error at the expense of more gate execution. The Hamiltonian of 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10" href="#eq10">equation (5)</a> can be divided in two groups of interactions, 
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>1</sub>, the sum of the first 10 terms that commute among them, and 
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>2</sub>, the sum of the last 4 terms that also commute among them. As commuting interactions do not generate digital error, the evolution of a symmetric Trotter step can be written as follows
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">52</a>,
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq12" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d33e501" xlink:href="srep27836-m12.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This protocol requires the implementation of the interactions of 
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>1</sub> one more time than in the regular digital protocol, thereby reducing the digital error. We introduce a fixed error for any two-qubit gate between nearest-neighbour qubits, without restricting ourselves to a specific setup or experimental source of error. Single-qubit gate errors are neglected due to their high fidelity with current technology. If the dominating error is the experimental one, then the aim is to reduce the number of gates and, consequently, the regular protocol gets better fidelities. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>, we analyze the errors of both the regular Trotter protocol and the symmetric protocol, and we give an upper bound of the total error summing the digital and the experimental error considering a range of values for the two-qubit gate error employed. For fixed number of Trotter steps, 
  <span class="italic">l</span> = 2, 3, 4, we observe crossing points between the errors associated with the symmetric protocol and the regular one whilst considering higher experimental gate error. On the left side of the crossing points, the experimental error is smaller and the symmetric protocol provides better results, whereas on the right side, as the experimental gate error grows, the regular protocol is more adequate. We also notice that, as the number of Trotter steps increases, the advantages of one protocol with respect to the other lessen. It is worthy to mention that the two-qubit gate errors are on the order of 10
  <span class="sup">−2 </span> in superconducting devices
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">54</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
