<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The F + H
  <sub>2</sub> reaction has been extensively studied for many years from a variety of perspectives, as reported in numerous papers and reviews appeared in the literature (see e.g., Manolopoulos, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">1997</a>; Liu, 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2001</a>; Der Chao and Skodje, 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">2002</a>; Althorpe and Clary, 
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">2003</a>; Qiu et al., 
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">2006</a>; Wang et al., 
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">2018</a> and references therein). Its peculiarity of being accessible both to theory and to experiments makes it an important prototype to validate methodologies to be used for more complex hydrogen atom transfer reactions, that show up in many areas of chemistry, ranging from processes in space (Neufeld et al., 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">2005</a>; Goumans and Kästner, 
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">2010</a>) to reactions in biological environments (Nagel and Klinman, 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">2006</a>). The discovery of the interstellar HF molecule (Neufeld et al., 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">1997</a>) and its recent observation in several astrophysical environments (see e.g., Emprechtinger et al., 
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">2012</a> and references therein), has also made this system very appealing for astro-chemistry. The large chemical stability and large dipole moment of the HF molecule make it favorably detectable, so that it may serve as a tracer for molecular hydrogen within the diffuse interstellar medium (Sonnentrucker et al., 
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">2010</a>), a valid alternative to CO molecule, the main tracer of molecular gas. An account of the chemistry of the HF molecule is given in Zhu et al. (
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">2002</a>). Being the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> reaction the only source of interstellar hydrogen fluoride, reliable kinetic data at low temperatures are of course highly desirable. In recent years, the field of cold and ultra-cold chemistry has seen a considerable growth becoming a frontier both for applied and theoretical research in physics and chemistry (see e.g., Smith, 
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">2008</a>; Krems et al., 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">2009</a>; Balakrishnan, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">2016</a>). The interested reader is directed to the recent review articles (Herschbach, 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">2009</a>; Hutzler et al., 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">2012</a>; Quemener and Julienne, 
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">2012</a>; van de Meerakker et al., 
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">2012</a>) for a detailed description of experimental and theoretical developments of the field of cold and ultra-cold molecules, and to (Lara et al., 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">2012</a>; Tizniti et al., 
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">2014</a>; Costes and Naulin, 
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">2016</a>) for progress on chemical reactivity at low temperature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The F + H
  <sub>2</sub> reaction and its isotopic counterpart F + D
  <sub>2</sub> are exothermic with a low energy barrier along the reaction path connecting reactants to products. At thermal or higher energies these reactions occur as thermally activated process. However, at sub-thermal energies the reaction gains access to quantum phenomena and the reactivity is higher than expected on the basis of classical theories. Quantum effects, such as scattering resonances, i.e., the formation of metastable states of the collision complex, and tunneling through the reaction barrier play a progressively larger role on the reactivity of these systems (see e.g., Althorpe and Clary, 
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">2003</a> and references therein), as energy or temperature decrease. Quantum threshold effects manifest themselves only at very low temperature, typically 1 K or less, when the de Broglie wavelength becomes comparable to, or longer than, the distances between colliding species (Simbotin et al., 
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">2011</a>, 
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">2014</a>). Theoretical approaches based on classical mechanics fail to describe the under-barrier reactivity, and therefore a detailed understanding of dynamics and kinetics requires quantum mechanical treatments and realistic potential energy surfaces. For a survey of the commonly used scattering theory methods see Schatz (
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">1996</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of the resonances for the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> reaction has been the subject of several previous theoretical and experimental works, for a recent review see Wang et al. (
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">2018</a>). Most of the effort has been devoted to understand the features above 20 meV coming from the large number of the metastable states supported by the van der Waals well in the exit channel (Manolopoulos, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">1997</a>; Der Chao and Skodje, 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">2002</a>; Aquilanti et al., 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">2004</a>). Nevertheless, it was also evident from experiments and theory (Takayanagi and Kurosaki, 
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">1998</a>; Aquilanti et al., 
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">2005a</a>) that resonances trapped by the van der Waals well in the entrance channel, although probably too narrow to be experimentally resolved, could play some role. In the following we show that the latter dominate the dynamics in the cold energy regime.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper we investigate the dynamics and kinetics of the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> and F + D
  <sub>2</sub> reactions at low temperatures, in a wide interval extending from near absolute zero to 50 K, where quantum mechanical effects control chemical reactivity. The aim is to determine how large they are and where they show up. In the quantum mechanical low-temperature regime, chemical reactivity is most sensitive to the details of the potential energy surface and small changes in the entrance channel interaction can enhance cross sections and rate constants by orders of magnitude. To this purpose, numerically exact quantum scattering calculations of integral cross sections and rate constants have been carried out on two potential energy surfaces, the Stark and Werner potential energy surface (SW PES hereafter) (Stark and Werner, 
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">1996</a>) and PES-II (Aquilanti et al., 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">2001</a>, 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">2005b</a>), differing only in the long-range interaction of the F atom with the H
  <sub>2</sub> molecule. Namely, the entrance channel van der Waals well of the PES-II is deeper, wider and shifted to larger intermolecular distances than for the SW PES, see Aquilanti et al. (
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">2005b</a>) for more details.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last ten years new 
  <span class="italic">ab-initio</span> potential energy surfaces have been published for this reaction: they are denoted FXZ (Fu et al., 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">2008</a>), CSZ (Chen et al., 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2015</a>), LWAL (Li et al., 
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">2007</a>; Lique et al., 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2011</a>) PESs. Unlike the SW PES, these surfaces include the effect of spin-orbit coupling. However, as more extensively discussed in a previous paper (De Fazio et al., 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">2016</a>), their reliability in describing the reaction dynamics in the cold and ultra-cold regimes is not as satisfactory as at higher energies. As is known, the neural network algorithm used in the fit of FXZ/CSZ PESs and the splines used to merge the three different local fits of LWAL PES can give rise to significant numerical instabilities when the ab-initio grid points are not dense enough, as they should be to push quantum scattering calculations down to the Wigner limit. The results of some test calculations below 1 K, have shown that none of them met the convergence requirements achieved with SW PES probably because of the artifacts of the fits to the ab initio points, and so we preferred not to present them. As pointed out in reference (Balakrishnan, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">2016</a>), the situation for the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> system is far from ideal. None of the available PESs provide an accurate treatment of the long-range interaction. As mentioned by the authors of both reference (Chen et al., 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2015</a>) and reference (Lique et al., 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2011</a>), further refinements in the description of the interaction around the van der Waals well in the entrance channel are needed in order to use CSZ and LWAL PESs in scattering calculations at energy below 0.1 meV.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The choice of PES-II is motivated by the recent experimental measurements (Tizniti et al., 
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">2014</a>) which have confirmed as realistic the description of the van der Waals region in the entrance channel, while the SW PES is used here for purpose of comparison with the results of other theoretical investigations. Further experimental evidences of the reliability of PES-II at low collision energies will be shown in the present article. The SW PES and PES-II have the same barrier height but a slightly different width. Thus, the comparison between the two PESs allows to assess the relevance that barrier width, other than barrier height and exo-ergicity, has on the intermolecular kinetic isotope effect of H-transfer reactions at low temperature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first quantum reactive scattering calculations for the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> system at ultra-cold temperatures were made more than 15 years ago (Balakrishnan and Dalgarno, 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">2001</a>; Bodo et al., 
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">2004</a>). However, these papers presented only calculations with zero total angular momentum, so that reliable information was obtained only in the Wigner regime. Convergent rate constants, calculated by the hyper-quantization technique (Aquilanti et al., 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">1998</a>), down to a few Kelvin, were published by our research group (Aquilanti et al., 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">2005b</a>). Here, we extend this previous study at very low temperatures where the sensitivity to the entrance channel interaction is larger. Because of the relevance that the analysis of the kinetic isotope effect (KIE) has especially in organic chemistry and biochemistry (see e.g., Roston et al., 
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">2013</a>), the temperature dependence of the intermolecular kinetic isotope effect has also been assessed. The quantum dynamics and kinetics of the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> and F + D
  <sub>2</sub> reactions are predicted form first principles using a coupled channel method summarized in section 2. The effects of tunneling, resonances and isotope substitution on cross sections and rate constants are discussed in section 3; conclusions follow in section 4.
 </p>
</sec>
