<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1. Kinetic Isotope Effect</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ratio between the rates of the lighter and the heavier isotopic combinations is a measure of the inter-molecular kinetic isotope effect (KIE) (Steckler et al., 
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">1985</a>). The temperature dependence of KIE is shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Figure 4</a>. The rate constant of the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> reaction increases drastically as temperature decreases, so that in the ultra-cold regime the fluorine atom is about one hundred times more reactive with H
  <sub>2</sub> than with D
  <sub>2</sub> on SW PES. We note that this effect is about two orders of magnitude larger than the semi-classical limit (Bigeleisen, 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">1949</a>), which applies above room temperature, where the tunnel effect is negligible and the main source of KIE comes from the difference among the reactants' zero point energies, the so-called primary KIE. At low temperatures (until 1 K), the features are markedly influenced by the tunnel effect giving an exponential enhancement (Bell, 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">1980</a>) more evident in PES-II where the barrier is thicker. Below 1 K the KIE behavior in two PESs is very different: a typical sigmoid curve is observed on SW PES, while the resonance enhancement of the rates give rise to a maximum observed at about 1 K in the case of PES-II. This big difference is of course due to the presence of the virtual state effect that enhances selectively the F + H
  <sub>2</sub> rate of the SW PES curve, hiding also the smaller resonance KIE effect. Below 1 mK the rates are temperature independent and therefore also is the KIE.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Temperature dependence of the inter-molecular kinetic isotope effect for the two potential energy surfaces investigated.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fchem-07-00328-g0004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
