<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reactivity of the F atom with the H
  <sub>2</sub> and D
  <sub>2</sub> molecules in their ground roto-vibrational state has been investigated in the quantum mechanical low-temperature regime (0.5 mK–50 K), where because of the prominent role of tunneling and resonances, the rates show pronounced deviations from the Arrhenius law before they become independent of temperature near absolute zero according to the Wigner law. The latter, unlike the Arrhenius' law, predicts that chemical reaction rates do not tend to zero when collision energies become vanishingly small. Total integral cross sections and rate constants have been calculated by numerically exact quantum reactive scattering calculations carried out on two potential energy surfaces, the widely used SW PES and a variant of it referred to as PES-II, differing in the description of the van der Waals well in the reactants' channel. The results have shown that the small changes in the entrance channel interaction and the isotopic substitution lead to the enhancement of cross sections and rate coefficients by many orders of magnitude and induce an unexpected dependence of the intermolecular kinetic isotope effect on temperature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A quantitative assessment of the extent of the roles of tunneling and resonances, as well as that of the energy region where these quantum effects show up, has been provided. We have shown that the wide interval of collision energies and temperatures analyzed can be adequately divided into smaller domains within which the reactivity is differently influenced by the different quantum mechanical effects: at ultra-cold energies, the title reaction and its isotopic variant occur only via the tunneling pathway possibly enhanced by virtual state effects; in the cold collision regime, cross sections and rate coefficients are additionally affected by shape resonances in the entrance channel of the potential energy surface, that enhance the contribution of the tunnel effect; finally, as the collision energy gets closer to the height of the classical barrier, the tunneling enhanced by a resonance state trapped in the transition state region of the potential energy surface competes with the over-barrier mechanism.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ultra-cold results obtained with the SW PES corroborate previous studies (Bodo et al., 
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">2004</a>; Simbotin and Côté, 
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">2015</a>) made with the same PES, namely that a virtual state in the reactants' van der Waals well deeply affects the ultra-cold reactivity of the F+H
  <sub>2</sub> reaction. However, no evidence of this effect is found in the PES-II calculations. The large difference in the KIE behavior between the two PES suggests that this is likely the most sensitive observable to emphasize these features.
 </p>
</sec>
