<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec id="sec001" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Objectives</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three strong interactions between amino acid side chains (salt bridge, cation-π, and amide bridge) are studied that are stronger than (or comparable to) the common hydrogen bond interactions, and play important roles in protein-protein interactions.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec002" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantum chemical methods MP2 and CCSD(T) are used in calculations of interaction energies and structural optimizations.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The energies of three types of amino acid side chain interactions in gaseous phase and in aqueous solutions are calculated using high level quantum chemical methods and basis sets. Typical examples of amino acid salt bridge, cation-π, and amide bridge interactions are analyzed, including the inhibitor design targeting neuraminidase (NA) enzyme of influenza A virus, and the ligand binding interactions in the HCV p7 ion channel. The inhibition mechanism of the M2 proton channel in the influenza A virus is analyzed based on strong amino acid interactions.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(1) The salt bridge interactions between acidic amino acids (Glu
   <span class="sup">-</span> and Asp
   <span class="sup">-</span>) and alkaline amino acids (Arg
   <span class="sup">+</span>, Lys
   <span class="sup">+</span> and His
   <span class="sup">+</span>) are the strongest residue-residue interactions. However, this type of interaction may be weakened by solvation effects and broken by lower pH conditions. (2) The cation- interactions between protonated amino acids (Arg
   <span class="sup">+</span>, Lys
   <span class="sup">+</span> and His
   <span class="sup">+</span>) and aromatic amino acids (Phe, Tyr, Trp and His) are 2.5 to 5-fold stronger than common hydrogen bond interactions and are less affected by the solvation environment. (3) The amide bridge interactions between the two amide-containing amino acids (Asn and Gln) are three times stronger than hydrogen bond interactions, which are less influenced by the pH of the solution. (4) Ten of the twenty natural amino acids are involved in salt bridge, or cation-, or amide bridge interactions that often play important roles in protein-protein, protein-peptide, protein-ligand, and protein-DNA interactions.
  </p>
 </sec>
</div>
