<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pyrite usually exists in magmatite rocks, contact metasomatic deposits and hydrothermal deposits. Coal pyrite is the pyrite produced in the coal environment and formed with the formation of coal. The floatability of pyrite is usually determined by its own nature, and the same is true for coal pyrite. The nature of coal pyrite is closely related to its lattice defects. Compared with pyrite, defects appear in the lattice of coal pyrite, and then the special physical and chemical properties form, which enhance its floatability [
  <a rid="B1-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-molecules-24-02285">1</a>]. To remove the coal pyrite during the flotation process efficiently, it is very important for the subsequent flotation desulfurization to study the hydrophobicity of the surface of coal pyrite and its forming mechanism. Many scholars have studied the relationship between the lattice defects of coal pyrite and its hydrophobicity [
  <a rid="B2-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-molecules-24-02285">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-molecules-24-02285">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-molecules-24-02285">4</a>]. The authors [
  <a rid="B5-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-molecules-24-02285">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-molecules-24-02285">6</a>] found that there existed doped carbon on the coal pyrite surface and only simulated the effect of carbon defects on the doping-position of coal pyrite. This finding revealed the mechanism of change in hydrophobicity at the doping-position using DFT. However, the macroscopic hydrophobicity of coal pyrite not only reflects the hydrophobic change at the doping-position but also reflects the overall change in hydrophobicity at all regions of the coal pyrite surface. Meanwhile, it was not accurate to determine the structure and electronic properties of pyrite only using DFT, resulting in a small band gap of strongly associated semiconductor materials. Many authors often employed the DFT+U method to calculate the electronic structure and properties of the simulated pyrite and found that the band gap was closer to the experimental value of 0.95 eV [
  <a rid="B7-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-molecules-24-02285">7</a>]. Zhang et al. [
  <a rid="B8-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-molecules-24-02285">8</a>] explored the effect of different U values on the band gap and finally concluded that the bulk pyrite band gap was 1.02 eV with a U value of 2.0 eV. Sun et al. [
  <a rid="B9-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-molecules-24-02285">9</a>] came to a conclusion that when the U value was 2.0 eV, the band gap of the bulk pyrite was 1.03 eV. Additionally, Li et al. [
  <a rid="B10-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-molecules-24-02285">10</a>] found that the band gap was 0.95 eV using the GGA+U with a U value of 1.2 eV.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Density Functional Theory (DFT) based on the first-principles method can give deep insights about the adsorption configuration between the adsorbates and the surface. Meanwhile, it can subsequently reveal the adsorption mechanism of the adsorbates on the surface. Chen et al. [
  <a rid="B11-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-molecules-24-02285">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-molecules-24-02285">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-molecules-24-02285">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-molecules-24-02285">14</a>] and Li et al. [
  <a rid="B15-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-02285">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-molecules-24-02285">16</a>] investigated the adsorption mechanism of H
  <sub>2</sub>O, CaOH, and O
  <sub>2</sub> on the pyrite surface. The above study showed that it is feasible to calculate the adsorption of the molecule on the pyrite surface based on the Density Functional Theory. The previous study only [
  <a rid="B5-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-molecules-24-02285">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-molecules-24-02285">6</a>] calculated the influence of the substituted and adsorbed carbon atoms on the adsorption of the single water molecule at the carbon atom doping- and adsorption position. The adsorption process, when the water molecule adsorbs on the other position of the whole one carbon atom-substituted pyrite surface, was not studied to reveal the mechanism of the whole coal pyrite’s hydrophilicity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the previous research, the adsorption processes of water molecules are simulated at the doping-position, ortho-position and meta-position of coal pyrite surface with the DFT+U method. The adsorption configuration, adsorption strength, bonding properties and bond strength, charge transfer and density of states of water molecules adsorbed at different positions on the coal pyrite surface containing carbon defects are compared with respect to adsorption energy, bond population and Mulliken charge population. The mechanism of the overall weakening of the hydrophilicity of coal pyrite under the condition of carbon defects is fully explained at the molecular level.</p>
</sec>
