<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Adsorption Configurations and Adsorption Energies</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the doped carbon atom as the centre of the coal pyrite, the “doping region” of coal pyrite means that the water molecule was adsorbed on the iron atom, which was connected to the carbon atom. The “ortho region” means that the adsorption site of the iron atom was not connected to the carbon atom and that the doped carbon atom did not directly participate in adsorption and bonding. The “meta region” means that the adsorption site was farther away from the centre, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f002" href="#molecules-24-02285-f002">Figure 2</a>. The “undoped region” means that the pyrite was ideal, with no carbon atom. The different adsorption sites of H
  <sub>2</sub>O on the coal pyrite surface are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f002" href="#molecules-24-02285-f002">Figure 2</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies [
  <a rid="B5-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-molecules-24-02285">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-molecules-24-02285">6</a>] have shown that the adsorption model of H
  <sub>2</sub>O on the pyrite surface (in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f003" href="#molecules-24-02285-f003">Figure 3</a>a) was more stable, which was selected as the basic model to explore the influence of doped carbon atoms on the adsorption configurations, E
  <sub>ads</sub>, bonding, charge transfer and density of states (DOS) of H
  <sub>2</sub>O on the pyrite surface in the paper. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The adsorption configurations and adsorption energies of water molecules on the ideal pyrite surface and the doping-position, ortho-position and meta-position of the surface doped with carbon atoms are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f003" href="#molecules-24-02285-f003">Figure 3</a> and 
  <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t002">Table 2</a>. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results revealed that the adsorption energies of the water molecule at the doping-position, ortho-position and meta-position of the pyrite surface doped with carbon atoms were lager than that of the ideal surface, and the adsorption energy respectively decreased, which gradually approached but remained lower than the E
  <sub>ads</sub> (−79.19 kJ/mol) of the ideal surface [
  <a rid="B22-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-molecules-24-02285">22</a>]. These results suggest that the water was easier to adsorb on the ideal surface and it was indicated that H
  <sub>2</sub>O can still be spontaneously adsorbed on any position of the pyrite surface doped with carbon atoms, but only the adsorption strength was relatively weaker. Meanwhile, with the distance from the doping centre, the negative value of adsorption energy of H
  <sub>2</sub>O on the surface increased gradually. The doping carbon atom had the greatest influence on the adsorption of H
  <sub>2</sub>O at the doping site, and the farther away from the doping centre, the smaller the adsorption effect. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above results showed that the macroscopic overall weakening of the hydrophilicity of coal pyrite doped by carbon atoms was due to the weakening of the adsorption of the water molecule at various positions (doping-position, ortho-position and meta-position) on the surface, which ultimately resulted in the coal pyrite showing the property of easier flotation during the process of slime flotation. </p>
</sec>
