<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Analysis of Bonding</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Mulliken population [
  <a rid="B29-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-molecules-24-02285">29</a>] showed the strength of the interaction between the bonding atoms after the adsorbate adsorbed on the adsorbent. Generally, the larger the bond Mulliken population, the shorter the bond length, and the stronger the covalent bond formed between atoms. The bond Mulliken population and bond length after adsorption of H
  <sub>2</sub>O on different sites of the pyrite surface are shown in 
  <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t003" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t003">Table 3</a>. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After H
  <sub>2</sub>O was adsorbed on the modified pyrite surface, the Fe–O covalent bond was formed and the bond population increased and approached that of the ideal surface gradually [
  <a rid="B23-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-molecules-24-02285">23</a>]. The Mulliken population results showed that the strength of the Fe–O bond increased gradually, and the farther away from the doping centre of carbon atoms, the more stable the adsorption of the water molecule was, which was in accordance with the results of E
  <sub>ads</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The electron density and the charge density difference with respect to both O and Fe were further analysed. The deeper the red in the charge density map, the greater the charge density there. The red was deeper and therefore exhibited more electron cloud between O and Fe, which indicated that the bond between them was strong, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f004" href="#molecules-24-02285-f004">Figure 4</a>. In the charge density difference map, the red region indicated an increase in electron density, and the blue region indicated a decrease, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f005" href="#molecules-24-02285-f005">Figure 5</a>. With the deviation from the doping centre, there were more charge density distributions and obvious charge transfers between the iron atom and the oxygen atom, which gradually approached but remained lower than that of the ideal surface. These results indicated that the interaction between the water molecule and the modified pyrite surface became stronger gradually with the distance of the doping centre, but was lower than that of the ideal surface.
 </p>
</sec>
