<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Adsorption Configurations and Adsorption Energies</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the doped carbon atom as the centre of the coal pyrite, the “doping region” of coal pyrite means that the water molecule was adsorbed on the iron atom, which was connected to the carbon atom. The “ortho region” means that the adsorption site of the iron atom was not connected to the carbon atom and that the doped carbon atom did not directly participate in adsorption and bonding. The “meta region” means that the adsorption site was farther away from the centre, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f002" href="#molecules-24-02285-f002">Figure 2</a>. The “undoped region” means that the pyrite was ideal, with no carbon atom. The different adsorption sites of H
   <sub>2</sub>O on the coal pyrite surface are shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f002" href="#molecules-24-02285-f002">Figure 2</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies [
   <a rid="B5-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-molecules-24-02285">5</a>,
   <a rid="B6-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-molecules-24-02285">6</a>] have shown that the adsorption model of H
   <sub>2</sub>O on the pyrite surface (in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f003" href="#molecules-24-02285-f003">Figure 3</a>a) was more stable, which was selected as the basic model to explore the influence of doped carbon atoms on the adsorption configurations, E
   <sub>ads</sub>, bonding, charge transfer and density of states (DOS) of H
   <sub>2</sub>O on the pyrite surface in the paper. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The adsorption configurations and adsorption energies of water molecules on the ideal pyrite surface and the doping-position, ortho-position and meta-position of the surface doped with carbon atoms are shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f003" href="#molecules-24-02285-f003">Figure 3</a> and 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t002" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t002">Table 2</a>. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results revealed that the adsorption energies of the water molecule at the doping-position, ortho-position and meta-position of the pyrite surface doped with carbon atoms were lager than that of the ideal surface, and the adsorption energy respectively decreased, which gradually approached but remained lower than the E
   <sub>ads</sub> (−79.19 kJ/mol) of the ideal surface [
   <a rid="B22-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-molecules-24-02285">22</a>]. These results suggest that the water was easier to adsorb on the ideal surface and it was indicated that H
   <sub>2</sub>O can still be spontaneously adsorbed on any position of the pyrite surface doped with carbon atoms, but only the adsorption strength was relatively weaker. Meanwhile, with the distance from the doping centre, the negative value of adsorption energy of H
   <sub>2</sub>O on the surface increased gradually. The doping carbon atom had the greatest influence on the adsorption of H
   <sub>2</sub>O at the doping site, and the farther away from the doping centre, the smaller the adsorption effect. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above results showed that the macroscopic overall weakening of the hydrophilicity of coal pyrite doped by carbon atoms was due to the weakening of the adsorption of the water molecule at various positions (doping-position, ortho-position and meta-position) on the surface, which ultimately resulted in the coal pyrite showing the property of easier flotation during the process of slime flotation. </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Analysis of Bonding</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Mulliken population [
   <a rid="B29-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-molecules-24-02285">29</a>] showed the strength of the interaction between the bonding atoms after the adsorbate adsorbed on the adsorbent. Generally, the larger the bond Mulliken population, the shorter the bond length, and the stronger the covalent bond formed between atoms. The bond Mulliken population and bond length after adsorption of H
   <sub>2</sub>O on different sites of the pyrite surface are shown in 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t003" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t003">Table 3</a>. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After H
   <sub>2</sub>O was adsorbed on the modified pyrite surface, the Fe–O covalent bond was formed and the bond population increased and approached that of the ideal surface gradually [
   <a rid="B23-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-molecules-24-02285">23</a>]. The Mulliken population results showed that the strength of the Fe–O bond increased gradually, and the farther away from the doping centre of carbon atoms, the more stable the adsorption of the water molecule was, which was in accordance with the results of E
   <sub>ads</sub>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The electron density and the charge density difference with respect to both O and Fe were further analysed. The deeper the red in the charge density map, the greater the charge density there. The red was deeper and therefore exhibited more electron cloud between O and Fe, which indicated that the bond between them was strong, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f004" href="#molecules-24-02285-f004">Figure 4</a>. In the charge density difference map, the red region indicated an increase in electron density, and the blue region indicated a decrease, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f005" href="#molecules-24-02285-f005">Figure 5</a>. With the deviation from the doping centre, there were more charge density distributions and obvious charge transfers between the iron atom and the oxygen atom, which gradually approached but remained lower than that of the ideal surface. These results indicated that the interaction between the water molecule and the modified pyrite surface became stronger gradually with the distance of the doping centre, but was lower than that of the ideal surface.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. The Charge Transfer</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The charge transfer refers to the loss and transfer of electrons between atoms after adsorption of adsorbate on the surface of the adsorbent, which was expressed by the Mulliken charge population (MCP), as shown in 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t004" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t004">Table 4</a>, 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t005" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t005">Table 5</a>, 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t006" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t006">Table 6</a> and 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t007" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t007">Table 7</a>, before adsorption (BA) and after adsorption (AA) of H
   <sub>2</sub>O on the surface of the ideal pyrite and at different positions of pyrite doped with carbon atoms. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar to the MCP results of atoms on the ideal surface, after the adsorption of H
   <sub>2</sub>O at the different sites of the pyrite surface with carbon defects, whether the water molecule adsorbed at the doping-position, ortho-position or meta-position, the negative charge of the oxygen atom in the water molecule also decreased due to the loss of approximately 0.20 e of the O 2p orbital, and the positive charge of the Fe atom on the surface also increased due to the gain of approximately 0.07 e, which may be the similar adsorption results of the single water molecule at various positions. Finally, electron aggregation enabled H
   <sub>2</sub>O to be stably adsorbed on the pyrite surface.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot4-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. The Density of States (DOS)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interaction between H
   <sub>2</sub>O and the coal pyrite was mainly through the interaction between O of the former, and C and Fe of the latter. Therefore, only the PDOS values of O, C and Fe were plotted before and after adsorption [
   <a rid="B30-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-molecules-24-02285">30</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After H
   <sub>2</sub>O was adsorbed on the different locations of the pyrite surface doped by carbon atoms (shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f006" href="#molecules-24-02285-f006">Figure 6</a>b–d), similarly to the results of the ideal surface [
   <a rid="B19-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-molecules-24-02285">19</a>], the covalent bond and anti-bond were formed between the water molecule and the pyrite surface through the O 2p orbital and the Fe 3d orbital. The bonding energy between Fe and O was very strong, while the anti-bonding was quite weak. However, the strength of the covalent bond increased with the distance from the carbon defect centre, which was close to that of the ideal pyrite surface. 
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
