<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Calculation Methods and Model</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Calculation Methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the process of structural optimizations, the module of CASTEP was used and the exchange-correlation interaction among electrons was described by the generalized-gradient approximation (GGA)-PW91. [
   <a rid="B17-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-molecules-24-02285">17</a>,
   <a rid="B18-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-molecules-24-02285">18</a>]. The interactions between the ionic cores and the valence electrons (Fe 3d
   <span class="sup">6</span>4s
   <span class="sup">2</span>, S 3s
   <span class="sup">2</span>3p4, C 2s
   <span class="sup">2</span>2p
   <span class="sup">2</span>) were modelled with ultra-soft pseudopotentials (USP) [
   <a rid="B19-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-molecules-24-02285">19</a>]. We used a cut-off of 350 eV for the plane-wave basis expansion [
   <a rid="B15-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-molecules-24-02285">15</a>] and a Monkhorst-Pack [
   <a rid="B20-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-molecules-24-02285">20</a>,
   <a rid="B21-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-molecules-24-02285">21</a>] k-point sampling density of 4 × 4 × 4 mesh. To more accurately describe the delocalization of electrons in the transition metal compound, the Hubbard U value of 1.2 eV was used to correct the orbit of Fe 3d. The Fe 3d was treated by the adoption of the Hubbard U correction in the paper and specified by tests in the previous paper [
   <a rid="B22-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-molecules-24-02285">22</a>,
   <a rid="B23-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-molecules-24-02285">23</a>]. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, we optimized the carbon atom and water molecule in a 20 × 20 × 20 Å cubic cell with Brillouin zone sampling restricted to the Gamma point in the calculation process. The other parameters were consistent with those reported above.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strengths of the interactions between the adsorbates (water molecules) and the adsorbent (pyrite surface) were expressed by the adsorption energy (E
   <sub>ads</sub>) in the paper [
   <a rid="B24-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-molecules-24-02285">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-molecules-24-02285">25</a>,
   <a rid="B26-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-molecules-24-02285">26</a>,
   <a rid="B27-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-molecules-24-02285">27</a>], defined as:
   <div class="disp-formula">E
    <sub>ads</sub> = E
    <sub>X/slab</sub> − nE
    <sub>X</sub> − E
    <sub>slab</sub>,
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
   </div> where E
   <sub>ads</sub> is the adsorption energy and X is the carbon atoms or water molecules. n is the number of carbon atoms or water molecules. E
   <sub>X/slab</sub> is the energy of the pyrite surface with water molecules. E
   <sub>slab</sub> and E
   <sub>X</sub> are the energy of the pyrite surface and H
   <sub>2</sub>O, respectively. The more negative the E
   <sub>ads</sub>, the stronger the interaction between the adsorbate and mineral surface.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-molecules-24-02285" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Surface Model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the paper, the FeS
   <sub>2</sub> (100) 2 × 2 × 1 supercell surface model cut from the optimized pyrite bulk cell was used as the undoped pyrite surface, which had 15 atomic layers, 15 Å vacuum layers and the bottom 9 atomic layers fixed. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pyrite surface model doped with carbon atoms was optimized by impurity substitution energy [
   <a rid="B28-molecules-24-02285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-molecules-24-02285">28</a>]. The impurity substitution energy was the energy required to replace atoms in the surface lattice with impurity atoms, which measured the difficulty of substitution, defined as:
   <div class="disp-formula">ΔE = E
    <sub>total/C</sub> + E
    <sub>X</sub> − E
    <sub>total/perfect</sub> − E
    <sub>C</sub>,
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
   </div> where △E is the impurity substitution energy and E
   <sub>total/C</sub> is the energy of the pyrite surface substituted by the carbon atom. E
   <sub>total/perfect</sub> is the energy of a perfect pyrite surface. E
   <sub>X</sub> and E
   <sub>C</sub> are the energies of the iron atom (or sulfur atom) and carbon atom, respectively. n is the number of carbon, sulfur or iron atoms. The △E was negative, which means that the substituted structure was feasible. The larger the negative value, the more stable the structure. The impurity substitution energy and substitution model are shown in 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t001" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t001">Table 1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f001" href="#molecules-24-02285-f001">Figure 1</a>, respectively, after the sulfur and iron atoms of the ideal pyrite surface were substituted by carbon atoms.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It can be seen from 
   <a rid="molecules-24-02285-t001" ref-type="table" href="#molecules-24-02285-t001">Table 1</a> that △E was negative after the substitution of a carbon atom for a sulfur atom, and the △E of HS had a larger negative value. However, the △E of F was positive (△E = 51.2 kJ/mol). It was indicated that the sulfur atom of the pyrite surface could be spontaneously replaced by the carbon atom, and stable configurations were finally formed (shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02285-f001" href="#molecules-24-02285-f001">Figure 1</a>c,d). Conversely, the iron atom can only be substituted by a certain amount of additional energy. The high-position sulfur atom and the low-position were, respectively, three coordination (unsaturated state) and four coordination (saturated state) so that it was easier for the high-position sulfur to be substituted. Simultaneously, because the properties of carbon atoms were close to those of sulfur atoms, but different from those of iron atoms, it was more difficult for iron atoms to be substituted, which was consistent with the theoretical calculations of isomorphism occurrence.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
