<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-nanomaterials-09-00495" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon quantum dots (CQDs) are a promising material, featuring fluorescent carbon nanoparticles of less than 10 nm in size with a high surface-to-volume ratio [
  <a rid="B1-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-nanomaterials-09-00495">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-nanomaterials-09-00495">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-nanomaterials-09-00495">3</a>]. Compared with other semiconductor QDs materials, such as CdS QDs, PbS QDs, etc., CQDs offer many advantages including good biocompatibility [
  <a rid="B4-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-nanomaterials-09-00495">4</a>], robust chemical inertness [
  <a rid="B5-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-nanomaterials-09-00495">5</a>], low toxicity [
  <a rid="B6-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-nanomaterials-09-00495">6</a>], and outstanding optical properties [
  <a rid="B7-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-nanomaterials-09-00495">7</a>], making them a promising carbon-based nanomaterial for applications such as biological sensing [
  <a rid="B8-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-nanomaterials-09-00495">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-nanomaterials-09-00495">9</a>], bioimaging and photodynamic therapy [
  <a rid="B10-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-nanomaterials-09-00495">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nanomaterials-09-00495">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nanomaterials-09-00495">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-nanomaterials-09-00495">13</a>], drug delivery [
  <a rid="B14-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nanomaterials-09-00495">14</a>] and analysis [
  <a rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nanomaterials-09-00495">15</a>], light-emitting diodes (LEDs) [
  <a rid="B16-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-nanomaterials-09-00495">16</a>], and solar cells [
  <a rid="B17-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-nanomaterials-09-00495">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To date, CQDs were synthesized via various methods which can be generally classified into two categories, “bottom-up” approaches and “top-down” approaches. In the “bottom-up” approaches, organic [
  <a rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-nanomaterials-09-00495">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-nanomaterials-09-00495">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nanomaterials-09-00495">20</a>] or natural substances are carbonized [
  <a rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-nanomaterials-09-00495">21</a>] to fabricate CQDs, and “top-down” approaches feature cutting large-sized carbon materials [
  <a rid="B1-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-nanomaterials-09-00495">1</a>,
  <a rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-nanomaterials-09-00495">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-nanomaterials-09-00495">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nanomaterials-09-00495">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-nanomaterials-09-00495">25</a>] (e.g., graphite, activated carbon, carbon nanotubes, graphene oxide, carbon soot, etc.) into small-sized CQDs. Among the various approaches, the acidic exfoliation method, hydrothermal method, and microwave-assisted treatment method are the most common and dominant approaches. Generally, these methods are relatively complex, expensive, and environmentally hazardous in preparation processes of CQDs. Most of the obtained CQDs have only one photoluminescence (PL) emission with size-dependent and surface-passivation-dependent properties, which limit their further applications in dual-wavelength fluorescent emissions. In addition, some impurities are always produced due to the introduction of a strong acid in the preparation process of CQDs, resulting in the PL mechanism of CQDs being ambiguous. Therefore, it is very important to understand the PL mechanism of CQDs, especially for CQDs with dual-wavelength PL emissions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared with the abovementioned methods, pulsed laser ablation (PLA) is a unique and novel approach, which is simple, cost-effective, and environmentally friendly in the fabrication process of carbon-based nanomaterials without any impurities [
  <a rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-nanomaterials-09-00495">26</a>]. Anomalous reactions and growth of the fragmented species can occur under non-equilibrium conditions, such as high temperature and high pressure in liquid. Many efforts showed the possibility for the synthesis of carbonic nanomaterial by nanosecond- or femtosecond-laser ablation of highly oriented pyrolytic graphite (HOPG) [
  <a rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-nanomaterials-09-00495">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00495">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-nanomaterials-09-00495">29</a>]. At present, the study of CQDs is in a new era. However, there are still many challenging issues to be solved, including the following: (1) carbon precursors for the preparation of CQDs by pulsed laser ablation are high-cost and non-renewable [
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00495">28</a>,
  <a rid="B30-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-nanomaterials-09-00495">30</a>]; (2) the fluorescence quantum yield of CQDs is relatively low in many solvents such as water and ethyl acetate oleamide (often less than 20%) using the pulsed laser ablation method [
  <a rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-nanomaterials-09-00495">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00495" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-nanomaterials-09-00495">28</a>], which limits their applications in biomedical imaging and optoelectronics; (3) the PL mechanism of CQDs, especially for dual-wavelength PL mechanism, remains ambiguous. Therefore, it is necessary to propose a new and cost-effective preparation strategy to obtain pure CQDs with a high quantum yield and dual-wavelength PL emission for an understanding of the PL mechanism and application in biomedical imaging and engineering.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this work, N-doped micropore CQDs (NM-CQDs) with a high quantum yield and dual-wavelength PL emission were fabricated using pulsed laser ablation from low-cost and sustainable 
  <span class="italic">Platanus</span> biomass rather than using expensive carbon precursors. Unlike most reports, the NM-CQDs passivated by formamide solvent presented two coexisting and excitation-independent PL emission peaks, elucidating that the excited electrons transited from the intrinsic π* orbital to the surface state (SS). The PL intensities of NM-CQDs were stable after nine days, and the PL quantum yield and average fluorescence lifetime (FL) were 32.4% and 6.56 ns, respectively. Further investigations indicated that the PL emission behaviors of the formamide-passivated NM-CQDs were still stable in various conditions. In addition, the obtained NM-CQDs are very suitable for cell bioimaging and show good internalization in different cells. Therefore, we propose a new preparation strategy for highly fluorescent NM-CQDs with great potential in biomedical imaging and engineering.
 </p>
</sec>
