<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot1-nanomaterials-09-00495" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Preparation of Highly Fluorescent NM-CQDs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00495-f001" href="#nanomaterials-09-00495-f001">Figure 1</a> shows the synthesis process scheme of NM-CQDs derived from waste 
  <span class="italic">Platanus</span> biomass. Firstly, fruits of waste 
  <span class="italic">Platanus</span> biomass were washed clean with deionized (DI) water, and were then dried in a vacuum-drying cabinet. Subsequently, the dried fruits were carbonized in a tube furnace filled with N
  <sub>2</sub> at 600 °C for 2 h. Then, 0.5 g of carbonized sample was mixed with 1 g of KOH in 20 mL of DI water. The mixture was sonicated and agitated for 30 min, and then dried in a vacuum cabinet again. Finally, the mixture was chemically activated in a tube furnace to form a microporous carbon material at 900 °C. For investigating the effect of micropores, another comparative experiment was performed without using KOH. Briefly, 0.5 g of carbonized powder was directly mixed with 20 mL of DI water, and then the mixture was sonicated and agitated for 30 min. The sample was dried and further carbonized to form a non-microporous carbon precursor in a tube furnace at 900 °C.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The porous carbon (PC) powder was dispersed in 5 mL of formamide solvent in a cuvette, and the opening was covered with a polystyrene cap. The cuvette was placed on a three-dimensional (3D) stage. The mixture solution was ablated by a pulsed laser beam with a continuously adjusting 3D stage. After that, the solution was centrifuged at 10,000 rpm five times. Finally, the yellow solution containing NM-CQDs was obtained. Here, apart from formamide, ethyl acetate and ethylene glycol solvent were also used in the preparation of CQDs, and they were called M-CQDs-EA and M-CQDs-EG, respectively. In addition, N-CQDs were prepared by pulsed laser ablation of the non-micropore carbon precursor target in formamide. Broadly speaking, the wavelength and the repetition rate of the neodymium-doped yttrium aluminum garnet (Nd:YAG) pulsed laser were 1064 nm and 10 Hz, respectively. The laser energy and the pulse width were modulated to around 20 mJ and 3–6 ns. The ablation time was about 30 min; the homemade pulsed laser ablation system is shown in 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-nanomaterials-09-00495" href="#app1-nanomaterials-09-00495">Figure S1 (Supplementary Materials)</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
