<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-nanomaterials-09-00495" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Characterization of Highly Fluorescent NM-CQDs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The surface morphology of the PC was imaged on a field-emission scanning electron microscope (Model: JSM-7500 F, JEOL Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). TEM and high-resolution TEM (HR-TEM) images of NM-CQDs were taken on a transmission electron microscope (Model: JEM 2100, JEOL Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). Specific areas and porosities of sample were acquired on an automated gas sorption analyzer (Model: BELSORP-MAX, Bel Japan Inc., Osaka, Japan). The atomic force microscopy (AFM) image of NM-CQDs was captured on an atomic force microscope (Model: Park System XE-100, Park Systems Corp., Sungnam). Measurements of X-ray photoelectron spectra (XPS) were performed on an ESCA lab 250 spectrometer. The X-ray powder diffraction pattern was acquired on a Brooker Model D8 superspeed with a scan speed of 10°/min. Fourier-transform infrared spectra (FTIR) were recorded with a Nicolet IS10 spectrophotometer. Raman spectra were recorded with a Renishaw spectrophotometer with an excitation wavelength of 532 nm. The zeta potential measurements and dynamic light scattering (DLS) measurements were performed on a Nano ZS90. Measurements of absorption spectra were performed on an ultraviolet–visible light (UV–Vis) spectrophotometer (Model: TU-1901, Beijing Purkinje General Instrument Co., Ltd., Beijing, China). Fluorescence spectra and absolute quantum yield (QY) were measured by a fluorescence spectrometer (Model: Edinburgh FLS 920 and Edinburgh FLS 980, Edinburgh Instruments Ltd., Livingston, England). Time-resolved photoluminescence was recorded on an Edinburgh spectrometer (Model: F900) with a 375-nm laser as an excitation source. Fluorescence images were recorded on a confocal laser scanning microscope (Model: Olympus-FV1000, Olympus Corp., Tokyo, Japan).</p>
</sec>
