<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In principle, hot carrier/exciton relaxation 
  <span class="italic">via</span> nonadiabatic transition induced by surface ligands should be universal for quantum-confined colloidal NCs. As such, this channel is also active for CdSe and PbSe QDs. For CdSe QDs, however, the Auger-type, electron-to-hole energy transfer adds an extra and dominant channel for hot electron relaxation, which explains their faster energy loss rates than PbSe QDs and CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs. PbSe QDs have similar but slightly lower hot carrier energy loss rates than CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs for 
  <span class="italic">R</span> &gt; 2 nm in which regime both are likely dominated by the ligand-induced nonadiabatic mechanism. However, PbSe QDs have yet another lattice-induced nonadiabatic mechanism which is also strongly enhanced by quantum confinement; as a result, their hot carrier energy loss rates become faster than those of CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs when 
  <span class="italic">R</span> &lt; 2 nm. These explanations qualitatively rationalize the comparison shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2b</a>. Nonetheless, several unknowns remain to be elucidated for a more quantitative interpretation of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2b</a>. The first one is related to how to quantify the ligand-induced nonadiabatic relaxation rates for NCs of different compositions. This would explain the slightly slower hot carrier energy loss rates in PbSe QDs than in CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs for 
  <span class="italic">R</span> &gt; 2 nm. Another unknown is why the lattice-induced nonadiabatic mechanism is significant in PbSe QDs but not in CdSe QDs and CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A more general issue associated with the study of hot carrier dynamics of colloidal NCs is how to disentangle the various hot carrier relaxation mechanisms and how to determine the absolute rate for each individual pathway. According to the unified relaxation picture established by Kambhampati 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>,
  <a rid="cit40" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit40">40</a>,
  <a rid="cit41" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit41">41</a> in many cases these mechanisms co-exist and thus it is very difficult to cleanly separate them. Experimental studies with more extensively tuned relaxation-related parameters (NC size, electronic structure, temperature, 
  <span class="italic">etc.</span>) combined with high-level theories would be required for this goal, which is beyond the scope of this work. The focus here is to unravel the dominant hot carrier relaxation mechanism responsible for the absence of a phonon bottleneck in strongly confined perovskite NCs.
 </p>
</sec>
