<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature and ligand independent relaxation dynamics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We examine possible mechanisms for the ultrafast hot exciton relaxation dynamics observed in CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs. As we mentioned in the Introduction, hot electron relaxation in II–VI group QDs (such as CdSe) has been attributed to the Auger-type, electron-to-hole energy transfer mechanism,
  <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a>,
  <a rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit25">25</a> because holes in these QDs can quickly relax 
  <span class="italic">via</span> emission of phonons due to the high density of states in the valence band.
  <a rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit34">34</a> This mechanism should not be applicable for CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs. Because of similar conduction and valence band structures near their edges and electron and hole effective masses,
  <a rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit12">12</a> both electron and hole energy levels in quantum-confined CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs should be discrete. This situation is similar to IV–VI group QDs (such as PbSe). The absence of the Auger relaxation mechanism might be responsible for the slower hot carrier energy loss rates of CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs and PbSe QDs than that of CdSe QDs plotted in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Fig. 2b</a>. Still, the energy loss rates of CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs and PbSe QDs are fast, only several fold slower than that of CdSe, suggesting alternative hot carrier/exciton cooling mechanisms in CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> and PbSe.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For PbSe QDs, a multi-phonon emission mechanism was proposed to account for the ultrafast hot carrier/exciton relaxation.
  <a rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit30">30</a> This mechanism is enabled by intrinsic nonadiabatic interactions induced by electron–lattice coupling and it requires thermal activation to cross the intersection point between 1
  <span class="italic">P</span> and 1
  <span class="italic">S</span> potential energy surfaces. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3a</a> shows the hot exciton relaxation dynamics (by monitoring B1 formation) for 
  <span class="italic">L</span> = 4.3 nm NCs measured at varying temperatures. The kinetic traces are virtually the same within the noise level, showing negligible temperature dependence. Measurements on another sample (
  <span class="italic">L</span> = 4.0 nm) show similar results (Fig. S10
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn2" href="#fn2">‡</a>). Thus, we can exclude the nonadiabatic multi-phonon emission as a major mechanism for hot exciton relaxation in CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs.
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">(a) Hot exciton relaxation dynamics (monitored at B1) for 
    <span class="italic">L</span> = 4.3 nm NCs at varying temperatures. (b) Hot exciton relaxation dynamics (monitored at B1) for 
    <span class="italic">L</span> = 4.3 nm pristine NCs (with OA ligands; orange diamonds) and DDT-capped NCs (wine circles).
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="c9sc01339c-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to intrinsic processes inside the NC volume, organic ligands on NC surfaces also act as a pathway for energy dissipation 
  <span class="italic">via</span> nonradiative, long-range electronic-to-vibrational energy transfer.
  <a rid="cit42" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit42">42</a>,
  <a rid="cit43" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit43">43</a> For example, the 1
  <span class="italic">P</span> to 1
  <span class="italic">S</span> relaxation rate in II–VI core/shell QDs was found to be strongly influenced by surface ligands;
  <a rid="cit44" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit44">44</a> the relaxation rate can be limited by more than one order of magnitude when the capping ligands were changed from stearic acid to 1-dodecanethiol (DDT) because the latter has a much weaker absorbance in the range of ∼0.2–0.3 eV. In order to test this possibility for CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs, we replaced their pristine oleic acid (OA) ligands with DDT using a literature method (see Methods and Fig. S11
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn2" href="#fn2">‡</a> for details). As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Fig. 3b</a>, OA and DDT capped NCs (
  <span class="italic">L</span> = 4.3 nm) show similar B1 formation dynamics. Measurements on other two samples (
  <span class="italic">L</span> = 4.0 and 5.0 nm) show similar results (Fig. S12
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn2" href="#fn2">‡</a>). Because these three samples have X
  <sub>2</sub> and X
  <sub>1</sub> energy differences (Δ
  <span class="italic">E</span>) exactly in the range of 0.2–0.3 eV (
  <a rid="tab1" ref-type="table" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>), similar ultrafast relaxation rates observed for OA and DDT capped NCs suggest that energy transfer to ligands is not the major channel for hot exciton relaxation either.
 </p>
</sec>
