<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis of CsPbBr
   <sub>3</sub> NCs
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We synthesized CsPbBr
   <sub>3</sub> NCs by modifying previously reported procedures.
   <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a> The synthesis started with the preparation of Cs oleate precursors. 0.25 g Cs
   <sub>2</sub>CO
   <sub>3</sub>, 0.8 g oleic acid (OA), and 7 g 1-octadecene (ODE) were loaded into a 50 mL 3-neck flask and vacuum-dried for 1 h at 120 °C using a Schlenk line. The mixture was heated under an argon atmosphere to 150 °C until all the Cs
   <sub>2</sub>CO
   <sub>3</sub> was dissolved. The Cs-oleate precursor solution was kept at 100 °C to prevent precipitation of Cs-oleate out of ODE. In another 25 mL 3-neck flask, a precursor solution of Pb and Br was prepared by dissolving 75 mg PbBr
   <sub>2</sub> and varying amounts of ZnBr
   <sub>2</sub> (0–600 mg) in a mixture of ODE (5 mL), OA (3 mL), and oleylamine (OAm, 3 mL). After the precursor solution of Pb and Br was vacuum-dried for 1 h at 120 °C, it was set to the reaction temperature under an argon atmosphere. The reaction temperature was varied depending on the desired NC sizes (88 °C for 2.6 nm, 93 °C for 3.0 nm, 100 °C for 3.5 nm, 110 °C for 4.0 nm, 120 °C for 4.3 nm and 4.5 nm, 130 °C for 5.0 nm and 140 °C for 6.2 nm QDs). When the reaction temperature was reached, 0.4 mL of Cs precursor solution was swiftly injected to initiate the reaction. The reaction was quenched after a short period of time (10–180 s, depending on the temperature in the range of 190–80 °C) by cooling the flask in an ice bath. After the crude solution was cooled down to room temperature, the product was centrifuged at 3500 rpm for 15 min to remove the unreacted salts as the precipitate, and the NCs dispersed in the supernatant were collected. For reactions conducted at higher temperatures (140–190 °C), only small amounts of unreacted salts remained in the solution, resulting in a higher reaction yield. 8 mL of acetone was directly added to the supernatant to precipitate the NCs followed by centrifugation at 3500 rpm for 3 min. For reactions conducted at lower temperatures (80–120 °C), larger amounts of unreacted salt remained in the supernatant after centrifugation. In this case, the supernatant was left on the benchtop under ambient conditions for ∼0.5 hour until the salts precipitated. Then the mixture was centrifuged at 3500 rpm for another 15 min. After obtaining a clear supernatant, the NCs were precipitated by dropwise adding acetone until the mixture just turned turbid to avoid decomposition of the NCs. Then the dried NCs were collected and dissolved in hexane. Note that in order to obtain very small size NCs (2.6–3.5 nm), the synthesis was scaled up by 3 times, and the reaction should be performed for relatively longer times (180 s for 2.6 nm, 120 s for 3.0 nm, and 100 s for 3.5 nm) without obvious temperature fluctuations.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thiol ligand exchange</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The thiol ligand exchange followed previously reported procedures.
   <a rid="cit45" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit45">45</a> 2 mL 1-dodecanethiol (DDT) and 5 mL hexane were vacuum-dried for 1 h at 100 °C using a Schlenk line to remove the moisture before the diluted 1-dodecanethiol solution was kept at 50 °C under an argon atmosphere. In a typical reaction, the pristine CsPbBr
   <sub>3</sub> NCs dispersed in hexane (2 mL) with oleic acid (OA) ligands were transferred into a sealed and argon-purged 4 mL chromatographic bottle, into which 0.1 mL dried DDT–hexane solution was injected. The mixture was sonicated at 50 °C for 2 h for ligand exchange.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pump–probe experiment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The femtosecond pump–probe TA measurements were performed using a regenerative amplified Ti:sapphire laser system (Coherent; 800 nm, 70 fs, 6 mJ per pulse, and 1 kHz repetition rate) as the laser source and a Femto-100 spectrometer (Time-Tech LLC) as the spectrometer. Briefly, the 800 nm output pulse from the regenerative amplifier was split in two parts with a 50% beam splitter. The transmitted part was used to pump a TOPAS Optical Parametric Amplifier (OPA) which generated a wavelength-tunable laser pulse from 250 nm to 2.5 μm as the pump beam. The reflected 800 nm beam was split again into two parts. One part with less than 10% was attenuated with a neutral density filter and focused into a 2 mm thick sapphire or CaF
   <sub>2</sub> window to generate a white light continuum (WLC) used as the probe beam. The probe beam was focused with an Al parabolic reflector onto the sample. After the sample, the probe beam was collimated and then focused into a fiber-coupled spectrometer with CMOS sensors and detected at a frequency of 1 kHz. The intensity of the pump pulse used in the experiment was controlled using a variable neutral-density filter wheel. The delay between the pump and probe pulses was controlled using a motorized delay stage. The pump pulses were chopped using a synchronized chopper at 500 Hz and the absorbance change was calculated with two adjacent probe pulses (pump-blocked and pump-unblocked). The samples were placed in 1 mm cuvettes and were vigorously stirred in all the measurements.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
