<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In typical semiconductors, photogenerated carriers with excess energy above band edges, the so-called hot carriers, rapidly relax to band edges mainly 
  <span class="italic">via</span> emission of phonons. The relaxation often occurs on a sub-ps timescale,
  <a rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit1">1</a>–
  <a rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit4">4</a> making the excess energy of hot carriers very difficult to harvest. As a result, this part of energy is wasted as heat in conventional optoelectronic devices such as solar cells, which is a major reason for the Shockley–Queisser limit for single-junction solar cells.
  <a rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit5">5</a> If hot carriers can be efficiently extracted to selective contacts,
  <a rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit6">6</a>–
  <a rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit8">8</a> the efficiency of solar cells can be pushed to as high as 66%.
  <a rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit6">6</a>,
  <a rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit9">9</a> As such, it is essential to understand the mechanisms of hot carrier relaxation and to prolong hot carrier lifetimes for next-generation solar cells.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lead halide perovskites (APbX
  <sub>3</sub>; with A = Cs, MA, and FA, and X = Cl, Br, I) have recently been proven to be technologically important for many light-harvesting and -emitting applications.
  <a rid="cit10" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit10">10</a>–
  <a rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit12">12</a> Hot carrier dynamics in these materials have also been intensively studied because of recent reports of long-lived hot carriers.
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a>–
  <a rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit15">15</a> It was proposed that their highly dynamic perovskite lattices facilitated the formation of large polarons which not only protected band edge carriers from trapping but also slowed down hot carrier cooling if the rate of polaron formation was faster than that of hot carrier relaxation.
  <a rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit13">13</a>,
  <a rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit16">16</a> On the other hand, however, recent studies indicated sub-ps hot carrier cooling in various types of bulk-like lead halide nanocrystals (NCs) including CsPbX
  <sub>3</sub> NCs,
  <a rid="cit17" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit17">17</a>–
  <a rid="cit20" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit20">20</a> MAPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs,
  <a rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit19">19</a>,
  <a rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit21">21</a> and FAPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs
  <a rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit19">19</a>,
  <a rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit22">22</a> at low excitation energy densities. Note that slower carrier cooling on 10s of ps timescale reported in 
  <a rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit19">ref. 19–22</a> is a result of Auger heating and 
  <span class="italic">hot</span> phonon bottlenecks that are significant only at higher excitation densities, which is beyond the scope of this work.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In light of these previous studies, it is interesting to examine whether strong quantum confinement can enable a phonon bottleneck and hence slow down hot carrier relaxation in lead halide perovskites, particularly because the Auger-type, electron-to-hole energy transfer mechanism responsible for sub-ps hot electron relaxation in typical CdSe quantum dots (QDs)
  <a rid="cit23" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit23">23</a>–
  <a rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit25">25</a> should be unavailable in these perovskite materials with similar electron and hole effective masses. This phonon bottleneck was theoretically predicted in a very recent study which calculated hot carrier cooling in CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs using the Red-field theory.
  <a rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit26">26</a> Experimentally, however, the effect of quantum confinement on hot carrier/exciton relaxation in perovskite NCs has never been systematically studied. Such a systematic study was mainly hindered by the lack of methods to synthesize mono-disperse and strongly confined perovskite NCs due to their rapid growth rates in hot-injection synthesis. Recent progress has enabled controllable synthesis of high-quality CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs in the quantum confinement regime,
  <a rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit27">27</a>–
  <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a> which should allow for examination of the effect of quantum confinement on hot carrier/exciton cooling as has been done for CdSe and PbSe QDs.
  <a rid="cit23" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit23">23</a>,
  <a rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit24">24</a>,
  <a rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit30">30</a>–
  <a rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit32">32</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we study hot exciton relaxation dynamics in mono-disperse CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs with varying edge lengths (
  <span class="italic">L</span>) in the range of 2.6 to 6.2 nm using transient absorption (TA) spectroscopy. We found the absence of a phonon bottleneck. The hot carrier/exciton energy loss rates increased with decreasing NC sizes. Similar electron and hole densities of states (near the band edge) in CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> exclude the Auger type electron-to-hole energy transfer mechanism. Temperature-independent relaxation rates were inconsistent with the nonadiabatic multi-phonon emission mechanism. NCs capped with alkane thiol ligands of low infrared absorbance showed similar relaxation rates to pristine NCs capped with oleic acid, which also excluded the mechanism of energy transfer to ligands. The hot exciton relaxation mechanism in CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs is most likely associated with nonadiabatic coupling between excitonic states and surface ligands.
 </p>
</sec>
