<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis of CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We synthesized CsPbBr
  <sub>3</sub> NCs by modifying previously reported procedures.
  <a rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit29">29</a> The synthesis started with the preparation of Cs oleate precursors. 0.25 g Cs
  <sub>2</sub>CO
  <sub>3</sub>, 0.8 g oleic acid (OA), and 7 g 1-octadecene (ODE) were loaded into a 50 mL 3-neck flask and vacuum-dried for 1 h at 120 °C using a Schlenk line. The mixture was heated under an argon atmosphere to 150 °C until all the Cs
  <sub>2</sub>CO
  <sub>3</sub> was dissolved. The Cs-oleate precursor solution was kept at 100 °C to prevent precipitation of Cs-oleate out of ODE. In another 25 mL 3-neck flask, a precursor solution of Pb and Br was prepared by dissolving 75 mg PbBr
  <sub>2</sub> and varying amounts of ZnBr
  <sub>2</sub> (0–600 mg) in a mixture of ODE (5 mL), OA (3 mL), and oleylamine (OAm, 3 mL). After the precursor solution of Pb and Br was vacuum-dried for 1 h at 120 °C, it was set to the reaction temperature under an argon atmosphere. The reaction temperature was varied depending on the desired NC sizes (88 °C for 2.6 nm, 93 °C for 3.0 nm, 100 °C for 3.5 nm, 110 °C for 4.0 nm, 120 °C for 4.3 nm and 4.5 nm, 130 °C for 5.0 nm and 140 °C for 6.2 nm QDs). When the reaction temperature was reached, 0.4 mL of Cs precursor solution was swiftly injected to initiate the reaction. The reaction was quenched after a short period of time (10–180 s, depending on the temperature in the range of 190–80 °C) by cooling the flask in an ice bath. After the crude solution was cooled down to room temperature, the product was centrifuged at 3500 rpm for 15 min to remove the unreacted salts as the precipitate, and the NCs dispersed in the supernatant were collected. For reactions conducted at higher temperatures (140–190 °C), only small amounts of unreacted salts remained in the solution, resulting in a higher reaction yield. 8 mL of acetone was directly added to the supernatant to precipitate the NCs followed by centrifugation at 3500 rpm for 3 min. For reactions conducted at lower temperatures (80–120 °C), larger amounts of unreacted salt remained in the supernatant after centrifugation. In this case, the supernatant was left on the benchtop under ambient conditions for ∼0.5 hour until the salts precipitated. Then the mixture was centrifuged at 3500 rpm for another 15 min. After obtaining a clear supernatant, the NCs were precipitated by dropwise adding acetone until the mixture just turned turbid to avoid decomposition of the NCs. Then the dried NCs were collected and dissolved in hexane. Note that in order to obtain very small size NCs (2.6–3.5 nm), the synthesis was scaled up by 3 times, and the reaction should be performed for relatively longer times (180 s for 2.6 nm, 120 s for 3.0 nm, and 100 s for 3.5 nm) without obvious temperature fluctuations.
 </p>
</sec>
