<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>, the calculated absorption spectrum is shown for the 2
  <sub>02</sub> state of HCO (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m9" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">X</span>
       <span stretchy="true" class="mo">~</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mmultiscripts">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">A</span>
        <span class="mo">′</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mprescripts"/>
       <span class="none"/>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>), which has a substantial population (
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.18, assuming Boltzmann) at the estimated experimental temperature of 20 K. In agreement with experiments (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>), the spectrum is dominated by a pure bending progression, denoted as (0, 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m10" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msubsup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
        <span class="mo">′</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">K</span>
        <span class="mo">′</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, 0). Strictly speaking, because of the Coriolis coupling, 
  <span class="italic">K</span>′ is not a good quantum number, but it can still be used to assign the peaks. It is apparent that the resonance width increases drastically with 
  <span class="italic">K</span>′ because of increased RT coupling (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>). As shown in table S1, the calculated transition frequencies and linewidths of the resonances are in excellent agreement with the existing experimental data, further validating the PESs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>, the measured CO (
  <span class="italic">v</span> = 0) product rotational state distributions following excitation to the HCO (
  <span class="italic">Ã</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="italic">A</span>′′) (0,10
  <span class="sup">1</span>,0) and (0,12
  <span class="sup">1</span>,0) states are compared with the calculated ones. The oscillatory structure in the experimental distributions noted previously by Houston and coworkers (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>) is unambiguously established and extended to the low-
  <span class="italic">j</span> region owing to the increased and uniform sensitivity of the high-
  <span class="italic">n</span> Rydberg-atom time-of-flight (HRTOF) technique and the CO background free product detection. The simulated product distributions obtained as thermal averages over initial rotational states (assuming 20 K beam temperature) are in very good agreement with the experiment. Any remaining differences between the measured and calculated distributions are most likely due to the strong sensitivity of the interference effect to subtleties of the PESs as well as to the experimental conditions. In fig. S7, the individual (initial rotational state) components are given. There, it can be seen that the rotational state distributions calculated from pure parent states are significantly more oscillatory than the experimental ones recorded at ~20 K, similar to those reported in earlier calculations (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). The less pronounced oscillation mainly reflects averaging over the initial rotational states but perhaps also contributions from broadening mechanisms (convolution of computed spectra with assumed linewidth parameters often leads to more similar comparisons).
 </p>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Comparison of calculated and measured CO rotational distributions.</div>
   <p>The observed oscillatory and highly excited inverted product distributions are closely reproduced in the calculations. Simulated distributions for pure initial states (or lower beam temperatures) are even more oscillatory (see the Supplementary Materials).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aau0582-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
