<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The HRTOF technique (
   <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
    <span class="italic">23</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
    <span class="italic">27</span>
   </a>) was used to obtain the H + CO product center-of-mass (CM) translational energy and angular distributions. A pulsed HCO beam was generated by photolyzing a ~2% mixture of acrolein in Ar with the 193-nm radiation of an ArF excimer laser focused in front of the pulse nozzle. The HCO radicals produced were entrained in the molecular beam and subsequently cooled (to ~20 K) by supersonic expansion. The radical beam was collimated and then crossed with the visible photolysis radiation from a Nd:YAG pumped dye laser (defined here as the photolysis laser). This photolysis laser radiation was slightly focused and properly delayed with respect to the 193-nm radical production laser but preceded the H-atom product probe lasers; its polarization can be rotated by a Fresnel-Rhomb achromatic λ/2 plate for product angular distribution studies. Hydrogen atoms produced from photodissociation were first excited to the 2
   <span class="sup">2</span>P level by a 121.6-nm Lyman-α (L-α) radiation generated by tripling a 364.7-nm dye-laser output in Kr (values given are vacuum wavelengths). The H atoms were further excited to a high-
   <span class="italic">n</span> Rydberg level by the 366.2-nm output of another dye laser (Rydberg probe laser). A small fraction of the radiatively metastable Rydberg atoms drifted with their nascent velocities to a microchannel plate detector that was perpendicular to the molecular beam, and were detected as ions after being field ionized in front of the detector. The nominal flight length was 37.1 cm. The accumulated H-atom TOF spectra represented 50,000 to 100,000 laser firings. Because the HRTOF tagging technique gives high resolution and uniform detection sensitivity for the kinetic energy of the H fragment and was rid of the CO background interference, the observed CO rotational-vibrational state distributions were well resolved and extended to the low-
   <span class="italic">j</span> states and can be more reliably interpreted than those reported previously (
   <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
    <span class="italic">15</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
    <span class="italic">18</span>
   </a>). It is clear from these experimental data that the CO rotational state distributions exhibit pronounced and reproducible oscillations in nascent product states, extending through the low-
   <span class="italic">j</span> excitation range (see 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). More details of the experiments and results are provided in the Supplementary Materials.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand these oscillatory features, we performed full-dimensional wave packet studies. While ab initio ground-state PESs of this system have been reported by several groups (
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
    <span class="italic">28</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
    <span class="italic">30</span>
   </a>), fully coupled PESs of the lowest few electronic states are rare (
   <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
    <span class="italic">20</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
    <span class="italic">31</span>
   </a>). The results reported here were obtained on the most recent coupled PESs determined from high-level ab initio calculations (
   <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
    <span class="italic">12</span>
   </a>), proven to be considerably more accurate than the previous PESs (
   <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
    <span class="italic">20</span>
   </a>). More details of these calculations are provided in the Supplementary Materials. Briefly, the RT coupling was treated using the theoretical approach of Petrongolo (
   <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
    <span class="italic">32</span>
   </a>) and Goldfield 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
    <span class="italic">19</span>
   </a>), as implemented in our recent work (
   <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
    <span class="italic">33</span>
   </a>). The strong Coriolis coupling was included explicitly while neglecting spin-orbit coupling. The photoexcitation was simulated using the Condon approximation by exciting the thermally populated low-lying rotationally excited but vibrationally cold eigenfunctions (labeled 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="m15" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">J</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">K</span>
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">a</span>
         </div>
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">K</span>
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">c</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>) from the ground 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="m16" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">X</span>
        <span stretchy="true" class="mo">~</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mmultiscripts">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">A</span>
         <span class="mo">′</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mprescripts"/>
        <span class="none"/>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> electronic state PES, up onto the 
   <span class="italic">Ã</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>
   <span class="italic">A</span>′′ state PES according to rigorous selection rules (the use of integer labels for 
   <span class="italic">J</span> in this spin doublet system is due to the neglect of spin-orbit coupling) (
   <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
    <span class="italic">34</span>
   </a>). They were then propagated on both coupled electronic states using the Chebyshev propagator (
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
    <span class="italic">35</span>
   </a>) until reaching the H + CO dissociation asymptote, where the CO rotational-vibrational state distributions were determined by projecting the wave packet onto asymptotic product-state bases on the 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="m17" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">X</span>
        <span stretchy="true" class="mo">~</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mmultiscripts">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">A</span>
         <span class="mo">′</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mprescripts"/>
        <span class="none"/>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> state PES (
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
    <span class="italic">36</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
