<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The discussed examples of the one-nucleus densities show that an important part of the chemical picture of a molecule can also be obtained within a quantum-mechanical treatment: Except for light quantum nuclei like hydrogen or deuterium, the one-nucleus density is very localized around the equilibrium position of the nuclei. Hence, it yields a three-dimensional relative arrangement of the nuclei that is similar to what is expected for a classical approximation of the nuclear wavefunction. It is interesting to compare this result with the similar three-dimensional representation of quantum nuclei by means of path integral methods, where the density matrix for finite temperatures is written as a path integral that can be interpreted as an integral over a classical system composed of “a chain of beads connected with springs” for each nucleus (Ceperley, 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">1995</a>). The path-integral formulation also yields a three-dimensional representation of the nuclear density that includes quantum effects (see e.g.,Richardson, 
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">2018</a>) but that does not correspond to any observable, whereas the one-nucleus density is an observable that can in principle be measured.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Importantly, in contrast to the one-electron density where the electronic state is in general not qualitatively visible (or where, to this authors knowledge, there are no rules available to predict if this is the case), the vibrational state of a molecule may be directly visible in the one-nucleus density. The presented LOCO rules allow to predict, from a normal mode analysis of the nuclear wavefunction, without much effort which vibrational excitations would be visible in the one-nucleus density. From the LOCO rules follows that in many case the classical idea that vibrationally excited molecules simply have a larger amplitude of vibration is in fact also what the one-nucleus density shows. Only for small molecules or certain vibrational modes the excitation can clearly be seen as qualitative change compared to the ground state.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The description of the potential energy surface can be important for the one-nucleus density, because the LOCO rules show that the relative amplitude of the normal modes matters. This relative amplitude has to be described accurately with a suitable electronic structure method. In this respect, the underlying harmonic approximation of the potential is a limitation of the model. Anharmonic effects will for many molecules not change the LOCO rules, but even for molecules that have no large-amplitude mode they can be important for the relative amplitudes of the different vibrations and thus for the influence that a certain mode has on the one-nucleus density. However, an extension of the harmonic model to include anharmonic effects is problematic because the advantage that the integrals can be treated analytically may be lost. A numerical evaluation of the high-dimensional becomes infeasible already for small molecules, hence analytic solutions are highly desirable.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the limitations of the presented analysis, a careful application of the LOCO rules together with the harmonic approximation can in principle be used to guide a possible experimental study: A suitable target molecule and target state for which the one-nucleus density might be measurable can be found, and the Python module 
  <span class="monospace">mQNMc</span> can be a useful for that purpose. Although it is difficult to measure details of a very localized density, the many-body nuclear density is a prohibitively complicated object for larger molecules because all electrons have to be measured in coincidence and because the data is hard to interpret. Thus, the one-nucleus density can be an interesting alternative observable to learn more about the quantum nature of molecular structure.
 </p>
</sec>
