<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis and materials preparation</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FAPbI
   <sub>3</sub> precursor solutions with different concentrations were prepared by dissolving FAI and PbI
   <sub>2</sub> with the molar ratios of 2:1 in DMF and stirring at 60 °C for 8 h in a nitrogen-filled glovebox.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Device fabrication</div>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The electron transport layer, ZnO-PEIE, hole transport layer, TFB and top electrodes, MoO
   <sub>x</sub>/Au were prepared as previous report
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
   </span>. Here the perovskite films were prepared by spin-coating the precursor solution onto the PEIE treated ZnO films, followed by annealing on a hot plate at 100 °C. During the spin-coating of perovskite film, 100 μl of chlorobenzene was dropped onto the film after delay time of 5 s from the start of spinning
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
   </span>. For PeLEDs with BA treatment, 30 μl of BA dissolved in chlorobenzene (1 vol.%) was spin-coated onto the annealed perovskite film. Then the BA treated perovskite film was annealed at 100 °C for 5 min to remove chlorobenzene.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characterization</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All perovskite LED devices were characterized by combination of a fiber integration sphere (FOIS-1) couple with a QE-6500 spectrometer and a Keithley 2400 source meter
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
   </span>. The devices were swept from zero bias to forward bias at a rate of 0.05 V s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simultaneous measurements of PL and EL were obtained by combination of lock-in amplifier (SR830), electric-meter (Keithley 2000, Keithley 2400), and photodector (Thorlabs PDA100A)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span>. The devices were encapsulated by glasses with ultraviolet-curable resin. During the measurement, the excitation light intensity (425 nm laser) was chopped (930 Hz) and kept extremely low, around 0.2 mW cm
   <span class="sup">−2</span>. The EL and PL signal can be separated by using lock-in amplifier. The atmosphere temperature is 18 °C and the relative humidity is 30%.
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PL and EL mapping measurements of devices without encapsulation were recorded in air by a WITec alpha 300 R confocal Raman microscope. For PL mapping, the devices were excited by a 633 nm laser with an intensity of 1 μW. The PL intensity maps are obtained before and after the biasing of devices. For EL test, the devices worked at a constant current density of 100 mA cm
   <span class="sup">−2</span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">HRTEM samples were prepared by using duel beam focused-ion beam (FIB) equipment (FEI Quata 3D FEG). First, a 1 μm of Pt was deposited upon the device in 2 min. Second, the HRTEM samples were cut from the devices by FIB with the current of 3 nA. Third, the HRTEM samples were fixed to the TEM copper mesh by depositing Pt on the edge of the samples with the FIB current of 50 pA. At last, the samples on the copper mesh were thinned to around 200 nm. After the preparation of the samples, we immediately transferred them into the HRTEM chamber. The HRTEM images were collected on a Tecnai G2 F20 microscope operated at 200 keV.</p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UV-vis absorbance spectra were recorded on a UV-vis spectrophotometer with an integrating sphere (Lambda 950, PerkinElmer). The time resolved fluorescence spectra of the perovskite films were obtained by using an Edinburgh Instruments (FLS920) spectrometer. For the time-resolved PL measurements, the perovskite films were excited by a 638 nm pulsed diode laser. A technique was used to obtain PLQE of perovskite films by combination of CW laser, optical fiber, spectrometer and integrating sphere
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The surface morphology of perovskite films was obtained by using a JEOL JSM-7800F SEM.</p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FTPS was measured combining a Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR, Vertex 70, Bruker Optics) with a low-noise current amplifier (SR570, Stanford Research Systems). The photocurrent produced by the devices was amplified and fed back into the external detector port of the FTIR. 
   <span class="italic">E</span>
   <sub>u</sub> was calculated by the IPCE data measured by FTPS, with a fitting error of ±0.1 meV.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
