<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, high-performance perovskite light-emitting diodes (PeLEDs) require high-quality perovskite thin films with good emission properties and complete surface coverage to minimize nonradiative recombination. Methylammonium (MA) based three-dimensional (3D) perovskites are found difficult to achieve thin films with complete coverage, although various interfacial approaches have been applied
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. By using around 400 nm perovskite film to improve the coverage, Cho et al. has obtained PeLED with an external quantum efficiency (EQE) of 8.3%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. However, such a thick perovskite film can reduce charge transport and increase operation voltage of the devices, which leads to low energy conversion efficiencies (ECEs). Alternatively, multiple-quantum-well (MQW) perovskites exhibit excellent film uniformity and emission properties, resulting in a high electroluminescence (EL) EQE of 11.7%, a good ECE of 5.5% at 100 mA cm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> and improved operation stability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Similar strategy was also independently developed by Yuan et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Recently, by using additive or insulating polymers to passivate defects or form microstructures to enhance the light outcoupling, the EQEs of PeLEDs have reached 20%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. However, the ECE of these PeLEDs can be potentially limited by unfavorable charge transport caused by additives or polymers incorporated in perovskite films
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. In principle, in order to improve the LED operation stability, high ECE is required to reduce the thermal energy generated in the device
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Therefore, ideal perovskite thin films for LED applications must have the synergistically integrated merits of high PLQEs and good charge transport, which are currently lacking. Here we demonstrate the fabrication of such perovskite films based on pure FAPbI
  <sub>3</sub> by simply controlling the concentration of the precursor solutions during spin-coating process.
 </p>
</sec>
