<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Properties of different concentration perovskite films</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high-quality perovskite film processed from the 10 wt.% precursor solution is critical to achieve the exceptional LED performance. Scanning electron microscope (SEM) characterizations show full coverage of this film (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), suggesting that leakage current due to direct contacting of ETLs and HTLs can be minimal. As shown in the Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, the film coverage becomes poor and discontinuous when the lower concentration solution is used. This leads to reduced EL efficiency due to the more morphological defects which can result in greater leakage current
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. In addition, the PL lifetime of the films with lower concentration are 21 ns for 7 wt.% film and 17 ns for 5 wt.% film under a fluence of 4 nJ cm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). The short PL lifetime can be attributed to the high defects presented in these poor perovskite films. In case of the higher concentration precursor solution than 10 wt.%, the perovskite film shows good coverage. However, we find that the optical properties of these perovskite films are much inferior to those of 10 wt.% film. Transient PL decay measurement shows that the PL lifetime of the 10 wt.% perovskite film is around 1 μs under a fluence of 4 nJ cm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>), indicating very low defect density. The PL lifetime is 68 and 59 ns for 15 wt.% and 20 wt.% films under the same fluence, respectively (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>), indicating high trap densities presented in these high concentration films. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a> also shows that PL lifetimes at various emission wavelengths are almost identical in the 10 wt.% perovskite film, which suggests that the PL spectrum is homogenously broadened in the perovskite film
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. This homogenously broadened PL emission can be observed in ordered system where the energy relaxation process is not important, such as high-quality vapor-deposited perovskite films
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. In contrast, for most 3D perovskites with energetic disorder, transient PL decay at lower energy emission shows longer lifetime due to the energy migration process
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, which is consistent with the results of those higher concentration film (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Optical properties of perovskite films. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Time-resolved PL for the FAPbI
     <sub>3</sub> films fabricated with different concentrations of precursor solutions under a fluence of 4 nJ cm
     <span class="sup">−2</span>. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Time-resolved PL of 10 wt.% FAPbI
     <sub>3</sub> film at various emission wavelengths, which are almost identical. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Normalized IPCE at the absorption onset for a device fabricated with 10 wt.% FAPbI
     <sub>3</sub> film, measured by using FTPS. An 
     <span class="italic">E</span>
     <sub>u</sub> of 14.3 meV can be calculated, as indicated by the red line. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> Excitation-intensity-dependent PLQE of FAPbI
     <sub>3</sub> films fabricated from precursor solutions with different concentrations. The maximum PLQEs for 20 wt.%, 15 wt.%, 10 wt.%, 7 wt.%, 5 wt.% and BA treated 10 wt.% perovskite films are 29, 42, 60, 46, 30, and 68%, respectively
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11567_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e930" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The electronic disorder of perovskite films can be further quantified by using Fourier-transform photocurrent spectroscopy (FTPS) to determine the Urbach energy (
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>u</sub>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a> show that the semi-log plot of incident photon-to-current efficiency (IPCE) absorption edge of the devices, which indicated an 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>u</sub> of 14.9 meV for the 10 wt.% perovskite film and 14.3 meV for the 10 wt.% perovskite film with BA treatment. We note these values are comparable to those previous reported 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>u</sub> for high-quality perovskite film (around 200 nm thickness)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, although our perovskite film is only 50 nm, which must be more seriously affected by surface defects. A high PLQE of 45% can be observed with the 10 wt.% perovskite film at an excitation as low as 0.1 mW cm
  <span class="sup">−2</span>, and the peak PLQE reaches up to 60% (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>). The transient PL, PLQE and 
  <span class="italic">E</span>
  <sub>u</sub> measurement results together suggest that the fabricated 10 wt.% FAPbI
  <sub>3</sub> perovskite thin film is highly energetically ordered with a very low level of defect density. While in regular 3D perovskite film, high PLQE can only be obtained at high excitation (higher than 100 mW cm
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) when the trap-induced nonradiative recombination centers are filled
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. The PLQEs of those higher concentration films are low (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>), which is also consistent with the FTPS measurement (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a>). We have further measured the fluence dependent PL lifetime for the films with different precursor concentrations. The results show that all the films have decreasing lifetimes with increasing fluence and the 10 wt.% film has the longest lifetime at the low fluence due to suppressed trap-induced non-radiative recombination
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>). In addition, after BA treatment, the PL lifetime and PLQE of the 10 wt.% film are further increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a, d</a>), which is consistent with the passivation effect of the BA treatment.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to investigate the microscopic origin of different levels of disorder presented in those different perovskite films, cross-sectional samples of the perovskite films were analyzed by a high-resolution transmission electron microscopy (HRTEM). The HRTEM images show that the each grain observed in the SEM images (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), consists of many small crystallites (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>). The lattice fringe confirms that the small crystallites are α-phase FAPbI
  <sub>3</sub> perovskites (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Moreover, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a> also shows that the sizes of the crystallites vary in the different concentration perovskite films. The 10 wt.% perovskite has the largest crystal size. And the higher concentration perovskite films show smaller crystallites dispersed in the grains, consistent with the higher level of disorder presented. The different crystal sizes inside the grains are also consistent with the different extent of blue-shifted PL/EL emission peaks of the perovskite films (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6d</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12b</a>). We think that the most blue-shifted PL/EL emission peak of the 20 wt.% films are likely due to the quantum-confinement effect of the small crystallites
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. The largest crystallite with the 10 wt.% film has the weakest confinement effect, resulting in least blue-shifted PL/EL emission spectrum to 3D FAPbI
  <sub>3</sub> perovskite film fabricated by non-anti-solvent method (805 nm)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Therefore, these results suggest that the high performance of 10 wt.% FAPbI
  <sub>3</sub> PeLED is due to both the full coverage of perovskite films consisting of grains and the low defect levels associated with the large crystallites inside the grains.
 </p>
</sec>
