<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6465357</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30988287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9737</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-09737-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Engineering Auger recombination in colloidal quantum dots via dielectric screening</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Xiaoqi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4788-0028</contrib-id><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3731-5236</contrib-id><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Haiyan</given-names></name><address><email>hattieqin@zju.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xuewen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Junliang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Jianhai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Liping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6169-7687</contrib-id><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Linjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lin-Wang</given-names></name><address><email>lwwang@lbl.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5606-8472</contrib-id><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Xiaogang</given-names></name><address><email>xpeng@zju.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1759 700X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13402.34</institution-id><institution>Center for Chemistry of Novel &#x00026; High-Performance Materials, and Department of Chemistry, </institution><institution>Zhejiang University, </institution></institution-wrap>310027 Hangzhou, People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2231 4551</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.184769.5</institution-id><institution>Material Science Division, </institution><institution>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, </institution></institution-wrap>Berkeley, CA 94720 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0368 7223</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.33199.31</institution-id><institution>School of Physics, </institution><institution>Huazhong University of Science and Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>430074 Wuhan, People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>1750</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Auger recombination is the main non-radiative decay pathway for multi-carrier states of colloidal quantum dots, which affects performance of most of their optical and optoelectronic applications. Outstanding single-exciton properties of CdSe/CdS core/shell quantum dots enable us to simultaneously study the two basic types of Auger recombination channels&#x02014;negative trion and positive trion channels. Though Auger rates of positive trion are regarded to be much faster than that of negative trion for II-VI quantum dots in literature, our experiments find the two rates can be inverted for certain core/shell geometries. This is confirmed by theoretical calculations as a result of geometry-dependent dielectric screening. By varying the core/shell geometry, both types of Auger rates can be independently tuned for ~&#x02009;1 order of magnitude. Experimental and theoretical findings shed new light on designing quantum dots with necessary Auger recombination characteristics for high-power light-emitting-diodes, lasers, single-molecular tracking, super-resolution microscope, and advanced quantum light sources.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Designing core/shell quantum dots with desired optoelectronic properties remains a challenge. Here, the authors investigate the negative and positive trions dynamics within a quantum dot, proposing an Auger engineering strategy based on geometry-dependent dielectrics for tuning&#x000a0;optical properties.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Optical materials</kwd><kwd>Quantum dots</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Colloidal quantum dots (QDs) are semiconductor nanocrystals with their sizes in the quantum-confinement regime<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. For multi-carrier states&#x02014;charged excitons and bi-/multi-excitons&#x02014;of QDs, Auger recombination consumes the energy of a photo- or electro-excited electron-hole pair (exciton) to promote another carrier to a high-energy level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Auger recombination is the main non-radiative energy dissipation pathway of multi-carrier states, affecting all aspects of their properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Because of relaxation of momentum conservation requirement and increased Coulomb interactions, Auger recombination is very efficient in QDs in comparison with the corresponding bulk semiconductors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Different from small-molecular emitters, multi-carrier states are quite commonly generated in QDs under either photo-excitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> or electro-excitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. For instance, due to Auger non-radiative recombination of multi-carrier states, short gain lifetime in QD lasing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> and efficiency roll-off in QD-based light-emitting-diodes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> are frequently observed. As the wavefunction of a band-edge hole (or electron) is mostly confined to the inner portion of a core/shell QD, charged QD is usually quite stable. Charging leads to photoluminescence blinking of single QD&#x02014;random switching of photoluminescence between a dim charged state with efficient Auger non-radiative recombination and a bright neutral state<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Photoluminescence blinking brings issues for certain applications, such as single-molecule tracking in biological systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. It is interesting to note that Auger recombination is not always detrimental. For instance, photoluminescence blinking of QDs can be applied for super-resolution microscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, and Auger is beneficial for purity of QD-based single-photon source powered by either photo-excitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> or electro-excitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. These facts suggest that the challenge is how to tune Auger non-radiative recombination of QDs in a controllable manner.</p><p id="Par4">Synthetic chemistry of QDs recently makes ideal single-exciton properties be accessible for the most developed CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, but synthetic control of multi-carrier states remains in its infancy primarily because of poor understanding of Auger non-radiative recombination in QDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Basic forms of multi-carrier states in a QD are negative and positive trions that are, respectively, composed of one exciton plus one extra electron or hole<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Interestingly, Auger non-radiative recombination of other multi-carrier states, such as biexciton and multi-exciton, can be treated as various combinations of negative- and positive-trion Auger pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, simplifying all Auger recombination processes into two basic channels.</p><p id="Par5">Continuous efforts have been devoted to study and tune Auger recombination in QDs in the past 20 years. Based on existing experimental results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, Klimov et al. summarized three strategies for Auger engineering, namely control of the overlap of electron and hole envelop wavefunctions, control of conduction- and valence-band mixing, and control of strength of the intraband transition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Although tuning Auger recombination of negative trion of QDs has been studied widely<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, behavior of Auger recombination of the positive trion is largely unknown. Furthermore, for commonly studied CdSe/CdS core/shell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, CdSe/gradient-shell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, and other II&#x02013;IV QDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, Auger recombination of positive trion has been regarded to be always dominating that of the corresponding negative trion.</p><p id="Par6">Using CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs as a model system, we show independent assessment of both basic Auger recombination channels by separately tuning dimensions of the CdSe core and CdS shell. Our results demonstrate that, for certain geometric structures, Auger recombination of positive trion can actually become significantly slower than that of the corresponding negative trion. By altering the core and/or shell dimensions, rates of both basic Auger recombination channels of CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs can be readily tuned by ~&#x02009;1 order of magnitude. Besides the known factors applied for Auger engineering for QDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, theoretical calculation demonstrates that the unexpected phenomena are associated with geometry-dependent dielectric screening. Given the critical role of Auger recombination for QDs, the experimental and theoretical results in this work should open a new door to design and synthesize QDs with desired optical and optoelectronic properties.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Optical properties of single-exciton and biexciton</title><p id="Par7">Previous reports indicate that properties of single-exciton in QDs are critical for reliably determining Auger recombination rates of multi-carrier states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Here, CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs with nearly ideal single-exciton properties are synthesized with various core sizes (3&#x02013;7&#x02009;nm) and shell thicknesses (4&#x02013;10 monolayers) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). For simplicity, this report adopts a systematic abbreviation, in which CdSe<sub>###</sub>/<italic>x</italic>CdS represents the first-exciton absorption peak of CdSe core at &#x0201c;###&#x0201d; nm with &#x0201c;<italic>x&#x0201d;</italic> monolayers of epitaxial CdS shell. For their single-exciton states, these QDs all possess nearly unity photoluminescence quantum yields (QY), similar photoluminescence peak widths for ensemble and single dots, and mono-exponential photoluminescence decay dynamics with similar lifetimes at both ensemble and single-dot levels (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a, b</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>, and Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). With such QDs, the radiative and Auger non-radiative recombination rates of multi-carrier states could be readily and reliably determined by photoluminescence decay dynamics and photoluminescence QYs of the given states following existing protocols (see Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Optical properties of exciton, biexciton and trion for CdSe/CdS core/shell quantum dots (QDs). <bold>a</bold> Normalized photoluminescence (PL) spectra of representative single (color-coded) and the corresponding ensemble (black) QDs with different CdSe core sizes (the first-exciton absorption peak of CdSe core at 550, 590, and 630&#x02009;nm, respectively) and six monolayers of CdS shell. <bold>b</bold> PL QYs and the goodness-of-fit (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub><sup>2</sup>) for mono-exponential fitting of PL decay curves for CdSe/CdS QDs with different core sizes or shell thicknesses. <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.30 and 1.00 are represented by dotted lines. <bold>c</bold> Schematic of a micro-liquid film of QDs excited by a microscope objective. <bold>d</bold> Pump-power dependence of PL intensity for four representative QD samples with different core sizes but the same shell thickness measured by the micro-liquid film approach. Solid lines are the fits to the &#x02018;PL saturation&#x02019;&#x02019; model. The dashed and dotted lines are the PL saturation models with multi-exciton QY being 0% and 100%, respectively. <bold>e</bold> PL decay curves of CdSe<sub>630</sub>/6CdS core/shell QDs as an representative sample with low (black) and relatively high (red) excitation power measured by the micro-liquid film approach. <bold>f</bold> Excitation power dependence of PL intensity of single-exciton (black circles) and biexciton (red diamonds). The slopes in the log&#x02013;log plot for both channels match the expected values. <bold>g</bold> Representative PL intensity trajectories (black) of CdSe<sub>630</sub>/6CdS core/shell QDs under different excitation power with background noises (gray) and the corresponding histograms. Bin time is 30&#x02009;ms. <bold>h</bold> PL decay curves of the photons from the bright (black) and dim state (red) corresponding to <bold>e</bold> (&#x0003c;<italic>N</italic>&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e572"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">With pulsed laser excitation at low power, area ratio between the center and side peaks (<inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$g_0^{\left( 2 \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) of the second-order photon intensity correlation curve of single QD equals to the biexciton QY, given the single-exciton QY being unity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Alternatively, biexciton QY has also been determined by emission saturation curve of either single-dot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> or ensemble samples in solid thin film<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The first approach becomes not reliable when <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$g_0^{\left( 2 \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is either too small or larger than 0.5. The second approach requires the dots simultaneously to be uncharged, anti-bleaching, and with equal excitation intensity for all dots under high excitation power, which are challenging for either single QD or solid-film ensemble measurements. A method using micro-liquid film of QDs is introduced here for saturation measurements (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>), which can overcome issues of saturation measurements with either single-dot or ensemble samples in thin solid-film (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref> and Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref> for experimental details). All saturation curves obtained using this method (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref> for example) begin to deviate from the Auger-free line when <italic>&#x0003c;N&#x0003e;</italic>, the average number of photons absorbed per excitation pulse, increases to ~&#x02009;0.5, which corresponds to &#x0003c;10% QDs at bi- or multi-exciton states assuming a Poisson distribution of <italic>N</italic>. Along with the emission-intensity deviation from the Auger-free line, the corresponding photoluminescence decay dynamics of the QDs gradually shows a fast-lifetime component, in addition to the mono-exponential photoluminescence decay of the single-exciton (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In contrast to linear dependence of the single-exciton emission on excitation power, the integrated emission intensity of the fast-lifetime component follows quadratic power law (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>). These results identify the fast-lifetime channel is associated with the biexciton emission rate (<inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>).</p><p id="Par9">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref> shows that all saturation curves of QD emission intensity can be well fitted using the standard saturation model (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref> and Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>), which yields biexciton QY (<inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$QY_{XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) with high accuracy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. For the QDs with relatively high biexciton QYs, the results are further verified by the second-order photon intensity correlation measurements of single QD (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref> shows that, as the core size increases, the saturation curves gradually depart from the single-exciton-only trend line&#x02014;zero quantum yield for bi- and multi-exciton emission&#x02014;and approach to the linear function (Auger-free line). This means that biexciton QY increases significantly by increasing the core size for the QDs with a fixed shell thickness (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>). In sharp contrast, the biexciton emission QYs for QDs with a fixed core size but different shell thicknesses are almost constant (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>), being consistent with the literature reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. With <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$QY_{XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, the radiative and Auger non-radiative recombination rates of biexciton (<inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{rad}},XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">rad</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) can be calculated. <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{rad}},XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">rad</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> shows similar dependence on core size and shell thickness, while <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},XX}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is much more sensitive to the core size than to the shell thickness (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref> and Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Quantitative results in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref> suggest that, instead of increasing the shell thickness, varying the core size is a more efficient way to tune Auger recombination rate and a sole way to tune biexciton QY in CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Properties of negative trions</title><p id="Par11">Photoluminescence blinking of single QD allows one to study its trion states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Single CdSe/CdS core/shell QD in this work turns from non-blinking to blinking by increasing the excitation power<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g</xref> for example). As long as <italic>&#x0003c;N&#x0003e;</italic> is &#x0003c;0.5 (the linear range of saturation curves in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>), the bright-state is equivalent to single-exciton emission and the photoluminescence QY remains near unity, and QY of the well-defined dim state in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g</xref> should thus be 29%, accounting for identical absorption cross sections of bright and dim state at the short excitation wavelength (see detail below). In previous reports, with the bright-state being assigned to the neutral-state emission of single CdSe/CdS core/shell QD, the most commonly observed dim state under mild excitation conditions is identified as a negative-trion emission state with different experimental methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. This is further confirmed by photon statistics method (see detail discussion in Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>). While the photoluminescence decay dynamics of the bright-state in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref> is identical as the single-exciton decay dynamics, the mono-exponential decay dynamics of the dim state is assigned to the negative-trion emission decay dynamics (see detail below). Combining the emission QY and mono-exponential decay lifetime of the negative trion, one can readily determine its radiative and Auger non-radiative recombination rates <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{rad}},X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">rad</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">To further verify the charge status and Auger recombination rate of the trion state, we apply photochemical doping in solution to directly prepare the negative trion state of colloidal QDs. It has been established that, upon photo-excitation of QDs, lithium triethylborohydride (LBH) in the solution can efficiently act as hole acceptor of QDs, which results in a negative trion in a QD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Without efficient electron acceptors in the solution, the negatively charged QDs should be sufficiently stable for spectroscopic identification. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>, by increasing the LBH concentration in the QD solution, the photoluminescence quantum yield of CdSe<sub>590</sub>/8CdS QDs decreases. Simultaneously, the first-exciton absorption of the QDs is photo-chemically bleached without affecting their absorption at high energy (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). These results further confirms that there is an extra electron in the conduction band of CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Photochemical electron-doping of CdSe/CdS core/shell quantum dots (QDs). <bold>a</bold> Schematic illustration of photochemical electron-doping and re-oxidizing processes. <bold>b&#x02013;</bold><bold>d</bold> Photoluminescence (PL) spectra, absorption spectra and PL decay curves of neutral (black) and negatively charged CdSe<sub>590</sub>/8CdS core/shell QDs at various stages of photochemical doping (different shades of blue). <bold>e</bold> The extracted negative-trion decay dynamics at various stages of photochemical doping by subtraction of tail-normalized PL decay dynamics of neutral QDs from that of the negatively charged QDs. The black dashed lines are the mono-exponential fitting of the extracted decay dynamics</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1042"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">Because of the mono-exponential decay dynamics of single-exciton emission of the CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs used here, the photoluminescence decay rate of the photo-chemically doped QDs&#x02014;QDs in their negative trion state&#x02014;can be readily separated from that of the undoped QDs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d, e</xref>). Given the unity photoluminescence QY of the single-exciton emission, radiative and Auger recombination rates of the photo-chemically doped QDs at their trion state can be calculated from their photoluminescence QY and experimental decay rates (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Evidently, both radiative and Auger recombination rates determined by the photochemical doping approach are in good agreement with the rates determined by the single-dot spectroscopy for the CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs with various core size and/or shell thickness (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>, and Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>), confirming the most prone to occur dim state observed by single-dot spectroscopy is a negative-trion emission state.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Recombination rates of different channels for CdSe/CdS QDs determined by the photochemical doping method</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>QD sample</th><th><italic>k</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub> (ns<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>)</th><th><inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (ns<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>)</th><th><inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}}\;X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (ns<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CdSe<sub>590</sub>/4CdS</td><td>0.054</td><td>0.64</td><td>0.58</td></tr><tr><td>CdSe<sub>590</sub>/6CdS</td><td>0.048</td><td>0.48</td><td>0.42</td></tr><tr><td>CdSe<sub>590</sub>/8CdS</td><td>0.043</td><td>0.29</td><td>0.24</td></tr><tr><td>CdSe<sub>630</sub>/6CdS</td><td>0.045</td><td>0.30</td><td>0.24</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par14">Importantly, photoluminescence, ultraviolet (UV)&#x02013;visible (Vis) absorption, and transient photoluminescence spectral properties are reversible upon exposure of the doped QDs to oxygen (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). This indicates that the spectral bleaching and appearance of the short-lifetime photoluminescence decay channel (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) are not due to surface degradation of the QDs caused by the chemical reduction. Recovery by exposure to oxygen&#x02014;a common electron acceptor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>&#x02014;is also consistent with negatively charging nature of the doped QDs.</p><p id="Par15">With the Auger recombination rates for both biexciton and negative trion, one could further obtain Auger non-radiative recombination rate of the corresponding positive trion (<inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ + }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) using the superposition principle (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>, and Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. For CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs, the superposition principle, namely <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},XX} = 2 \left( {k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ + } + k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ - }} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, has been repeatedly verified in both single-dot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and ensemble<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> experiments and widely applied in theoretical studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> as well. For the current system, our measurements can directly determine the three rates (<inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},XX},k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ + },\;{\mathrm{and}}\;k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) (see below) for some samples, which also confirms the superposition principle (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Core size and shell thickness dependence of Auger recombination rates. <bold>a</bold> Illustration of Auger recombination pathways for negative trion (X<sup>&#x02212;</sup>), positive trion (X<sup>+</sup>), and biexciton (XX), and the relation among three rates. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Core size dependence of Auger recombination rates of X<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (red) and X<sup>+</sup> (blue) for CdSe/CdS core/shell quantum dots (QDs) with four and eight monolayers of shells, respectively. <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> Shell thickness dependence of Auger recombination rates of X<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (red) and X<sup>+</sup> (blue) for CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs with the first-exciton absorption peak of core at 550, 590, and 630&#x02009;nm, respectively. The data for CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs with the first-exciton absorption peak of core at 550&#x02009;nm and 16 monolayers of shell in <bold>d</bold> (light blue and light red) is from ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Error bars are defined as s.d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1453"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Crossover of Auger rates of positive and negative trions</title><p id="Par16">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref> illustrates Auger recombination rates of negative and positive trions of CdSe/6CdS core/shell QDs with different core sizes. In sharp contrast to literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, the Auger rates of negative trions of these QDs are universally faster than those of the corresponding positive trions. As core size increases in the experimental range, ratio between Auger rates of positive and negative trions reduces from ~90% to ~45%. Interestingly, for QDs with 8 monolayers of the CdS shells, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref> gives results qualitatively similar to that reported in literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, i.e., the Auger recombination rates of negative trions being always slower than those of the corresponding positive trions. Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b, c</xref> suggest that a crossover of the Auger recombination rates of negative and positive trions should exist for the QDs with any given core size, but different shell thicknesses. This is confirmed by systematic measurements for QDs with different core sizes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d&#x02013;f</xref>). It should be noted that, with either hexahedral or spherical shape of the core/shell QDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, the trends shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> are almost identical (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">11</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">Literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> reported that Auger recombination lifetime scales linearly with the nanocrystal volume (known as &#x0201c;volume scaling&#x0201d;). However, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d&#x02013;f</xref> demonstrate that, the rates of the two basic types of Auger recombination evolve in different patterns with their shell thicknesses (or total volume). Quantitatively, for the positive trion, Auger recombination rate is in good volume scaling with the core of the core/shell QD (<inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{{\mathrm{core}}}^{2.8}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">core</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{{\mathrm{core}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">core</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> as the core radius of the core/shell QDs) but exhibits poor correlation with the whole volume of core/shell QD (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">12</xref>). Conversely, Auger recombination rate of the negative trion is in good volume scaling with the whole core/shell QD (<inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R^{3.7}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <italic>R</italic> as the core/shell total radius) but not well correlated with the core radius (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">12</xref>). Overall, doubling the core radius (or whole radius) of a core/shell QD increases the Auger recombination lifetime of positive (or negative) trion by around one order of magnitude.</p><p id="Par18">It should be noted that, majority of studies related to Auger recombination on CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs have been focused on small cores (typically ~3 nm in size) and thick CdS shells (&#x0003e;10 monolayers)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, which should thus not observe the rate crossover discussed above. For example, one set of experimental results from literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> is plotted along with the results in this work (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). Evidently, though the literature results were obtained using a different method, they were consistent with the general geometry-dependent trends for both types of Auger recombination. In addition, recent reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> discovered that the relatively poor optical quality of the CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs studied previously might have caused large uncertainty to resolve the crossover.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Inversion of quantum yields of negative and positive trions</title><p id="Par19">The crossover of Auger rates between the two basic types of Auger channels should result in inversion of their QYs for the CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs. Because of the comparatively low Auger rates of the QDs with large core sizes, their crossover of Auger recombination rates and inversion of emission QYs of positive and negative trions should be readily observable in single QD experiments.</p><p id="Par20">Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>, respectively, show the photoluminescence intensity trajectories for representative single QDs for CdSe<sub>630</sub>/8CdS and CdSe<sub>630</sub>/4CdS core/shell samples. For the top trajectory in each case, excitation power is increased to a medium level to induce a decent amount of the first dim state (noted as &#x02018;Dim 1'). By further increasing the excitation power (still satisfying <italic>&#x0003c;N&#x0003e;</italic> is &#x0003c;0.5 to guarantee the bright-state being mainly single-exciton emission), an additional dim state (noted as &#x02018;Dim 2') becomes visible in the bottom trajectory for each case. For the CdSe<sub>630</sub>/8CdS core/shell QD in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, the emission QYs of the first and second dim states are ~46% and ~31%, respectively. Conversely, the emission QY of the first dim state ('Dim 1', 20%) is significantly lower than that of the second one ('Dim 2', ~35%) for the CdSe<sub>630</sub>/4CdS core/shell QD in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>. Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c, d</xref> reveal that, for either of the two QDs, the mono-exponential lifetime values of photoluminescence decay dynamics of both bright-state and &#x02018;Dim 1'&#x02014;unaltered by changing the excitation power&#x02014;are consistent with the single-exciton and negative trion emission, respectively. Similarly, &#x02018;Dim 2' for both QDs possesses mono-exponential photoluminescence decay dynamics (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c, d</xref>), implying &#x02018;Dim 2' is unlikely a mixture of multiple emissive states.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Inversion of emission quantum efficiency of negative and positive trions. <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> PL intensity trajectories and histograms for single CdSe<sub>630</sub>/8CdS and CdSe<sub>630</sub>/4CdS core/shell quantum dots (QDs). The two distinct dim states with different emission intensities are shaded in red ('Dim 1') and blue ('Dim 2'), which are corresponding to negative and positive trion states, respectively. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> PL decay curves of the three emission states in <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold>. <bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold> The plot of quantum yields (QYs) (<bold>e</bold>) and Auger rates (<bold>f</bold>) of positive trions versus those of negative trions for ten single CdSe630/8CdS (green circles) and CdSe630/4CdS (blue triangles) core/shell QDs . The dashed line (gray) in <bold>e</bold> represents <inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$QY_{X^ + } = QY_{X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The gray and black dashed lines in <bold>f</bold> represent <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ + } = k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ + } = 3k_{{\mathrm{Auger}},X^ - }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Auger</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1812"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e</xref> illustrates that the inversion of emission QYs of &#x02018;Dim 1' and &#x02018;Dim 2' is statistically reproducible, given the diagonal line being equal QYs for the two dim states. With both photoluminescence quantum yield and mono-exponential decay lifetime of &#x02018;Dim 1' and &#x02018;Dim 2', one can directly calculate their Auger recombination rates (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref>). As demonstrated above, the most prone to occur dim state ('Dim 1') for single CdSe/CdS core/shell QD is confirmed to be the negative-trion emission<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Nature of the second occurring dim state ('Dim 2') needs to be determined experimentally, which could be either positive trion or negative tetron (three electrons and one hole) after excluding the possibility of being a mixed state.</p><p id="Par22">For Auger recombination, theoretical<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> and experimental<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> studies reported that Auger recombination rate of a negative tetron should be 3&#x02013;5 times faster than that for the corresponding negative trion, which is inconsistent with the results for multiple dots for either sample (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref>). In fact, instead of being 3&#x02013;5 times faster than the negative trion, Auger recombination rate of &#x02018;Dim 2' for CdSe<sub>630</sub>/4CdS core/shell QDs is statistically below 30% of that of the corresponding negative trion (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref>). Thus, results in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref> confirm that &#x02018;Dim 2' cannot be associated with negative tetron. Additional measurements (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>, and Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>) further support that &#x02018;Dim 1' and &#x02018;Dim 2' in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> are originated from the emission of negative and positive trions, respectively.</p><p id="Par23">The diagonal line in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref> indicates equal Auger rates of positive and negative trions. The distribution of the experimental results in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref> statistically confirms both key findings in the above section, i.e., a slower Auger recombination rate for the negative trion than the corresponding positive trion for QDs with specific geometric structures and a rate crossover between the two basic Auger recombination channels by varying the geometric structure of the core/shell QDs. Furthermore, these results are found to be consistent with those based on the superposition principle (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">In the&#x000a0;literature, positive trion of single CdSe/CdS core/shell QD has been reported to possess a lower emission QY than the corresponding negative trion does<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. However, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">e</xref> indicate that the emission QY of a positive trion can be much higher than that of the corresponding negative trion. As expected, the inversion of the emission quantum yield (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e</xref>) is correlated with the rate crossover of the two basic channels of Auger recombination (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref>). These results demonstrate that Auger engineering through varying geometry of the core/shell QDs can specifically manipulate optical and optoelectronic properties of multi-carrier states of QDs, such as the blinking behavior of single QDs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Theoretical interpretation</title><p id="Par25">The electronic structures of CdSe/CdS core/shell nanocrystals have been studied intensively. It is well established that the valence band maximum (VBM) state is strongly confined in the CdSe core as a result of the large valence band offset between CdS and CdSe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. However, their conduction band offset is small<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>, thus the conduction band minimum (CBM) confinement in the core/shell structure is much weaker<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Depending on the shape and size of the core and shell, the band alignment can be either type-I or quasi-type-II<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Theoretical studies also revealed that the Auger processes for positive and negative trions in CdSe/CdS QDs are asymmetric. From tight-binding calculations, Sargent and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> reported that in a CdSe/CdS QD with 4&#x02009;nm core and 10&#x02009;nm shell, Auger recombination can be six times faster for positive trions compared to negative ones. Using the k&#x000b7;p method, Efros et al. showed that increasing the CdS shell thickness can lead to a much stronger suppression on the Auger recombination for negative trion than for positive trion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. These calculations agree with some of our experimental results.</p><p id="Par26">In order to thoroughly understand the unexpected experimental phenomena descried above, time-dependent perturbation theory<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> coupled with density functional theory with the charge patching method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> and the folded spectrum method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> is applied for theoretical study of the Auger recombination in CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs (see Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). Near the band-edge of a CdSe/CdS core/shell QD, the density of hole energy levels is much higher than that of electron energy levels, which suggests more Auger recombination pathways for a positive trion hence more efficient Auger recombination for positive trion than the negative trion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. However, the picture is incomplete without considering the coupling between initial and final states for each pathway, where geometry-dependent dielectric screening should play a critical role.</p><p id="Par27">Using Slater determinants to describe the initial and final many-particle states in Auger recombination, we can evaluate their coupling strength based on Coulomb integrals in the form <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\boldsymbol{J}}(j,k,l,m) = {\int\!\!\!\int} {\left[ {\varphi _j^ \ast \left( {\mathbf{r}} \right)\varphi _k^ \ast \left( {{\mathbf{r}}\prime } \right)\varphi _l\left( {\mathbf{r}} \right)\varphi _m\left( {{\mathbf{r}}\prime } \right)e^2} \right]/\left[ {\epsilon \left( {{\mathbf{r}},{\mathbf{r}}\prime } \right)|{\mathbf{r}} - {\mathbf{r}}\prime |} \right]d{\mathbf{r}}d{\mathbf{r}}\prime }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02215;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="[" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02223;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>,here <inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\left\{ \varphi \right\}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:mfenced close="}" open="{" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> are the wavefunctions of the relevant single-particle states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. When the initial single-particle states are degenerate or nearly degenerate, a configuration-interaction (CI) expansion of the many-particle states is used to account for the coupling between the nearly degenerate Slater determinants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. This is especially important for the positive trion due to the almost degenerate single-particle states.</p><p id="Par28">The term <inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\epsilon \left( {{\mathbf{r}},{\mathbf{r}} \prime } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:mi>&#x003f5;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">r</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is dielectric function accounting for the screening effect. Larger <bold><italic>J</italic></bold> leads to higher Auger rate. Actually, the dielectric constant can change with the quantum dot size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Theoretically, one approach is to describe the reduction of the overall dielectric constant as a consequence of the increase band gap in the QD. For example, Efros et. al. investigated the intraband and interband Auger processes in CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs by introducing reduced dielectric screening as an input parameter in the calculation. The best agreement<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> between theory and experiment was obtained with the effective dielectric constant being ~&#x02009;40% of the bulk semiconductor. Alternatively, the reduced overall dielectric constant can be described as a reduction of dielectric response for the locations near the inorganic&#x02013;organic interface<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. Such microscropic picture of the dielectric response allows us to develop a location dependent dielectric function model, which is used in the current work.</p><p id="Par29">For Auger recombination of a negative trion, the relevant Coulomb integral is <inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\boldsymbol{J}}(e^1,e^2,e_n,h)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <italic>e</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>e</italic><sup>2</sup>, and <italic>h</italic> are the two CBM states and one VBM state involved in the trion, and <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> is the final electron state in the higher conduction band. The corresponding Auger process is: <italic>e</italic><sup>2</sup> recombines with <italic>h</italic>, and <italic>e</italic><sup>1</sup> jumps into <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>. Similarly, the relevant Coulomb integral for Auger recombination of a positive trion is <inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\boldsymbol{J}}(h^1,h^2,h_n,e)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, corresponding to <italic>h</italic><sup>2</sup> recombines with <italic>e</italic>, and <italic>h</italic><sup>1</sup> jumps to <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>. Thus, the magnitude of either <bold><italic>J</italic></bold> strongly depends on the characters of CBM and VBM states involved in a specific Auger recombination. From this aspect, co-localization of all wavefunctions within the geometric boundary of a QD will lead to efficient Auger recombination for either positive or negative trion in comparison to the corresponding bulk crystal. The small geometric size of a QD would also enable significant penetration of electric-field lines of the carriers into the ligand/solvent environment, whose very-low dielectric constants would largely reduce the dielectric screening of those wavefunctions close to the interface and hence accelerate Auger recombination of the corresponding trion.</p><p id="Par30">For three representative QDs, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> illustrates characters of the relevant states involved in Auger recombination, namely, CBM, VBM, representative high-energy electron (<italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>), and high-energy hole (<italic>h</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub><italic>)</italic> states. The valence band offset is much larger than the conduction band offset between CdSe and CdS and the electron is lighter than the hole<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>, which implies that CBM wavefunction is much more delocalized than the corresponding VBM wavefunction in CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs. The high-energy <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> and <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> states are delocalized over the whole QD.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Snapshot of the charge density and the theoretical calculation results. <bold>a</bold> The charge density of the conduction band minimum (CBM), valence band maximum (VBM), and averaged <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> and <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> states for CdSe<sub>550</sub>/4CdS quantum dots (QDs), CdSe<sub>550</sub>/8CdS QDs and CdSe<sub>630</sub>/4CdS QDs. <bold>b</bold> The theoretical calculation results of the Auger recombination rates for negative and positive trions for CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs with the same core size but different shell thicknesses. <bold>c</bold> The theoretical calculation results for the Auger recombination rates for negative and positive trions for CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs with the same shell thickness but different core sizes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2404"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">When the shell is thin, wavefunction of CBM extends into regions close to the inorganic&#x02013;organic interface, where the dielectric screening is much weaker than the QD interior. This leads to larger Coulomb integral <bold><italic>J</italic></bold> for a negative trion, thus higher Auger rate. Given a fixed core size, increase of the CdS shell thickness pushes CBM wavefunction away from the interface (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>), implying increased dielectric screening for the negative trion. Simultaneously, CBM wavefunction is also more delocalized, which decreases the <italic>e</italic><sup>1</sup>/<italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> overlap. Both factors would contribute decrease of the Coulomb integral <bold><italic>J</italic></bold> and result in a reduced Auger rate of the negative trion. However, increasing shell thickness has small effects on the <italic>h</italic><sup>1</sup>/<italic>h</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> overlap and the dielectric screening, implying insensitive Auger rate of positive trion to varying the shell thickness. These combined effects on negative and positive trions would result in the Auger rate crossover observed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d&#x02013;f</xref>, which is captured by our computation using the model discussed above (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">When the core size of core/shell QDs increases with a fixed shell thickness, wavefunctions of both CBM and VBM are confined more in the core but become more delocalized within the core. These factors cause significant decrease of the <italic>h</italic><sup>1</sup>/<italic>h</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> and <italic>e</italic><sup>1</sup>/<italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> overlap and enhanced dielectric screening for both CBM and VBM, which results in simultaneous decrease of Auger rates for both types of trions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b, c</xref>). Given the relatively small radius of wavefuntion of VBM than that of CBM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>), the effects of the core size would have more impact on the positive trion than on the negative one. Again, our computation captures the trends (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">For commonly studied II&#x02013;VI and III&#x02212;V semiconductors, effective mass of hole is significantly heavier than that of the corresponding electron<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. As a result, for type-I&#x02014;bottom of conduction band (top of valence band) of the core being lower (higher) than those of the shell&#x02014;core/shell QDs, the band-edge hole wavefunction (VBM in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) is more localized within the inner part of a core/shell QD than the band-edge electron wavefunction (CBM in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Thus, the two wavefunctions could experience very different dielectric screening, given the ligand/solvent environment possessing much smaller dielectric constant than the semiconductors. Alternatively, we can state that the dielectric screening becomes geometry-dependent for core/shell QDs and it is no longer suited to treat dielectric screening as the same constant for the two types of basic Auger channels in a given core/shell QD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. Specifically, for certain core/shell geometry, positive trion may experience substantially stronger dielectric screening than the corresponding negative trion, which would cause reduced Auger rates for the positive trion in comparison with the corresponding negative trion. Evidently, this is a counter factor to the other well-known factors, such as density of states and two types of wavefunction overlapping discussed above. As pointed out above, the latter ones always suggest more efficient Auger recombination of positive trions than that of the corresponding negative trions for CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par34">Crossover of the Auger rates of two types of basic channels observed here has neither been predicted by theory nor reported experimentally yet. The experimental and theoretical results suggest that, for the CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs&#x02014;regardless of the core size&#x02014;with relatively thin CdS shells, the counter effect of geometry-dependent screening can dominate the other factors for determining the relative Auger rates of the two basic channels. This would result in overall less efficient Auger recombination of positive trion than that of the corresponding negative trion for those specific QDs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref> and &#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref> show that, as the core size increases, the dominating role of geometry-dependent dielectric screening for the QDs with relatively thin CdS shells becomes more dramatic. As the shell thickness increases, the other factors well documented in literature overtake the dominating role and cause rate crossover between the Auger recombination of two basic channels.</p><p id="Par35">Geometry-dependent dielectric screening not only is responsible for the Auger rate crossover but also represents a new strategy for Auger engineering, which can independently tune the rate of either basic type of Auger recombination. For instance, by coating core/shell QDs with a medium with high (or low) dielectric constant&#x02014;either inorganic shell or organic solvent/matrix, Auger recombination rates can be greatly reduced (or enhanced). We are actively working on these directions, aiming to further enlarge the tuning range of the rates of two basic types of Auger recombination.</p><p id="Par36">In terms of non-radiative carrier dynamics, two elementary processes are important. One is the carrier cooling assisted by electron-phonon coupling after excitation, and the other is the electron-electron interaction induced Auger recombination. In the current experiment, the measured photoluminescence decay dynamics is in the nanosecond time range after the initial excitation. This is far beyond the initial hot carrier cooling, which typically happens within a few picoseconds. We can thus assume the Auger processes start from the ground state of a trion.</p><p id="Par37">There is a phonon-assisted Auger process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. Within this process, not only the electron (or hole) can be excited to their higher energy states through the electron-electron interaction, but phonons can be absorbed or emitted. However, these additional channels do not change the overall oscillator strength of the Auger process. Instead, they just spread out the original zero phonon Auger line, thus broadening the Auger peak. In the current study, this effect has been approximated by using a finite broadening of the energy delta function in the Fermi golden rule in Eq. S6. We have used a peak width of 10&#x02009;meV (close to kT) to represent this effect. Further increasing the peak width does not significantly change the results.</p><p id="Par38">In summary, our results suggest that further suppression (or enhancement) of Auger recombination is feasible with the new strategy. Related, improvement (or reduction) of the quantum yields of multi-carrier states&#x02014;bi/multi-excitons and trions&#x02014;of QDs should be possible. Although the results here are obtained with CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs, above discussion tells us that the new strategy based on geometry-dependent dielectric screening should be generally applicable to nearly all types of core/shell QDs. The core/shell QDs with rationally engineered Auger recombination should greatly promote QDs for important applications, such as high-power light-emitting-diodes, lasers, single-molecule tracking, super-resolution microscope, and advanced quantum light sources.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Sample preparations</title><p id="Par39">The zinc-blende CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs with different core sizes and shell thicknesses were prepared according to the method reported in our previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. For conventional ensemble optical measurements, QD samples were diluted in toluene until the optical density was around 0.1 at the first-exciton absorption peak. QD micro-liquid films were fabricated by transferring a droplet of QD solution (~&#x02009;10&#x02009;&#x000b5;L) to a clean cover slip and mounting another cover slip on the top. The thickness of QD liquid film between two cover slips was around 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;m determined by imaging the uppermost and lowermost emitting QDs in the liquid film using a fluorescence microscope (see details below). For single-dot spectroscopy experiments, diluted QD solution in toluene with 2.5%&#x02009;PMMA by weight was spin-casted on a clean cover slip. All optical measurements were performed at room temperature.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Optical measurements on QDs at ensemble level</title><p id="Par40">UV&#x02212;Vis spectra were taken on an Agilent Technologies Cary 4000 UV&#x02212;visible spectrophotometer. Steady-state and transient photoluminescence spectra were recorded on an Edinburgh Instruments FLS920 spectrometer. Transient photoluminescence spectra were measured via the time-correlated single-photon counting (TCSPC) method with a 405&#x02009;nm picosecond laser diode with 2&#x02009;MHz repetition rate. The photoluminescence lifetime <italic>&#x003c4;</italic> was obtained by fitting the decay curves by a single-exponential decay function with an acceptable goodness-of-fit <inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$(\chi _R^2)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c7;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The absolute photoluminescence QY was measured using an Ocean Optics FOIS-1 integrating sphere coupled with a QE pro spectrometer. The system was calibrated with a DH-3-cal standard light source.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Optical measurements on QDs using fluorescence microscope</title><p id="Par41">Optical properties of QD micro-liquid films and single QDs were measured using an inverted epifluorescence microscope (Olympus IX 83) equipped with a 60&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;oil immersion objective (N.A.&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.49) and suitable spectral filters. In order to measure the steady-state photoluminescence spectra of single QDs, a 405&#x02009;nm continuous wave laser (PicoQuant) was used as the excitation light source and a spectrometer with EMCCD (Andor Shamrock 303i) was used to record the spectra.</p><p id="Par42">The 405&#x02009;nm laser was switched to a pulsed mode with 1&#x02009;MHz repetition and ~&#x02009;50&#x02009;ps pulse width for time-resolved photoluminescence spectra measurements. For measuring the biexciton emission lifetime, a 405&#x02009;nm femtosecond pulsed laser (Light Conversion Pharos&#x02009;+&#x02009;Orpheus&#x02009;+&#x02009;LYRA) with 1&#x02009;MHz was used instead.</p><p id="Par43">In order to measure the biexciton lifetime and QY of QD micro-liquid films, the emission signals were collected and recorded by a single-photon counting system (a Micro Photon Devices MPD-050-CTD-FC photon detectors with 50&#x02009;ps resolution and PicoQunat Picoharp 300 TCSPC module) in a TCSPC mode. With different excitation power densities, a series of transient photoluminescence spectra were obtained and thus the biexciton lifetime and QY could be calculated.</p><p id="Par44">Photoluminescence intensity trajectories and transient photoluminescence spectra of single QD were measured simultaneously with the same single-photon counting system mentioned above in a time-tagged time-resolved (TTTR) mode. The integration time for each data point in the photoluminescence intensity trajectories was 30&#x02009;ms. Second-order photon intensity correlation measurements were performed with the same system and module with a Hanbury-Brown and Twiss (HBT) intensity correlation set-up comprised of a 50/50 beam splitter and two single-photon detectors.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Photochemical electron-doping of QDs</title><p id="Par45">Lithium triethylborohydride (Li(Et<sub>3</sub>BH), 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 1&#x02009;mol/L) in tetrahydrofuran (Sigma-Aldrich) was added to 1&#x02009;mL of anhydrous toluene to form photochemical electron-doping solution. The solution of CdSe/CdS core/shell QDs (optical density of band-edge absorption peak&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1) in anhydrous toluene and 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of trioctylphosphine was loaded into an air-tight cuvette. Into the QD solution in the cuvette, the Li(Et<sub>3</sub>BH) solution was added stepwise with 50&#x02212;1000 equivalent of CdSe/CdS QDs. The resulting solutions were exposed to a 365&#x02009;nm LED (&#x0223c;&#x02009;6&#x02009;mW) for photochemical electron-doping. After a few minutes of photo-radiation, the QD sample reached a steady-state, indicated by stable absorption and photoluminescence spectra.</p><p id="Par46">All above operations were performed at room temperature and under N<sub>2</sub> atmosphere in a glove box. By varying the amount of Li(Et<sub>3</sub>BH) added, the portion of negatively charged QDs in a solution was controlled.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec14"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Journal peer review information</bold>: <italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks Stefan Wuttke, Matthew Pelton, and the other anonymous reviewer for their contribution to the peer review of this work. Peer reviewer reports are available.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>7/9/2019</p><p>An amendment to this paper has been published and can be accessed via a link at the top of the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41467-019-09737-2.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the National Program on Key Research and Development Project (2016YFB0401600) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grants 21573194, 21803053 and 21703202). J. Kang and L.W. Wang were supported by the Director, Office of Science, the Office of Basic Energy Sciences (BES), Materials Sciences and Engineering (MSE) Division of the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) through the organic/inorganic nanocomposite program (KC3104) under contract DE-AC02-05CH11231. It used the computational resource of the Oak Ridge Leadership Computing Facility at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory through the INCITE project.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>H.Q. and X.P. conceived the idea and supervised the&#x000a0;experimental studies. L.W.-W. designed and supervised the&#x000a0;theoretical studies. X.H. conducted&#x000a0;the synthesis and spectroscopy experiments. J.K. performed&#x000a0;the theoretical calculations. J.M. designed the micro-liquid film experiments. J.Z. supported synthesis. X.C., L.C., and L.W. participated in the&#x000a0;interpretation of results.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The authors declare that all data supporting the findings of this investigation are available within the article, its Supplementary Information, and from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par47">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brus</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron electron and electron-hole interactions in small semiconductor crystallites&#x02014;the size dependence of the lowest excited electronic state</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1984</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>4403</fpage><lpage>4409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.447218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chepic</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Auger ionization of semiconductor quantum drops in a glass matrix</article-title><source>J. Lumin.</source><year>1990</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2313(90)90007-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klimov</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantization of multiparticle Auger rates in semiconductor quantum dots</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.287.5455.1011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10669406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pietryga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spectroscopic and device aspects of nanocrystal quantum dots</article-title><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2016</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>10513</fpage><lpage>10622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.6b00169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27677521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Califano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zunger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Franceschetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudopotential theory of Auger processes in CdSe quantum dots</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2003</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>056404</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.91.056404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12906614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klimov</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optical gain and stimulated emission in nanocrystal quantum dots</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.290.5490.314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11030645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Cordoba</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wave function engineering for efficient extraction of up to nineteen electrons from one CdSe/CdS quasi-type II quantum dot</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>4250</fpage><lpage>4257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja210312s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22329340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Continuous-wave lasing in colloidal quantum dot solids enabled by facet-selective epitaxy</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>544</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature21424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28321128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Supran</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bawendi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergence of colloidal quantum-dot light-emitting technologies</article-title><source>Nat. Photon.</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphoton.2012.328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Droop-free colloidal quantum dot light-emitting diodes</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6645</fpage><lpage>6653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.nanolett.8b03457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30198267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Controlling the influence of Auger recombination on the performance of quantum-dot light-emitting diodes</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2661</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms3661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24157692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nirmal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fluorescence intermittency in single cadmium selenide nanocrystals</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>802</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/383802a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efros</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesbitt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin and control of blinking in quantum dots</article-title><source>Nat. Nanotech.</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nnano.2016.140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photoluminescence intermittency and photo-bleaching of single colloidal quantum dot</article-title><source>Adv. Mater.</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1606923</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adma.201606923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lidke</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jovin</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heintzmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superresolution by localization of quantum dots using blinking statistics</article-title><source>Opt. Express</source><year>2005</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>7052</fpage><lpage>7062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1364/OPEX.13.007052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19498727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinaud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sittner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probing cellular events, one quantum dot at a time</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dertinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fast, background-free, 3D super-resolution optical fluctuation imaging (SOFI)</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>22287</fpage><lpage>22292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0907866106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20018714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lounis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Photon antibunching in single CdSe/ZnS quantum dot fluorescence</article-title><source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source><year>2000</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-2614(00)01042-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A quantum dot single-photon turnstile device</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>2282</fpage><lpage>2285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.290.5500.2282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brokmann</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacobino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermier</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly efficient triggered emission of single photons by colloidal CdSe/ZnS nanocrystals</article-title><source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source><year>2004</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1775280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Electrically-driven single-photon sources based on colloidal quantum dots with near-optimal antibunching at room temperature</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1132</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-01379-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29070867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compact high-quality CdSe-CdS core-shell nanocrystals with narrow emission linewidths and suppressed blinking</article-title><source>Nat. Mater.</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmat3539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23377294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ideal CdSe/CdS core/shell nanocrystals enabled by entropic ligands and their core size-, shell thickness-, and ligand-dependent photoluminescence properties</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>16556</fpage><lpage>16567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.7b07434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29094943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthetic control of exciton behavior in colloidal quantum dots</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>3302</fpage><lpage>3311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.6b11431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28170239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietryga</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimov</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auger recombination of biexcitons and negative and positive trions in individual quantum dots</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>7288</fpage><lpage>7296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn5023473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24909861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimov</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superposition principle in Auger recombination of charged and neutral multicarrier states in semiconductor quantum dots</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>8437</fpage><lpage>8447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.7b04079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28723072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Banin</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiexcitons in type-II colloidal semiconductor quantum dots</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. B</source><year>2007</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>035330</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.75.035330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyot-Sionnest</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small bright charged colloidal quantum dots</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn403893b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24350673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of the core/shell interface on Auger recombination evaluated by single-quantum-dot spectroscopy</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl403289w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24397307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasilowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinicelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Patriarche</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubertret</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gradient CdSe/CdS quantum dots with room temperature biexciton unity quantum yield</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>3953</fpage><lpage>3958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.nanolett.5b00838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25990468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyot-Sionnest</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trion decay in colloidal quantum dots</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn9001177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19341263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Controlled alloying of the core-shell interface in CdSe/CdS quantum dots for suppression of Auger recombination</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>3411</fpage><lpage>3419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn4002825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23521208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabouw</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduced Auger recombination in single CdSe/CdS nanorods by one-dimensional electron delocalization</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>4884</fpage><lpage>4892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl4027567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24010869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Size dependence of negative trion Auger recombination in photodoped CdSe nanocrystals</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl4041675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24328385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasfeld</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bawendi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biexciton quantum yield heterogeneities in single CdSe (CdS) core (shell) nanocrystals and its correlation to exciton blinking</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>4477</fpage><lpage>4483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl3013727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22871126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orfield</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantum yield heterogeneity among single nonblinking quantum dots revealed by atomic structure-quantum optics correlation</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1960</fpage><lpage>1968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.5b05876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26849531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bawendi</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biexciton quantum yield of single semiconductor nanocrystals from photon statistics</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl104054t</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21288042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Caruge</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zehnder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bawendi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Room-temperature ordered photon emission from multiexciton states in single CdSe core-shell nanocrystals</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2005</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>087403</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.087403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15783930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Near-unity quantum yields of biexciton emission from CdSe/CdS nanocrystals measured using single-particle spectroscopy</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2011</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>187401</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.106.187401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21635124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Size-dependent biexciton quantum yields and carrier dynamics of quasi-two-dimensional core/shell nanoplatelets</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>9119</fpage><lpage>9127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.7b03943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28787569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mangum</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influence of the core size on biexciton quantum yield of giant CdSe/CdS nanocrystals</article-title><source>Nanoscale</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3712</fpage><lpage>3720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c3nr06558h</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24569861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spinicelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bright and grey states in CdSe-CdS nanocrystals exhibiting strongly reduced blinking</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2009</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>136801</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.102.136801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19392384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Javaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Thermal activation of non-radiative Auger recombination in charged colloidal nanocrystals</article-title><source>Nat. Nanotech.</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nnano.2012.260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banin</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a thermal contribution to emission intermittency in single CdSe/CdS core/shell nanocrystals</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1999</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.478161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exciton-trion transitions in single CdSe-CdS core-shell nanocrystals</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>2281</fpage><lpage>2287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn900296q</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19655720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyot-Sionnest</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for the role of holes in blinking: negative and oxidized CdSe/CdS dots</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>9125</fpage><lpage>9132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn303396c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23006012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deciphering charging status, absolute quantum efficiency, and absorption cross section of multicarrier states in single colloidal quantum dots</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>7487</fpage><lpage>7493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.nanolett.7b03399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29160715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinehart</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Photochemical electronic doping of colloidal CdSe nanocrystals</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2013</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>18782</fpage><lpage>18785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja410825c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyot-Sionnest</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N-type colloidal semiconductor nanocrystals</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>407</volume><fpage>981</fpage><lpage>983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35039577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Atomistic design of CdSe/CdS core-shell quantum dots with suppressed Auger recombination</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>6491</fpage><lpage>6496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.nanolett.6b03059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27668685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartstein</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Electron stability and negative-tetron luminescence in free-standing colloidal n-type CdSe/CdS quantum dots</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>10430</fpage><lpage>10438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.7b05551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28915009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First principle study of core/shell structure quantum dots</article-title><source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source><year>2004</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>3648</fpage><lpage>3650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1737470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eshet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The electronic structure of CdSe/CdS core/shell seeded nanorods: Type-I or quasi-Type-II?</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>5880</fpage><lpage>5885</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl402722n</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24215466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electronic structures of the CdSe/CdS core-shell nanorods</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn9010279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20043692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schrier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electronic structure of nanocrystal quantum-dot quantum wells</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. B</source><year>2006</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>245332</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.73.245332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaxenburg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lifshitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Efros</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biexciton Auger recombination in CdSe/CdS core/shell semiconductor nanocrystals</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2503</fpage><lpage>2511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.nanolett.6b00066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26950398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charge-density patching method for unconventional semiconductor binary systems</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2002</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>256402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.88.256402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12097107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zunger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solving schrodingers equation around a desired energy&#x02014;application to silicon quantum dots</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1994</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>2394</fpage><lpage>2397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.466486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korkusinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Voznyy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawrylak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Theory of highly excited semiconductor nanostructures including Auger coupling: Exciton-biexciton mixing in CdSe nanocrystals</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. B</source><year>2011</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>155327</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.84.155327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zunger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dielectric-constants of silicon quantum dots</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>1994</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.73.1039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10057604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabouw</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of intraband and interband Auger processes in colloidal core-shell quantum dots</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>10366</fpage><lpage>10376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.5b04491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26389562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cartoixa</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microscopic dielectric response functions in semiconductor quantum dots</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>2005</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>236804</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.236804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16090495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawaetz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Valence-band parameters in cubic semiconductors</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. B</source><year>1971</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>3460</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.4.3460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korkusinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Voznyy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawrylak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine structure and size dependence of exciton and biexciton optical spectra in CdSe nanocrystals</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. B</source><year>2010</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>245304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.82.245304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyeon-Deuk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence of phonon-assisted Auger recombination and multiple exciton generation in semiconductor quantum dots revealed by temperature-dependent phonon dynamics</article-title><source>J. Phys. Chem. Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jz402305r</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26276187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinkie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellotti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct and phonon-assisted indirect Auger and radiative recombination lifetime in HgCdTe, InAsSb, and InGaAs computed using Green&#x02019;s function formalism</article-title><source>J. Appl. Phys.</source><year>2015</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>015702</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4923059</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>