<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig1" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Optical properties of exciton, biexciton and trion for CdSe/CdS core/shell quantum dots (QDs). 
   <span class="bold">a</span> Normalized photoluminescence (PL) spectra of representative single (color-coded) and the corresponding ensemble (black) QDs with different CdSe core sizes (the first-exciton absorption peak of CdSe core at 550, 590, and 630 nm, respectively) and six monolayers of CdS shell. 
   <span class="bold">b</span> PL QYs and the goodness-of-fit (
   <span class="italic">χ</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">R</span>
   </sub>
   <span class="sup">2</span>) for mono-exponential fitting of PL decay curves for CdSe/CdS QDs with different core sizes or shell thicknesses. 
   <span class="italic">χ</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">R</span>
   </sub>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 1.30 and 1.00 are represented by dotted lines. 
   <span class="bold">c</span> Schematic of a micro-liquid film of QDs excited by a microscope objective. 
   <span class="bold">d</span> Pump-power dependence of PL intensity for four representative QD samples with different core sizes but the same shell thickness measured by the micro-liquid film approach. Solid lines are the fits to the ‘PL saturation’’ model. The dashed and dotted lines are the PL saturation models with multi-exciton QY being 0% and 100%, respectively. 
   <span class="bold">e</span> PL decay curves of CdSe
   <sub>630</sub>/6CdS core/shell QDs as an representative sample with low (black) and relatively high (red) excitation power measured by the micro-liquid film approach. 
   <span class="bold">f</span> Excitation power dependence of PL intensity of single-exciton (black circles) and biexciton (red diamonds). The slopes in the log–log plot for both channels match the expected values. 
   <span class="bold">g</span> Representative PL intensity trajectories (black) of CdSe
   <sub>630</sub>/6CdS core/shell QDs under different excitation power with background noises (gray) and the corresponding histograms. Bin time is 30 ms. 
   <span class="bold">h</span> PL decay curves of the photons from the bright (black) and dim state (red) corresponding to 
   <span class="bold">e</span> (&lt;
   <span class="italic">N</span>&gt; = 0.1)
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9737_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e572" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
