<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Details of the quantum mechanical calculations</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All CCSD/daDZ, B3LYP/daDZ, and B3LYP/daTZ calculations were carried out using Psi4 v1.1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>, while all SCAN0/daDZ calculations were performed with Q-Chem v5.0
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. At the CCSD/daDZ level, all 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </span> tensors, unrelaxed dipole moments, 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
  </span>, and unrelaxed quadrupole moments, 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">Q</span>
  </span>, were calculated using LR-CCSD/daDZ, with the exception of the ten largest molecules in the AlphaML showcase database (
  <span class="italic">e</span>.
  <span class="italic">g</span>., (18) Phenylalanine, (19) Tyrosine, (20) Tryptophan, (21) Caffeine, (23) Aspirin, (25) Acyclovir, (26) D-Fructose, (27) 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-D-Fructofuranose, (28) D-Glucose, and (29) 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-D-glucopyranose, see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). For these molecules, the memory requirements required to solve the Λ-CC equations at the LR-CCSD/daDZ level were computationally prohibitive, and only energy calculations with CCSD/daDZ could be performed with the available computational resources. For consistency, this required the use of the orbital-
  <span class="italic">unrelaxed</span> finite-field method, in which the molecular orbitals were obtained from a field-free (unperturbed) Hartree-Fock calculation. To obtain 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
  </span> and 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </span>, we computed first and second derivatives of the CCSD/daDZ energy (
  <span class="italic">U</span>) with respect to an external electric field, 
  <span class="bold">E</span>, 
  <span class="italic">i</span>.
  <span class="italic">e</span>., 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
  </span> = ∂
  <span class="italic">U</span>/∂
  <span class="bold">E</span> and 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </span> = ∂
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <span class="italic">U</span>/∂
  <span class="bold">E</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>. 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">Q</span>
  </span> values were not computed for the ten largest molecules in the AlphaML showcase database. All DFT calculations used the orbital-
  <span class="italic">relaxed</span> finite-field method, in which a self-consistent field (SCF) was obtained in the presence of each applied field, and 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </span> was computed via 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </span> = ∂
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
  </span>/∂
  <span class="bold">E</span>. All other molecular properties at the DFT level (
  <span class="italic">vide infra</span>) were obtained directly from the field-free (unperturbed) calculation. All derivatives were computed numerically using two-point (for first derivatives) and three-point (for second derivatives) central difference formulae and a step size of 
  <span class="bold">E</span> = 1.8897261250 × 10
  <span class="sup">−5</span> atomic units.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all LR-CCSD/daDZ calculations, the convergence criteria were set to their default values in Psi4, 
  <span class="italic">i</span>.
  <span class="italic">e</span>., E_convergence = 1.0E-10 and D_convergence = 1.0E-10 for the energy and density during the solution of the HF equations, and E_convergence = 1.0E-08 and R_convergence = 1.0E-07 for the energy and residuals during the solution of the CCSD equations. For the ten largest molecules in the AlphaML showcase database, the finite-field CCSD/daDZ calculations were performed using the following convergence criteria in Psi4: E_convergence = 5.0E-10 and D_convergence = 5.0E-10 for the energy and density during the solution of the HF equations. Significantly tighter convergence criteria of E_convergence = 5.0E-10 and R_convergence = 5.0E-09 were employed for the energy and residuals during the solution of the CCSD equations to minimize errors in the numerical evaluation of 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
  </span> and 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </span>. The frozen core (FC) approximation and scf_type = direct were used for all LR-CCSD/daDZ and CCSD/daDZ calculations. For all B3LYP/daDZ and B3LYP/daTZ calculations, the convergence criteria in Psi4 were again set to tight values to minimize numerical error in the finite-difference evaluation of 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </span>: E_convergence = 1.0E-10 and D_convergence = 1.0E-10 for the energy and density during the solution of the Kohn-Sham equations. For all the SCAN0/daDZ calculations, the convergence criteria were set to scf_convergence = 1.0E-10 and thresh = 1.0E-13 for the DIIS error and integral thresholding in Q-Chem. The Dunning-style daDZ and daTZ basis sets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> were obtained from the EMSL Basis Set Library
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
