<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this work, we perform a systematic study on how the size of the hysteresis loops observed in the conductance measurements during forward and reverse sweeps evolves in a number of asymmetrically biased side-gated InAs QPCs (with different lithographic channel widths while keeping their lithographic channel length fixed). QPC devices were fabricated using a high-electron-mobility InAs/InAlAs quantum well based 2DEG. The details of the quantum well structure and QPC fabrication process are described elsewhere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Shubnikov-de Haas and quantum Hall measurements at 4.2 K were used to determine the carrier concentration and electron mobility of the 2DEG which were found to be equal to 2.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">16</span>/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> and 3.67 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>/Vs, respectively
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. As shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, electron beam lithography and a wet etching technique were used to define deep trenches in the 2DEG to form narrow QPC constrictions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Schematic representation and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) scanning electron micrograph (SEM) of an InAs based QPC with two in-plane SGs (G1 and G2). Dark areas are the deep-etched isolation trenches defining the two SGs. The current flows in the x-direction. Application of an asymmetric bias potential between the SGs leads to a lateral electric field along y-direction. The latter is responsible for LSOC in the QPC narrow portion. The 2DEG lies on the xy-plane. The z axis is the direction of growth of the heterostructure.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48380_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e671" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We fabricated seven QPCs with different aspect ratios (i.e., ratio of lithographic width over lithographic length). Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a,b</a> represent a schematic and a scanning electron micrograph of one of our fabricated QPC structures with in-plane SGs (G1 and G2), respectively. In QPC 1 through 7, the narrow portion had the same lithographic length (L ~ 890 nm) but different lithographic widths (W) varying from 220 nm, 260 nm, 330 nm, 410 nm, 520 nm, 640 nm, and 780 nm, respectively. This corresponds to a QPC aspect ratio (W/L) ranging from 0.247, 0.292, 0.371, 0.461, 0.584, 0.719 to 0.876 for QPC 1 through 7, respectively. The reason the maximum lithographic length of the channel for all QPC devices was maintained around 890 nm is because InAs has a measured electron spin coherence length less than a micron at 4.2 K
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. In fact, one of our earlier reports
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> has shown the existence of the broadest 0.5G
  <sub>o</sub> plateau for an InAs QPC having lithographic channel length around 930 nm. We varied the electrostatic width of the QPC channel by applying a bias to the ohmic in-plane SGs. This leads to a depletion of the channel in the narrow portion of the QPC. DC bias was applied to maintain fixed negative voltages 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G2</sub> on the two SGs, as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>. The QPC devices were first cooled down to liquid nitrogen (77 K) and then to liquid helium (4.2 K). Further details of our conductance measurements are provided elsewhere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. The QPC conductance was measured as a function of a common sweep voltage, 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G</sub>, applied to the two SGs. A four-probe lock-in technique with a drive frequency of 17 Hz was used to measure the linear conductance 
  <span class="italic">G</span> (=
  <span class="italic">I</span>/
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ds</span>
  </sub>) of the QPC channel for different bias asymmetry Δ
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G</sub> while varying the common sweep voltage 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G</sub> applied to the two SGs. In all conductance measurements performed at 4.2 K, a small source-to-drain voltage of 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ds</span>
  </sub> = 100 μV was applied across the QPC. For all QPCs, the negative voltages 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G2</sub> applied to the two SGs were varied until a robust 0.5G
  <sub>o</sub> plateau was observed as the common gate voltage 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>G</sub> was continuously swept
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
