<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemistry</div>
 <p id="p0085" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All reagents were purchased from either Merck (Darmstadt, Germany) or Sigma and Aldrich Chemical Co (St. Louis, MO, USA) and used without further purification. All products were characterized by spectral data (IR, MS, 
  <span class="sup">1</span>H-NMR, 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C-NMR). NMR spectra (
  <span class="sup">1</span>H and 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C) were measured on a Bruker Ultrashield-400 spectrometer (Rheinstetten, Germany), using CDCl
  <sub>3</sub> as solvent and reference. 
  <span class="italic">J</span> values are reported in Hz; chemical shifts are reported in ppm (δ) relative to the solvent peak (residual CHCl
  <sub>3</sub> in CDCl
  <sub>3</sub> at 7.26 ppm for protons and 77 ppm for carbon atoms). Signals were designated as follows: s, singlet; d, doublet; dd, doublet of doublets; t, triplet; td, triplet of doublets; q, quartet; m, multiplet, and br., broad. IR spectra (KBr pellets, 500–4000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) were recorded on a NEXUS 670 FT-IR spectrophotometer (Thermo Nicolet, Madison, WI, USA). GC-MS analyses were performed on a model Trace 1300 GC-MS instrument (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) equipped with a Rtx-5MS on-column auto-injector and a fused silica capillary column (DB-5, 30 m ˆ 0.25 mm ID, 0.25 μm film thickness). MS were recorded in electron ionization (EI) mode, with the energy of 70 eV. The ion source temperature was 200 °C; 4.00 min solvent cut time. Melting points (uncorrected) were measured on an Electrothermal IA9100 melting point apparatus (Stone, Staffs, UK). The reaction progress was monitored using thin layer chromatography on PF254 TLC aluminum sheets from Merck. Column chromatography was performed using Silica gel (60–120 mesh) and Solvents employed were of analytical grade.
 </p>
</sec>
