<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="p0010" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the research of biologically active molecules, free radicals have been linked to several degenerative diseases including neurodegenerative and cardiovascular disorder, atherosclerosis and cancer (
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">Aruoma, 1998</a>). Although the discovery of antioxidant compounds has been an area widely studied (
  <a rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib15">Kouznetsov et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">Bulut et al., 2018</a>; 
  <a rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19">Martelli and Giacomini, 2018</a>) it is necessary to continue in the search of new natural or synthetic compounds that can act as free radical scavengers and help in the treatment or control of diseases related to oxidative stress.
 </p>
 <p id="p0015" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterocyclic compounds, especially nitrogen heterocycles, are a very important class of compounds with application in the pharmaceutical industries, which comprise about 60% of all pharmacological substances. The tetrahydroquinoline (THQ) ring system, in particular, is a common structural motif found in numerous biologically active natural products showing broad biological activities (
  <a rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21">Nammalwar and Bunce, 2014</a>). Because of the significance of these scaffolds in drug discovery and medicinal chemistry, the development of new methodologies for the synthesis of THQs derivatives continues to be an active field of investigation, as is evidenced by the appearance of over 400 research articles in this area during the last years (
  <a rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib27">Sridharan et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">Katritzky et al., 1996</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0020" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last decades, a great number of synthetic methods for access to THQs derivatives have been reported (
  <a rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib27">Sridharan et al., 2011</a>). In many cases, these methodologies involve an intramolecular Friedel-Crafts reaction of 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-substituted anilines with a suitable functional group bound to the nitrogen atom (
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">Abonia et al., 2013</a>). In this sense, the use of multicomponent Povarov reaction, catalyzed by Lewis or Brønsted acids between 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-arylimines (obtained from anilines and aryl (alkyl)aldehydes) and electron-rich alkenes, is maybe the most powerful tool that provides quick and efficiently THQ scaffold with great structural diversity. Recently, we have been successfully exploring the cationic version of the Povarov reaction (a domino Mannich/Friedel-Crafts reaction). This method resulted highly efficient to access different N-derivatives of THQs (
  <a rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib25">Romero Bohórquez et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Acelas et al., 2017</a>), including the synthesis of new 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-allyl/propargyl 1,2,3,4-THQs, promissory dual inhibitors against AChE and BChE enzymes (
  <a rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib24">Rodriguez et al., 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0025" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diverse amine derivatives with the propargyl fragment in its structure are versatile compounds with demonstrated pharmacological and pharmaceutical applications such as antioxidant agents (
  <a rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib8">Dragoni et al., 2006</a>) and as inhibitors of some monoamine oxidases MAO-B. Selegiline, Rasagiline, Pargyline, and Ladostigil drugs are widely used as enzymatic inhibitors in treatments of neurodegenerative diseases (
  <a rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>) (
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Baranyi et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">Bolea et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">Mao et al., 2015</a>). Taking into account all the above, in the present study, we report the synthesis, spectroscopic characterization and antioxidant activity of a new series of 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-propargyl-THQs obtained via mild and expeditious InCl
  <sub>3</sub> catalyzed-cationic Povarov reaction. Results indicated that some THQs derivatives evaluated showed good activity as potential free radical scavengers. In addition, theoretical studies of Molecular Quantum Similarity Measure allowed explaining the biological activity reported. Local reactivity descriptors like the local softness and electrophilicity indices were obtained with the help of Fukui function calculation.
  <div id="fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Propargylamines inhibitors of monoamine oxidases MAO-A and MAO-B.</p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0015" class="alt-text">Fig. 1</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
