<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of ABTS radical scavenging activity</div>
 <p id="p0150" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ABTS (2,2′-Azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) radical scavenging assay is a rapid and efficient method, based on the ability of the hydrogen donating antioxidants to scavenge the long-life radical cation ABTS
  <span class="sup">•+</span>. In this method, the preformed radical monocation of ABTS is generated by the oxidation of ABTS with potassium persulfate and is reduced in the presence of such hydrogen donating antioxidants (
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">Karadag et al., 2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0155" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ABTS assay was performed according to the protocol (
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Polo et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib23">Re et al., 1999</a>). The ABTS radical cation (ABTS
  <span class="sup">•+</span>) was produced by reaction of 7 mM stock solution of ABTS with 2.45 mM potassium persulfate and allowing the mixture to stand in dark at room temperature for 12 h before use. The ABTS
  <span class="sup">•+</span> solution was diluted with methanol to give an absorbance of 0.7 ± 0.01 at 745 nm. Compounds (1 mL) were allowed to react with 2 ml of the ABTS
  <span class="sup">•+</span> solution and the absorbance was measured at 745 nm after 1 min. Data for each assay was recorded in triplicate. Ascorbic acid was used as positive controls with IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of 35 μg/mL. The scavenging activity was estimated based on the percentage of ABTS radicals scavenged by the following formula:
  <div id="ufd2" class="disp-formula">% scavenging = [(A0 − As)/A0] × 100</div>Where A0 is the absorption of control, AS is the absorption of a tested compound solution.
 </p>
</sec>
